
<TEI.2 id="APB0763">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-03-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 807-808</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Nathaniel Cox</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Nathaniel Cox to Stephen F. Austin, 06-03-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Orleans, LA</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Hawkin's estate and his expenditures for the colony. General Wilkinson.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 807-808</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-17-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0763T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Hawkin's estate and his expenditures for the colony. General Wilkinson.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="06-03-1824">3. June 1824</date_mentioned>.</p>
<p><person_mentioned>Colo. S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Dear Sir, Your letter dated the <date_mentioned n="04-20-1824">20 April</date_mentioned> has just reached me
thro' the <location_mentioned>post office</location_mentioned>—and I have particularly noted the contents—</p><barker_pb n="808"/>

<p>I have wrote you several times by persons going to the <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned>
Since the death of our much lamented friend <person_mentioned>Hawkins</person_mentioned>, giving an
account of the moneys he has Expended in Effecting the object,
now under consideration—and still hope some of my letters may
get safe to hand—</p>

<p>The amount which appears to have been so appropriated by him
Exceeds Thirty Thousand dollars—this includes the purchas of
Vessells, Cargoes, and disbursements to <person_mentioned>officers </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>seamen</person_mentioned>—Loans
to individuals traveling to and from the grant, who are unknown
to me, and lost to his <person_mentioned>Heirs </person_mentioned>Except as a charge to the grant—
payments made to you and on your draft—and the dreadfull Item of
Usurious Interest to money <person_mentioned>Brokers </person_mentioned>for loans at difft  times—</p>

<p>After the death of our friend <person_mentioned>Mrs. Hawkins</person_mentioned> made up her mind to
return to <location_mentioned>Kentucky</location_mentioned>, leaving with me full power and authority to
transact all business connected with the Estate of her deceased 
<person_mentioned>Husband </person_mentioned>upon which she administered, and so far I have done all I
could do in Settling the Estate, but which from the nature of the
obligations of <person_mentioned>Mr Hawkins</person_mentioned> leaves but little to do, for he had 
mortgaged all his real property and the furniture was under Execution
at the time of his death—</p>

<p>I fully approve the resolution you have adopted with regard to
the <location_mentioned>Texas property</location_mentioned>, for it would now only be sacrificed if put in
his name, and pay none of the Debts—for I do not beleive if the
whole grant was put up at auction a Sale could be effected for One
Hundred dollars—Therefore the only plan wh. can avail <person_mentioned>Mrs 
Hawkins</person_mentioned> and her children is the one you have adopted—and the time
may come when it may make them independent—</p>

<p>I would answer your Enquires as to a Vessell for the purpose of
communicating with the <location_mentioned>Brasos </location_mentioned>if I could do So with any degree
of Satisfaction—I should however suppose one of 30 to 40 Tons
might be had for 1000 or 1200 $ pble [payable] one half Cash and
the balance at 6 or 8 months—but I have so little intercourse with
the Lake craft that my statemt is founded on uncertainty-</p>

<p><person_mentioned>General Wilkinson</person_mentioned> has not yet returned to <location_mentioned>Louisiana</location_mentioned>, nor do we
expect him for some months yet—he remains as he says in letters
to his <person_mentioned>wife </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Son</person_mentioned>, to close the accounts of Individuals who put
claims into his hands for advances to the Republic many years ago,
and which from all I can learn remain as much unsettled as the
day he reached <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Nath. Cox</person_mentioned>.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
