
<TEI.2 id="APB0503">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-26-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 500-502</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Maria Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Maria Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 04-26-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Herculaneum, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Colorado, TX</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Family news. Reports of Indian outrages.   Religious toleration.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Original in possession of Mrs. Emmett L. Perry</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 500-502</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0503T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Family news. Reports of Indian outrages.   Religious toleration.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Herculaneum </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="04-26-1822">Aprill the 26 1822</date_mentioned></p>
<p>I have a good opportunity of droping a few hasty lines to my
beloved <person_mentioned>Sons</person_mentioned>—by <person_mentioned>Mr Honey</person_mentioned>, he arrived in the Dolphen <date_mentioned n="04-25-1822">last night</date_mentioned>
from <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned>, has Purchased a Share in hur and Starts in two
hours for <location_mentioned>New Orleins</location_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Mary </person_mentioned>sent for me to Stay with hur during
his abcence. I have promisd to remain with hur till the last weeck
in <date_mentioned n="05-xx-1822">may</date_mentioned>, when I must attend your <person_mentioned>Sister </person_mentioned>as She expects to be 
confined in <date_mentioned n="06-xx-1822">June</date_mentioned>— I am well pleased to find your <person_mentioned>cousin Mary</person_mentioned> so
happy and pleasantly Situated, She has every Convenience and
comfort that is requisite to render the marriage quite happy and
blessed with a very lovely and healthy boy Six months old I wrote
my dear <person_mentioned>Sons </person_mentioned>not long Since by the two Alleys and Expressed in
that letter my great anxiety to hear from you and your <person_mentioned>brother </person_mentioned>and
Since my arrival here my fealing had been greatly agitated by a
report that the <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>had Commenced on your <location_mentioned>Infant Colony</location_mentioned> and
had carried of[f] all the horses and Stock theay could find—this
unwellcome news was brought by some <person_mentioned>travallers from <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>—but I
still flatter myself the report is not true, Since nothing of the kind
is mentioned in the <location_mentioned>papers </location_mentioned>on the contrary the <location_mentioned>papers </location_mentioned>Speaks—of
very favourable changes taken place da[i]ly in the <location_mentioned>Spanish 
provinces</location_mentioned>, boath in politicks and religeon, I am very willing my dear
<person_mentioned>Son </person_mentioned>to view the bright side of the prospect at the same time I cannot
divest my mind of a thousand Apprehentions for your Safety, as I
well know your dear <person_mentioned>Father </person_mentioned>Anticipated trouble from the <person_mentioned>Savages</person_mentioned>
and he intended to erect a <location_mentioned>fort</location_mentioned>, I have often heard him Say that
the first worck that was don[e] Should be the building of a kind of
<location_mentioned>fort </location_mentioned>where he and his <person_mentioned>Compannions </person_mentioned>would be Safe in case of an
attack from the hostile <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>—pray write me the particulars of
every thing for though I could do you no Servise I Still wish to
know the truth of every thing and shall be unhappy in mind till I
have letters from you and <person_mentioned>Brown</person_mentioned>—I had the Satisfaction of 
Spending part of a day with your amiable <person_mentioned>Cousin N Carr</person_mentioned>—She has gown
to <location_mentioned>St Geneveive</location_mentioned> to mack a visit to hur poor <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>A Eliot</person_mentioned> he is<barker_pb n="501"/>
in a miserable State of health, brought on in a great measure by his
on Imprudence I am told he drinks hard and is hardly ever Sober
unhappy young man, I fear by all accounts, he is not [long] for
this world— I have directed <person_mentioned>Mr Honey</person_mentioned> in case he does not meet
you in <location_mentioned>New Orleins</location_mentioned>, to inquire what is the price of buck horns for
handels for knives and if theay will bring any thing I will send
them down to your friend <person_mentioned>Mr H[awkins]</person_mentioned>—when <person_mentioned>Mr Honey</person_mentioned> takes
another trip also the plough shars and I wish you to let me know
if you wish me to send down any of my things, if you and <person_mentioned>Brown</person_mentioned>
go to houskeeping I could send several articles that you will want,
I wish my dear <person_mentioned>Son </person_mentioned>to let me know what time he thinks we had
better go down, your <person_mentioned>Sister </person_mentioned>and myself will not wish to spend 
another winter in this unfriendly climate we are sitting [a] round a
large fire and can Scarcely keep ourselves warm, the frost, 
notwithstanding the Sceason is so far advanced is So sevear that all
the fruit is killed and in the place of the gay verdure of Spring -
the face of nature assums the appearance of Autum, I care not how
Soon I leave So unpleasant Climate and so very unfriendly to my
Constitution— <person_mentioned>Mr Bryan</person_mentioned> is now in <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned>, he left your <person_mentioned>Sister</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>famaly </person_mentioned>all well, your old <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>in this place are all well except
<person_mentioned>Nancy Bates</person_mentioned> She has been Sick all <date_mentioned n="WInter-1821">winter </date_mentioned>as well as my self, but
has not recruted so fast as I have, She is I think in a low state of
health, tell <person_mentioned>Brown </person_mentioned>his poor <person_mentioned>Cousin Maria</person_mentioned> has been gilied by <person_mentioned>Mr W</person_mentioned>
a gentleman he had formd a high opinion of—he was to have been
back in <date_mentioned n="10-xx-1821">October last</date_mentioned> and in the coars of the <date_mentioned n="Winter-1821">winter </date_mentioned>he was to be
maried to <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>M B</person_mentioned></hi> he has not wrote hur for a long time and it tis 
reported he is married to a lady of large fortune in <location_mentioned>Virginia</location_mentioned>, this may
be So, and it may not— I wish my dear <person_mentioned>Son </person_mentioned>to be particular on the
Subject of religious toloration, Some Says every permanent <person_mentioned>Settler</person_mentioned>
must become <person_mentioned>roman Catholicks</person_mentioned>—I can not think or beleive that so
arbitory a Sistem will be adopted if it Should, it will put a Stop
to Emigration, if you Should happen to meet with <person_mentioned>Honey </person_mentioned>in
<location_mentioned>Orleins </location_mentioned>I will thank my <person_mentioned>Son </person_mentioned>to send me Some good Snuf and the
Journal your dear <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>wrote many years ago—he always kept it
in his writing desk—<person_mentioned>Mr Schoolcraft</person_mentioned> wishes to pubblish the 
Biography of his life, and wished me to Send him a memorandum of the
dates . . . and when he came to this Country with a variety of
particulars two tedious to mention in a letter, I thought if ... he
feels himself under many obligations to my dear departed <person_mentioned>Husband</person_mentioned>
for the friendship and hospatality shone him when he came to this
country, he is now in <location_mentioned>New york</location_mentioned> preparing to publish an account of
his late travels. He wished me to send a Short account of the life
of your <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>from the time he left <location_mentioned>Virginia </location_mentioned>till his death, I must
bid you farewell   <person_mentioned>Mr H</person_mentioned> has arrived to bid adieu to his <person_mentioned>wife </person_mentioned>and<barker_pb n="502"/>
<person_mentioned>child</person_mentioned>— <person_mentioned>Mary</person_mentioned> Joines me in affectionate love to you and dear
<person_mentioned>Brown </person_mentioned>may god bless you boath and take you into his holy keeping
is the constant prayer of your anxious <person_mentioned>mother</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mary Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Stepehen F. Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Austintino Colerado Texas</location_mentioned>   
politness of <person_mentioned>Capn John W. Honey</person_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
