
<TEI.2 id="APB0419">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-03-1821</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 424-425</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Robert Andrews</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Robert Andrews to Stephen F. Austin, 11-03-1821</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Mount Prairie, AR</sent_from>
	<sent_to>New Orleans, LA</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Emigration promised from southern Arkansas.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 424-425</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-10-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0419T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Emigration promised from southern Arkansas.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>[Mou]nt Prairie [Arkansas]</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="11-03-1821">Nov 3d 1821</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I have frequently recd letters from you in the course of the 
<date_mentioned n="Summer-1821">summer</date_mentioned>, but in consequence of your continually mooving situation I
defered answering untill now, on the <date_mentioned n="10-27-1821">27th- Oct.</date_mentioned> on my arival from
the Legislature I recd yrs of <date_mentioned n="11-10-1821">10th Inst,</date_mentioned> written at <location_mentioned>Natchitoches</location_mentioned>, in
which you requested that I go on and join <person_mentioned>Mr Bell</person_mentioned> and proceed on
to survey for the <location_mentioned>settlers</location_mentioned>듮his, be assured sir, I will attend to as
promptly as my circumstances and present situation will permit들t
is with extacy that myself and many other <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>of yours hear
of your success so far, and see the vastly flattering prospects ahead<barker_pb n="425"/>
in colonizing with enlightened and respectable <person_mentioned>citizens</person_mentioned>듮hat vast
<location_mentioned>Spanish wilderness</location_mentioned> hitherto almost unobserved and unknown듈n
two weeks from this time <person_mentioned>Jas. Clark</person_mentioned> and myself with several other
mechanics etc. will set out for <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned> to which place we will
make all possible speed, and if I can learn where you will land or
where you design laying off a Town I will proceed immediately to
the spot if nothing more important prevents having finished my
functions as a representative of the people I am perfectly at liberty
to undertake in any enterprize드nd was extremely happy to find
such demands for me in your country I shall go on prepared with
Instruments for 2 companies of <person_mentioned>surveyors </person_mentioned>to work, I said I defered
answering until now, I forgot I wrote by Col. . . [torn] who is now
on a visit to <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></hi>, but I have learned that he unfortunately did
not meet with you <hi rend="italic">The Spanish Country</hi> is all the rage in the
<location_mentioned>southern end of the Territory</location_mentioned> and if I could wait 2 months I have
no doubt that my company would consist of <person_mentioned>50 persons</person_mentioned>, most of
whom would intend making corn before their return If no 
interruption in government takes place, a great many of the most 
respectable farmers in this country will certainly moove immediately on to
your grant. I with the rest of your friends will do all we can to
forward emmigration. I shall take on some medicines and wish you
to buy <person_mentioned>Thomas</person_mentioned>'s practice if convenient and take it on for me, we
will attend to having your Trunk and books sent on which is at
<person_mentioned>Vaughn</person_mentioned>'s under some little imbarrisment. It is not necessary to
write much at present suffice it to say that between the <date_mentioned n="12-10-1821">10th </date_mentioned>and
<date_mentioned n="12-15-1821">15th of Decr</date_mentioned> I will be at <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned> and on the <date_mentioned n="12-25-1821">25th</date_mentioned> could be at the
<location_mentioned>coast </location_mentioned>if necessary듈 write now in order to let you know that I will
certainly be in your country that you may know how to make any
arangements that may depend on me듈 wish to get imploy if any
there is both for myself and some other young men who will go on
with me듕e will meet if God . . . [permits]. [I will then] have
a full opportunity [of talking to you] on matters of moment 
[Permit me] to present the good wishes of a large [Majori?]ty of our
county드lso those with deep sencerity of</p>

<p><person_mentioned>R. Andrews</person_mentioned>    [Rubric]</p>
<p>[Addressed:]<person_mentioned> Hon. Stephen F Austin Esqr</person_mentioned>   Late of <location_mentioned>Arkansas</location_mentioned>, now
at <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned>  </p> 
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
