
<TEI.2 id="APB0022">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-20-1796</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 28-29</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Partnership Agreement</document_type>
<document_author>Moses Austin, Thomas Norvell, and Parsons Bates</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Unknown</document_recipient>
<document_title>Moses Austin, Thomas Norvell, and Parsons Bates to Unknown, 04-20-1796</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Moses Austin, Parsons Bates, and Thomas Norvell.   Button factory at Richmond.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 28-29</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-12-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0022T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Moses Austin, Parsons Bates, and Thomas Norvell.   Button factory at Richmond.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>Partnership Agreement</p>

<p>Memorandum of an agreement made and enterd into this <date_mentioned n="04-20-1796">20th. day
of april 1796</date_mentioned> Between <person_mentioned>Moses Austin</person_mentioned> on the one part and <person_mentioned>Thomas
Norvell</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Parsons Bates</person_mentioned> of the other Witnesseth That the said
<person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>and the said <person_mentioned>Norvell </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Bates </person_mentioned>doth covenant and agree each
with the other to establish a button manufactory in the city of 
<location_mentioned>Richmond </location_mentioned>which shall be under the firm [name] of <person_mentioned>Parsons Bates and
Company</person_mentioned> to continue for the term of one year from the date hereof
under the management of the said <person_mentioned>Norvell and Bates</person_mentioned> as follows the
said <person_mentioned>Bates </person_mentioned>shall attend to the workmanship in said factory with the<barker_pb n="29"/>
strictest attention for the benefit of said <person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>and the said 
<person_mentioned>Norvell </person_mentioned>shall attend to the out business with the strictest attention for
the interest of said <person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>and shall open a sett of books and keep
such account as shall appear necessary for the advantage of the
company and all expences arising necessarily for the advantage of
the business shall be equally devided and paid by each and at the
experation of the year the books shall be settled up, and the profits
or losses shall be equally shared after paying the said <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>out of
the joint stock such advances as he shall make in furnishing and
keeping the business supplyd with the necessary stock. The said
<person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>doth agree on his part to furnish the <person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>with as
much stock as shall be necessary to put the said business in motion
and keep it supplyd untill it shall be enabled to make such advances
as may be necessary for the carrying on said business to advantage
the said <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>doth also agree to furnish a <location_mentioned>store house</location_mentioned> free from any
expence to the <person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>for the purpose of Carrying on said business</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Thomas Norvell.</person_mentioned>                  [seal]</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Parsons Bates</person_mentioned>                     [seal]</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Moses Austin</person_mentioned>    [Rubric]    [seal]</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
