
<TEI.2 id="APB0546">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-22-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 554-555</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Edward Lovelace</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Edward Lovelace, 11-22-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Mexico City, MX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Summary of political movements in Mexico. Difficulty over the status of slavery. Mexicans not prepared for a republican government.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>But compare Lovelace to Austin, June 28, 1822.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 554-555</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0546T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Summary of political movements in Mexico. Difficulty over the status of slavery. Mexicans not prepared for a republican government.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>City of Mexico</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="11-22-1822">November 22nd 1822</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p>When I arrived here <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>were sitting but progressing
very slowly, the discord and jealousy manifested from the first day
of the session of <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>against the <person_mentioned>Generalissimo Iturbide</person_mentioned> (now
<person_mentioned>Emperor</person_mentioned>) was increasing daily and everything was at a stand -
There were three distinct <person_mentioned>parties in Congress</person_mentioned>, one for a <person_mentioned>Bourbon
King</person_mentioned>, one for an <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>from this country, and the other for a
<person_mentioned>Republic</person_mentioned>, in this state of things the <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>was approximating
towards Anarchy, when on the night of the <date_mentioned n="05-18-1822">18 of May</date_mentioned> the <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned>
stationed in this city proclaimed <person_mentioned>Iturbide Emperor</person_mentioned>, the next day
<person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>elected him in due form and on the <date_mentioned n="05-21-1822">21</date_mentioned> he took the oath,
these things put a stop to all business for some time - Agreeably to
the <person_mentioned>Emperor</person_mentioned>s Oath he could do nothing without the consent of 
<person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>and this body moved most astonishingly slow and were more
occupied in watching the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>than in attending to the interest
of the country - On the <date_mentioned n="07-21-1822">21 July</date_mentioned> the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>was crowned, and
very soon after serious collisions began to arise between him and
<person_mentioned>Congress</person_mentioned>, the latter wished to keep all power in their hands and
things were getting worse every day all was at a dead stand, for
<person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>would do nothing for fear of granting a little power to
the <person_mentioned>executive</person_mentioned>, and the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>could do nothing so long as 
<person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>existed without its sanction - In this state of things it was in
vain for an individual to urge his business, however important and
mine with all other individual applications was laid on one side—
Matters progressed in this manner from bad to worse and were
again verging towards Anarchy; one dangerous conspiracy was 
discovered and quelled by the imprisonment of about 70, amongst whom
were 20 <person_mentioned>members of Congress</person_mentioned> and at length finding that nothing
but an extraordinary and desicive step could save the nation from
the confusion and the established government from ruin, the 
<person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>desolved <person_mentioned>congress </person_mentioned>by a decree of his own on the <date_mentioned n="10-31-1822">31 of October</date_mentioned>
last and created a national <person_mentioned>Junta </person_mentioned>of his own choosing from amongst<barker_pb n="555"/>
the <person_mentioned>members of Congress</person_mentioned> - since then things have gone on better
and with more harmony - My business relative to the <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>is
now acting on and in less than 10 days I shall be dispatched with
everything freely arranged. The principal difficulty is slavery, this
they will not admit - as the law is all <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>are to be free in ten
years, but I am trying to have it amended so as to make them <person_mentioned>slaves</person_mentioned>
for life and their <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>free at 21 years - but do not think I shall
succeed in this point, and that the law will pass as it now is, that is,
that the <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>introduced by the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>shall be free after 10
years - As regards all other matters there will be no difficulty, I will
write you again from here after I get through and let you know
the particulars. I am doubtful nothing can be done about getting
land at or near <location_mentioned>Galveston</location_mentioned>, the <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>seems opposed to any 
<location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>being formed so near the <location_mentioned>borders of the United States</location_mentioned>, when
I return to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>I will write you very fully - you must not be
frightened at the name of an <person_mentioned>Imperial government</person_mentioned>, you like myself
have lived under a Monarchy, when <location_mentioned>Louisiana </location_mentioned>belonged to <location_mentioned>Spain </location_mentioned>and
I think we lived as happy then as under the <person_mentioned>government of the
<location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> - The <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>has his <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>and in the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>
the <person_mentioned>Democrats </person_mentioned>will abuse him no doubt, but he is doing the best for
his country. These people will not do for a <person_mentioned>Republic </person_mentioned>nothing but a
Monarchy can save them from Anarchy -</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>This is a true copy of the letter, recd from <person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned>.
Received from <person_mentioned>Mrs. Bell</person_mentioned> and I presume was addressed to her</p>

<p><person_mentioned>husband </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Josiah H Bell</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Guy M Bryan </person_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
