
<TEI.2 id="APB0219">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-21-1812</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 211-213</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Maria Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Moses Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Maria Austin to Moses Austin, 06-21-1812</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Philadelphia, PA</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Burton Mine, LA</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Declaration of War with England. Anxiety.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Mrs. Austin left Missouri in June, 1811, and was absent in Philadelphia, Camden,
New York, and New Haven until 1813. Mrs. Emmett L. Perry has in her possession
twenty-five letters written by Mrs. Austin to her husband during this period. They have
considerable value for phases of the social history of those cities.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 211-213</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-30-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0219T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Declaration of War with England. Anxiety.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Philadelphia</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="06-21-1812">June the 21-1812</date_mentioned></p>
<p>it tis with heart felt sorrow I take up my pen to Inform my dear
<person_mentioned>Husband </person_mentioned>that, <hi rend="italic">War</hi>, is Absolutely declared, the <person_mentioned>Express </person_mentioned>arrived
from <location_mentioned>Washington </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="06-20-1812">last Evening</date_mentioned>, and in a little time all will be in
bussel and Confusion—I have always dreaded a war so much, I
could not allow myself to think their would be Declaration of it—
but it tis two true—and my fears for my Dr <person_mentioned>friends in <location_mentioned>Louisianna</location_mentioned></person_mentioned><barker_pb n="212"/>
is now greater than theay ever have beene—it, will now be the 
Interest of the <person_mentioned>British </person_mentioned>to Urge on the <person_mentioned>Savages </person_mentioned>and O I greatly fear
the Consequences will be dreadfull—I am also Extreamly Unhappy
on our <person_mentioned>Son</person_mentioned>s account—least he should be taken on his Voyage and
should this Unfortunately happen, your famaly here will be in a
very Unpleasant Situation, in short we shall be holy Dependent on
our <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>, who Sertinly are very good and kind at present, but was
I to be deprived of those Remittances you are Sending on, I know
not what Change might take place, however I will not Anticipate
so great a Misfortune, but Indeed my dear it gives me Inexpressable
Uneasiness—I wrote you a long letter which I Expected to have sent
by <person_mentioned>Major Penrose</person_mentioned>, he being detained I sent it by post also a letter
to <person_mentioned>Sister Peggy</person_mentioned>—I gave up all hope of Seeing <person_mentioned>Sister Becca</person_mentioned> in the
<location_mentioned>City</location_mentioned>—and after waiting for hur two weeks—I went to <location_mentioned>Jersey </location_mentioned>where
I meant to stay till <person_mentioned>Stephen </person_mentioned>arrived—but two days ago, <person_mentioned>Sister </person_mentioned>came
up, and as soon as I got word of her arrival I Came to town, and
had the pleasure to find hur in perty good health—if any misfortune
should befal our dr <person_mentioned>Son</person_mentioned>—I should go to <location_mentioned>Dellaware </location_mentioned>with hur and
run the Chance of my health—for I should fell better sattisfyd
with a <person_mentioned>Sister </person_mentioned>in the Situation I should be placed in, than with any
other person—I received a letter from <person_mentioned>Mr Whittlesey</person_mentioned> a few days
past—he Informs me my dear <person_mentioned>little B [Brown Austin]</person_mentioned> is in good
Health but that a verry dangerous disease had raged with great
violence in that part of the <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>and that <person_mentioned>Mrs W—</person_mentioned> had been at
deaths dore with the fatal disorder—which was the cause of hur
not answering my letter I wrote from <location_mentioned>N York</location_mentioned>—at the same time he
beges me not to be alarmed on <person_mentioned>James [i. e., James Brown Austin]</person_mentioned>
Account, that he is in perfect health, grows and improves verry
fast, and that the fever is now Subsiding—Notwithstanding this I
am very unhappy least our dear boy should be taken ill, was it in
my power I think I would go on—but that is Imposably till I get
money to bare my Expences—I have many things to distress my
mind my dear <person_mentioned>Husband</person_mentioned>, in short I shall not know what happyniss
or Comfort is, till I am Restord to the Society of my <person_mentioned>Husband </person_mentioned>and
<person_mentioned>famaly</person_mentioned>—which, may the god of all goodness, Speadily grant and
in the Interam, may theay all be preserved in his holy keeping—I
am spending the day with <person_mentioned>Mrs Darah</person_mentioned> and withdrew from the 
Company to write this hasty scrall, that it might go by the Mail 
<date_mentioned n="06-22-1812">tomorrow</date_mentioned>, I thought you ought to know that war was declard <person_mentioned>Sister</person_mentioned>
Joines me in love to you and <person_mentioned>peggy</person_mentioned>—I am my dear <person_mentioned>Husband </person_mentioned>with
every sentiment of love and Anxiety your loveing <person_mentioned>Wife</person_mentioned></p>
 
<p><person_mentioned>Maria Austin.</person_mentioned></p><barker_pb n="213"/>

<p>I had a letter from <person_mentioned>Emily </person_mentioned><date_mentioned n="06-20-1812">Yesterday</date_mentioned>. She is well and in good
Spirits at the Idea of soon seeing her dear <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned>, god grant she
may not be disappointed is my prayr</p>

<p>[Address:] <person_mentioned>Mr. Moses Austin P. M.</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Mine a Burton Upper 
Louisianna</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
