
<TEI.2 id="APB0269">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>03-22-1816</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 255-258</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Circular</document_type>
<document_author>John Scott</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>John Andrews</document_recipient>
<document_title>John Scott to John Andrews, 03-22-1816</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>St Louis, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Big River</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Opening of Salines and lead mines to private purchase; abandonment of Government trading houses among Indians and opening of trade to individuals; exclusion of British traders; encouragement of immigration by reduction of price of land or by reduction of the minimum quantity purchasable; relief for ousted settlers.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 255-258</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-02-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0269T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Opening of Salines and lead mines to private purchase; abandonment of Government trading houses among Indians and opening of trade to individuals; exclusion of British traders; encouragement of immigration by reduction of price of land or by reduction of the minimum quantity purchasable; relief for ousted settlers.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>(Circular)</p>
<p>[Printed broadside.]</p>

<p>To the <person_mentioned>Citizens of <location_mentioned>Missouri Territory</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>" The period of the next election of a delegate to represent you in
the <location_mentioned>Congress of the United States </location_mentioned>being not far distant, and the time
actually arrived, when your thoughts must be employed in 
designating the person to be clothed with that important trust, I beg leave
to make you a tender of my services, and to request that I may be
considered as a <person_mentioned>candidate </person_mentioned>for your suffrage."</p>

<p>Be assured fellow <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>that this tender of my humble services
has not been made, without a strict regard to all the considerations
appertaining to the relations, that binds a good citizen to his
country.—Born a <person_mentioned>citizen </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>, now by choice one of
this <location_mentioned>territory</location_mentioned>: and being identified in the same interests, and political<barker_pb n="256"/>
principles with the mass of its population, whose friendship I have
long experienced, and sincerely reciprocated; I shall have every 
inducement to act correctly; and to regard the good of all, in 
preference to any considerations drawn from mere local situation.</p>

<p>As I am known to be a <person_mentioned>republican</person_mentioned>, I do not think it necessary to
say any thing in detail, with regard to my political principles.—
There are however some points of policy, which have been adopted
by the <person_mentioned>general government</person_mentioned>, in relation to this, and other <location_mentioned>territories</location_mentioned>,
upon which a distinct expression of my opinions and views, is due to
candor, and necessary to enable you to decide upon the correctness
of the course, which if honored with your confidence, I shall endeavor
to pursue.</p>

<p>The reservation of <location_mentioned>salt licks</location_mentioned>, and <location_mentioned>lead mines</location_mentioned> from public sale, I
consider to be inconsistent with an enlightened policy, injurious to
the general interest of this <location_mentioned>territory</location_mentioned>, and particularly oppressive
upon certain parts thereof.</p>

<p>Placed as those objects are within our <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>; it must be 
presumed that the allwise author of the universe intended them, for the
use, convenience, and benefit of its <person_mentioned>inhabitants</person_mentioned>: but the practical 
operation of the present plan of the government is calculated to 
counteract that benevolent intention, without the prospect of any real
advantage to itself, for while individuals are strictly prohibited
from using or occupying those favours bestowed upon us by a 
beneficent providence, they have heretofore remained, and without an
entire change of measures must hereafter continue to be, a useless
monopoly in the hands of the <person_mentioned>government</person_mentioned>, which is equally 
forbidden by a regard to its own interest, and by justice to its <person_mentioned>citizens</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Were proper encouragement given to our <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>to explore those
hidden resources of individual wealth, and national prosperity; no
rational man can doubt, that it would contribute infinitely more to
the true and substantial interest of the <person_mentioned>nation </person_mentioned>at large, than the
present contracted policy, which although injurious to the general
government, is at the same time ruinous to the welfare of the 
<location_mentioned>territory</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Salt being an article essentially necessary to the wants of every
description of our <person_mentioned>inhabitants</person_mentioned>, measures to render its acquisition
easy and convenient to both rich, and poor, are equally dictated by
justice, and philanthropy. Yet though our country abounds with
excellent public <location_mentioned>salines</location_mentioned>, there is no manufactory of salt established
at any one of them, either by any individual authorised by the 
government, or by the government itself. And so long as this state of
things continues, no reduction of the price, nor deminution of the
trouble, difficulty and risk of the transportation of that article can<barker_pb n="257"/>
be expected to take place but all of them must increase with the 
enlargement of our population, and the expansion of our <location_mentioned>settlements</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>This however is not all: For should such reservations be adhered
to, even the bounty of nature in providing liberally for our wants
and necessities, will be converted into the most serious injury, to a
large and respectable part of our population, for there are such a
multitude of <location_mentioned>salt licks</location_mentioned> in the <location_mentioned>county of Howard</location_mentioned>, that many of the
meritorious, and patriotic <person_mentioned>inhabitants of <location_mentioned>Boons Lick settlement</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, who
bore the brunt of the late savage war, will be driven from those
<location_mentioned>habitations</location_mentioned>, which at immense sacrifices they maintained, and 
defended, with a valor and perseverance that never has been surpassed;
and one of the fairest portions of our <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>must remain 
uncultivated, and uninhabited. Surely if <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>can be made sensible of
these serious objections to their present law, some beneficial change of
measures ought reasonably to be expected.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>indian </person_mentioned>trade, I conceive to be of vast importance to this 
<location_mentioned>Territory</location_mentioned>, and calculated to advance its prosperity more rapidly and 
certainly, than any other object within our reach. It was formerly in
the hands of the <person_mentioned>inhabitants of this country,</person_mentioned> their principal support
was derived from the prosecution of it, many of their <location_mentioned>houses </location_mentioned>(as
may be seen in our <location_mentioned>villages</location_mentioned>) were constructed for the purpose of
receiving the deposits of its proceeds: their local situation seems to
give them a natural right to participate in it—but though the 
government has not declared in explicit terms, that they shall not enjoy
that right, yet that such has been the necessary result, of the 
establishment of <location_mentioned>public factories</location_mentioned> or <location_mentioned>trading houses</location_mentioned> amongst the <person_mentioned>indians</person_mentioned>,
is well known to many, and has been severely felt, as is amply 
testified by the continued emptiness of those former depositaries of furs
and peltries.</p>

<p>The present plan of the government has been tried for several
years in succession, and has it is believed eventuated in a diminution
of the trade itself; without having produced a single advantage to
recommend its continuation; while it has greatly injured many
worthy <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>and checked their laudable enterprises, which 
otherwise would have contributed, both to their own, and the public
advantage.</p>

<p>Wishing therefore to see the <location_mentioned>public factories</location_mentioned> abolished, and all
pretext for their continuance removed, by a total and complete 
exclusion of all <person_mentioned>British traders</person_mentioned>, from any participation in the trade with
the <person_mentioned>indians</person_mentioned>, within our limits, I am decidedly in favor of 
rendering that trade as accessable as possible, to the capital, and enterprise
of our own <person_mentioned>citizens</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Anxious to see our <location_mentioned>territory </location_mentioned>freed from the shackles of colonial
dependence, I shall be in favor of every measure calculated to<barker_pb n="258"/>
facilitate, and hasten its progress to that maturity, which will enable
it to become a member of the federal Union, upon an equal footing
with the rest of the states, and for that purpose it appears to me very
desirable that all proper encouragement should be given to 
<person_mentioned>emigrants</person_mentioned>, to our <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>—the public surveying should be accelerated,
the <location_mentioned>public land</location_mentioned> offered for sale without delay, its price if possible
reduced, and at all events to be sold in as small quantities as eighty
acres, in order to accommodate that class of our <location_mentioned>citizens</location_mentioned>, who are
unable to pay for more. The opening of <location_mentioned>public roads</location_mentioned>, and 
establishing of <location_mentioned>public schools</location_mentioned>, upon such a plan as would render education
attainable by the <person_mentioned>poor</person_mentioned>, as well as the <person_mentioned>rich</person_mentioned>, (for which the 
reservations of land by the <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>are amply sufficient) would promote
the present convenience of our population, and contribute greatly to
its future increase.</p>

<p>Whatever may be the fate of the late proclamation of the 
<person_mentioned>President of the United States</person_mentioned> which menaces with serious consequences
the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>upon <location_mentioned>public lands</location_mentioned>, I shall always think that neither
justice, or policy, required that the <person_mentioned>people of this <location_mentioned>territory</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> should
be removed from <location_mentioned>lands </location_mentioned>which they had ameliorated by their labour,
and defended by their bravery, before an opportunity of buying was
afforded them; and indeed before they had received the pay which
the <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>owes them for defending even the country itself,
against our <person_mentioned>savage enemies</person_mentioned>. I hope that kind providence will ward
off the afflictive blow with which this class of our <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>are 
threatened, but should it be otherwise, they shall have my best exertions to
procure them the remedy which their case will imperiously call for,
and believing the law upon which the proclamation issued to be
unjust and unnecessary, as to the universality of its application, I
shall be in favor of its total repeal, or of such a modification of it, at
least, as will prevent a repetition of the evils at present, so greatly
and so justly dreaded.</p>

<p>These, and other regulations, such as establishing <location_mentioned>mail routs</location_mentioned>, and
<location_mentioned>post offices</location_mentioned>, &c. I believe would conduce to the interest of our country.
But I do not wish it understood, that I pledge myself to effect all,
or any part of the measures above enumerated, I only intended to
state my opinion of their propriety and utility, and my willingness,
and determination to aid in promoting them, and any other objects
of the public good. All that I can promise is, that so far as 
attention to your interest, and zeal in the maintenance thereof, can supply
the want of better talents, you shall have no cause to repent any
confidence, with which you may honor me.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>John Scott</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p><location_mentioned>St. Louis</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="03-22-1816">March 22d, 1816</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>John Andrews Esq </person_mentioned>  <location_mentioned>Big River</location_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
