
<TEI.2 id="APB0150">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-03-1809</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 154-155</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Moses Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Hart, Barton, and Hart</document_recipient>
<document_title>Moses Austin to Hart, Barton, and Hart, 05-03-1809</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Lexington, KY</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Bills of exchange and lead.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 154-155</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-28-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0150T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Bills of exchange and lead.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Mine a Burton</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="05-03-1809">May 3, 1809</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Mess Hart Barton and Hart</person_mentioned> [Lexington, Ky.]</p>

<p>Gentl I have eclos'd to you Drafts on the <person_mentioned>House of Mess.
Bellows and Cochran <location_mentioned>Boston</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> for five thousand Dollars— Which
Drafts I request you to forward on to your <person_mentioned>friends in <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>—
to be by them forwarded on to <location_mentioned>Boston </location_mentioned>for acceptance and When
accepted to have them discounted in <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned> if such a thing can
be done Which I make not a doubt provided the <person_mentioned>House in <location_mentioned>Boston</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
is of sufficient standing to justify such a confidence in them. It is
my Wish that this money may be plac'd to your Cr in <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned>
and that you accomodate me with the amount in <location_mentioned>Lexington </location_mentioned>Which
If the Bills are found good may be of no small advantage the object
of this establishment is for the shipment of large quantities of Lead
to <location_mentioned>Boston </location_mentioned>and I shall want a friend in <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>to receive and 
[forward] shipments of Lead from that place either to <location_mentioned>Boston </location_mentioned>or <location_mentioned>New
York</location_mentioned> as may best answer the objects of this Establishment it is 
intended to extend the business of shipping Lead from this Country
wherefore it becomes our object to know on What terms your <person_mentioned>House
in <location_mentioned>Orleans</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> will receive and forward Lead for the account of Myself
and friends</p><barker_pb n="155"/>

<p>I know that Bills on <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned> and <location_mentioned>Philadelphia </location_mentioned>have sold in
<location_mentioned>Lexington </location_mentioned>at an advance of from lp to 2 pre If the arrangements I
have mentioned should be faithfully executed I think great and
mutual advantage will result from this business— my object is to
carry it into immediate Execution and as soon as you can obtain
information how they are rec'd you will give me information. Money
in this <location_mentioned>County </location_mentioned>is of Great consequence and I may say greater than
in any I have been acquainted With there being no such thing as
accomodations in the money Way— in consequence of which Money
is of high Value— I Wrote you <date_mentioned n="05-02-1809">yesterday </date_mentioned>respecting the lead at
the <location_mentioned>Mouth of the Ohio</location_mentioned>— I can engage a Boat to take it on board
on condition it is not taken away before she arrives— I again
mention that to have deliver'd the Lead at the <location_mentioned>mouth of the Ohio</location_mentioned>,
by the <date_mentioned n="03-01-1809">first day of March</date_mentioned> was rendered out of the question from
the State of the season, I therefore hope and trust you will not attach
blame to me on that account. It is always my Wish to execute my
engagement prompt [ly] and with good faith, and in this light I
wish you to consider my intentions in this transaction the Barge
the took the Lead to the <location_mentioned>Ohio </location_mentioned>could not take on board the full amount
that is the 40 thousand— trusting that you Will be so good as
to give me immediate information as to the fate of my draft and
what accomodation you can make for me in <location_mentioned>Lexington </location_mentioned>and on what
terms you will receive them</p>

<p>[Moses Austin.]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
