
<TEI.2 id="APB0508">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-10-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 507-510</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Anastacio Bustamante</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Anastacio Bustamante, 05-10-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Mexico</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>American traders encourage hostility of Comanches and Lipans against Mexicans. Three routes of trade. Indians can be pacified by breaking off this commerce, supplying in its place a licensed trade under direction of Mexican Government, and strengthening the settlements of Texas.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Anastacio Bustamante was Captain General o£ the Provincias Internas</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 507-510</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0508T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>American traders encourage hostility of Comanches and Lipans against Mexicans. Three routes of trade. Indians can be pacified by breaking off this commerce, supplying in its place a licensed trade under direction of Mexican Government, and strengthening the settlements of Texas.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="05-10-1822">May 10. 1822</date_mentioned></p>
<p>The knowledge which I have obtained during my residence in the
<location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned> of the situation and disposition of the hostile 
<person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>who are harrassing it, having enabled me to make some 
observations on the causes of that hostility, and some reflections as to
the surest means of terminating it by a lasting peace; and feeling a
deep interest in the welfare of that province and of the <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>
generally; I beg leave to submit a few remarks on this subject to your
Excellency as the <person_mentioned>superior political head of the Eastern division of
the nation</person_mentioned>, feeling confident that your Paternal solicitude for the
happiness of the <location_mentioned>Provinces </location_mentioned>under your command will insure a 
favorable reception to any well founded suggestion calculated to
ameliorate their condition, and that your natural goodness of heart
will appreciate my motive and pardon me for attempting to advise
on a subject of such importance</p>

<p>The war with the <person_mentioned>Comanches </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Lipanis Indians</person_mentioned> owes its origin
to the Revolution in the <location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned> in the year <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1812">1812</date_mentioned>—those
<person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>and many others, being employed at that time by the 
<person_mentioned>Insurgents </person_mentioned>to fight the <person_mentioned>Royal forces</person_mentioned>. After the defeat of <person_mentioned>Toledo </person_mentioned>at the
<location_mentioned>River Medina</location_mentioned> and the dispersion of his <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned>, many of the <person_mentioned>old 
Inhabitants of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> fled to the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> and settled in the 
<location_mentioned>neighborhood of Nachistoches</location_mentioned> where they are now living; some of these
<person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>being well acquainted with the <person_mentioned>Comanches </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Lipanis
Indians</person_mentioned> and with the country they inhabitated, united themselves
with the <person_mentioned>American Traders at <location_mentioned>Nachistoches</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and opened a contraband
traffic with those, and other <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>living in the <location_mentioned>Province of Texas
</location_mentioned>taking out Goods and receiving Horses and Mules in exchange—This<barker_pb n="508"/>
trade was found to be very lucrative to those engaged in it, and the
<person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>finding a good market for their Horses and Mules, were 
encouraged to prosecute a plundering war against the <location_mentioned>frontiers of
Texas</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Quahuila</location_mentioned>, and <location_mentioned>Nuevo Santender</location_mentioned>, robbing those <location_mentioned>Provinces </location_mentioned>of
Horses and Mules to sell to the <person_mentioned>traders </person_mentioned>for Merchandise and this 
traffic having continued up to the present time is the real cause of the
continuation of the <person_mentioned>Comanche </person_mentioned>war— It therefore being a war of
individual interest to the <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>will never cease until that 
interest is distroyed, by stoping the <person_mentioned>Indian </person_mentioned>trade as it is now carried on,
and confining it to a particular channel where it would be under
the immediate control of <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p>There are three routes by which mules are introduced into the
<location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> from the <person_mentioned>Comanches</person_mentioned>—one is by <location_mentioned>Nacodoches</location_mentioned>, another
is by <location_mentioned>Pecon Point</location_mentioned> on <location_mentioned>Red River </location_mentioned>above <location_mentioned>Nachistoches</location_mentioned>, and the third
route is to the north by way of the <location_mentioned>Kansas River</location_mentioned> to the <location_mentioned>Missouri
River</location_mentioned>, the trade on this last route is principally carried on by 
<person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>from one <person_mentioned>nation </person_mentioned>to another until the mules reach the 
<location_mentioned>Missouri </location_mentioned>where they are bought by <person_mentioned>American traders</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p>The first route by <location_mentioned>Nacogdoches </location_mentioned>can be easily stoped by a 
<location_mentioned>Garrison </location_mentioned>at that place—the second route by <location_mentioned>Pecon Point</location_mentioned> can also be
stoped by a <location_mentioned>Garrison </location_mentioned>on the <location_mentioned>bank of Red River</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>oposite the mouth
of the Kiamiche River</location_mentioned> where there is a good situation—oposite to
this place within the limits of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> there is a <location_mentioned>settlement</location_mentioned>
of about <person_mentioned>two hundred families</person_mentioned> who are included within the limits of a
district of <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>which has lately been ceded by the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>
to the <person_mentioned>Choctaw Indians</person_mentioned>, those <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>would willingly remove and
settle round the <location_mentioned>Fort at Pecon Point</location_mentioned> and in a short time would supply
the <location_mentioned>Garrison </location_mentioned>with Provisions—</p>

<p>The third route to the north by way of the <location_mentioned>River Kansas</location_mentioned> to the
<location_mentioned>Missouri </location_mentioned>is more difficult to stop, the only effectual way of doing it
that I can see is by representing the iniquity of this trade to the
<person_mentioned>Government of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and getting an order from that
<person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>prohibiting their <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>from buying Horses or Mules
introduced from the <person_mentioned>Comanches </person_mentioned>either by this or any other route—It
is an established principle in the law of nations, and one that has
been repeatedly recognized and enforced by the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> that
where two nations are at peace, the <person_mentioned>Citizens </person_mentioned>of one, can not fit out
within its limits, an expedition with an intention of making war,
or aiding to make war against the other—now this principle will
apply to the <person_mentioned>Comanche </person_mentioned>trade—The <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> and this <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>
are at peace, and are united by the strongest ties of friendship—The
<person_mentioned>traders from the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> fit out <person_mentioned>expeditions </person_mentioned>to the <person_mentioned>Comanches</person_mentioned>
and other nations of <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>who are at war with this <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, and
not only furnish them with arms and amunition to carry on the
wars but actually hire them to pillage the <location_mentioned>frontiers </location_mentioned>by purchasing <barker_pb n="509"/>
the fruits of that pillage—and therefore, these trading expeditions
are fitted out for the express purpose of annoying a nation with
whom the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> are at peace, and is evidently contrary to the
above principle of the law of Nations—</p>

<p>Another view of this Subject is that this trade is a species of land
Piracy which is carried on by those <person_mentioned>traders </person_mentioned>against the <person_mentioned>Citizens </person_mentioned>of
this nation, for it amounts to the same thing whether those <person_mentioned>traders</person_mentioned>
plunder Mules themselves, or hire the <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>to do it—I therefore
have no doubt that if this subject was represented to the <person_mentioned>Government
of the United States</person_mentioned>, that a law would be passed which would 
effectually stop this iniquitous traffic—</p>

<p>After the avenues by which this trade have heretofore been 
carried on are closed, there will still be two other important objects to
effect before a permanent peace can be relied on, One is, the 
establishment of a regular system by which those <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>could be 
supplied with Goods, and other necessary articles which they have 
heretofore received from the <person_mentioned>American traders</person_mentioned>, and without which they
will not be satisfied—The other is, to strengthen the <location_mentioned>Province of
Texas</location_mentioned> by fostering the <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>which is already formed on the
<location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Brazos </location_mentioned>by me, and encouraging the introduction of
more <location_mentioned>settlers</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>In conversing with the <person_mentioned>Baron de Bastrop</person_mentioned>, and several other 
<person_mentioned>citizens of <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> on this subject I suggested several methods of 
regulating the <person_mentioned>Indian </person_mentioned>trade,—One was to incorporate a <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>to whom
the whole <person_mentioned>Indian </person_mentioned>trade of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and of the <location_mentioned>Rio Grande Del Norte</location_mentioned>
should be given—This <person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>by having fixed laws for its 
regulation could concentrate and control the <person_mentioned>Indian </person_mentioned>trade, and thereby
prevent abuses.—Another method was for the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>to 
establish <location_mentioned>factories </location_mentioned>at convenient points, where constant supplies could be
kept for the <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>. And a fourth plan was to grant Licenses to
Individuals to carry on said trade each <person_mentioned>trader </person_mentioned>to furnish his own 
capital and to be independent of each other—of these plans I think the
first one by the incorporation of a <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>the best, for if a liberal
charter was granted to the <person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>foreigners </person_mentioned>permitted to hold
Stock in it, I have no doubt that a sufficient Capital could be raised
in the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> to effect all the objects required, and the trade
could be Managed so as to be profitable to the <person_mentioned>Company</person_mentioned>, and usefull
to this <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>—Should this plan meet the views of the 
<person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>I would submit the outlines of A Charter which I think would
embrace all the objects necessary, and should the charter be granted
I could be of some use in aiding to raise the Capital by inducing 
<person_mentioned>Merchants </person_mentioned>in the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> to take the Stock.</p>

<p>There is one thing more necessary besides regulating the trade
to insure a lasting peace with the <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>, and that is to strengthen
the <location_mentioned>settlements </location_mentioned>of that <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned>, so as to enable it to overpower and<barker_pb n="510"/>
subdue the <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>, if they still continue hostile this can be done,
and the whole <location_mentioned>frontier of the Eastern Provinces</location_mentioned> defended with little
or no expense to the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>If the <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>will grant me the privilege of settling the 
district of Country designated in my Memorial, I will obligate myself
as stated in my memorial to organize the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>into <person_mentioned>Rifle Companies</person_mentioned>
and arm them, and to hold them in readiness at all times to march
against the <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>within said <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>whenever called on—These
<person_mentioned>companies </person_mentioned>will be sufficient in conjunction with the regular <person_mentioned>troops
and militia of the <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to subdue the <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>and keep them
at peace.</p>

<p>[The following paragraph Austin deleted]</p>

<p>The organizing of these <person_mentioned>Rifle Companies</person_mentioned> with arms ready for
service, and the other services mentioned in my memorial, which
I have agreed to render the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, I hope may be considered a
sufficient equivalent for the privileges asked for in that memorial-
Having been the first who commenced the settlement of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>I
feel great anxiety that the settlement should succeed and my 
experience on this subject, and the examples which history afford of
the difficulty of forming a <location_mentioned>settlement in a wilderness</location_mentioned> has convinced
me that the first establishment in a <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>Inhabited by <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>
cannot succeed unless it is very strong, and under the direction of
one individual, for a multiplicity of directors in the same 
establishment will produce confusion and division, and there will neither
be that security or progress in improvement which would arise from
system union and consert in all the motions of the <location_mentioned>settlers </location_mentioned>a thing
which can only be produced by assigning the formation of the first
settlement within particular limits to one person—</p>

<p>The welfare of the new <person_mentioned>Settlers </person_mentioned>which I have brought into <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
is closely connected with these subjects We are all equally interested
in procuring a peace with the <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>, I therefore offer my services
in any way that the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>may want them towards effecting
this desirable object, or in any other manner in which I can render
any service to the nation</p>

<p>With considerations of the most profound Respect I am your
Excellencys most obt. Humble servt.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
