
<TEI.2 id="APB0309">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>03-04-1818</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 329</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>William M. O'Hara</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to William M. O'Hara, 03-04-1818</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Herculaneum</sent_from>
	<sent_to>St. Louis, MO</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>New Madrid land certificates.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From the Darby Collection, Missouri Historical Society. For this and the other
letters from the Missouri Historical Society I am indebted to the kindness of Miss Stella
M. Drumm, Librarian.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 329</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-06-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0309T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>New Madrid land certificates.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Herculanium </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="03-04-1818">March 4, 1818</date_mentioned>.</p>
<p>Dr. <person_mentioned>Friend</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p>My Brother <person_mentioned>James B. Austin</person_mentioned> will hand you this by whom you
can send the paper for me- I expect to start from here in the
course of next week, but have some business yet unfinished that will
require my presence at the <location_mentioned>mines</location_mentioned>. I have a favor to ask of you
which will greatly oblige me, and hasten my departure, which is of
great consequence to us both - that is to lend me one hundred and
fifty Dollars<hi rend="italic"> for ten days</hi>, - I have money owe me from various
sources which will come in before, or by that time (some of it on
judgements which must be collected by then)- but I have 150 Dols to
pay in a day or two which must be paid- and I have not the money
nor can I get it without spending time which ought to be employed
in preparations for the trip- you may positively rely on getting
it back again in ten days should you be obliged to have it in that
time- and you will confer a particular favor on me-</p>

<p>I have nothing more to say as to our speculations below, and I
think it would be safest not to make any more locations until I go
down I am trying to arrange my affairs so as to go immediately
down by land- which I shall be able to do if I could raise about
150 Dols- which I hope you will lend me- Enclosed is a recept for it-</p>

<p>The money must be <hi rend="italic">Bankable</hi>, as none other will do</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>W. M. Ohara</person_mentioned></p>

<p>My <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>was unable to go up I have therefore sent the <person_mentioned>negro
Boy </person_mentioned><hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Baptiste</person_mentioned></hi>, to whom you will please deliver the letter to me - also
please direct him to <person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">Robert </hi>Wash</person_mentioned>, and also please dispatch him as
soon as possible</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<p>[Endorsed:] <person_mentioned>Mr. Will. M. Ohara</person_mentioned>    <location_mentioned>St. Louis</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
