
<TEI.2 id="APB0750">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-24-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 800</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Alcalde</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Alcalde, 05-24-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Transmitting civil and criminal code approved by political chief. Judicial procedure. Indian policy.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Printed in <hi rend="italic">A Comprehensive History of Texas</hi>, I, 481-492.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 800</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-17-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0750T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin to [alcalde], May [24], 1824. Transmitting civil and criminal code approved by political chief.   Judicial procedure.   Indian policy.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><date_mentioned n="05-xx-1824">May [24] 1824</date_mentioned></p>
<p>I enclose to you the temporary and provisional regulations 
approved by the <person_mentioned>Political Chief of this <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> which are to 
govern for the present and untill we receive copies of the laws-—You
will post them up in a secure place in your <location_mentioned>House </location_mentioned>where all may
read them, and in all cases that may occur be regulated by them</p>

<p>It should be your particular attention to try in all cases to effect
a compromise between parties and to discourage litigation as much
as possible and endeavor by gentle and persuasive means to 
preserve harmony between the <person_mentioned>inhabitants of your <location_mentioned>District</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and 
reconcile any little neighborhood difficulties without lawrsuits—The 
common good of us all most imperiously requires that we should 
establish a general character for sobriety, industry and Harmony, And
it is the duty of the <person_mentioned>Alcalde</person_mentioned>, and of every good man to 
discountenance every thing that tends to breed disorder or to interrupt the
harmony of a neighborhood.</p>

<p>You will appoint a <person_mentioned>Constable </person_mentioned>for your <location_mentioned>district </location_mentioned>and take a bond
with securities from him as is directed by the I Article of the
Civil regulations and make a return thereof to me—Should any
thing remarkable occur you will give me information thereof.—
Be attentive to cultivate the most friendly understanding with the
<person_mentioned>Coshatta </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Choctaw Indians</person_mentioned> in your <location_mentioned>neighborhood </location_mentioned>and inform
them that the <person_mentioned>americans </person_mentioned>consider them as their <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>and 
<person_mentioned>Brothers</person_mentioned>—It should be the particular care of every one to treat all the
<person_mentioned>Spaniards </person_mentioned>who behave properly with attention and respect, 
avoiding as Much as possible all difficulties or disputes with them, to effect
this much caution is necessary in trading with them particularly for
Horses and Mules and the safest rule is not to purchace from them
at all unless the Horse or mule in counter-branded for otherwise
the purchacer runs the risk of loosing him.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
