
<TEI.2 id="APB0331">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-07-1819</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 342-343</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>William O'Hara</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to William O'Hara, 04-07-1819</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Herculaneum, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>St. Louis, MO</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Financial difficulties. Departure for Arkansas. Bank of St. Louis.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Darby collection, Missouri Historical Society</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 342-343</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-08-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0331T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Financial difficulties. Departure for Arkansas. Bank of St. Louis.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Hercum </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="04-07-1819">April 7, 1819</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p>I have recd yours by <person_mentioned>T Collet</person_mentioned>—the Power of Attorney given me
to sell lots &c is agreeably to your request herewith returned— I
should very willingly take the claim of 640 acres for Stock but I
have it not to spare— When I borrowed the 150$ from you I had
every assurance that men could give that I should have <hi rend="italic">that</hi>, and
a much greater amnt before this time—I have been disappointed—
I have sent you enclosed a power of Attorney to sell <hi rend="italic">three Shares of
Bank Stock</hi>—Collet tells me it is worth 85. to go if so, <hi rend="italic">2 shares</hi> will
more than pay the 150.$ however raise the 150.$ out of the stock
if it takes <hi rend="italic">all three shares</hi> I depend on your getting the best price
you can for them— I have been greatly disappointed—perplexed and
delayed in my arrangements, but Shall be off I think on Sunday—
I do not wish you to purchase any more claims on our agreement
untill you hear from me after my arrival at <location_mentioned>Red River</location_mentioned>,-— the 
arrangement with <person_mentioned>Browne </person_mentioned>I suppose is only conditional, I shall try to
sell some claims for <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Clark </person_mentioned></hi>when I arrive there and if a prise can be
had that will justify I will send up an express</p>

<p>My route will be from here to <location_mentioned>Red River</location_mentioned> by water, thence 
immediately after my arrival, to the <location_mentioned>oucita </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Arkansaw </location_mentioned>by land and
through the country as occation may require— I wrote you some
time ago by <person_mentioned>Doctor R. Andrews</person_mentioned>, proposing to give him a share in
our <location_mentioned>Washitaw </location_mentioned>location on certain terms mentioned therein— on this
subject you can act as you think proper— if andrews could be 
appointed <person_mentioned>deputy Surveyor</person_mentioned> to lay off our tracts, it would be much to
our advantage-</p>

<p>have you heard anything from <person_mentioned>T. Rector</person_mentioned> since his return, or any
other person, wheither the country at the <location_mentioned>Little Rock</location_mentioned>, or on <location_mentioned>washitaw</location_mentioned>
<location_mentioned>at the mouth of the Caddo</location_mentioned> or on <location_mentioned>Red River </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>at the mouth of Little
River</location_mentioned> has been <hi rend="italic">surveyed</hi>, or wheither order of survey can be had for
our locations this point is material I would take the 640 acres for
Stock but my <person_mentioned>Father </person_mentioned>wishes to appropriate all the Stock he has to
discharge his Bank debt— After I arrive where I can get 
information that will be of use to us, you may expect to hear from me very
often— I regret much that it has been out of my power to send the
150.$, but, <hi rend="italic">so it is</hi>—- I am very much embarrased, as every cent I owe
in the Country must be paid before I can start— and I have now
nearly settled all my affairs— My bank debt will be arranged by my
father who has assured the payment of it, and when I start I shall
be able to go nearly <hi rend="italic">quite free</hi> the period of my return to this 
country is some what doubtfull, tho, probably in the <date_mentioned n="Fall-1819">fall</date_mentioned>—    however<barker_pb n="343"/>
should I find it necessary to come up on our business I shall do so,
on this subject however I shall act as occation may require.</p>

<p>If you have an opportunity before Sunday morning write me, and
say what is the state of the <location_mentioned>Bank</location_mentioned>, have you heard from <person_mentioned>Price</person_mentioned>, have
[you] heard who are the <person_mentioned>officers of <location_mentioned>Arkansaw Territory</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>— what ammt
of claims have you purchased since I left you the payments and also
what prospect there is of getting an order of Survey—</p>

<p>Compliments to <person_mentioned>Mrs. Ohara</person_mentioned> and your <person_mentioned>Mother</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Mr. William M Ohara</person_mentioned><location_mentioned> St Louis</location_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
