
<TEI.2 id="APB0558">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>01-23-1823</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 572-574</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Arthur G. Wavell</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Arthur G. Wavell to Stephen F. Austin, 01-23-1823</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Horwood House, England</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Recent "wildcat" speculation in Spanish America has made English capital cautious. Wants confirmation of grant, description of coast, map, etc. Plans to export timber from Texas.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 572-574</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0558T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Recent "wildcat" speculation in Spanish America has made English capital cautious. Wants confirmation of grant, description of coast, map, etc. Plans to export timber from Texas.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Horwood House</location_mentioned></p>

<p><date_mentioned n="01-23-1823">23 Jany 1823</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Not a single line from you or any soul in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>has reached me
since my arrival in this country and I leave you to guess what anxiety
I feel to receive intelligence relative to the state of the Country and
of our concerns. The infernal <person_mentioned>Pirates </person_mentioned>have done us an incalculable
injury at least for the present [thou]gh as I before informed you<barker_pb n="573"/>
whenever I can produce sufficient proof of our possessing the land
to enable me to sell a part we will as the <person_mentioned>sailors </person_mentioned>say make up our
lee-way with a wet sail, since I trust our fortunes will ere long be
made—We shall I trust then be enabled to do without any <person_mentioned>partners</person_mentioned>
but if we have any they shall be such as to give us no trouble about
business in any but that liberal Gentlemanly way which would be
consonant writh our feelings and interests the papers are at present
indeed in the hands of a <person_mentioned>gentleman of very large fortune</person_mentioned> who will
possibly join us in the speculation but two very unfavorable events
have occurred which throw very serious obstacles in the way of the
accomplishment of our schemes, The <person_mentioned>Columbian Govt. Agent </person_mentioned>raised
a loan in this Country a short time since which that <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>. now in
part disavows which has tended to discredit beyond measure the
character and good faith of <person_mentioned>Spanish Americans</person_mentioned> in general and a
<person_mentioned>Scotchman </person_mentioned>by the name of <person_mentioned>Macgregor </person_mentioned>has of late raised a loan on
a tract of land which he states to be ceded to him by the <person_mentioned>Chief of
some Indian Nation</person_mentioned> on the <location_mentioned>Mosquito Shore</location_mentioned> the fever [got up and
he] received they state about 20,000£ but the bubble has burst and
all the <person_mentioned>speculators </person_mentioned>are anxious to get rid of the business in addition
to which the <person_mentioned>Pirates </person_mentioned>have been so successful and hitherto 
uncontrolled that few now venture to risk property in the <location_mentioned>Gulf of Mexico</location_mentioned>
Therefore we must have a little patience although I much fear it
will be irksome to you to remain in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>doing little or nothing.
With regard to Mining that will be I trust effected on a very grand
scale since <person_mentioned>merchants </person_mentioned>have enabled me to make very advantageous
proposals, and for an immense sum of money five or ten millions of
Dollars [the] very moment I can bring our schemes to bear every thing
[realised] on your [part] shall be sent to you indeed the very 
moment I receive an answer to my late dispatches from <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>I will
forward to you a full statement and will do every thing en debida
forma. Pray send on as soon as possible a plan of the <location_mentioned>estate </location_mentioned>and of
the <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>with as full a detail of the weather on the <location_mentioned>Coast</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>entrance
of rivers </location_mentioned>etc., etc. as you so well know as can be porcured also EVERY
EVERY <hi rend="italic">thing </hi>relative to the price at which you can afford Timber of
what dimensions and description since the <location_mentioned>forests </location_mentioned>alone shall I 
intend furnish us with fortunes as large as we could wish when you
give me sufficient [information to enter] into contracts in this 
country on this subject you cannot be too explicit also where when and
how Vessels could take it in I suspect large ships will not with
saftey lye opposite the <location_mentioned>mouths of the Rivers</location_mentioned> during the <hi rend="italic">Summer </hi>and
it be rafted down to them. Let us not be [discouraged but] put our
shoulders to the wheel and make our fortunes I promise [to work]
most indefatigably whenever enabled to do so wh[en you] write me
directing to me at <location_mentioned>105 Fenchurch Street London</location_mentioned> Papers descriptions<barker_pb n="574"/>
calculations &c &c of every sort and land and believe me ever most
faithfully yours</p>

<p><person_mentioned>A. G. Wavell</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed] <person_mentioned>Stephen F Austin Esq.</person_mentioned> to the care of <person_mentioned>J. H. Hawkins
Esq.</person_mentioned> [New] <location_mentioned>Orleans   </location_mentioned>pr <person_mentioned>Maria</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Forwarded by your most obt servt <location_mentioned>Liverpool </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="01-27-1823">27 Jan 1823</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>R. McNeel</person_mentioned></p>

<p>I am at present at my <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>father</person_mentioned>s </location_mentioned>but shall return to <location_mentioned>London </location_mentioned>in a very
few days [more] . . . [torn] our <location_mentioned>mines </location_mentioned>and seen the new Steam 
Engines <hi rend="italic">very much improved</hi> we have one hear of a <hi rend="italic">400 horse power</hi>
</p></div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
