
<TEI.2 id="APB0556">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>01-16-1823</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 568-572</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Junta Instituyente</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Junta Instituyente, 01-16-1823</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Mexico City, MX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>The nature of government. The Junta has no authority to frame a constitution. Suggests constitutional congress.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Whether this document, in translation, was ever presented to the Junta is not known.
More probably Austin merely gave it to some member of the Junta with whom he was on confidential terms.

The declaration of revolution by Father Miguel Hidalgo y Costilla, September 16, 1810.

The Emperor, Iturbide.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 568-572</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0556T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>The nature of government. The Junta has no authority to frame a constitution. Suggests constitutional congress.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>The objects of the war which has raged within the limits of this
extended <location_mentioned>Empire</location_mentioned>, since the ever memorable and glorious cry which
was raised in <location_mentioned>Dolores</location_mentioned>, in favor of the rights of Man, and the 
independence of <location_mentioned>Anahuac</location_mentioned>, has undoubtedly been the happiness of the
<person_mentioned>Mexican people</person_mentioned>. Unfortunately, the arbitrary power of <location_mentioned>Spain</location_mentioned>, a
power founded in its origin in usurpation dessolation and blood, and
continued by injustice and oppression, to [by] intrigue and 
corruption, prolonged the struggle for independence untill the <person_mentioned>Hero of
<location_mentioned>Iguala</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> devised a plan, which uniting all interests and all <person_mentioned>parties</person_mentioned>
effected the long desired emancipation in a few months.</p>

<p>All that then remained to complete the happiness of the 
<person_mentioned>Mexican people</person_mentioned>, was the establishment of a system of Government, which
would effectually secure to them and their posterity, the rich reward
of so many years of toil, so many sacrifices and the ... [A line
is lost here.]</p>

<p>Although the <location_mentioned>Empire </location_mentioned>has been absolutely independent for two
years, this great and paramount object of all their labours remains
yet uncompleted. This delay in the organization and consolidation
of the Government, if unavoidable is one of the greatest misfortunes
that could have befallen the nation; short of the total loss of its 
independence ; and if it has been produced by intrigue, corruption, force,
ambition, or any other means tending to blind the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>, or usurp
their rights for the purpose of individual agrandisement and the
establishment of despotic power; it is a crime which merits the 
execration of every honest man, and the vengence of the injured and insulted
nation. The most pernicious concequences have already resulted
from this illtimed procrastination the nation has even approximated
to the very brink of ruin, civil war threatens us with all its horrors;
it is even proclaimed, and unless speedily checked, may spread like a
desolating    ...    [A line is lost here.]    to a state of ruin and<barker_pb n="569"/>
Misery, the bare contemplation of which overwhelms every reflecting
and philanthropic mind with sorrow.</p>

<p>In this state of things it is the duty of all, and more especially of
the <person_mentioned>Junta Instituyente</person_mentioned> to avert the impending evils, [if practicable
and rescue the nation from the dreadful anarchy which threatens it.
The individual interest and safety, as well as the collective happiness
and prosperity of the <person_mentioned>Mexican people </person_mentioned>imperiously call upon the
<person_mentioned>Junta Instituyente</person_mentioned>, if they consider themselves to be the 
representatives of the <person_mentioned>People</person_mentioned>, to take that firm and [decisive stand which the
high and sacred responsibility of their stations as legislators 
imposes upon them. If they are not the legal representatives of the
<person_mentioned>People</person_mentioned>, they can have no legislative powers except provisional ones,
in which case the only justification for the exercise of them at all,
is the force of circumstances and the necessity of the case. But in
either situation they are charged with duties of the most sacred and
serviceable nature, duties the violation of which may involve crimes
of the deepest die, for it may involve the ruin and dessolation of their
country, the loss of its liberty, and the misery and slaughter of its
<person_mentioned>inhabitants</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>New Governments are established either [by] <hi rend="italic">force</hi>, or by <hi rend="italic">common
consent.</hi> In the former case the result is despotism, for it must be
evident that the only object of employing force in the formation of
the Government, after all foreign <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>are expelled, and 
independence secured, is to establish a particular system in opposition to
the wishes of the nation and the will of the People. In the latter
case, where the Government is formed by common consent, it must
be free, for we cannot suppose that a whole people, when left to their
own free will would ens [lave] themselves. Which of these two would
be most just or most condusive to the Gel good?</p>

<p>It is a principle founded in natural justice, and natural law, and
which therefore originated at the creation as an imprescriptable 
inheritance given by the great God of truth and justice to man and can
only cease when all [subl] unary things shall have been swept from
existence and lost in the vast ocean of eternity. " That all Government
of right originates "from the People—is founded on consent—and
is instituted " for the general good and happiness of the whole"</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>then, and they alone, have the right, and the sole right
of electing their form of Government, and forming their 
Constitution, and any intervention of force or power in opposition to their
will, is an unjust usurpation of their rights. Taking this principle for
a basis, let the question be asked have the <person_mentioned>Mexican People</person_mentioned> chosen
their form of Government?—have they formed their Constitution?</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Congress Constituyente</person_mentioned>, declared that the form of Government
should be a <hi rend="italic">Constitutional, limited, hereditary Monarchy.</hi>   And that<barker_pb n="570"/>
<person_mentioned>Don Agustín de Iturbide</person_mentioned> should be <person_mentioned>Emperor of the <location_mentioned>Empire of
Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>—But it is a principle, universally- recognised, that nothing
produced by undue and improper coertion is valid. Supposing 
therefore this act of the <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>to have been free, Spontanious and 
uninfluenced by fear or force, the <location_mentioned>mexican nation</location_mentioned> have legally chosen
their form of Government: and supposing the election of his <person_mentioned>Majesty
Don Agustin 1st</person_mentioned> to have been equally free and uninfluenced by 
improper force or power, the election of the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>is the legal act of
the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The form of Government therefore admitting the above 
suppositions to be facts has been elected by the <person_mentioned>People</person_mentioned>, and the <person_mentioned>Emperor</person_mentioned>
chosen: but the foundation, the soul of all free political institutions,
the <hi rend="italic">Constitution </hi>is still wanting. This, the people have not yet
made—they have not yet declared how the <person_mentioned>Monarchy </person_mentioned>shall be 
constituted, how the powers of the different branches of Government
shall be divided, distributed and limited, and in fact what powers
are given up to the Government by the <person_mentioned>People</person_mentioned>, and what are reserved.
The great work then of making and adopting a Constitution 
conforming to the system of Government already elected proclaimed
and sworn to is yet to be done and the want of this constitution is
the great cause of the present evils which afflict the nation.</p>

<p>The Law of nature, of reason, and of truth, is the law of God;
and that law declares that " all Government of right originates from
the People"—The <person_mentioned>People </person_mentioned>therefore have not only a right to elect
the <hi rend="italic">form </hi>of their Government and chuse their <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Emperor</person_mentioned></hi>, but also
to prescribe laws to that <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned></hi>and consolidate that <hi rend="italic">form </hi>of 
Government into a system by a <hi rend="italic">Constitution</hi>, which is the paramount law
of the <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>and the foundation of all other laws—But the <person_mentioned>People</person_mentioned>
collectively cannot assemble and debate and vote on the Constitution,
the only legal manner therefore in which it can be decreed and 
sanctioned, is by the legal Representatives of the <person_mentioned>People </person_mentioned>in <person_mentioned>Congress</person_mentioned>
assembled—</p>

<p>A free Congress of the nation unites all <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>and all interests,
except those which tend to the distruction of its independence, or the
usurpation of its liberties—No real friend of his Country therefore
ought to oppose the immediate convocation of a general Congress-
Such a measure ought at once to satisfy all parties, and thus suspend
the further progress of the civil war, which like the warning 
thunders of a volcano previous to its irruption, now threatens the 
nation—It is therefore the duty of the <person_mentioned>Junta</person_mentioned>, if they have any authority
to use it in calling a General Congress of the nation, and if they are
only <person_mentioned>councellors of the Emperor</person_mentioned> in the provisional administration
of the Government, they ought to advise his <person_mentioned>Majesty </person_mentioned>to order a new
<person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>immediately.</p><barker_pb n="571"/>

<p>But the <person_mentioned>Junta </person_mentioned>are directed by the organic basis decreed by the
<person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>at their formation to form a project of a Constitution. If
they do so, are the future Congress bound to adopt it whether they
approve of it or not? Agreeably to the golden rule herein stated the
People alone have the right of forming their Constitution: and will
any one say, that the <person_mentioned>People </person_mentioned>of this nation created the <person_mentioned>Junta</person_mentioned>, or
authorised them to form a Constitution for them?</p>

<p>All then that the <person_mentioned>Junta </person_mentioned>can legally do is to call a General 
Congress—The only thing that can unite the conflicting interests of the
nation, is a general Congress—The only legal mode of consolidating
and firmly establishing the Government, is by a General Congress—
The only power that has, or can have legal authority to form the
Constitution, is a General Congress—And all that can save the 
<location_mentioned>Nation </location_mentioned>from the horrors of a civil war is a General Congress.</p>

<p>The voice of your Country, therefore, a voice which none but
<person_mentioned>Tyrants </person_mentioned>disregard, and one which every true <person_mentioned>patriot </person_mentioned>considers as
sacred as that which spoke in thunder from Mount Sinai, calls
upon you for a General Congress. With this sacred appeal 
souning in your ears, will your consciences permit you to waste away time
so precious to the nation, in debating the project of a Constitution
which you have no right to sanction, when by so doing you 
jeopardise the peace of your country and perhaps involve it in Civil war
by delaying the Convocation of Congress?</p>

<p>Let the <person_mentioned>Junta </person_mentioned>therefore adopt the following propositions in order
to shew the <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>how far the Government is legally constituted,
what rights appertain to the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>, and what they have yet to
perform</p>

<p>1—That all Government of right originates from the <person_mentioned>People</person_mentioned>—is
founded in consent—and is instituted for the general good—</p>

<p>2—That the <person_mentioned>People </person_mentioned>by their legal representatives in Congress 
assembled have declared that the <person_mentioned>Government of the <location_mentioned>Mexican Nation</location_mentioned>
</person_mentioned>should be a Constitutional, limited, hereditary Monarchy, which
declaration was made freely without the influence of force or fear—</p>

<p>3—That the <person_mentioned>People </person_mentioned>by their legal representatives in Congress 
assembled, did on the <date_mentioned n="05-19-1822">19th of May last</date_mentioned> elect <person_mentioned>Don Agustin 1. Emperor
of the <location_mentioned>Mexican Nation</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and that said election was freely made 
without the influence of force or fear</p>

<p>4—That therefore the <hi rend="italic">form </hi>of Government of the <location_mentioned>Mexican Nation</location_mentioned>
is legally adopted and the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>legally chosen</p>

<p>5—That the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>have not yet formed their Constitution, and
they, and they only, have the sole and absolute power of forming it—</p>

<p>6—That as the <person_mentioned>People </person_mentioned>cannot all assemble and debate and vote on
the Constitution, the only legal mode of doing it is by their 
representatives, freely chosen and assembled in a General Congress—</p><barker_pb n="572"/>

<p>7—That said <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>cannot execute the duties intrusted to them
by the <person_mentioned>People</person_mentioned>, without the secure and inviolable guarantee of liberty
of speech, and personal security—</p>

<p>8—That to insure the observance of said guarantee all the <person_mentioned>troops</person_mentioned>
within the <location_mentioned>city </location_mentioned>where <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>sits ought to be under their direction,
and commanded by a <person_mentioned>General </person_mentioned>of their nominating—</p>

<p>9—That the <person_mentioned>junta </person_mentioned>have no authority to form a Constitution, and
that it is therefore inexpedient to spend time debating a project of
a Constitution which they have no authority to sanction—</p>

<p>10—That the immediate convocation of <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>is necessary to
save the <location_mentioned>Nation </location_mentioned>from a civil war—</p>

<p>These principles being established let the <person_mentioned>Junta </person_mentioned>pass a decree 
immediately for the new Convocation, and send it to the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>for
his approbation—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. A— </person_mentioned>  [Rubric]</p>
<p><location_mentioned>City of Mexico</location_mentioned></p>

<p><date_mentioned n="01-16-1823">January 16. 1823</date_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
