
<TEI.2 id="APB0043">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-30-1800</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 55-56</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Antoine Soulard</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Moses Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Antoine Soulard to Moses Austin, 06-30-1800</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>St Louis, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Concerning survey of Austin's grant. Claims  of other  inhabitants.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 55-56</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-21-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0043T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Concerning survey of Austin's grant. Claims  of other  inhabitants.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p><location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="06-30-1800">June the 30th, 1800</date_mentioned>.</p>
<p>Sir</p>

<p>[From what] you told me I expected to have seen you soon after
I came up, You would have found Mr [undecipherable] who is to Set
out in a few days and will be the <person_mentioned>Bearer </person_mentioned>of this, after having made
to <person_mentioned>Mr Lieutn Governor</person_mentioned> an official return of the Survey of Your Land,
I freely deliver'd to him my private opinion on the matter, and I 
confidentially say, that the Survey which has been made, will stand as it
is without any alteration, 'till the decision of the <person_mentioned>Government General</person_mentioned>,
and the business cannot be brought there, unless the <person_mentioned>Inhabitants</person_mentioned>
concerned can prove in writing that the manner in which your Land
was Survey'd is prejudicial and ruinous to them: I likewise believe
that <person_mentioned>M. Delassus</person_mentioned> will inform in your favor, a friend of mine being
now with me, enables me to Speak to you Somewhat more openly
than I could have done otherwise. I have no doubt but that you will
Judge rightly of My Motives, and keep all this between Ourselves—</p>

<p>In the course of next month I shall draw on You for 150 Dlls in
lead @ 5 dols p H in favor of <person_mentioned>Mr Pascal-Detchemendy</person_mentioned> and Should<barker_pb n="56"/>
Your Survey be approved of, as it is, You will pay me 75 Dlls. when
you receive Your Certificate which will make up the 225 Dlls. that
you agreed to pay me, if ever Your Survay Should Stand, and I
shall settle with <person_mentioned>Mr Maddin</person_mentioned> for what he has done. But if Your
Survey should not be apprved of, I should have nothing further to
demand from You when You have paid up the 150 Dlls. agreed upon
and in this case only <person_mentioned>Mr. Maddin</person_mentioned>'s fees must be paid by you. Such
you will certainly remember to have been our mutual agreement and
the payment was to take place in the course of <date_mentioned n="07-xx-1800">July</date_mentioned>, agreeable to
Your Verbal and written promises.</p>

<p>You are no doubt fully satisfied at this time that My Intentions
toward you have been constantly the Same, and that nothing could
make me alter them.</p>

<p>Please to present my respectful devo[tions] to <person_mentioned>Mrs Austin</person_mentioned> and
believe Me Most perfectly       Sir</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Anto Soulard</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>P. S. I had Your letter to <person_mentioned>Mr. de h .. . e</person_mentioned> translated by <person_mentioned>Mr. Bellier?</person_mentioned>
and it had, I believe a Good effect.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
