
<TEI.2 id="APB0613">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>08-06-1823</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 679-681</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Colonists</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Colonists, 08-06-1823</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Announcing confirmation of his grant and his authority with the commissioner to issue titles. Terms of payment for the land. Colonists must allow him to direct their relations with the Government. Must respect Catholic religion. Indians.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 679-681</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-15-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0613T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Announcing confirmation of his grant and his authority with the commissioner to issue titles. Terms of payment for the land. Colonists must allow him to direct their relations with the Government. Must respect Catholic religion. Indians.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Colarado River House of <person_mentioned>Mr Castleman</person_mentioned>s</location_mentioned></p>

<p><date_mentioned n="08-06-1823">August 6 1823.</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Fellow <person_mentioned>Citizens</person_mentioned>,</p>

<p>I have once more the pleasure of addressing you a few lines from
the <location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned>— My absence has been protracted greatly beyond my
calculations and has been in the highest degree unpleasant to me, as
it has retarded the progress of the most favourite enterprise I ever
engaged in in my life; but I now flatter myself with the hope of 
receiving a full compensation for the difficulties I have encountered by
witnessing the happiness of those who compose this <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>. I assure
you that if my own private and personal interest had been the only
incentive to induce me to persevere I should probably have abandoned
the enterprise rather than surmounted the difficulties produced by
the constant state of revolution in which the country has been, since
my arrival in the <location_mentioned>city of Mexico</location_mentioned>. But I was animated by the 
gratifying hope of providing a home for a number of meritorious <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>and
of placing them and their <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>in a situation to make themselves
happy the balance of their lives. One of the greatest pleasures a 
virtuous mind can receive in this world is the consciousness of having
benefited others, this pleasure I now have in prospect. The titles
to your land is indisputable—the original grant for this <location_mentioned>settlement</location_mentioned>
was made by the <person_mentioned>Spanish Government</person_mentioned> before the Revolution, it was
then confirmed and the quantity of land designated by the decree of
the <person_mentioned>Emperor Agustin Iturbide</person_mentioned> on the <date_mentioned n="02-18-1823">18th of February last</date_mentioned>, and the
whole was again approved and confirmed by the <person_mentioned>Sovereign Congress
of the Mexican Nation</person_mentioned> on the <date_mentioned n="04-14-1823">14 of April last</date_mentioned> after the fall of the
<person_mentioned>Emperor</person_mentioned>. The titles are made by me and the <person_mentioned>Commissioner of the
Government</person_mentioned>, and are then perfect and complete for ever, and each
<person_mentioned>settler </person_mentioned>may sell his land the same as he could do in the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>All that depends on me, towards the advancement of the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>
will be executed in good faith, so far as my abilities extend, and with
all the promptness in my power: but to enable me to benefit them
to the full extent that I wish, it is necessary that the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>should
have confidence in me, and be directed by me I have a better 
opportunity of knowing what will be advantageous to them as regards
their conduct and intercourse with the Government than any of them
could have had, and I feel almost the same interest for their 
prosperity that I do for my own <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>—in fact I look upon them as<barker_pb n="680"/>
one great <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>who are under my care. I wish the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>to
remember that the Roman Catholic is the religion of this <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, I
have taken measures to have <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Father Miness [Maynes]</person_mentioned></hi> formerly of
<location_mentioned>Nachitoches</location_mentioned>, appointed our <person_mentioned>Curate</person_mentioned>, he is a good man and 
acquainted with the <person_mentioned>Americans</person_mentioned>—we must all be particular on this
subject and respect the Catholic religion with all that attention due
to its sacredness and to the laws of the land.</p>

<p>I have so far paid all the expenses attending this enterprise out
of my own funds. I have spent much time and lost much property
on the <location_mentioned>coast </location_mentioned>in my absence—I am now engaged in surveying
the land and must pay money to the <person_mentioned>surveyors </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>hands </person_mentioned>
employed besides which I have to pay the expenses of the <person_mentioned>Commissioner</person_mentioned>,
and heavy expenses attending the completion and recording of the
titles. A moments reflection will convince the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>that all this
cannot be done without some aid from them, but as regards this point
they may expect all the indulgence possible. Those who have the
means must pay me a little money on receipt of their titles; from
those who have not money I will receive any kind of property that
will not be a dead loss to me, such as horses, mules, cattle, hogs,
peltry, Furs, bees wax, home made cloth, dressed deer skins, etc.
Only a small part will be required in hand, for the balance I will
wait one, two, and three years, according to the capacity of the
person to pay—-In fact I will accomodate the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>to the 
greatest extent in my power. I think that those who know me can state
that my disposition is not to oppress any man; it is a pleasure for
me to benefit my fellow <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>and I will sacrifice my own interest
rather than distress them for one cent of money. But I have many
sacred duties to attend which cannot be executed without money.
The most of what I receive from the settlers will be applied for their
own benefit, and I think they must all agree that it is also my duty
to provide for my own family, and that in justice I ought to be 
compensated for the losses and fatigues I have sustained in this 
business, particularly when my labors secure handsome fortunes to my
<person_mentioned>followers</person_mentioned>. I could exact the payment of all the expenses in hand
before the titles are delivered, but shall not do so, the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>may
all rely on the terms above stated The smallest quantity of land a
<person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>will receive is one thousand yards square which may be 
increased by me and the <person_mentioned>Commissioner </person_mentioned>without limit in proportion to
the size of the <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Young men must join and take land in the name of one. All thus
united will be ranked as one family, they can then divide the land
amongst themselves—</p>

<p>I shall proceed immediately to the <location_mentioned>mouth of this River</location_mentioned>, and on
my return go to the <location_mentioned>Brazos   </location_mentioned>The <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>have now nothing to fear,<barker_pb n="681"/>
there is no longer any cause for uneasiness, they must not be 
discouraged at any little depradations of <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>, they must remember
that <hi rend="italic">American blood</hi> flows in their veins, and that they must not 
dishonor that noble blood by yielding to trifling difficulties. I shall
adopt every possible means for their security and defence, I have
brought some powder from <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>, a part of which will be sent to
<person_mentioned>Capt. Robison</person_mentioned> for the use of the <person_mentioned>militia </person_mentioned>when needed—Let every
man do his duty, and we have nothing to fear—<hi rend="italic">Let us he united as
one man—discord must he hanished from amongst us, or those who
cause it will meet with most severe treatment</hi></p>

<p>Hoping to meet you soon in peace and happiness, I am Resptlly
your friend and fellow citizen</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>To <person_mentioned>J. H. Bell</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Andw Robertson</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Abner Kuykendall</person_mentioned> and other 
<person_mentioned>settlers on the <location_mentioned>Brazos River</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>—</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
