
<TEI.2 id="APB0041">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-01-1800</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 54</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Antoine Soulard</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Moses Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Antoine Soulard to Moses Austin, 05-01-1800</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>St Louis, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Concerning survey of Austin's grant. Advises compromise to save difficulty.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 54</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-21-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0041T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Concerning survey of Austin's grant. Advises compromise to save difficulty.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="05-01-1800">May 1st. 1800</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Sir</p>

<p>I just this moment received your favor of the <date_mentioned n="04-25-1800">25th of April</date_mentioned> and
will immediately answer to it not in an official but in a more familiar
way and Consequently easier to tell you my opinion. I should
have Left this to go Down to you if <person_mentioned>Mr Robidoux</person_mentioned>'s Bateau which
is to set off in about eight or ten Days did not Detain me here upon
the account of some Indispensable Business I shall Start 
immediatly after its Departure to go down to See you. I should 
extremely be Desirous that before that time you might inform me
provided you have an opportunity whether <person_mentioned>Mr Fr[anc]is Vallé</person_mentioned>
as <person_mentioned>Commandant </person_mentioned>and others who hold an interest in the <location_mentioned>mines </location_mentioned>have
agreed with you to have your Lands Survey'd in a Way that will
prevent all Difficulties which might arise if you Still would insist
to have them Survey'd agreably to the plan which you have 
presented to Government in that manner</p>

<p>My going down to the <location_mentioned>mines </location_mentioned>Should'nt have been [A third of the
page is here torn away] has brought envy upon you Some would
perhaps See you out of the Country Distroy the unjust Cabal risen
against you Sacrifice Something to be Definitively put in possession
of the Square League which has been Granted to you at the <location_mentioned>mines</location_mentioned>
you are established upon it and your Situation will become every
Day more interesting the More there will be people and the better
you will be yourself a french proverb Says that flys are not Caught
with Vinegar Kindness with people with whom you Live if you
mean to Do one Day as you please Speak to Day as they Do Speak
Bad people Can nether take off from you the Superiority of your
talents nor your industry Sacrifices I say it again establish yourself
in a Solid manner expect every thing from your perseverance and
time</p>

<p>Unless I receive Some particular orders from the <person_mentioned>Lieut Governor
</person_mentioned>I shall set off agreably to your letter just after the Departure of <person_mentioned>Mr.
robidoux</person_mentioned>'s Boat—try before that to write to me whether you have
made the agreements with the Gentlemen and in the Contrary [torn
as on preceding page.] . . . terminate nothing.</p>

<p>I never Doubted your Delicacy and Do think that you will act
with me as I have a right to expect a word from you before my
Leaving this would have saved trouble to me and to you expenses
without profit and do every thing to prevent the Same 
Inconveniences for this time</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Ante Soulard</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
