
<TEI.2 id="APB0534">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>08-xx-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 538-541</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Plan</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Unknown</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Unknown, 08-xx-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin's plan for organization of Mexican Congress, August, 1822. Combination of existing institutions, the Spanish constitution and the Constitution of the United States.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 538-541</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0534T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin's plan for organization of Mexican Congress, August, 1822. Combination of existing institutions, the Spanish constitution and the Constitution of the United States.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><person_mentioned>City of Mexico</person_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="08-xx-1822">August 1822</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Plan for the organization of <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>for the <location_mentioned>Empire of Mexico</location_mentioned> —</p>

<p>As a <person_mentioned>citizen of this <location_mentioned>Empire</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> I should be wanting in my duty did
I not feel that anxiety for the common welfare of my Country which
ought to animate the bosom of every good man. I have therefoie
viewed with great interest the political agitations of the nation, and
particularly of this <location_mentioned>Capital </location_mentioned>for the last two months; and believing
that the evils which now embarrass the operations of Government
arise solely from a defect in the organization of the <person_mentioned>Legislative 
department</person_mentioned>; I have taken the Liberty to offer my ideas on the subject,
hoping that my motives may excuse my presumption</p>

<p>Agreeably to the Basis which has governed since the glorious 
declaration of independence in <location_mentioned>Iguala</location_mentioned>, the fundamental principles of
the Government are established—It is to be a <hi rend="italic">Constitutional 
Monarchy</hi>—This Basis has been recognised as the foundation on which
the superstructure of the Constitution is to be erected. The leading
features of the Government is therefore no longer a question, and
any remarks on that subject would be irrellevant and improper: the
on[l]y question to be considered is the details of a system the 
foundation of which is already laid</p>

<p>The strength and beauty of architectural structures depend on the
symmetry, order and connection of their parts; so in the formation
of political institutions their capacity to sustain the shocks of
conflicting interests is of Primary import and must depend on the
harmony and dependent relations of the constituent parts—It would
seem that these circumstances have not been sufficiently attended to
in the organization of the Government, so far as it has progressed;
the consequences have resulted that the <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>on the one hand,
tenacious of its authority have been contending about forms, and
have wasted much time without a single salutory effect, being more
intent to extend its own Power than to promote the public good</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Executive </person_mentioned>on the other hand without a precise definition of
its powers have been obliged to wait the inefficient operations of the
<person_mentioned>Legislature</person_mentioned>—In this political [cataclysm(?)] the welfare of the State
is disregarded and discontents and distrusts are generated which
menace the most pernicious consequences—</p>

<p>What is the cause of this state of things?—The answer is 
evident—It is that which has overthrown so many Governments in the
old world, and plunged whole nations into civil wars, anarchy and
desolation—that which like an overwhelming volcano burst upon
devoted <location_mentioned>France </location_mentioned>and after drenching her plains with the blood of
her choicest <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>only prepared her for the chains of a <person_mentioned>despot</person_mentioned>.<barker_pb n="539"/>
It is the want of a proper <hi rend="italic">division, definition,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">limitation</hi>, of the
powers of the several branches and departments of Government—</p>

<p>I lay it down as an axiom which history will support and prove,
that there is as much danger to be apprehended from the hasty 
imprudence, intemperate decisions, and despotism of a single 
representative body or <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>convened and united in one chamber as
there is from the despotism of a Single individual at the head of a
nation, and consequently that there is the same necessity for a check
to the <person_mentioned>Legislature</person_mentioned>, that there is for the <person_mentioned>Executive</person_mentioned>. This principle
is acknowledged even in the <person_mentioned>Government of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>,
which is the most perfect republic that exists. The division of the
Legislative powers in that Government into two separate and 
distinct branches, the <person_mentioned>House of Representatives</person_mentioned>, and the <person_mentioned>Senate</person_mentioned>, both
of which are to a limited extent controuled by the <person_mentioned>Executive</person_mentioned>, operates
as a check or balance in the exercise of them.</p>

<p>The first great and preparitory step therefore towards the firm and
final organization of this Government is to regulate the Legislative
department so that its deliberations may be free and independent,
and at the same time controuled so as to be incapable of exceeding its
authority, or clashing with that of another. To do this I propose the
following system for the organization of <person_mentioned>Congress</person_mentioned></p>

<p>1—The Legislative powers shall be vested in a <person_mentioned>Congress</person_mentioned>, which
shall be composed of two chambers one to be called the <p><person_mentioned>Chamber of
the Commons</person_mentioned></p>, the other the <p>Senate</p></p>

<p>2—The <person_mentioned>Commons </person_mentioned>shall be elected every 2d year by the People in
the following manner—There shall be one <person_mentioned>Deputy </person_mentioned>for every 70,000
<person_mentioned>inhabitants</person_mentioned>. The <person_mentioned>Provincial deputations</person_mentioned> of each <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>shall,
immediately proceed to take an enumeration of the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>of
their respective <location_mentioned>provinces </location_mentioned>and after this is completed they shall lay
them off into as many districts as the Province is entitled to Deputies
agreeably to the above ratio, which <location_mentioned>districts </location_mentioned>shall contain an equal
number of <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>so far as is practicable—Each of said districts
shall elect one <person_mentioned>Deputy </person_mentioned>to the <person_mentioned>Chamber of Commons</person_mentioned>, who shall be over
21 years of age, an <person_mentioned>inhabitant </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>district </location_mentioned>for which he is elected,
and have been at least three years a Citizen of this <location_mentioned>Empire</location_mentioned>, and "tener
una renta anual proporcionada procedente de bienes propios—"</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Provincial deputations</person_mentioned> shall appoint <person_mentioned>Officers </person_mentioned>to preside at such
elections who shall make out certificates for the person or persons
elected, which certificate after being countersigned by the <person_mentioned>Captain
General of the <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> shall be evidence of a right to a Seat in the
<person_mentioned>Commons</person_mentioned>—The <person_mentioned>Captain Generals</person_mentioned> or <person_mentioned>Political Chiefs of <location_mentioned>Provinces</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
shall give said signatures without delay when called on</p>

<p>3—The <person_mentioned>Senate </person_mentioned>shall be appointed in the following manner. The
<person_mentioned>Provincial Deputations</person_mentioned> shall elect two <person_mentioned>Senators </person_mentioned>for each <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned><barker_pb n="540"/>
who shall hold their offices for 8 years and who shall be over thirty
years of age, an <person_mentioned>inhabitant of the <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> for which they are elected
and have been at least five years a Citizen of this <location_mentioned>Empire</location_mentioned>. The
<person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>with the Consent of the <person_mentioned>Council </person_mentioned>shall appoint one <person_mentioned>Senator</person_mentioned>
for each <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>to be selected from any part of the <location_mentioned>Empire </location_mentioned>he may
think proper, and without any restriction as to qualifications</p>

<p>4. The <person_mentioned>Senate </person_mentioned>at their first session shall divide themselves into
four classes, the seats of the first class shall be vacated the 2d year,
those of the 2d class the 4th year and so on, so that one-fourth should
be chosen every 2d year—</p>

<p>5 Each chamber shall judge of the qualifications of its <person_mentioned>members</person_mentioned>,
appoint its own <person_mentioned>President </person_mentioned>and other <person_mentioned>officers</person_mentioned>—determine the rules of
its proceedings and with the concurrence of two thirds expel a
<person_mentioned>Member</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p>6. The <person_mentioned>Chambers </person_mentioned>shall hold their sessions in separate and 
distinct Halls, and each one shall keep a journal of its proceedings which
shall be published except such parts as may require secrecy—</p>

<p>7 Neither chamber shall adjourn during the session of <person_mentioned>Congress</person_mentioned>
without the Consent of the other, for more than four clays at a time,
nor to any other place—</p>

<p>8—The wages of the <person_mentioned>Deputies </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Senators </person_mentioned>shall be fixed by law,
and untill that is done to continue the same as in the <person_mentioned>Spanish </person_mentioned>
Constitution—The <person_mentioned>Senators </person_mentioned>shall be paid out of the publick Treasury, and
the <person_mentioned>Deputies </person_mentioned>by the <location_mentioned>Provinces </location_mentioned>who send them—</p>

<p>9—The <person_mentioned>deputies </person_mentioned>to the <person_mentioned>Commons </person_mentioned>shall not receive any office from
the <person_mentioned>Emporer </person_mentioned>while they continue <person_mentioned>Members</person_mentioned></p>

<p>10 All laws shall pass through both chambers and be approved
and promulgated by the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>as in the Spanish Constitution</p>

<p>11—The powers of <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>shall [be] the same that is given to
the <person_mentioned>Cortes </person_mentioned>by the Spanish Constitution except that the <person_mentioned>Senate </person_mentioned>alone
shall be consulted on all matters relating to foreign treaties, and
shall have the same power as to ratifying them that is given by the
Spanish Constitution to the <person_mentioned>Cortes</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p>12 The <person_mentioned>Emporer </person_mentioned>may convene the Senate whenever he thinks
proper to consult them as to foreign treaties or other subjects of
importance to the <location_mentioned>Nation</location_mentioned></p>

<p>13—There shall be at least one session of <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>every two years
and as much oftener as the <person_mentioned>Emporer </person_mentioned>may think proper He may
convene them at any time by proclamation—</p>

<p>14—There shall be no permanent deputation of <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>as fixed
in the Spanish Constitution—and should it be necessary to convoke
<person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>on the Death of the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>or any casualty happening
to him, it shall be done by the <person_mentioned>Council of State</person_mentioned>—</p><barker_pb n="541"/>

<p>Agreeably to this plan the <person_mentioned>People </person_mentioned>would have a full and fair
representation in the <person_mentioned>Commons </person_mentioned>in proportion to their <person_mentioned>members</person_mentioned>-</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Senate </person_mentioned>would be a Territorial representation and being 
composed of <person_mentioned>members </person_mentioned>elected by the <person_mentioned>Provincial Deputations</person_mentioned> and the
<person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>would combine the General interests of the <location_mentioned>Nation</location_mentioned>—This
<person_mentioned>Chamber </person_mentioned>would also be to the Throne what the <person_mentioned>House of Lords</person_mentioned> is
in <location_mentioned>England</location_mentioned>, one of its main pillars and supporters—for the 
<person_mentioned>Captain Generals</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Governors of Provinces</person_mentioned> are appointed by the 
<person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>and their influence in the <person_mentioned>provincial Deputations</person_mentioned> would be
sufficient in Most instances to secure the election of <person_mentioned>Senators </person_mentioned>well
disposed to the <person_mentioned>Emperor</person_mentioned>—, this added to the power of appointing
one third of the senate and of distributing rewards and titles to the
<person_mentioned>Senators </person_mentioned>would make that chamber more dependent on the <person_mentioned>Throne</person_mentioned>
than the <person_mentioned>House of Lords</person_mentioned> is in <location_mentioned>England</location_mentioned>, for they are hereditary
<person_mentioned>Senators </person_mentioned>and do not depend on the <person_mentioned>Crown </person_mentioned>for their appointments—</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>would then be composed of a <person_mentioned>Chamber of 
Commons</person_mentioned> as.purely democratic as a representative body can be,—of a
<person_mentioned>Senate</person_mentioned>, independent of the other branch, and united by interest to
the <person_mentioned>Emperor</person_mentioned>, but whose legal existance at the same time would de-
pend on sustaining the <person_mentioned>Chamber of Commons</person_mentioned> in the event of any
attempt to distroy it by the <person_mentioned>Executive</person_mentioned>; for if one branch of the
Government was to be anihilated, the whole must fall, and a new 
organization be made—This chamber then would serve as a barrier to
prevent the Mutual encroachment of the <person_mentioned>Executive </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Commons</person_mentioned>
upon the authority of each other—</p>

<p>One great advantage in this plan is that many of its leading 
features resembles the <person_mentioned>Government of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and would
therefore be calculated to please that part of the people who wish
to approximate towards a <location_mentioned>republic</location_mentioned>; but in fact the operation of the
system would be to strengthen the <person_mentioned>Emperor</person_mentioned>; for the <person_mentioned>Senate </person_mentioned>in effect
would be the Mere creature of the <person_mentioned>Throne </person_mentioned>although in appearance it
is an independent representation of the <location_mentioned>Nation</location_mentioned>; and thus public
opinion would probably unite in adopting the system, and prudent
management would soon confirm their confidence in it—</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
