
<TEI.2 id="APB0484">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>03-12-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 482</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>James H. Penrose</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>James H. Penrose to Stephen F. Austin, 03-12-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>St. Charles, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>New Orleans, LA</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Desires information. Many anxious to go to Texas. Political news of Missouri. Scarcity of money. Loan-office money worth only 3 per cent.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Printed in <hi rend="italic">Texas History Teacher's Bulletin</hi>, November, 1917.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 482</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0484T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Desires information. Many anxious to go to Texas. Political news of Missouri. Scarcity of money. Loan-office money worth only 3 per cent.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>St Charles [Missouri]</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="03-12-1822">12 March 1822</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>Being desirous of leaving <location_mentioned>Missouri </location_mentioned>for a more genial country and
one that is less embarrassed . I have thought of yours as one that
might be advantageous for a young man just setting out in life
whose dependence must be entirely on himself for his support. As
you know; I was brought up a merchant but from the change in 
affairs in this our embarrassd country my <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>will not be able to
advance me any capital. Therefore I cannot come in that capacity,
but must depend upon my information and industry for my 
passport. To you Dear Sir, therefore I have determined to impose the
task of giving me an impartial and unbiased account of the 
prospects and advantages which the country affords, believing that to no
one could I apply with so great a prospect of success as to yourself.
There are many young men in this country who are in the same 
situation with myself who would willingly join me provided there was
any probability of their meeting with encouragement.</p>

<p>News. I can give you but little if any, and that is of a local 
nature <person_mentioned>Judge Stuart</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>John Scott</person_mentioned> are the <person_mentioned>candidates </person_mentioned>for the next
<person_mentioned>congress</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Scott </person_mentioned>I think will be elected altho the <person_mentioned>Judge </person_mentioned>is making
every exertion and is now on his electionering campaign, going to
<location_mentioned>every county in the state</location_mentioned> making very lengthy stump speeches. Our
country is very much embarrassed. The only money almost we have
is our Loan Office which is only worth at present 3% cts in the $1.00
this you will say is poor indeed.</p>

<p>My <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>desire to be remembered to you.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>James H. Penrose</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:]    <person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin Esqr.</person_mentioned>   <location_mentioned>New Orleans.</location_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
