
<TEI.2 id="APB0226">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-19-1812</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 218-219</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Moses Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>James Bryan</document_recipient>
<document_title>Moses Austin to James Bryan, 10-19-1812</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Durham Hall, Burton Mine, LA</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Philadelphia, PA</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Lead. Militia. Indians.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Original in possession of Mrs. Emmett L. Perry.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 218-219</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-30-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0226T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Lead. Militia. Indians.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Durham Hall Mine A Burton</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="10-19-1812">Octbr 19 1812</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Mr James Bryan</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Dear S-r I have wrote you sundry times since you left us, to <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Louis
Vill</location_mentioned></hi> . . . and <location_mentioned>Pittsburg</location_mentioned>, and last to <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Philadelphia</location_mentioned></hi>, and have only
recvd two letters from you up to this month. I have recvd from our
friend and son <person_mentioned>Stephen F Austin</person_mentioned> information that he had raised his
Cargo with but little loss, and that he was in expectation of leaving
<location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>in or about the <date_mentioned n="10-01-1812">first of Octbr</date_mentioned> that he would obtain 12 Cents
for his shott by Draght on <location_mentioned>Philadelphia </location_mentioned>and that he should be
obliged to return by way of <location_mentioned>Nashville </location_mentioned>as the <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>rendered the
<location_mentioned>Georgia rout</location_mentioned> dangerous so that I expect he will forward on his
Draght, and take the <location_mentioned>Mines </location_mentioned>in his way to the <location_mentioned>North</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Altho business was dul and collections almost impossible when you
left us its much more difficult to obtain either lead or money at this
time then in the <date_mentioned n="Spring-1813">Spring</date_mentioned>, for the last two months almost every man in
the Country has Either been out on the <location_mentioned>frountier </location_mentioned>or are held in 
requisition to march at a moments notice this as you may suppose, has
put a full Stop to all business and all Collection, the <person_mentioned>Courts </person_mentioned>have don
no business the <person_mentioned>General Court</person_mentioned> did not attempt, any thing, not to,
call the suites, and Very little lead has been made this <date_mentioned n="Summer-1812">summer </date_mentioned>and
not much will be made this <date_mentioned n="Fall-1812">fall </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="Winter-1812">Winter</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Its my opinion that lead must be up. the quantity made and that
will be made, in this Country cannot furnish the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I have sent a small quantity of shott to <location_mentioned>Nashville </location_mentioned>which I am
doubtful I shall not do much, If I obtain 14 Dollars its the most
and I am doubtfull 12$50 or 13 will be about the price they will
command. I had your, <hi rend="italic">boat</hi>, put in good Order to take a Cargo, but
believe me She is not the boat you bought her for. I put 12 Thousand
only into her and about 5000 on freight and <person_mentioned>Mr Ray</person_mentioned> told me that
he had to make use of uncommon precaution in assendg. the <location_mentioned>Ohio </location_mentioned>with
that load and advises never to attempt a load in her equal to what
you have calculated, I think <person_mentioned>Mr Ray</person_mentioned> will be back in all this week—</p>

<p>I have a mill now ready for milling sheet lead, and the price now
in <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>is such as to Justify sending down, from 20 to 25 Dollars
is Now the price of Milled Sheet Lead in <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>and I think by
exertions I may make out a Small Cargo in all Next month If the
<location_mentioned>mines </location_mentioned>turn out as, I have reason to expect—</p>

<p>I trust ear this reaches you you will have heard of the rumors.
Storm at <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> and the damage that has been sustained.
Thank God <person_mentioned>Stephen </person_mentioned>has Escaped as his Cargo was.   at the place his<barker_pb n="219"/>
boat, <hi rend="italic">sank</hi>—and he did not arrive untill the day after. <person_mentioned>John Perry</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>Mc Guir</person_mentioned> returned <date_mentioned n="10-18-1812">yesterday </date_mentioned>and have lost every thing, their
boat and Cargo Sank in Sixty or Seventy feet Water they sold out for
100 Dollars, the Chance of the Cargo. <person_mentioned>Mc Guir</person_mentioned> I think will Never see
<location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>again, or any Other Country, he is almost done with this
World. <person_mentioned>John Perry</person_mentioned> is laso much unwell. <person_mentioned>Stephen </person_mentioned>has enjoyed
good health, he says the Country agrees with him and that it has been
quite healthy this <date_mentioned n="Summer-1812">summer</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I think the <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>, have receivd a Check and that they will not
trouble us any more this fall. I think <person_mentioned>William Bates</person_mentioned> will be at
home in a day or two. I am told the <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>was dischargd at <person_mentioned>St
Louis</person_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="10-18-1812">yesterday</date_mentioned>, and that <person_mentioned>William </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Bates </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Evans </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Mc <hi rend="italic">Gahan</hi></person_mentioned>
will be at the <location_mentioned>mines </location_mentioned>on <date_mentioned n="10-20-182-12">the Morrow</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Ashley and Hews Companey</person_mentioned> will also be discharged and the place
of the <person_mentioned>Troops from this <location_mentioned>quarter</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> will be replaced—by—<person_mentioned>companeys.
from the <location_mentioned>Cape Girardeau</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and I am in hopes we shall not be called
on again this fall—but every thing depends on the advance of <person_mentioned>troops</person_mentioned>
<location_mentioned>North Ward</location_mentioned>—the fall of <person_mentioned>General Hull</person_mentioned> has induced all the <person_mentioned>Indians
on the <location_mentioned>Illinois </location_mentioned>and high up the <location_mentioned>Mississippi</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to arrise against us—</p>

<p>If my son <person_mentioned>Stephen </person_mentioned>Should return to the <location_mentioned>mines </location_mentioned>he will stay but a
day or two before he takes his Journey to <location_mentioned>Philadelphia </location_mentioned>so as to be
on, in, time to return with the <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned></p>

<p>As to goods such is the difficulty in Obtaining payments, that I
am determined Never to have any more untill times alter, If I can
collect half the dabts now Due, Its more than I Expect, at the same
time goods will be I think in demand in the <date_mentioned n="SPring-1813">Spring</date_mentioned>, As soon as 
<person_mentioned>William Bates</person_mentioned> returns I think some lead may be collected and. I shall
give every Assistance in my power</p>

<p><date_mentioned n="10-18-1812">Yesterday </date_mentioned>brought letters from <person_mentioned>Mrs Austin</person_mentioned> She seamed to think
that If she could see you it would give her some releaf She has
recovered her law Suite, by which she will be put in possession of
a handsome property and some money—at least for Spending money
She was in hopes you would be in <location_mentioned>Philadelphia </location_mentioned>in time to go to the
<location_mentioned>Northward </location_mentioned>with her—I look forward to the time when I shall See
you all return in Safety</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Moses Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Mr William Bates</person_mentioned> has this day returned from <location_mentioned>St Charles </location_mentioned>  the
<person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>were discharged only two Days since Say on the <date_mentioned n="10-20-1812"><hi rend="italic">20th </hi>Ins-t</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>MA</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Mr James Bryan</person_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Philadelphia</location_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
