
<TEI.2 id="APB0625">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>08-xx-1823</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 691-692</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>License</document_type>
<document_author>Unknown</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Unknown</document_recipient>
<document_title>Unknown to Unknown, 08-xx-1823</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin's license to Dr. Johnson Hunter to sail a coasting vessel.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 691-692</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-15-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0625T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin's license to Dr. Johnson Hunter to sail a coasting vessel.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>[August—,1823?]</p>
<p><person_mentioned>Dr. Johnson Hunter</person_mentioned> a native of the <location_mentioned>United States of America</location_mentioned> and
a <person_mentioned>settler </person_mentioned>near the mouth of the <location_mentioned>San Jacinto River</location_mentioned> in the <location_mentioned>Province of
Texas</location_mentioned> having been received as an <person_mentioned>inhabitant of the <location_mentioned>Mexican Republic</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
in conformity with the order of <person_mentioned>Don Jose Antonio Saucedo Political
Chief of the <location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and included as one of the <person_mentioned>300
families</person_mentioned> which I am authorised by the <person_mentioned>Mexican Government</person_mentioned> to
settle in this <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned>, and the said <person_mentioned>Hunter </person_mentioned>having heretofore obtaind
the permit of <person_mentioned>Col. Antonio Martinez</person_mentioned> to sail the small vessel called the
Santa Maria of San Jacinto which vessel it has been proven to me
was lost to said <person_mentioned>Hunter </person_mentioned>and the sd. <person_mentioned>Hunter </person_mentioned>having petitioned for<barker_pb n="692"/>
license to sail a small vessel called the Adven[ture], and it 
appearing that the situation of said <person_mentioned>Hunters family </person_mentioned>as well as that of
others settled in his <location_mentioned>neighborhood </location_mentioned>requires that his solicitud should
be granted. Therefore in virtue of the authority vested in me by
the decree of <person_mentioned>Don Felipe de la Garza, Commandant Genl. of the
Eastern Internal Provs.</person_mentioned> dated at the <location_mentioned>city of Monterrey</location_mentioned> the <date_mentioned n="06-16-1823">16 day of
June 1823</date_mentioned> directing me to give license to any of the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>of this
colony to sail vessels from any part of the <location_mentioned>coast </location_mentioned>of this jurisdiction
for the purpose of procuring supplies. I do here by and in the name
of the <person_mentioned>Govt. of the <location_mentioned>Republic of Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> give full license to said
<person_mentioned>John H.</person_mentioned> to sail the said vessel called the Adve. &c to any <location_mentioned>port </location_mentioned>he may
deem proper for the purpose of procuring supplies of provissions or
merchandise for the use of His <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>or others settld in this <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>,
subjecting himself in all cases to the laws of the <location_mentioned>Mexican Nation</location_mentioned> as
prescribed in the within license of <person_mentioned>Govr. Martinez</person_mentioned>, and that the said
<person_mentioned>Hunter </person_mentioned>or his <person_mentioned>Agent </person_mentioned>on board said vessel may not be considered as
suspicious persons sailing without legal authority I give him this
document and respectfully request all <person_mentioned>officers </person_mentioned>or <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>of any 
<location_mentioned>foreign nation</location_mentioned> with whom the <location_mentioned>Mexican Republic</location_mentioned> are on amicable terms
who may meet with the said vessel sailing under this license not to
impede or embarrass its progress but on the contrary to extend to it
their protection and assistance should it be needed.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. A. Empresario</person_mentioned> for the establishment of <person_mentioned>300 families</person_mentioned> in the P.
of <person_mentioned>T. Judge</person_mentioned> commissioned by the<person_mentioned> Mexican Govt </person_mentioned>for said <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and
<person_mentioned>Lieut. Col. commandant of the Militia</person_mentioned> of the same discription of the
vessel The Adventurer Skiff built tonage between five and Six Tons</p>

<p>[Endorsed:] <person_mentioned>Hunter</person_mentioned>s license to sail a vessel on the <location_mentioned>coast</location_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
