
<TEI.2 id="APB0028">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-29-1797</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 36-37</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>James Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen Austin to James Austin, 06-29-1797</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Philadelphia, PA</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Austin Ville Lead Mines, Wythe County, VA</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Management of lead mines.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Original in possession of Mrs. Emmett L. Perry.
That is forty shillings.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 36-37</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-21-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0028T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Management of lead mines.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Philada </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="06-29-1797">29th June 1797</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Mr <person_mentioned>James Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Sir being informd by my <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>that he has appointed you 
<person_mentioned>Superintendant of our Bussiness at <location_mentioned>Austin Ville</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>— I have now to request
your Perticular attention to, Sundry Matters of Bussiness Viz—the
State of the <person_mentioned>Company</person_mentioned>s finances here are Such as demand the greatest
Exertion on your Part by Every Possible Means to Raise Money
for the Purpose of forwarding on to me to Discharge Several Most
Pressing Demand for Cash, the Extreem Disepointment in My
<person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>Not b[r]inging on 4 or five thousand Dollars is Such to me<barker_pb n="37"/>
that I know Not what to do— the 1500 from <person_mentioned>Mr Mourey</person_mentioned> I have ben
daly Expecting what Can be the Cause of this detention—as <person_mentioned>Mr
Bradley</person_mentioned> was Sent on to Expedite this Bussiness— However from
your Letter to My <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>by <person_mentioned>Mr Droap</person_mentioned> [ ?] I dere Say No time will
be Lost in your forwarding it when it Comes to hand-— I wish your
Exertion in the Selling of Lead to Raise Money and to Induce 
<person_mentioned>Purchasers </person_mentioned>to Come forward take of [f] the 40/1 pr ton which my <person_mentioned>brother</person_mentioned>
had requested you to put on and if you think 20/ pr Ton will be an
Inducement do it as the Lead must if Possible be Turnd into Cash
as fast as it is Smelted and to do this I had rather sacrifice 40/ pr
Ton—this I shall submit to your discretion My <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>and My
Self have Concluded to Sell 10 of the Mules if you Can get 80 Dollars
for them—they ought to bring 100 Dollar Each which obtain if you
Can the <location_mentioned>Plantation </location_mentioned>which my <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>has advertiz for Sale I hope
you May meet with <person_mentioned>purchasers </person_mentioned>for in Part if Not all— I have Met
with a young Man a <person_mentioned>Hatter </person_mentioned>who is a good workman and a steady
Man who I have engagd to Carry on the Bussiness, at the <location_mentioned>Mines </location_mentioned>he
will Come on with my <person_mentioned>Brothers family</person_mentioned> who will Leave Town in a
day or Two—you will therefore Not dispose of any of the Platters
Tools Utentials etc as <person_mentioned>M A </person_mentioned>say he left you orders to Sell them—
the washing and smelting Let be Pushed On as much as Possible
and the quantity of ore Raisd I expect will be sufficient to Keep the
Furnace Constantly in Blast if you can but Keep ahead with the
washing—which is always the Most Tedious Part of the Bussiness—
I will thank you to Make me Constantly Acquainted with all your
Proceedings at the <location_mentioned>Mines </location_mentioned>by Post as Rude Conveyances are very
Uncertain—</p>

<p>My Son <person_mentioned>Charles </person_mentioned>leave this in a few days by Land for the <location_mentioned>Mines </location_mentioned>by
him I shall write you again Please Present My respects to the <person_mentioned>Mr
Bates</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Kendall Bell</person_mentioned> etc and Accept the Same your Self</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Mr James Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Austin Ville Lead Mines Wythe
County Virginia</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
