
<TEI.2 id="APB0826">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>08-20-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 877-878</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Agreement</document_type>
<document_author>Horatio Chriesman</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Horatio Chriesman to Stephen F. Austin, 08-20-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, YX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Agreement between Austin and Horatio Chriesman for surveying.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 877-878</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-18-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0826T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Agreement between Austin and Horatio Chriesman for surveying.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p>This agreement entered into at the <location_mentioned>Town of San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned>
in the <location_mentioned>province of Texas</location_mentioned> between <person_mentioned>Stephen F Austin Empresario</person_mentioned> for
the settlement of <person_mentioned>three hundred familie</person_mentioned>s in this <location_mentioned>province </location_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Horatio
Chriesman surveyor</person_mentioned>, is To Witness—That said <person_mentioned>Chriesman </person_mentioned>agrees to
survey such Tracts of Land in this <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>as he may be directed to
Survey by sd <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>and the <person_mentioned>Commissioner of the Government</person_mentioned> in
the form and manner which they may direct using the Mexican Vara
as the standard for regulating their chains and running by the true
meridian after Calculating the Variation of the compass—and the<barker_pb n="878"/>
said <person_mentioned>Chriesman </person_mentioned>agrees to execute his work accurately and in a good
and workman like manner and to complete it as speedily as possible
establishing Corners with bearing true at each principal corner of a
survey with the initials of the <person_mentioned>Owners </person_mentioned>names marked on the bearing
Trees where the Owner is known or erecting sufficient mounds of
Earth in <location_mentioned>Prairie </location_mentioned>at least Three feet high and marking every line
not bounded by a River or Creek which runs through Timber so that
it can be easily Traced and followed and finally To make out correct
returns and plots of Each survey To sd <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>on completion of the
work in the manner above stated the sd <person_mentioned>Chriesman </person_mentioned>shall be entitled
to demand and receive from each <person_mentioned>settler </person_mentioned>pay for surveying their
lands at the rate of five dollars pr Spanish mile payable in property
or three dollars pr mile payable in Cash to be paid by the <person_mentioned>settler </person_mentioned>and
for which payment the said <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>is not to be in any manner 
accountable or responsible more than to refuse to deliver the titles to
any <person_mentioned>settler </person_mentioned>until he brings a certificate from the <person_mentioned>surveyor </person_mentioned>or stating
that the surveying fees of his land were paid or settled For the
faithful complyance of all which the sd <person_mentioned>Chriesman </person_mentioned>Obligates himself
under the penalty of being liable for any damages which may arise
from a non or incorrect Compliance with this Contract</p>
<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="08-24-1824">Augt 20th 1824</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Horatio Chriesman</person_mentioned>    [Rubric]</p>
<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
