
<TEI.2 id="APB0572">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>03-16-1823</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 589-590</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>James E. B. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>J. H. Bell</document_recipient>
<document_title>James E. B. Austin to J. H. Bell, 03-16-1823</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>St. Antonio de Bexar, TX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Provisions of imperial colonization law. Work of S. F. Austin in its passage. Slavery. Scarcity of corn.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 589-590</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0572T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Provisions of imperial colonization law. Work of S. F. Austin in its passage. Slavery. Scarcity of corn.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p><location_mentioned>St Antonio de Bexar</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="03-16-1823">March 16th /23</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>Some time has elapsed since I have had an opportunity of writing
to the <person_mentioned>settlers on the <location_mentioned>Brazos </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, but now I have the
pleasure of announcing to them that my <person_mentioned>brother </person_mentioned>has left <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>
with his business concluded to his satisfaction, the law of 
colonization has already arrived and I find it much more liberal than I 
expected.</p>

<p>Some of the items are that you are free from Taxes dutys 
contributions under whatever name they may be for six years and for six
following pay but half that the other <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>Empire</location_mentioned>
pay—All <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>already introduced and all that are introduced 
hereafter for the use of the settlement are <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>for life their children
are free at the age of 14 years Traffic in <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>is prohibited in toto.</p>

<p>You are all perfectly secure as to your lands all that now remains
is the usual paper form and the land is yours forever there are many<barker_pb n="590"/>
other very liberal articles which you will see in a short time, the
quantity of land is somewhat greater for each family—but all is
ovmg to his stay untill the business was concluded if he had not
have done so it is extremely doubtful whether the law had been 
concluded this year—he pressed it every day until at length they 
concluded it and presented it to the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>who sancioned it 
immediately.</p>

<p>I have understood that my <person_mentioned>brother </person_mentioned>left <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>on the <date_mentioned n="01-22-1823">22d of Jany</date_mentioned>
if so he will be here in a tew days he comes on fully vested with
power to secure your lands forever—the <person_mentioned>gov</person_mentioned>. tells me that he will
send the law of colonization to the <location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned>, and the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>thereof
will forward it on to you by this conveyance.</p>

<p>We have in this place the greatest scarcity of corn and flour 
imaginable the council of the town have sent to the <location_mentioned>Interior </location_mentioned>for corn
but it is not to be had and now they send to the <location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned>, If any
person should have a little corn to sell either on the <location_mentioned>Brazos </location_mentioned>or 
<location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>they can now sell it for almost what they please and deliver it
at their <location_mentioned>homes</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I expect my <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>every day; I hope that in a short time I shall
have the pleasure of seeing you on the <location_mentioned>Brazos    </location_mentioned>Untill then
I remain yours</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Jas E. B. Austin </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Josiah H Bell Alcalde on the <location_mentioned>Rio Brasos</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
