
<TEI.2 id="APB0746">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-21-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 796</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Proclamation</document_type>
<document_author>Jose Antonio Saucedo</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Colonists</document_recipient>
<document_title>Jose Antonio Saucedo to Colonists, 05-21-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, TX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Proclamation of political chief (Saucedo). Assuring the colonists of Austin's ample authority.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>This translation is attested by Austin but was not made by him. There is a Spanish
copy written by Austin and signed by Saucedo.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 796</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-17-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0746T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Proclamation of political chief (Saucedo). Assuring the colonists of Austin's ample authority.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>[Translation]</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Political Chief of the <location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to the <person_mentioned>inhabitants of
the <location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Brazos</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> in the Colony formed by the <person_mentioned>Empresario
Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Understanding that in consequence of my arrival in these parts
some of the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>have erroneously persuaded themselves that
the object of my visit here has been to deprive the <person_mentioned>Empresiario
Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned> of the power which the government had granted
him to organize its commencement this new establishment and to
administer justice, Stop all differences that might arise between the
<person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>and preserve good order, until thicker settled and better
informed as to the laws that govern in the new Country which you
have adopted, You acquire the necessary elements to apoint your
justices, and the <person_mentioned>Ayuntamentos </person_mentioned>or representative bodies, designated
by the laws to watch over the public order and promote whatever
may tend to the prosperity of the People, fearing from this measure
unfavourable results which would lead to confusion and possible
tend to your ruin—-</p>

<p>But far from me has been all such ideas, and I hope that you will
see by what will be communicated to you that my measures have
been directed to your good, and I now positively assure you that
said <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>is completely authorized by the Supreme Government to
found this <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>and unless he forfits the good opinion that is now
entertained of him he will continue to exercise the Civil and Military
powers he now has untill the organization of this <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>is 
completed and you acquire the nessisary elements to govern yourselves
by means of the authorities above indicated.</p>

<p>Signed <person_mentioned>Jose Antonio Saucedo</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p><location_mentioned>Town of San Filipe de Austin</location_mentioned>
<date_mentioned n="05-21-1824">May 21st 1824— 4 and 3</date_mentioned></p>

<p>A true translation</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>    [Rubric]</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
