
<TEI.2 id="APB0940">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-10-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 987-988</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>John Sibley</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>John Sibley to Stephen F. Austin, 12-10-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>State (Louisiana) and national politics. Internal improvements. Europe. Can buy up claims of Gutierrez's men if Mexican Government will recognize them.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 987-988</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-18-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0940T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>State (Louisiana) and national politics. Internal improvements. Europe. Can buy up claims of Gutierrez's men if Mexican Government will recognize them.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><date_mentioned n="12-10-1824">Dec. 10th 1824</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>By <person_mentioned>Mr Allen</person_mentioned> the oppty. offers of sending you a line with some
<location_mentioned>News papers</location_mentioned>, you will find them much taken up with the Accounts
of the Reception of <person_mentioned>Genl. Lafayette</person_mentioned>.   The Presidential Election is<barker_pb n="988"/>
next in Order, who the Successful <person_mentioned>Candidate </person_mentioned>will be is yet doubtfull.
there is no prospect that Either will be primarily Elected. <person_mentioned>Genl
Jackson</person_mentioned> now appears to run Ahead, but the <person_mentioned>House of Representatives</person_mentioned>
Vote by <location_mentioned>States </location_mentioned>in that case the result may be different, in <location_mentioned>New York
</location_mentioned>we hear that <person_mentioned>Jackson </person_mentioned>had 29 and <person_mentioned>Clay </person_mentioned>7— this State will give 
<person_mentioned>Jackson </person_mentioned>3 and <person_mentioned>Adams </person_mentioned>2. the Ballotings were <person_mentioned>Jackson </person_mentioned>30 and <person_mentioned>Clay </person_mentioned>29.
three <person_mentioned>senators </person_mentioned>were absent friendly to <person_mentioned>Clay </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Dominique Boliney
[Bouligny]</person_mentioned> is Elected <person_mentioned>Senator </person_mentioned>in place of <person_mentioned>Harry Johnston</person_mentioned> who is
<person_mentioned>Governor </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Genl Thomas</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Harper </person_mentioned>had a few votes. <person_mentioned>Mr. 
Livingston</person_mentioned> was not put up Some think he is kept Back to go into the
New <person_mentioned>Cabinet</person_mentioned>, most probably in place of <person_mentioned>J. Q. Adams</person_mentioned>.— <location_mentioned>The Great
National Canal from Potomac to Monongehala</location_mentioned> will now certainly
go on, the <person_mentioned>Commissioners </person_mentioned>have reported in favour of it, on the
summit Level water to feed the <location_mentioned>Locks </location_mentioned>at all seasons will be found
in abundance— The whol of our New State Loan has been taken by
an <person_mentioned>English Company</person_mentioned> at five pr cent it will soon go into operation.—</p>

<p>We have had no deaths but <person_mentioned>Davenport </person_mentioned>lately that I Recollect.
<location_mentioned>Red River</location_mentioned> is so high and rising that Steam Boats will be looked for
Next-Week.— The crop of cotton will exceed that of the last or
any former year. Corn is scarce, all Other Provisions plenty and
cheap— The Country is healthy and slowly improving.-— If <person_mentioned>Mr.
Smyth</person_mentioned> is in you quarter Please to present to him my best wishes. I
hope his health is improved It is a pity a Man of his Sterling
worth should be so afflicted by Physical infirmity—- Present my
compliments Likewise to <person_mentioned>Mr. Cook</person_mentioned>, the ebolutions of <person_mentioned>Mr. Holtham</person_mentioned>
Ought to give him no uneasiness, it certainly will do him no harm
Amongst those who know him, as well as his adversary. I have a
great desire to See your Country, but whether or not I shall be
able to do so, the prosperity of your settlemt has my warmest
Wishes. The papers will inform you of the Political State of
<location_mentioned>Europe</location_mentioned>, The <person_mentioned>Duke D'Artoi of <location_mentioned>France</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> Succeeds <person_mentioned>Louis 18</person_mentioned> and will be
called <person_mentioned>Charles the tenth</person_mentioned>, he is sixty five; without issue, and was a
<person_mentioned>libertine</person_mentioned>, till his Constitution Obliged him to be Otherwise.— I
wrote you lately on the Subject of the Late <person_mentioned>Doctor Robinson</person_mentioned>s 
Account with the <person_mentioned>Mexican Government</person_mentioned> I hope you will be able to 
procure for his Amiable <person_mentioned>Widow </person_mentioned>a Satisfactory Account of the matter.—
You will oblige me If you will inform me wheather the <person_mentioned>officers </person_mentioned>and
Men who served under <person_mentioned>Bernardo Gutieras</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Toledo </person_mentioned>will be allowed
the Land promised them, or Any other compensation Many of thos
Claims might be Bought up on Reasonable terms.—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>John Sibley </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Judge Austin</person_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
