
<TEI.2 id="APB0552">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-xx-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 562-564</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Document</document_type>
<document_author>Unknown</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Unknown</document_recipient>
<document_title>Unknown to Unknown, 12-xx-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Mexican politics. Santa Anna's proclamation of a republic. Honors to Iturbide in the Capital, December 14.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>This was probably written by Austin in 1829. In much briefer form it appears in a
pamphlet which he published in that year and which is reprinted in part in<hi rend="italic"> A 
Comprehensive History of Texas,</hi> I, 454. The paper is published here for its description of the
celebration of December 14 in Mexico City. For a general account of the period see
H. H. Bancroft, History of Mexico, IV, 786-94.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 562-564</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0552T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Mexican politics. Santa Anna's proclamation of a republic. Honors to Iturbide in the Capital, December 14.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>on the <date_mentioned n="12-02-1822">2d. of December 1823 [1822]</date_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Brigr. Genl Don Antonio
Lopes de Santana</person_mentioned> proclaimed in favour of a Republic in the <location_mentioned>city of
Vera Cruz</location_mentioned> at the head of his Regiment No 8 of infantry—
amounting to about 800 <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>well provided with amunition small arms and
cannon and mortars, provided for the attack on the <location_mentioned>castle</location_mentioned>—the civil
authority of <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned> seconded him, and a plan was published on
the 6 stating the basis of future operations—<person_mentioned>Genl. Guadalupe 
Victoria</person_mentioned> soon after joined <person_mentioned>Santana </person_mentioned>with a considerable body of <person_mentioned>troops</person_mentioned>
and took command of the Strong and important fortified position
of <location_mentioned>Puente de Rey (Kings Bridge)</location_mentioned> on the Main road from <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz
</location_mentioned>to <location_mentioned>Xalapa </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>Puebla </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>—<date_mentioned n="12-09-1822">about the 9</date_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Santana </person_mentioned>left <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned>
and marched in the direction of <location_mentioned>Cordova </location_mentioned>with the intention as was
said of endeavouring to induce <person_mentioned>Genl. Lobato</person_mentioned> and the division under
his command to join him—<person_mentioned>Lobato </person_mentioned>however attacked his advance
guard repulsed them and took two small field pieces and a few 
<person_mentioned>prisoners</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Santana </person_mentioned>then collecting about 1000 <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>took the main road
to the <location_mentioned>city of Mexico</location_mentioned> and having surprised and cut off, by a rapid
movement, a detachment of the <person_mentioned>Imperial troops</person_mentioned> at the <location_mentioned>Plan del Rio</location_mentioned>,
in advance of the <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Puente del Rey</location_mentioned></hi> near <location_mentioned>Xalapa</location_mentioned>, made an attack on
the latter city on the <date_mentioned n="12-23-1822">23 Decr.</date_mentioned> at daylight and was repulsed with
considerable loss in killed wounded and <person_mentioned>Prisioners</person_mentioned>,—This obliged
him to retreat rapidly to <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned> in which city he shut himself up
with the remnant of his <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Victoria </person_mentioned>remaining in possession of
the <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Puente del Rey</location_mentioned></hi>—during this period the town of <location_mentioned>Alvarado</location_mentioned>, which
had followed the example of <location_mentioned>vera Cruz</location_mentioned> a few days after the 
proclamation of the <date_mentioned n="12-02-1822">2d Decr</date_mentioned>. redeclared for the <person_mentioned>Emperor</person_mentioned>—and was taken
possession by <person_mentioned>Genl. Lobato</person_mentioned>—The <person_mentioned>Captain General of the Province
of <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> field <person_mentioned>Martial Echavari</person_mentioned> uniting the divisions of <person_mentioned>Genl.
Lobato</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Cortázar </person_mentioned>and adding to them a few <person_mentioned>troops from <location_mentioned>Xalapa</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
encamped before <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned> and commenced the siege of that city
with about____on the____day of ____ leaving a detachment to
besiege <person_mentioned>Victoria </person_mentioned>at the <location_mentioned>Puente del Rey</location_mentioned> under the command of <person_mentioned>Genl.<barker_pb n="563"/>
Calderón</person_mentioned> The sieges of these two places was continued without any
important occurrance save occasional skirmishes, and the scarcity
of provisions in <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned>, untill the day of—when the besieging
army under <person_mentioned>Echavarri </person_mentioned>entered into a convention with <person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento
of <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, called the convention of <location_mentioned>Casa Mata</location_mentioned> from its bearing
date at that place   this convention is as follows—&c, &c.</p>

<p>In the mean time the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>who left <location_mentioned>Xalapa </location_mentioned>the <date_mentioned n="12-01-1822">1 Decr </date_mentioned>entered
<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>on the <date_mentioned n="12-12-1822">12th Decr</date_mentioned> and was received with great demonstrations
<person_mentioned>fryars </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>priests </person_mentioned>bearing crosses, a splendid Image of <person_mentioned>the virgin</person_mentioned>
at the head of <location_mentioned>calle de los Plateros</location_mentioned> fronting the <location_mentioned>great square</location_mentioned>—
another at the entrance of his <location_mentioned>Palace </location_mentioned>the windows and doors of
which were hung with curtains and festoons, as was also the street
leading from the tryumphal arch to the <location_mentioned>Palace</location_mentioned>, the whole of which
was fancifully illuminated with small lamps suspended in festoons
across the street throughout its whole extent presenting when viewed
from either extremity the appearance of Millions of stars suspended
over the Street below the eves of the houses—a Splendid Gilt 
tryumphal car was also made at the cost of the <location_mentioned>City </location_mentioned>in which it was
intended to have drawn the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>into the <location_mentioned>City </location_mentioned>from the Gate;
but he, probably thinking that his journey had afforded no cause of
tryumph, prudently defeated this design by making his entrance
in the night previous to the day he was expected—</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>admirers of H. M.</person_mentioned> however were determined their labour
should not be lost, and accordingly a procession was formed which
moved from the <location_mentioned>Monastary of St. Francisco </location_mentioned>composed of about 100
<person_mentioned>fryars </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>priests </person_mentioned>bearing crosses, a splendid Image of the <person_mentioned>Virgin
Mary</person_mentioned> as large as life clothed in silver and standing on a fanciful
pedestal of Glass—<person_mentioned>Christ </person_mentioned>on the Cross and a quantity of <person_mentioned>Saints</person_mentioned>—
Preceeded by the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>[75] body Guard of Horse next followed
the Car drawn by <person_mentioned>fryars </person_mentioned>in which was the Portrait of <person_mentioned>H. M.</person_mentioned> 
supported by two <person_mentioned>Priests</person_mentioned>—a full <person_mentioned>Band </person_mentioned>of Music a <person_mentioned>detachment of
Infantry</person_mentioned> and an immence crowd of the Rabie populace closed the
line—This farce was succeeded [by] others of a similar character,
the Car was hauled and rehauled through the Streets and 
illuminations and incessant and deafning peals of Bells seemed to occupy
the whole attention of the <person_mentioned>People</person_mentioned>—It was however manifest to all
and was even observed with regret by the tools and creatures of the
<person_mentioned>Emperor</person_mentioned>, that the great mass of the respectable and intelligent part
of the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>viewed these displays with the disapprobation and
contempt they merited—in the train of the Car was seen none but
<person_mentioned>fryars</person_mentioned>, a few servile <person_mentioned>officers </person_mentioned>who had been promoted for their 
personal exertions in proclaiming the <person_mentioned>Emperor </person_mentioned>or insulting the <person_mentioned>congress</person_mentioned>
and the lowest dregs of the Rabble who are a nearly perfect 
conterpart of the <person_mentioned>Lazeroni of <location_mentioned>Naples</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> except being a mixture of <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned><barker_pb n="564"/>
half and quarter <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>etc. and in the last grade of ignorance
fanatisicm poverty, nakedness and misery—The <person_mentioned>Ayuntamiento</person_mentioned>
about this time also set to work preparing for the "Jura" or 
cerimony of taking the oath of allegiance of the <person_mentioned>E.</person_mentioned>—a temple was erected
in the <location_mentioned>great square</location_mentioned> nearly fronting the <location_mentioned>Cathedral </location_mentioned>presenting 
porticoes on the four sides supported by collumns about 20 feet in
height, the entablatures and fronts of which adorned with large 
historical paintings representing the "<person_mentioned>Heroe of Iguala</person_mentioned>" in the various
stages of his progress from a Spanish Colonel to Imperial diadem-—
such as proclaiming the plan of <location_mentioned>Iguala </location_mentioned>on the <date_mentioned n="02-24-1820">24 February 1820</date_mentioned> [sic],
the ratification of the treaty of <location_mentioned>Cordova</location_mentioned>, the takeing of <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>by the
<person_mentioned>trigarante army</person_mentioned> on the <date_mentioned n="09-27-1821">27 Sept.</date_mentioned> following, his proclamation as
<location_mentioned>Emperor </location_mentioned>on the night of <date_mentioned n="05-18-1822">18 May 1822</date_mentioned>, his coronation on the <date_mentioned n="07-21-1822">21
July </date_mentioned>&c, &c. An <location_mentioned>amphitheater </location_mentioned>for the Bull fight was also erected
in a part of the same <location_mentioned>square </location_mentioned>fronting the <location_mentioned>Palace </location_mentioned>of the <person_mentioned>Vice Roys
</person_mentioned>now <location_mentioned>Imperial Palace</location_mentioned>, and on the site of the circular enclosure which
surrounded the Collossal Brown Statue of <person_mentioned>Charles the 4</person_mentioned>, Mounted
on horseback, this enclosure was about 100 yards in diamiter
entirely of hewn and carved stone, within the surface was elevated
about 4 feet above the level of the <location_mentioned>great square</location_mentioned> and paved with hewn
stone up to the foot of the statue, which rose in the center on a
pedestal</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
