
<TEI.2 id="APB0590">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-20-1823</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 644-645</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>James E. B. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to James E. B. Austin, 05-20-1823</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Monterrey, Coahuila</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Sentiment strong for Federal Republic. Evils of Central Republic. The clergy. The people "priest-ridden," superstitious, and fanatical.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>The suggestion was sufficient. On June 5: "Ordered by the president of the Junta
that two copies should be sent to the Colorado and Brazos—Baron de Bastrop, Presidente
de la Junta." The copy to the citizens of the Brazos is the same as the letter to the
Junta, May 17, above, but is dated May 20. A copy by Mirabeau B. Lamar, without
date, and differing slightly from this, is in the Lamar Papers, Texas State Library.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 644-645</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0590T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Sentiment strong for Federal Republic. Evils of Central Republic. The clergy. The people "priest-ridden," superstitious, and fanatical.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Monterrey </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="05-20-1823">May 20. 1823</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned></p>

<p>I have been here several days wating for the <person_mentioned>Comt Genl</person_mentioned> who is
expected this evening. I shall probably start in three or four days
after his arrival and hope to embrace you once more in a short time.</p>

<p>I have written to the <person_mentioned>Junta Governativa</person_mentioned> and to the <person_mentioned>Baron </person_mentioned>
informing them of my arrival thus far and I wish you to send notice 
thereof to the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>as I am told they are very much discouraged and
that many talk of returning back—It will be an unfortunate event
for the whole <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>if this <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>is broken up, and I think
it would have a good effect on the minds of the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>if the <person_mentioned>Junta</person_mentioned>
could publish my letter to them, but say nothing of this to any one
except the <person_mentioned>Baron </person_mentioned>or <person_mentioned>Erasmo</person_mentioned>. I am told you have a <location_mentioned>newspaper </location_mentioned>in
<location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>which I am rejoiced to hear it will be of incalculable 
advantage to <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>and the whole <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned>—I have no company but
one <person_mentioned>servant</person_mentioned>, and if I meet with none at <location_mentioned>Laredo </location_mentioned>shall go through with
him for I am so anxious to get home that nothing shall detain me—
The <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>is parched with the drought and corn very high—
the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>in this quarter are all in favor of a <location_mentioned>Federal Republic</location_mentioned> I
hope <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>is the same a <location_mentioned>Central Republic </location_mentioned>is the worst Govt in
the world—for all the power will be in the hands of a few men in
<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and instead of a <location_mentioned>Republic </location_mentioned>it will in effect be an <location_mentioned>aristocracy</location_mentioned>
which is worse than a <location_mentioned>monarchy</location_mentioned>, for in it we shall have 100 <person_mentioned>Tyrants</person_mentioned><barker_pb n="645"/>
instead of one, I do not wish to take an active part in politics, but
if I can do anything in favour of the confederate system, I will do
so with pleasure—In the <location_mentioned>city of Mexico</location_mentioned> and everywhere else where
there are <person_mentioned>Fryars </person_mentioned>this system will be opposed those miserable drones
are the <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>of liberty, of human happiness and of the human
race—their <person_mentioned>converts </person_mentioned>instead of being consecrated to the sacred and
immaculate religion they profess are dens of "corruption, of 
intrigue, of infamy and vice—there never was a people so dreadfully
priestridden and enslaved by superstition and fanaticism as the
great part of this nation The <person_mentioned>clergy </person_mentioned>literally suck the blood of
the unfortunate people—will the great God of Justice and of truth,
will the lights of the age, permit such horrible abuses to exist much
longer? No—<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>has recoverd her civil liberty—She will soon
assume her rights in full, and bursting the chains of superstition
declare that <hi rend="italic">man has a right to think for himself.</hi></p>

<p>Farewell may we soon meet in happiness remember me to all
<person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Estevan F. Austin</person_mentioned>    [Rubric]</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
