
<TEI.2 id="APB0854">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>09-11-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 894</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Henry Holstein</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Henry Holstein to Stephen F. Austin, 09-11-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Impediments to emigration to Texas.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 894</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-18-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0854T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Impediments to emigration to Texas.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><date_mentioned n="09-11-1824">September the 11 1824</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear sir I take this opportunity of informing you that I am
well and hope these few lines will find you in the same state of good
health. Sir I wish you to let me kno the first opportunity that offers
whether there is any Chance for me to hold that land I was to of
had In your settlement I kno that you are not under any 
obligatons to me now as I did not fufill my part of the Contract but sir
I think if you will take every thing into Consideration and hear the
Cause of my not being there on time in the first place the 
inteligence that we had hear that the vessel was lost with <person_mentioned>edward Lovelaice</person_mentioned>
and the <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>was the Cause of my not Coming to that country
against the time mentioned in the articles and soon after hearing
that you was drownded Causd me to abandon the idia of ever setlin
in that province but hearing you are now on the <location_mentioned>labrasos [Brazos]</location_mentioned>
and has nearly made an end of your business I wish you would
right to me the first opportunity and let me kno whether you will
let me have the land or not I doo not expet to get Choice but would
be glad to get any good place the town lot I would be glad to
hold</p>

<p>If you think propper to grant me the quantity of land mentioned
I will be a Citizen of that place as soon as my situation will permit
which will be soon after hearing from you I will be glad if you will
wright me a satisfactory letter on the subject</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Henry H. Holstein</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] To <person_mentioned>Mr Stephen F. Osten</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Province of Texes Osten
settlement</location_mentioned>.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
