
<TEI.2 id="APB0238">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-29-1813</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 232-233</document_citation>
<document_language>english</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>S. Hammond</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Moses Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>S. Hammond to Moses Austin, 12-29-1813</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>St Louis, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Burton Mine, MO</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Charter of the Bank of St. Louis. Speculation at Herculaneum.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 232-233</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-30-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0238T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Charter of the Bank of St. Louis. Speculation at Herculaneum.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p><location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="12-29-1813">29th Decr 1813</date_mentioned>.</p>
<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p>Your favor of the <date_mentioned n="12-26-1813">26th </date_mentioned>came to hand by your <person_mentioned>Son </person_mentioned><date_mentioned n="12-28-1813">last Evening</date_mentioned>, I
am sorry you could not yourself make us a Visite during Our present
Session, I think you could have aided the progress of Our banking
Schemes—We have had several meetings of the <person_mentioned>Commissioners </person_mentioned>I
have finally agreed upon attempting by petition to obtain a New
Charter; Which Charter drawn up will accompany the Petition and
probably be presented <date_mentioned n="12-30-1813">tomorrow</date_mentioned>, the new Charter will imbrace
most of the alterations proposed by you and also much of the Old
bill— We hold fast the Old Charter, so that if we fail to procure
a new Charter the old one stands secure and <location_mentioned>St Genevieve</location_mentioned> will also
fail in their application—after which I presume they would go
heartily into the <location_mentioned>bank </location_mentioned>under the Old Law—I wish <person_mentioned>Stephen </person_mentioned>was not
so much hurreyed up on his Return—I could have wished that he
should have seen the new Charter, but if he goes (as he intends)
today, he can not have a perusal thereof— the new bill has been
drawn by <person_mentioned>Easton</person_mentioned>, under the superintendance of <person_mentioned>Judge Lucas</person_mentioned> and
assisted by <person_mentioned>Christian Wilt</person_mentioned>.</p><barker_pb n="233"/>

<p>With Respect to <location_mentioned>Herculaneum </location_mentioned>I feel myself necessitated to sell my
Proportion as Soon as Convenient to free me from approaching 
imbarrassments— My Estimate of the Value of <location_mentioned>Herculaneum </location_mentioned>is much
beyond what Could be expected to be obtained for it at this time. I
have been offered for all the unsold lotts in the town together with
all the Residue of the tract of land out of which the Town has been
taken and also the lotts and Improvements therein formerly Occupied
by <person_mentioned>Baker</person_mentioned>, Three Thousand Dollars One Half in goods at stipulated
advance and the Other in money in the month of <date_mentioned n="05-xx-1814">May next</date_mentioned>—this
offer, I do not find entirely meeting my convenience because I have
no occasion for goods and have no wish to be peddling— Your
friend <person_mentioned>Mr Bryant</person_mentioned> or your self may have the same property for the
same Price if you wish it and the Payments shall be made as 
Convenient as my Circumstances will admit off— I could wish to know
your determination upon the subject before we adjourn as I would
like to Close a sale to Others if you decline to purchase, before I go
from this, and also I should think it would be to your interest and
for your convenience to have a division of the unsold lotts before
I sell to any persons not of your family or friends—this is altogether.
a measure for your convenience and will be governed by your Will—
I am sorry I cannot write you more fully I could indeed explain
more satisfactorily to <person_mentioned>both parties</person_mentioned> Verbally—therefore I will hope
to see you or <person_mentioned>Mr Bryant</person_mentioned> on the subject Either while I remain here or
immediately upon my Return Home— Please make a tender of
Respects and good wishes acceptable to <person_mentioned>Mr Austin</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Mr Bryant</person_mentioned> and
am Sincerely</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. Hammond </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>My Opinion of the Value of the <location_mentioned>property at Herculaneum </location_mentioned>offered
for sale is as follows—</p>

<p>221. Lotts unsold or there about cheap @ 80 Each is ______ 	$6630. 00

Resedue of the Tract of land______________________________   3000.
										_________
										 9630. 00
<location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Baker</person_mentioned>s House</location_mentioned> and two lots cost me_________________________     35. 00 [Sic]
										_________
										 9665. 00</p>
<p>1/2 9630
________
    4815
     350 <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Baker</person_mentioned>s lotts</location_mentioned> etc
________
    5165 Exclusive of the ferry and <location_mentioned>forfeited lotts</location_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Moses Austin Esquire</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Mine a Breton County of
Washington</location_mentioned> Hand by <person_mentioned>Mr. S. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
