
<TEI.2 id="APB0367">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-23-1820</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 370-371</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Examination of Moses Austin</document_type>
<document_author>Unknown</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Unknown</document_recipient>
<document_title>Unknown to Unknown, 12-23-1820</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Fernando de Bexar</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Examination of Moses Austin before Gov. Martinez. Conditions on the Texan-United States frontier. Purpose of journey to Texas.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>A liberal translation of a Spanish copy in the Nacogdoches Archives, Texas State
Library.
Dr. James Long, whose invasion of Texas had been repelled m 1819 He was known
to be preparing a second invasion which, in fact began the following February.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 370-371</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-10-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0367T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Examination of Moses Austin before Gov. Martinez. Conditions on the Texan-United States frontier. Purpose of journey to Texas.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>At the <location_mentioned>City of San Fernando de Bexar</location_mentioned>, the <date_mentioned n="12-3-1820">23d day of December,
A D 1820</date_mentioned>: The <person_mentioned>Governor of the <location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned>, Colonel Don
Antonio Martinez</person_mentioned>, in order to obtain detailed information about
the condition of affairs and movements on the <location_mentioned>frontier of the United
States</location_mentioned>, and the assembly of men in <location_mentioned>Galveston Island</location_mentioned>, summoned to
appear at this office the foreigner <person_mentioned>Moses Austin</person_mentioned>, who arrived <date_mentioned n="12-23-1820">to-day</date_mentioned>
in this city, with two other persons. Said <person_mentioned>Moses Austin</person_mentioned> being 
present was required through the <person_mentioned>Baron de Bastrop</person_mentioned> who had promised
well and truly to discharge the duty of <person_mentioned>Interpreter</person_mentioned>, to make true
answers to such questions as might be propounded to him, answered
as follows.</p>

<p>Questioned as to his name, native country and residence—
Answered : That he is a native of the <location_mentioned>State of Connecticut</location_mentioned>, actually a
<person_mentioned>resident of <location_mentioned>Missouri</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, is a <person_mentioned>catholic</person_mentioned>, a <person_mentioned>merchant </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>dealer in lead ore</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Asked:—Whence he came, who accompanied him, and what is his
object in entering this <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned>? Answered: That he came from
<location_mentioned>Missouri </location_mentioned>through <location_mentioned>Nachitotches</location_mentioned>, that he had been accompanied by
a <person_mentioned>negro boy</person_mentioned> belonging to him, and two other <person_mentioned>Americans</person_mentioned>; that he came
to this <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>for the purpose of applying to the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>for
authorization to settle himself in it with his <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>, inasmuch as he
had already been a <person_mentioned>subject of the Government of <location_mentioned>Spain</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, as is proved
by a passport, which he presented, signed by <person_mentioned>Don Carlos Martinez
de Irujo, Minister Plenipotentiary of His Majesty</person_mentioned>, signed at 
<location_mentioned>Philadelphia</location_mentioned>, the <date_mentioned n="07-13-1797">13th July, 1797</date_mentioned>; and that it is his intention to provide
for his subsistance by raising sugar and Cotton.</p>

<p>Asked: what observations he made on his way from <location_mentioned>Missouri</location_mentioned>; if
he knows anything about the movements of the <person_mentioned>banditti </person_mentioned>on the 
<location_mentioned>frontier of the United States</location_mentioned>, if he has seen, or heard, anything of the
state of affairs in <location_mentioned>Galveston Island</location_mentioned>, and to state whatever incident
may have called his attention.—Answered: That he has observed
nothing on his way from <location_mentioned>Missouri</location_mentioned>; that he had only heard it said at
<location_mentioned>Natchitoches </location_mentioned>that <person_mentioned>Long </person_mentioned>has been abandoned by his men, <person_mentioned>20 or 30
men</person_mentioned> only still remaining with him; that <person_mentioned>Lafitte </person_mentioned>has abandoned 
<location_mentioned>Galveston Island</location_mentioned>, after having been attacked by an American frigate,
and that the <person_mentioned>President of the Congress</person_mentioned> had promised a reward of
500 Dollars for the apprehension of <person_mentioned>Long [Lafitte]</person_mentioned> That <person_mentioned>Lafitte</person_mentioned>
repaired to <location_mentioned>South America</location_mentioned>, but that, on his departure from <location_mentioned>Galveston</location_mentioned>,
he captured an <person_mentioned>American </person_mentioned>ship, and put to death all her <person_mentioned>crew</person_mentioned>, except
two men who made good their escape; and finally, that he has read in<barker_pb n="371"/>
the <location_mentioned>American newspapers</location_mentioned> a treaty made by <location_mentioned>Don Luis de Onis, Spanish
Minister</location_mentioned>, with the <person_mentioned>American Congress</person_mentioned>, which treaty was already
signed by the <person_mentioned>King </person_mentioned>and approved by the <person_mentioned>Sovereign Congress of the
Cortes</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Asked; How, having obtained in<date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1797"> 1797</date_mentioned>, a passport from the <person_mentioned>Spanish
Minister</person_mentioned>, he has not applied sooner for the <location_mentioned>Settlement </location_mentioned>he intends
to make in this <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned>?—Answered,—that, since the year above
mentioned, he went to reside at<location_mentioned> Saint Louis (Missouri)</location_mentioned> which 
<location_mentioned>territory </location_mentioned>belonged, then to <location_mentioned>Spain</location_mentioned>; he had there <location_mentioned>lead mines</location_mentioned>, the produce
of which he exported to <location_mentioned>Havana</location_mentioned>, until the year <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1800">1800</date_mentioned> [sic], when the
<person_mentioned>American Government</person_mentioned> having prohibited the working of <location_mentioned>mines </location_mentioned>by
private enterprise, he lost all the benefit of his labor; but now, in view
of the new system of Government adopted by <location_mentioned>Spain</location_mentioned>, he resolved
upon aplying for authorization to settle in this <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned></p>

<p>Asked; If he, or his <person_mentioned>associates </person_mentioned>have with them any merchandize,
to declare the same in which case it should be sequestered and 
returned to them previous to their leaving this <location_mentioned>territory</location_mentioned>, or otherwise,
it should be seized upon as unlawful ?—Answered, that all the 
property he has with him, is an escopet, a pistol, two horses, some clothing
for his personal use, and the necessary amount of money for his
traveling expences; that, those who accompany him are not under
his control, and joined him at about six leagues from <location_mentioned>Natchitoches</location_mentioned>;
Still, he is satisfied that they have no goods of illicit trade</p>.

<p>Asked: If he has any further statements to make; Answered in the
negative, He, further, ratified the foregoing answers, and declared
himself to be 53 years of age; Whereupon, he signed these presents,
with me and assisting <person_mentioned>witnesses</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Moses Austin</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Antonio Martinez</person_mentioned>—
<person_mentioned>Baron de Bastrop</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Francisco Montes</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Ylario de la Garza</person_mentioned>.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
