
<TEI.2 id="APB0100">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-28-1806</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 105-107</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>William C Carr</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Moses Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>William C Carr to Moses Austin, 06-28-1806</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>St Genevieve, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary> Antedated mining surveys and titles.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Original in possession of Mrs. Emmett L. Perry.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 105-107</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-24-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0100T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Antedated mining surveys and titles.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>St Genevieve</location_mentioned> Sunday Morning <date_mentioned n="06-28-1806">28th. June 1806</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Dr Sir I arrived here on <date_mentioned n="06-23-1806">tuesday evening</date_mentioned>; before which many of
the large concessions in this <location_mentioned>district </location_mentioned>had undergone a partial 
investigation before the honorable board, However I arrived time enough
to have my eyes blessed with a sight of <location_mentioned>Prattes mine</location_mentioned> concession,
and his <person_mentioned>sons</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Camille Lassus</person_mentioned>' on flat river, <person_mentioned>Masons </person_mentioned>at <location_mentioned>Mine au
Breton</location_mentioned> etc. every one of which immediately on sight of them, I
challenged as <hi rend="italic">anti dated</hi>. This was the tocsin of alarm; and every
day we have had more or less <hi rend="italic">sparring </hi>on this subject, by the army
of anti daters</p>

<p>We have had <person_mentioned>C. Lassus</person_mentioned> title before us two or three times, and I
have proved by <person_mentioned>Madden </person_mentioned>that his survey is antidated from about
<date_mentioned n="08-xx-1802">August 1802</date_mentioned>, the time when it was actually made to the year <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1800">1800</date_mentioned>
at which time the virtuous <person_mentioned>Mr Soulard</person_mentioned>, certifies it was made. <person_mentioned>Mr
Maddin</person_mentioned> in giving in his testimony (or rather after we had for that
time closed it) was so eager to serve the <location_mentioned>U. S</location_mentioned> with evidence that he
produced one of your letters to him dated the <date_mentioned n="02-09-1802">9th February 1802</date_mentioned>, on
the subject of <person_mentioned>Camille </person_mentioned>surveying the <location_mentioned>Mine on flat river</location_mentioned>—" Stating
your surprise" at his attempts to acquire the land, (he <person_mentioned>Mr C.</person_mentioned>) 
knowing the pretensions you had thereto. Al tho a certificate which you
mention as having been given by <person_mentioned>Mr Maddin</person_mentioned> and now, lodged at
<location_mentioned>Orleans</location_mentioned>, and which upon interrogation he told me went to the point
of the Vacancy of the land He said, he also supposed you had 
obtained a similar one from <person_mentioned>Francois Vallée</person_mentioned> Further that you were
in daily expectations of hearing from <location_mentioned>Orleans</location_mentioned>, on the subject of
your application (I suppose) This letter al tho apparently produced
to benefit the <person_mentioned>U S</person_mentioned> in proving the date of <person_mentioned>C</person_mentioned>'s survey, were 
nevertheless produced to injure you; by shewing in the first place your 
intention to defraud <person_mentioned>Luzierre </person_mentioned>out of the land or to prevent him from
obtaining it; or secondly to manifest your disposition and desire of
obtaining concessions which must have been antidated;  and also<barker_pb n="106"/>
much land. To accomplish this patriotic and laudable object, they
have filed the letter, and ordered it to be spread upon the Records,
The intent was so plain, that nothing but the pleasure of 
anticipating the effect which this stroke of malice must unavoidably produce ;
could have prevented me at the time from manifesting that dignity
of contempt with which such pitiful actions ought to be treated.</p>

<p><location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Mason</person_mentioned>s survey </location_mentioned>is also antidated 3 years, proven by <person_mentioned>Maddin</person_mentioned>. This
petition, <person_mentioned>Old Prattes</person_mentioned>, and his <person_mentioned>sons </person_mentioned>are all in the hand writing of
<person_mentioned>Bte Pratte</person_mentioned>; and it now depends on his testimony to prove them
antidated or not. I do not know how he will swear But one thing is
[certain] if he does prove those of his <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>brother </person_mentioned>to have
been written at the time they bear date his testimony shall not be
conclusive; I strongly believe, these concessions and <person_mentioned>Mason</person_mentioned>s also are
antidated—   But whether I shall be able to prove it I cannot tell.</p>

<p>Much disputation has taken place, about the time of <person_mentioned>Mason</person_mentioned>s 
making his first establishment at the <location_mentioned>Mines</location_mentioned>; 1st when did he first work
the <location_mentioned>Mines</location_mentioned>? 2ndly When did he first inclose and cultivate any land
there ? 3rdly. When did he move his <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>there ?—<person_mentioned>Mr Bte Valle</person_mentioned>,
swore he went there in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1797">97</date_mentioned> and (probably) built a cabbin, raised a
crop in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1798">98</date_mentioned> and moved his <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>on it in that year or <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1799">99</date_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Old Mr
Decelle</person_mentioned> appears to be some what at variance with <person_mentioned>Mr Valle</person_mentioned>, as to
the quantity of ground cultivated and the time of moving on the
<person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>— It must have been late in the year of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1799">99 </date_mentioned>that his <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>
went on it; if at all that year. Because in <date_mentioned n="03-14-1799">March 14th. 99</date_mentioned> a sale was
effected by <person_mentioned>Mason </person_mentioned>to you of a <location_mentioned>house and lot in this Village</location_mentioned>; and <person_mentioned>Doctr.
Fenwick</person_mentioned> says he lived in it with his <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>some time after the
sale. These are points to be ascertained and you must not be 
surprised if my duty compells me to summon you with <person_mentioned>Elias Bates</person_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>Mr Decelle </person_mentioned>etc etc. on behalf the <location_mentioned>U S</location_mentioned> to attend at <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned>. If I
had have known old <person_mentioned>Mr Decelle</person_mentioned>s intention of visiting this place I
should certainly have requested him to have brought with him his
documents on the subject of land titles</p>.

<p>The testimony in <person_mentioned>old Prattes</person_mentioned> case is very strong— That he began
the establishment in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1797">97</date_mentioned> or <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1798">98 </date_mentioned>and cultivated and improved it ever
since. I informed the <person_mentioned>Commissioners </person_mentioned>of the Memorial in my 
possession, but at <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned> from the <person_mentioned>inhabitants of <location_mentioned>big river</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> on this
subject, which I should take an opportunity of showing to them at
that place— As to this claim I shall Summon the <person_mentioned>Alley</person_mentioned>'s, <person_mentioned>Andrews</person_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>Baker </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Pagette</person_mentioned>. And in the case of <person_mentioned>Camille Lassus</person_mentioned>, as to the
date of concession I shall summon <person_mentioned>Moses Austin</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Abraham 
Armstrong</person_mentioned>, as to the discovery and cultivation, <person_mentioned>Armstrong</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Purceall </person_mentioned>the
<person_mentioned>Alley</person_mentioned>s— Information on these subjects will be gratefully received
as to the requisites of the Act of Congress and the <person_mentioned>witnesses </person_mentioned>to sup-<barker_pb n="107"/>
port them or <person_mentioned>witnesses </person_mentioned>to disprove what has already been, (in my
opinion in several occasions) erroneously established.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Commrs</person_mentioned>. discover much anxiety to know whether you intend
to have your title passed before them or not and from their 
suggestions they think it is not a complete title. On this subject you need
not be uneasy, as I very well know you will not. you shall hear
from me again on this subject if time and opportunity permit.</p>

<p>I am exceedingly anxious about the collection of testimony which
I am ordered to make, touching the title of the <location_mentioned>lead mines</location_mentioned>— I have
not received such satisfactory information as to the title to <location_mentioned>Mine
La motte</location_mentioned> as I wished and. expected— It appears that the <person_mentioned>claimants</person_mentioned>
have acted very, unwisely on this subject, for they have not had any
of the <location_mentioned>old French grants</location_mentioned> given in 61.2 3 and 4 recorded; but <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Lassus</person_mentioned>'
grant of 2 leagues</location_mentioned> under which I suspect they will find it difficult to
hold such property. I wish to God you would make me a statement
of the probable amount of lead made at <location_mentioned>Mine a Breton</location_mentioned> and <location_mentioned>old
Mines</location_mentioned> for the year of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1804">1804 </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1805">5</date_mentioned>. I shall see you again I suppose 
before you start down the river.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Comrs</person_mentioned>. finished their sessions here <date_mentioned n="06-27-1806">yesterday </date_mentioned>and took their
departure for <location_mentioned>St. Louis</location_mentioned> to celebrate the <date_mentioned n="07-04-1806">4th of July</date_mentioned>— I shall leave
this <date_mentioned n="06-29-1806">tomorrow </date_mentioned>I expect and it is not unlikely that I shall be at the
<location_mentioned>Mines </location_mentioned>again e'er long.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Will C. Carr</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>How do your charming <person_mentioned>guests</person_mentioned>? are they speedily recruiting?
Do they often visit the <location_mentioned>Hop Walk</location_mentioned>? etc etc etc My respects will be
borne them I trust by you, as also to <person_mentioned>Mrs Austin</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Mr. and Mrs.
Penniman</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>W. C. C</person_mentioned>.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
