
<TEI.2 id="APB0660">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-04-1823</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 714-715</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Josiah H. Bell</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Josiah H. Bell, 12-04-1823</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Barter. Conflicting land claims.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 714-715</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-16-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0660T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Barter. Conflicting land claims.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><date_mentioned n="12-04-1823">Decr 4, 1823</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p>I wish you to attend particularly to the enclosed and pray try
and get me all the money you can as I must have some to send for
my <person_mentioned>mother </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>sister</person_mentioned>—Sell the powder for $2 in cash or 250 in
shaved deer skins at 15 cents pr pound or Bees wax at 5 cents pr
pound I wish to get <person_mentioned>Capt Ga . . .</person_mentioned> [mutilated] to take care of my
colts—when you move bring down my little things that I left with
you clothe etc as far as this—</p>

<p>I thought all <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>were satisfied relative to the land below
when you left here—there will be no cause for dissatisfaction—
When I first explored that part of the country two years ago I
chose two places, one on the <location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>and one here, the one on the
<location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>was occupied on my return from <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and I have given
it up and the one <location_mentioned>on this river</location_mentioned> is now taken by you and earner—
I am not difficult to please nor avaricious and will sacrifice my own
interests at any time in favor of those I esteem or wish to serve—
You and <person_mentioned>Varner </person_mentioned>told me there was another <location_mentioned>creek </location_mentioned>below the one
you chose, I am told by others that there is none and no <location_mentioned>prairie</location_mentioned>. I
wanted a place at the <location_mentioned>bottom of the big Prairie</location_mentioned> to live at and I
thought after what passed between us here that all <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>were
satisfied but from what I have heard since you are dissatisfied that
I should take a quarter of a league there and have made reflections
that if it had not been for you the whole settlement would have
b[roken] etc. I will never suffer any man to lay me under an
obligation  without  more than  an  equivalent  and  shall  therefore<barker_pb n="715"/>
not take an inch at that place if I have to drink river water you
can therefore remove as soon as you please with the assurance that
no one shall interfere with you; all I wish in future relative to
such matters is that when an understanding is once made let there
be no reflections made about it afterwards—</p>

<p>Present my respects to <person_mentioned>Mrs Bell</person_mentioned> and be assured that I am</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>J. H. Bell</person_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
