
<TEI.2 id="APB0770">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-05-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 825-827</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Public</document_status>
<document_type>Petition</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Congress</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Congress, 06-05-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, TX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Privilege of raising tobacco. Argument for encouragement of agriculture.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>This date should be June 16. See page 832.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 825-827</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-17-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0770T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Privilege of raising tobacco. Argument for encouragement of agriculture.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>[Copy by Austin.]</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Jared E. Groce</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>James Cummings</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Jno.
P Coles</person_mentioned> a <person_mentioned>Committe </person_mentioned>unamimously appointed at a General Meeting
held on the <date_mentioned n="06-05-1824">5th of June</date_mentioned> instant the <person_mentioned>Inhabitants of the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> formd
in the <person_mentioned>Province of Texas</person_mentioned> by the <person_mentioned>empresario S F Austin</person_mentioned> in the name<barker_pb n="826"/>
and in the behalf of said <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>respectfully represent to your
sovereignty that should it be deemed Consistent with the general 
interest of the Nation they solicit that the priviledge of raising Tobacco
should be granted to the <location_mentioned>province of Texas</location_mentioned> on the same terms as
allowed to the Towns <location_mentioned>Orizava </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>Cordova </location_mentioned>etc or on such terms as your
sovereignty may deem proper and also the priviledge of raising that
article for exportation—</p>

<p>This is a priviledge if granted will in the humble Opinion of these
<person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>Greatly benefit the <location_mentioned>eastern section of the Nation</location_mentioned> 
without in the least injuring that branch of the Revenue derived from
Tobacco and it is also one which it is conceived that the peculiar
situation of this <location_mentioned>province </location_mentioned>and the long sufferings and distresses of
its <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>gives them strong Claims to ask for— The <location_mentioned>province
of Texas</location_mentioned> must solely depend upon Agriculture for its support 
having no <location_mentioned>mines </location_mentioned>to enrich it. Also its situation on the <location_mentioned>sea Coast</location_mentioned> will
afford great facilities for the exportation of its Agricultural 
productions</p>

<p>If therefore the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>will encourage its Agriculture it
Might rise from its present state of wretchedness and misery and 
instead of being an expense to the <location_mentioned>Nation </location_mentioned>to defend it from the 
<person_mentioned>savages </person_mentioned>as it now is it probably would in a short time be able to afford
its full quota with the other States towards the support and defence
of the <person_mentioned>Mexican Government</person_mentioned>— It therefore appears to these 
<person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>that numerous benefits would result from this priviledge—it
would aid the distressed <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>of this Country [to recover] the
losses caused by 10 years horrid war with <person_mentioned>savages </person_mentioned>it would encourage
agriculture which has alwas been considered the safest and most
solid weath of any nation—and which has therefore been protected
and encouraged by the Civilised World, it would save in the Country
much money that would be otherwise sent out to purchase Tobacco
for the National Estanque and it would actually bring into the
Country large sums of Money and Merchandise that would be 
received in <location_mentioned>foreign Countries</location_mentioned> for the exported Tobacco and thus give
greater activity and extention to our Commerce and industry and
oil these advantages it appears to these Inhabitants would be 
produced without in the least injuring the national Revenue produced
from Tobacco because all that would be sold in the Country would
be delivered to the Government and Consequently the monopoly in
that Article would continue unimpaired—</p>

<p>Should it not be considered proper to grant this priviledge to this
whole province these <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>respectfully hope that the 
distresses and Sufferings they have undergone in Establishing a 
<location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>in an entire <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>surrounded on every side by hostile.
<person_mentioned>savages </person_mentioned>and struggling as they have through one whole year with<barker_pb n="827"/>
famine will plead for them with your sovereignty to grant to this
Colonial establishment the priviledge of raising Tobacco being a
species of Culture which these <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>have been accustomed to
from their Childhood and in which they Can therefor promise 
themselves the greatest success.</p>

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="06-10-1824">June 10, 1824</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Signed  <person_mentioned>Estevan F Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<person_mentioned>Jared E. Groce</person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>Santiago Cummings</person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>Jno P. Coles</person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>Comte</person_mentioned>.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
