
<TEI.2 id="APB0865">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>09-21-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 900-904</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>John Hawkins</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>John Hawkins to Stephen F. Austin, 09-21-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Missouri</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Washington County, Mo. Evil reports check emigration to Texas. Merchants opposed to anyone's moving. Truth barely reaches Red River going northward before it is "detected and stopped." Mexican Constitution good, except religious intolerance. Conditions in Missouri.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Printed in the <hi rend="italic">Texas History Teacher's Bulletin</hi>, February, 1918.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 900-904</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-18-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
 
<text id="APB0865T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Washington County, Mo. Evil reports check emigration to Texas. Merchants opposed to anyone's moving. Truth barely reaches Red River going northward before it is "detected and stopped." Mexican Constitution good, except religious intolerance. Conditions in Missouri.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Prearie Spring County of Washington Missouri</location_mentioned></p>

<p><date_mentioned n="09-21-1824">Sept the 21th—1824</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Sr</p>

<p>I am here yet, Contrary to my wishes. I was in hopes of being
with you before now—but I find it one of the hardest things I ever
had to undergo—to have the Consent of my <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>to be seperated.
I would have been there before this time had It not been on that
acct I have no Chance to go without I Can take them all. I have
hopes of Bringing that About in the Course of one or two years,
if I Live So Long— <person_mentioned>John Jones</person_mentioned> has Exchanged his house and Lot
where he kept <location_mentioned>Publick house</location_mentioned>, the <location_mentioned>League house</location_mentioned> where <person_mentioned>Amable 
partney</person_mentioned> Lived to <person_mentioned>Danl Dunklin</person_mentioned> for his house and Lot and got Eight
hundred and fifty Dollars to boot—As he has began to Trade and
move suppose it is a very small Distance. It may be a begining of
fixing for moving A Longer, the minds of men Changes sometimes
very suddenly and very Contrary to what they once Expected. And
I have some hopes of that being the case with <person_mentioned>Messrs Jones and<barker_pb n="901"/>
Browne</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Betsey </person_mentioned>Is married and Living in the <location_mentioned>Allabamy </location_mentioned>It is no
difference to her wheather we go or stay—I am tinder many 
obligations to you for the statement you gave me dated <date_mentioned n="08-10-1823">10th august 1823</date_mentioned>—
I also Recd one Dated <date_mentioned n="07-17-1823">July 17</date_mentioned>—Emediatly on your arrivel from
<location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>—I have done Every thing in my power to Cause the people
to Emigrate to that Country, but so many fals Reports Comes from
there that If a man has not been there he is too apt to believe such
Reports and Decline going for my part I am better pleased with
the Country than Any I Ever saw—I was some uneasy when I heard
that <person_mentioned>Iterbide </person_mentioned>was about to go back, but I saw In the <location_mentioned>St. Louis</location_mentioned> 
paper that him and two <person_mentioned>priests </person_mentioned>ware on their way to <location_mentioned>Spain </location_mentioned>and landed
at some <location_mentioned>Spanish Island</location_mentioned> and ware arrested and he was tried and
Condemned and shot I do not at this time Recollect what <location_mentioned>Island</location_mentioned>
It was since that I understand It has made Its appearance In 
several other papers so that I hope It is True and hope you will have
peace if It is so that he is Dead, the priests Remained in 
Confinement—I wish you to give me an acct of whare you Expect [to] Erect
or Establish your <location_mentioned>port of Entry</location_mentioned> and tell me If any thing Can be
Carried from this Country for your Markit that will comand Cash
or Cotton Let me know if there will be much Cotton made there
Next season, Let me know If you would have any kind of Business
you Could put me at that I Could Make money at for a few months
I have a wish to Come again and visit that Country—If I Could do
it to some advantage I would be willing to stay a year if I Could
get Into Business that would justify staying I Can do nothing here
more than Live, If there is the Least appearance of my making
money directly there Is an Execution and Disconsirts all my plans
so that I have Intirely quit Trying for any thing more than to
Make what we Can comfortably Live on—all the Inginuity that has
been made use of against me has Not Deprived me of Living 
tollerable well and I hope will Not, My <person_mentioned>Boys </person_mentioned>are got to be able to Carry
on the <location_mentioned>farm </location_mentioned>very well now and to Do business in their own Names
So that they Cannot take Every thing as they have done before—
please to write me frequently as you Can send to me by mail If
you send it by private Conveyence to any <location_mentioned>post office</location_mentioned> It will Come
Safe most Commonly, but If I send to you By mail It stops at the
outside office and the post masters will not Try to forward them,
when <person_mentioned>John Jones</person_mentioned> wrote me and Requested the <person_mentioned>post master at 
<location_mentioned>Natchitoches</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to forward it on to the <location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>But it stoped there, until
I Came in, on My way <location_mentioned>home </location_mentioned>and was that Day I applied for It,
had been packed up to send to <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>post master general</person_mentioned>'s office</location_mentioned>, I sent
6 or 7 Letters to <location_mentioned>Natchitoches </location_mentioned>and had put in the office and all Came
safe to my <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>—Only Letters you Can git safe in to the <location_mentioned>Office</location_mentioned>
will Come safe No doubt, I had several Letters from Different<barker_pb n="902"/>
parts that ware put into that office that Came as soon as I had a
right to Expect them— If any thing should offer that you think
would be profitable that I Could take a hold of, with one of my
sons If it was necessary to Bring one with me please to Let me know
as soon as you Can in the way have above mentioned as I am 
Desirious to be in that Country and In giting into business in some
Rich way It would be a means of giting my family all in a way to
go—when they once begin to see that some thing was Doing to 
advantage a hope of gain is the great spring to Every thing almost
that we undertake, for my own part I have my own consent to put
off, as soon as possible I have six sons and all able to Do some thing
on a farm but one Some of them Capable of almost any business
If your port of Entry was Established and a ware house Errected
If you think we Could fill the place of attending to that and had
not promised It to some other person I would be willing to Try that
Business a while or any thing Else that I Could make money at If
I Could go there my self and git into Business my <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>would
soon after agree to go But there is such numorous Reports 
unfavourable to the Country that It is hard to make people believe the
Truth the <person_mentioned>Merchants </person_mentioned>in particular are more opposed to people
moving to that Country or any other than Ever I saw people before
my life but It is not all they Can say will alter my mind a thing that
I know of my own knowledge I should have been with you this
<date_mentioned n="Summer-1824">last summer </date_mentioned>But I was Like to Loose my Eye sight for near two
months But have Recovered It again about as well as usual— I
wish you to write by <person_mentioned>Mr Hail</person_mentioned> Consearning the government If times
has got quiet at <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and like to Remain so— I have seen the
Constitution your [brother?] had it I think well of It [if] they
will only Live up to it—it is a good one so far as I Can Judge of
It Except that of Religion is an objection to a great Number of
people for my own part I Care nothing about it know I Can be
as good a <person_mentioned>Cristian </person_mentioned>there as I can here It is only a name anyhow
I think you had better have the Constitution published in the 
<location_mentioned>St-Louis paper</location_mentioned> and In <location_mentioned>Kintucky paper</location_mentioned> If you wish the Country to
Emigrate very fast they Do not generally believe that the 
Constitution Is as good as It is— Any advantages that Country has
that is Not generally known you would do well to have published
as Ever good thing is kept Consealed as much as possible It is
very hard for the Truth [to] git as far as here it scearcely Can
git on this side <location_mentioned>Red River</location_mentioned> before It is Detected and stoped I 
understand <person_mentioned>Mr Rob and Mr Jos. Kuykndale</person_mentioned> has moved from where
I left them on the <location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>and as that is the Case you need not
Reserve that Land for me any Longer as I wish to be attached to
some strong <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>when I come   I also wish to be as near the<barker_pb n="903"/>
<location_mentioned>town </location_mentioned>as I Can git—so as to be Convenient to markit If we Should
have any thing to sell I wish If I am not too Late a speaking, you
would Reserve me a good situation as near the town as Can be had—
with a good Spring on It as that is a very particular thing with
<person_mentioned>Mrs Hawkins</person_mentioned> on acct of making Butter I hope in god I shall be
with you <date_mentioned n="Summer-1825">Next Summer</date_mentioned> Either with or without my <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>— Now
we will talk of the affairs of my own Country We have good Crops
of Corn heare this season Crops of wheat not good the wetest Spring
and Summer and up to the <date_mentioned n="09-10-1824">10th Sept</date_mentioned> I believe I Ever saw in this
Country people very healthy through out the State in General—<person_mentioned>Mrs
Brady</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Scott the Lawyer</person_mentioned> was married Last Monday Evening
the <date_mentioned n="09-20-1824">20th Instant</date_mentioned> and your sister <person_mentioned>Mrs Bryens</person_mentioned> will be married 
<date_mentioned n="09-23-1824">Thursday Evening the 23rd Instant</date_mentioned> to <person_mentioned>Mr Jas F perry</person_mentioned> which I think a
very suitable good Match your <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>will have to Return with
out her, there is <person_mentioned>Mrs Dedrick</person_mentioned> an other fine young <person_mentioned>widow </person_mentioned>Remains,
If you was here you perhaps might git her as there Is so much
friendship Existing between you and her <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Col° John Smith
T</person_mentioned>— It is supposed that <person_mentioned>Robt Brown</person_mentioned> and her will unite in the Bonds
of Matrimony Shortly— <person_mentioned>Edward Brown</person_mentioned> his <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>died three
weeks past in <location_mentioned>St Louis</location_mentioned> and was brought Down to <location_mentioned>potosi </location_mentioned>and Buried
with his <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned>— <person_mentioned>Major Henry</person_mentioned> has Returned from
beyond the <location_mentioned>Rocky mountains</location_mentioned> he supposes he was <date_mentioned n="Spring-1824">Last Spring</date_mentioned> on
the <location_mentioned>Colorado of the west</location_mentioned> that Runs into the <location_mentioned>bay of Callaforny</location_mentioned> from
the best acct he could git from the <person_mentioned>Crow Indians</person_mentioned> he brought Down
something more than ten thousand dollars worth of furs he also
sent Down Last fall about the same quantity Last fall, he has left
<person_mentioned>John H weber </person_mentioned>on the <location_mentioned>missouri </location_mentioned>when he Left there and thirty men
with him which was to start Emidiatly after <person_mentioned>Henry </person_mentioned>left them a
Cross to where <person_mentioned>henry </person_mentioned>had been in the <date_mentioned n="Spring-1824">spring </date_mentioned>there to stay until
<date_mentioned n="Spring-1825">Next Spring</date_mentioned> and then Return and Come home <date_mentioned n="Fall-1825">next fall</date_mentioned>,—<person_mentioned>Henry</person_mentioned>
talks of going back Emidiatly by land to try to Join <person_mentioned>weber </person_mentioned>this
Ensuing <date_mentioned n="Winter-1824">winter</date_mentioned> he will pass the <location_mentioned>head waters of the arkansas</location_mentioned> 
Leaving <location_mentioned>Sttefee [Santa Fe]</location_mentioned> to the left and the <location_mentioned>waters of Missouri</location_mentioned> to
the Right he tells me he wintered <date_mentioned n="Winter-1823">last winter</date_mentioned> on the <location_mentioned>head waters
of the Yellow Stone River</location_mentioned> and as soon as he was able to travil <date_mentioned n="Spring-1824">Last
Spring</date_mentioned> he came Down and Cross and crossed the <location_mentioned>missouri </location_mentioned>and went
a south Course about four hundred miles and there Came on this
he speaks of and found beavour in abundance and saw no <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>
until he Returned to the <location_mentioned>Missouri </location_mentioned>again he found a great 
Difficulty on the <location_mentioned>Missouri </location_mentioned>Lost several of his men killed at Different
times as much as between twenty and thirty first and Last he tells
me a fortune Could soon be made was it not for the Difficulty of
the <person_mentioned>Indians   </person_mentioned>they are Incouraged by <person_mentioned>British Traders</person_mentioned>,   we are cara-<barker_pb n="904"/>
ing on a smart Trade with <location_mentioned>Sttefee </location_mentioned>from the <location_mentioned>boons lick Country</location_mentioned>
Sr try to suit <person_mentioned>Mr Hail</person_mentioned> he is a good citizen—</p>

<p>I Conclue by subscribing myself your friend Most Sinsearly</p>

<p><person_mentioned>John Hawkins</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Col° Stephen F Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Inquire of <person_mentioned>Mr Hail</person_mentioned> for the balance</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
