
<TEI.2 id="APB0435">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-26-1821</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 437-438</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Erasmus Ellis</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Erasmus Ellis to Stephen F. Austin, 11-26-1821</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Ibirville Parish, LA</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Interest of Iberville Parish, La., in emigration.   Wants information.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>This and several letters to follow have been Polished in the <hi rend="italic">Texas History Teachers'
Bullitin</hi> (University of Texas). They are included here because the <hi rend="italic">Bulletin </hi>is limited
to local circulation. This letter appeared in the issue for November, 1917</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 437-438</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-10-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0435T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Interest of Iberville Parish, La., in emigration. Wants information.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Ibirville Parish [Louisiana]</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="11-26-1821">26th Novr 1821.</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin Esqr</person_mentioned></p>

<p>D[ea]r Sir My object for visiting this country at this time, was
to see my <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>who resides here, and with a hope of seeing you in
<location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned>, and making some arrangements to emigrate to the
<location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned>, and within the Bounds of the <location_mentioned>Settlement </location_mentioned>you are
now making—</p>

<p>I expect, Sir, if I can hear from you shortly, that early next Sprint
I can leave <location_mentioned>Cape Girardeau County</location_mentioned> with Several respectable <person_mentioned>families</person_mentioned><barker_pb n="438"/>
together with several Young men <person_mentioned>Mechanics </person_mentioned>of almost every 
description for that country, and will endeavour to be there in time to make
a Crop, as it is my wish to go by water, which rout I conceive, can
be performed with greater facility, and in much less time, than by
Land, But your advice on this subject will be very acceptable, and
on all other points or matters necessary or relative to the Voyage
there, and internal police of the <location_mentioned>Settlement</location_mentioned>—I shall indeavor to
collect all your publications, which have come out in the <location_mentioned>Louisiana
Advertiser</location_mentioned>, for the purpose of carrying them home with me, and
shewing them to those who are on the wing of emigrating to that
country, which I conceive will be a great satisfaction to them, as they
have never had an opportunity of seeing them as yet—</p>

<p>As you have by your last publication started to that Country I
have thought it best to inclose this letter to the <person_mentioned>Editor of the
Louisiana Advertiser in <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and request him to convey it to
you, by the best and shortest way, and by the same rout you will be
so good as to write to me, and address it to the <location_mentioned>postoffiee in Iberville
Parrish</location_mentioned> near the church, kept by my brother <person_mentioned>Allen Ellis</person_mentioned> you will
confer a lasting obligation on me and many others who are desirous
of emigrating to that country, by answering this letter immediately,
and giving me every information that you may think necessary on the
subject—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Erasmus Ellis </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>P. S. I shall leave this place in a few days for the <location_mentioned>State of 
Missouri</location_mentioned> and any letters sent to this office addressed to me will be sent
on immediately by my <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F Austin Esqr</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>E. Ellis   </person_mentioned> [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Stephen F Austin Esqr</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned></p>.
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
