
<TEI.2 id="APB0723">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-20-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 768-769</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Jose Antonio Saucedo</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Jose Antonio Saucedo, 04-20-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, TX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Bastrop elected to represent the colony in State Congress. Has received the acta constitutiva.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 768-769</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-17-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0723T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Bastrop elected to represent the colony in State Congress. Has received the acta constitutiva.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="04-20-1824">April 20, 1824.</date_mentioned>
I received only <date_mentioned n="04-19-1824">yesterday </date_mentioned>your communication of the <date_mentioned n="03-18-1824">18th of
March last</date_mentioned>, in which amongst other things, you instruct me to send
a certified power of the people of this <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, appointing an elector
to proceed to the electoral meeting for electing a <person_mentioned>Representative in
the Legislature of the State</person_mentioned>, I lost no time in sending expresses in
every direction to obtain the votes of the <person_mentioned>Colonists</person_mentioned>, and I am 
authorized by over one half of them to say to you that they have elected<barker_pb n="769"/>
the <person_mentioned>Baron de Bastrop</person_mentioned>, our Representative in the Most Excellent
Deputation, to be our <person_mentioned>elector </person_mentioned>for the above mentioned object. As
soon as I receive the votes of the others, I shall forward them to
the <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>, for due authenticity. In the meanwhile, and at
the request of those who have already voted, I send to you the 
inclosed power certified by the <person_mentioned>Alcalde of this District of San Felipe</person_mentioned>,
that of the <location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned>, and myself, for the truthfulness of which we
are personally responsible. We can also assure you that the <person_mentioned>Baron
de Bastrop</person_mentioned> will be unanimously elected by the <person_mentioned>people of this
<location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. Time has not allowed me to do anything else because, is
I have already said, your communication was received <date_mentioned n="04-19-1824">yesterday</date_mentioned>
only; and I have thought advisable to avail myself of an occasion
offering to day for <location_mentioned>La Bahia</location_mentioned>, to report the subject to you, I have
received the Constitutive Act and the Law creating the Legislature
of this State; in Compliance with your order, I have appointed the
<date_mentioned n="05-01-1824">1st of May next</date_mentioned> for proclaiming and swearing to said Constitutive
Act with all the solemnity and enthusiasm required by that 
important, and glorious subject, of which I shall give you a 
circumstantial account by next occasion. There has been nothing new in
the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, since the encounter of a party of <person_mentioned>Karankauases </person_mentioned>some
time since, by some <person_mentioned>inhabitants of this <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, which incident I
have reported to the <person_mentioned>Military Commander</person_mentioned>. It has not been possible
as yet to sell the corn contributed by these people for the 
<person_mentioned>Representative in Congress</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Estevan F Austin
Political Chief of the
<location_mentioned>Colony on the Colorado and Brazos</location_mentioned></person_mentioned></p>

<p>I pray you to excuse my erasures and bad Spanish; but the 
person who will take this letter is about to leave, and will not wait until
I can have a clean copy made</p>

<p><person_mentioned>E F Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>José Antonio Saucedo,
Political Chief of the <location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
