
<TEI.2 id="APB0504">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-29-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 502-504</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>John Hawkins</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>John Hawkins to Stephen F. Austin, 04-29-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Refugio, MX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>St. Antonio, TX</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Misdoings of William Kinchelow, who claims to be your partner, has checked enthusiasm for immigration. One hundred families were ready to move from Alabama. Hardships in Texas. Report on form of government and terms.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 502-504</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0504T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Misdoings of William Kinchelow, who claims to be your partner, has checked enthusiasm for immigration. One hundred families were ready to move from Alabama. Hardships in Texas. Report on form of government and terms.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Mission Lafoughoa or Lafouha [Refugio]</location_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>20 miles south of Labbedee [La Bahia]</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="04-29-1822">Aprill the 29th 1822</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Sr. On the <date_mentioned n="04-24-1822">24th Instant</date_mentioned> I met with a <person_mentioned>Mr Whitson</person_mentioned> at <location_mentioned>Labbedee </location_mentioned>who
Came with <person_mentioned>Kinchelow </person_mentioned>from <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>In a Sloop Kinchelow 
purchased, together with six or seven other <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Mr Kinchelow</person_mentioned>
undertook to land them at the <location_mentioned>Mouth of Colorado</location_mentioned> and kept the
people three months on bord the Vessel sounding and Trying to find
the <location_mentioned>Mouth of Colorado</location_mentioned> hailing the Vessel over <location_mentioned>shoals </location_mentioned>and so fatigued
the men and worn them out, some wanted to land at <location_mentioned>Galveston </location_mentioned>others
at the <location_mentioned>Mouth of the Brasses</location_mentioned> but he would not suffer them to Do so,
for some Considerable time at Last they got out in some way and
at some place after Keeping them on bord until all their provisions
ware spoiled and the people suffering very much Each <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>made
his way Back to the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> again or was Trying to Do so—
<person_mentioned>Mr Whitson</person_mentioned> Told me that <person_mentioned>Mr Kinshalow</person_mentioned> told the people he was a
<person_mentioned>partner </person_mentioned>of yours in the <location_mentioned>grant </location_mentioned>you had obtained from the <person_mentioned>Spanish
government</person_mentioned> which Done you More harm than he Ever will have in
his power to Repare again in his whole life, they found him to be a
man so far from being a man of Truth and honour they are 
Determ[in]ed to have Nothing to Do with you nor your Claim 
believing him to be <person_mentioned>partner </person_mentioned>of yours in the <location_mentioned>Grant </location_mentioned>I Done what I could
to get <person_mentioned>Mr Whits[on]</person_mentioned> to stay until you would Return but he stated
He had been kept on Bord so long that his provisions ware all spoiled
and he had Nothing to subsist on and would Try to take his <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>
towards <location_mentioned>Natchitotches</location_mentioned>, your Schooner [the Lively] was in company
with <person_mentioned>Mr Kinchelow</person_mentioned> also was in the same way, provisions all spoiled
goods much damaged your schooner Came on last <date_mentioned n="Winter-1821">winter </date_mentioned>and stayed
about the <location_mentioned>Brasses </location_mentioned>until pretty well eat out their provisions and went
back again to <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>with their cargo and <person_mentioned>Colo Hawkins</person_mentioned> fitted them
Out again with fresh supplies and they came on with <person_mentioned>Kinchelow</person_mentioned>
and have acted in the same way until their provisions are all spoiled
<person_mentioned>Mr Whitson</person_mentioned> Could not tell me whether th[e]y would Land or go
back we heard as we Came by the <location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>they had Landed and
left the cargo the first time but there was no truth in it— what I<barker_pb n="503"/>
tell you I believe is True <person_mentioned>Mr Whitson</person_mentioned> appears to be [a] very steady
Genteel man such as I would take for a man of Truth he told me
there would not [have] been less than <person_mentioned>100 families</person_mentioned> on next fall had
It not been for the conduct of <person_mentioned>Kinchelow </person_mentioned>from the <person_mentioned>Alabama people
of property</person_mentioned>, If <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>decides favourable to the Emigration to
this <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>It will be well for you Emediately to advertise In the
Different <location_mentioned>states </location_mentioned>again as Bad News has sirculated every where almost
as Respects the <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>Especially advertise in <location_mentioned>Mississippi </location_mentioned>and
<location_mentioned>Allabama </location_mentioned>states as <person_mentioned>Kinchelow </person_mentioned>has made the people believe as much
as he Could that he was Intrested with you and the people who
have had some Trial of him and Dealings are so Disgusted with him
believing him to have some Controle over the <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>that they
will not have anything to do with it on acct of him I asserted to <person_mentioned>Mr
Whitson</person_mentioned> that <person_mentioned>Kinchelow </person_mentioned>had no Intrest in the <location_mentioned>Claime </location_mentioned>only as a
settler Under you the same as other settlers from what I had 
understood Except I understood he had a privilege of settling <person_mentioned>20 families</person_mentioned>
It is not my wish Nor intention to Do the man any harm, but I
wish to notify you in such a way that he may Do you No [more]
hearm than he has already done which I am afraid he has Done you
many thousand dollars Dammage the man Is a stranger to me I never
saw him in my life to my Knowledge but for the good will I have
for you and your <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>I feel myself Bound to Let you Know in
what way he has Injured you and I hope you will have no Confidence
in what he may tell you from Character In the <location_mentioned>Boons Lick country
</location_mentioned>from whence he Came I hope you will Not Let him Disceave you,
I have heard a great Deal said about him <date_mentioned n="Fall-1821">Last fall</date_mentioned> when I was In
that <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>I Do not wish you to Expose him only take Care to
have No Confidence— Now sr I wish to tell you something of my
business I Came a long way to see you and the <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>together I
have seen a Tollarable shear of the Country but had Not the 
happiness of seeing you as I am very anxious to Do But fortune seems to
forbid, <person_mentioned>Mr Bruffey</person_mentioned> and my self Came Down here with a hope of
giting into some business until you Might return But our 
Expectations have failed Now we are under necessity of making homewards
as fast as we Can—</p>

<p>Times are hard No provisions to be had or we would wait your 
return to Know the Determination of [the government]—<person_mentioned>Mr Bruffey</person_mentioned>
and myself are well pleased with the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>with some Exceptions
that of the scarcity of Timber and some as to springs upon the whole
we both intend Moving to the Country. If we are pleased with the
government Much will Depend on the Report we make and the 
government when we return, when I left home the whole <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>almost
Talked of Coming we was Detained one Month beyond the <location_mentioned>Sabbean</location_mentioned>
waiting for grass to grow or Else we would have been here before<barker_pb n="504"/>
you put off, we arrived at <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned> on the <date_mentioned n="04-15-1822">15th Instant</date_mentioned>. Came with
my surveyin[g] Instruments thinking I might get into Business In
that way perhaps I am Disappointed in all views but the sight of the
Country that is a satisfaction To me that I have seen so Desireable a
Country and Climate I wish you to write me as soon as the nature
of times will admit and give me a true statement of the <person_mentioned>government</person_mentioned>
If Times are settled to your wishes or Expectations and there should
be [a] good Job of surveying to be had more than you have already
promised be good Enough to Try to procure a place for me and let
me know what time will be best to Come I would not be worth while
to Come for less than a Job of five or six hundred dollars I also wish
you to Try to suit ftie in a situation of Land such a one as you think
will suit, on Conditions the Tearms of the government will suit-
<person_mentioned>John Jones</person_mentioned> give his Compliments to you and told me to Inform you
he Recd a Letter from you which gave pleasure and put him In mind
of old times when you all put in your time in splendor About <location_mentioned>Mine
a burton</location_mentioned>, But the most of the young <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Ladies </person_mentioned>that was grown
when you left there, Is married and scattered off from that place—
If there should be any profitable place to fill in your section of Country
which is Not Disposed of If you think <person_mentioned>John Jones </person_mentioned>Could fill I should
be glad to have It offered to him I am somewhat afraid I shall Not
Get Him to Come Along with me He is doing very well in <location_mentioned>mine
a-burton</location_mentioned> he is <person_mentioned>clerk of the Circuit Court</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>recorder </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>post 
Master</person_mentioned> and is doing a very good business in Keeping <location_mentioned>Publick House</location_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>Augustis Jones</person_mentioned> was Red hot for Coming when I left <person_mentioned>Home </person_mentioned>but Many
accounts may have Reached that since I left home we scarcely ever
could hear the Truth as we came on to this <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>I have not time
nor Room at present to say much More so I will Conclude by 
subsubscribing my self your sinceare friend and humble servt</p>

<p><person_mentioned>John Hawkins</person_mentioned></p>
<p>[Addressed:]    <person_mentioned>Mr Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned>   To the care of <person_mentioned>James B.
Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
