
<TEI.2 id="APB0325">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>02-26-1819</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 336-337</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Advertisement</document_type>
<document_author>Moses Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Unknown</document_recipient>
<document_title>Moses Austin to Unknown, 02-26-1819</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Potosi, Washington County, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Advertisement of auction sale of land and town lots in and adjoining Potosi.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Signed byt not written by Moses Austin.  Pasted on cloth and orginally tacked up.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 336-337</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-08-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0325T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Advertisement of auction sale of land and town lots in and adjoining Potosi.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>Notice! An Advantageous Speculation in Land.<hi rend="italic">At Auction?</hi></p>

<p>On the <date_mentioned n="03-15-1819">third Monday of March next</date_mentioned> at the Town of <location_mentioned>Potosi</location_mentioned>, (being
Court week for <location_mentioned>Washington County</location_mentioned>,) I shall offer for sale a 
Thousand acres of land, commencing near the <location_mentioned>court House</location_mentioned>, and extending
along the <location_mentioned>Boon's Lick Road</location_mentioned>, divided into Lots of from one to a
Hundred acres each. The land I now offer for sale is included in my
<location_mentioned>Mine A Burton</location_mentioned> Survey, and of good quality. Persons wishing to
possess themselves of Land either for <location_mentioned>Building Lots</location_mentioned> near the Town,
or for farming, have now an opportunity to obtain a situation and to
establish themselves near the <location_mentioned>County town of Washington</location_mentioned> on better
terms than ever will again be presented to the public in this county.
The sales will commence after the rising of the <person_mentioned>court </person_mentioned>on the first and
second days.— CONDITIONS OF SALE are, four, six, and nine
months credit!— the purchases secured by executing Notes, with
approved endorsers.— If purchases for Cash, Bank Stock and Bank
Notes on the <person_mentioned>Bank of St. Louis</person_mentioned> will be received at par of 
Exchange.—Deeds will be executed so soon as the money is secured, or
Stock properly transfered to me: and the executing of Notes, and
transfer of Stock will be expected in two weeks after the purchases,
or they will be considered as <hi rend="italic">Cash Sales.</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Herculaneum Town Lots</location_mentioned></hi>.</p>

<p>I shall also offer for sale on the <date_mentioned n="03-22-1819">4th Monday of March</date_mentioned>, (being
court-Day,) a number of Lots in the Town of <location_mentioned>Herculaneum</location_mentioned>.—This
town having become the county seat, for <location_mentioned>Jefferson County</location_mentioned>, and 
advantageously situated for business on the <location_mentioned>banks of the Mississippi</location_mentioned>,
will soon become a place of first consequence.—I shall close the sale
of Lots in <location_mentioned>Herculaneum </location_mentioned>on the first and second days of court.—
Persons wishing to possess themselves of Lots, had better now come 
forward and embrace the present opportunity to purchase. 
CONDITIONS OF SALE, three, six, and eight months credit!—If 
purchased for cash Bank Stock and Bank Notes on the <person_mentioned>Bank of St.
Louis</person_mentioned> will be taken <hi rend="italic">at par.</hi>   The cash purchases must be secured by<barker_pb n="337"/>
Notes with approved endorsers, and if not executed in ten days from
the purchase, or the stock properly transferred, will be considered as
Cash Sales.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Moses Austin </person_mentioned>   [Rubric]</p>
<p><location_mentioned>Potosi Washington County</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="02-26-1819">26th February 1819</date_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
