
<TEI.2 id="APB0771">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-10-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 827-828</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Public</document_status>
<document_type>Petition</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Federal Congress</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Federal Congress, 06-10-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, TX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Law under which the colony was established recognized slavery; slaves necessary to furnish labor to improve the country; not intended for trade.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>This seems to be the original draft. A Spanish translation, in Austin's hand, with
autograph signatures, is slightly stronger in the last paragraph than the English.
Article 30 of the Imperial Colonization law: "After the publication of this law, there
can be no sale or purchase of slaves which may be introduced into the Empire. The
children of slaves born in the Empire, shall be free at fourteen years of age."</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 827-828</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-17-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0771T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Law under which the colony was established recognized slavery; slaves necessary to furnish labor to improve the country; not intended for trade.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F Austin</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Jared E. Groce</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>James Cummings</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Jno
P Coles</person_mentioned> a <person_mentioned>Committe </person_mentioned>Unanimously appointed at a general meeting
held on the <date_mentioned n="06-05-1824">5th June instant</date_mentioned> by the <person_mentioned>Inhabitants of the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> formed
in the <location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned> by the <person_mentioned>empresario S F Austin</person_mentioned> in the name
and in the behalf of said <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>respectfully represent to your
sovereignty that these <person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>emigrated to this establishment
from <location_mentioned>Louisiana </location_mentioned>in Consequence of the Invitation of said <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>
and many of them brought their <person_mentioned>negro slaves</person_mentioned> with them as also all
their property intending to establish themselves permanantly in this
<location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned>. They have been much alarmed by the news Communicated
through the <location_mentioned>public Gazette</location_mentioned> that your Sovereignty were about to
pass a Law freeing all the <person_mentioned>Slaves </person_mentioned>that were introduced by the
<person_mentioned>emigrants</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>These <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>respectfully represent to your sovereignty that
the <person_mentioned>Slaves </person_mentioned>introduced into this establishment by the <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>were
not brought here for the purpose of Trade or speculation neither
are they <person_mentioned>Africans </person_mentioned>but are the <person_mentioned>family servants</person_mentioned> of the <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>and
raised by them as such from their infancy and were intended to aid
in clearing the Land and establishing their <location_mentioned>farms </location_mentioned>which these
<person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>Could not have effected without them for this <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>is
entirely uninhabited and great Labor required in Opening <location_mentioned>farms</location_mentioned>
and as the Law sanctioned the introduction of <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>into the
Country the <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>felt entirely safe in bringing them.</p>

<p>These <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>therefore respectfully solicit that your 
sovereignty will take into Consideration the right of property they have
to their <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>that they brought them here As a necessary part of
the Capital required by the desert State of the Country to establish
their <location_mentioned>farms </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Ranches </location_mentioned>and if freed the loss of their value added<barker_pb n="828"/>
to the very heavy expenees of removing such a distance and settling
in An entire <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>and suffering all (he miseries of Hunger, 
exposed to the attack of Hostile <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>will complete their total
ruin— Also these <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>respectfully represent that some of
their <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>and Relations visited this Country <date_mentioned n="Spring-1824">last spring</date_mentioned> and
<date_mentioned n="Winter-1823">winter </date_mentioned>and selected their Lands as a part of the Above named 300
<person_mentioned>families</person_mentioned> After building <location_mentioned>Cabins </location_mentioned>they returned to move out their
<person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>this <date_mentioned n="Summer-1824">summer </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="Fall-1824">fall </date_mentioned>and are now on the Road bringing
their <person_mentioned>Slaves </person_mentioned>with them relying on the faith of the Colonization Law
under which <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>'s establishment</location_mentioned> is formed— Article [30] of
which Law Authorises the introduction of <person_mentioned>Slaves </person_mentioned>by the <person_mentioned>Colonists</person_mentioned>
those <person_mentioned>emigrants </person_mentioned>therefore who are on the Road and are detained
by the excessive heat and destructive drouth that now prevodes this
whole <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>will be totally and forever ruined if on their arrival
here after so much fatigue labor and expense in removing they are
to loose their <person_mentioned>Slaves </person_mentioned>and besides that be liable to heavy punishment
for bringing them—</p>

<p>These <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>therefore respectfully pray that your 
sovereignty may take their Case into Consideration and declare that the
<person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>and their <person_mentioned>descendents </person_mentioned>of the <person_mentioned>300 families</person_mentioned> who emigrate to
the <location_mentioned>Establishment </location_mentioned>formed by the <person_mentioned>Emprasario Stephen F Austin</person_mentioned> in
this province shall be <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>for Life and that the emancipation Law
which we have been informed has lately passed shall not apply to
the <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>of the said <person_mentioned>300 families</person_mentioned> except so far as prohibits all trade
or trafic of them and should this solicitation be incompatible with
the intentions of your sovereignty these <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>pray that the
necessary time may be allowed them to remove their <person_mentioned>slaves </person_mentioned>back to
the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></p>

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="06-10-1824">June 10, 1824</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Signed  <person_mentioned>Estevan F Austin</person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>Jared E. Groce</person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>Santiago Cummings</person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>Jno P. Coles</person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>Comte</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>[To Federal Congress or Executive.]</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
