
<TEI.2 id="APB0540">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-16-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 547-548</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Robert C. Bruffey</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Robert C. Bruffey to Stephen F. Austin, 10-16-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Colorado, TX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Losses in coming to Texas and disappointment in learning nothing of Government and status of the colony. Write information about Government, toleration, terms.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 547-548</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0540T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Losses in coming to Texas and disappointment in learning nothing of Government and status of the colony. Write information about Government, toleration, terms.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-16-1822">October 16th 1822</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I have detained here upwards of 6 months for the Purpose of
having an Interview with you but now am forced to leave the
country unsatisfied I left the papers relative to the Business for
which I wanted to see you with your <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>there you may see what
the True State of it is. God onley knows what it may yet cost me
now allready it has been Ruinous from last years Trip to <location_mentioned>New
Orleans</location_mentioned> and this year to this country in addition to what I have
actually paid and what I may actually have to pay hereafter with
loss of Time and all included will leave me in a State but little
better than wreatched if not quite so in a pecuniary sence if not
attended with loss of peace of mind I am also Truly Sorry that it
was impossible to obtain the satisfaction of gaining one scrap of
information Relative to your claim the Terms of Settlement the
constitution of the government on its political situation as I had
a strong intention to emigrate and thereby could have induced many<barker_pb n="548"/>
others but now I can do nothing positive for which I am Truly
sorry both on my own account as well as yours for I Truly wish you
Success I wish you to write me on the Subject when you find it in
your power and if possible make some arrangement for the Money
for which I am bound as my property may have fallen a sacrifice
unless the Laws of Replevin should have prevented before this time
I have or may draw an order on you in favor of <person_mentioned>Mr Robert 
Cuykendall</person_mentioned> for thirty dollars from absolute necessity in order to get home
if you can possible cansell it I would be much obliged when you
write please say all that can be said with Regard to the Government
liberality Toleration Terms of Settlement etc</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Robert C. Bruffy</person_mentioned></p>
<p>[Addressed:]   <person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin Esqr</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
