
<TEI.2 id="APB0795">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>07-08-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 847-849</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Dr. John Sibley</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Dr. John Sibley to Stephen F. Austin, 07-08-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Nackitosh, LA</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Good report of Texas. Mexican Constitution good, except article establishing Catholic religion, which he thinks will be tacitly disregarded in Texas. England and the holy alliance. Mail service between Mexico and United States, State and Katonal politics.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 847-849</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-17-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0795T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Dr. John Sibley to Austin, Natchitoches, July 8, 1824. Good report of Texas. Mexican Constitution good, except article establishing Catholic religion, which he thinks will be tacitly disregarded in Texas. England and the holy alliance. Mail service between Mexico and United States, State and Katonal politics.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Nackitosh </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="07-08-1824">July 8th 1824</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>I had the double pleasure of receiving your letter and by the
hand of your <person_mentioned>brother</person_mentioned>, no opportunity has offered of writing to you
since. The <person_mentioned>Bearers</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Messrs. Cherbonier</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Trizena </person_mentioned>are fitting out
a trading voyage and are desirous of visiting your <location_mentioned>Settlement </location_mentioned>if they
can—<person_mentioned>Mr Cherbonier</person_mentioned> is a man of integrity and honour, has for a 
considerable time had the charge of our Public Academy, the other
gentleman I know only as a <person_mentioned>merchant</person_mentioned>, they are worthy your 
attention</p>

<p>I hear from every body that you have a prospect of abundant
crops, so that those who may desire to emigrate thither need be
under no apprehension for the want of provisions. I am highly
pleased with the description your brother gives of your whol 
Establishment Particularly the Town, the purity of your well water is of
the first Consideration, the mills will give great facility to building,
as well as grinding.</p>

<p>I coppied the Mexican Constitution to send to <location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned>, but
at the same time found by the papers it was there, I have no
objections to it Except the Article of Religion, and in Taxes—I
think it will in a short time be silent (or tacit) as the <person_mentioned>inhabitants</person_mentioned>
will be mostly <person_mentioned>Americans </person_mentioned>the happiness of the People depends
more on the <person_mentioned>administration </person_mentioned>than the form of government, you will
govern yourselves; your <person_mentioned>brother </person_mentioned>informd me your <location_mentioned>Town lotts</location_mentioned> would
be sold at Auction to raise a fund for the improvement of the Same—
As I always intended to be a <person_mentioned>proprietor </person_mentioned>and may move there, I wish
vou to secure for me a Couple of Lotts adjoining or a whol Square as
you may think proper; I am fond of Building and am used to it,<barker_pb n="848"/>
and never like to be crampt. I shall want near, lands for a small
farm; I intend to come and see you, but cannot now fix the time.—</p>

<p>I am sorry I cannot send you a Newspaper containing<person_mentioned> W. Canning
the English Minister</person_mentioned>s rejoly to <person_mentioned>Prince Polinaz </person_mentioned>who came to <location_mentioned>England</location_mentioned>
from <location_mentioned>Paris </location_mentioned>to move the <person_mentioned>English Govt</person_mentioned> to send a delegate to meet
<person_mentioned>delegates from the holy Alliance</person_mentioned> (or Allied powers) at the request
of the <person_mentioned>king of <location_mentioned>Spain</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to concert measures to reduce again under
the <person_mentioned>king of <location_mentioned>Spain</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Spanish America</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Mr Cannings</person_mentioned> reply is clear and
prompt he says they will not meet at <location_mentioned>Paris </location_mentioned>for the <person_mentioned>King of <location_mentioned>Spain</location_mentioned>
</person_mentioned>well knows the opinion of <location_mentioned>England </location_mentioned>which will not be changed. 
<location_mentioned>England </location_mentioned>will not interfere If <location_mentioned>Spain </location_mentioned>chooses to exhaust herself in so 
fruitless an attempt, but will not suffer any other power to assist her,
and should any attempt it, <location_mentioned>England </location_mentioned>will immediately Acknowledge
their independence and defend them, which has been too long 
delayed, the reply is a positive Avowall of the determination of 
<location_mentioned>England</location_mentioned>, It has disconcerted the <person_mentioned>Allies </person_mentioned>and no doubt decided the 
Independence of <location_mentioned>Spanish America</location_mentioned>, which will soon be Recognized by
all <location_mentioned>Europe </location_mentioned>at least that is the opinion in this Country.</p>

<p>You mention the intention of sending a Regular Mail, could it be
connected with <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>I have no doubt Our <person_mentioned>Post Master-General
</person_mentioned>will meet the proposal for an exchange of Mail as is now done in
the <location_mentioned>Canada </location_mentioned>line and <location_mentioned>Nova Scotia</location_mentioned>. I am not Acquainted with the
<person_mentioned>Postmaster General now Mr. McLean of <location_mentioned>Ohio</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> but through Our
<person_mentioned>delegates in Congress</person_mentioned> I can have the subject discussed, and no doubt
the thing can be affected, we now have a Newspaper Published
here, I have in this packet of <location_mentioned>News papers</location_mentioned> Inclosed the <location_mentioned>Printers
Prospectus</location_mentioned>, he asks your Patronage.</p>

<p>Our <person_mentioned>candidates for President</person_mentioned> are <person_mentioned>J. Q. Adams</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>W. H. Crawford</person_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>H. Clay</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Genl Jackson</person_mentioned> and you can as well judge who will be
the successful <person_mentioned>Candidate </person_mentioned>as we can <person_mentioned>Clay </person_mentioned>or <person_mentioned>Jackson </person_mentioned>will feel more
interested for <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and of course will be our choice; I see a Bill
has passed in <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>to Extend further west the <location_mentioned>Boundary of
Arkensa</location_mentioned>. it is a little curious that, that <location_mentioned>Territory </location_mentioned>extends 
jurisdiction to the <location_mentioned>settlements on the South side of Red River in Texas</location_mentioned>,
collects taxes and inforces her Laws—You will see by the Papers
the appointment of <person_mentioned>Ninian Edwards Minister to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, but his
getting into a dispute with <person_mentioned>Crawford Secty of the Treasury</person_mentioned>, 'tis
thought will so affect him that he will not be permitted to proceed
on the <location_mentioned>embassy</location_mentioned>—It is said here on the Authority of Our <person_mentioned>Member
of Congress Col Brent</person_mentioned>, that our Govt will not regard the <location_mentioned>Sabine </location_mentioned>as
Our <location_mentioned>Boundary</location_mentioned>, but will renew our Claim to the <location_mentioned>River Grand</location_mentioned>; Our
<person_mentioned>Minister </person_mentioned>will be instructed as to that the papers will acquaint you
of the Nature of the difficulty between <person_mentioned>Mr Edwards</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Mr 
Crawford</person_mentioned>—We cannot yet know the Result of the Election in this State,<barker_pb n="849"/>
a <person_mentioned>governor</person_mentioned>, three <person_mentioned>Members of Congress</person_mentioned>, and Our <person_mentioned>State Legislature</person_mentioned>
have just been voted for. The <person_mentioned>Candidates for Governor</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Henry
Johnston Late Senator in Congress</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Villere Marigney</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Genl Thomas</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>Judge Butler</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Johnston </person_mentioned>has resigned as <person_mentioned>Senator </person_mentioned>that he may
be <person_mentioned>Governor</person_mentioned>, that gives <person_mentioned>Mr Livingston</person_mentioned> a place in the <person_mentioned>Senate </person_mentioned>and
<person_mentioned>Grymes </person_mentioned>in the <person_mentioned>House of Representatives</person_mentioned> where <person_mentioned>Mr Livingston</person_mentioned> now
is—<person_mentioned>J. S. Johnston</person_mentioned> remains one year more in the <person_mentioned>Senate </person_mentioned>and will
probably be Reelected for six years. <person_mentioned>Judge Bullard</person_mentioned> is a <person_mentioned>Candidate
for Congress</person_mentioned> in place of <person_mentioned>Mr Brent</person_mentioned> but many think he will fail partly
owing to some illiberal pieces that have been published against
<person_mentioned>Brent</person_mentioned>, not avowed by <person_mentioned>Mr Bullard</person_mentioned> nor disavowed.—The last month
<date_mentioned n="06-xx-1824">June </date_mentioned>has been the Hottest Month here for 21 years since I have
lived here the Mercury in all the Month has from 3. to 5 P. M.
"vibrated betwen 95 and 100 in a cool exposure rather too cool a place
than too warm, and the same Month has been Remarkably dry,
which with the Ravages of the Web worm has much injured the corn
and cotton in many places—This part of <location_mentioned>Louissiana </location_mentioned>sets in rather
sickley. The Measles has ran through our <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>and the
Whooping Cough is following with a Bowel Complaint of which
several have died—The River did not raise for Steam Boats till Late,
it is now getting too low, two steam boats were here 3 or 4 days ago,
there is one below Expected up tomorrow, this town is pretty well
supplied with every Article for the season.—I am always glad to
hear from you. No one more ardently wishes for the prosperity of
your <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>and for your individual health and happiness.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>John Sibley</person_mentioned>.</p>
<p><person_mentioned>Judge Austin</person_mentioned>.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
