
<TEI.2 id="APB0216">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-28-1812</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 202-205</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Moses Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Moses Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 04-28-1812</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Durham Hall, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Herculaneum, MO</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary> Advice for sailing down the Mississippi; clothes and deportment in New Orleans and Philadelphia; slave trade in Louisiana; conditions of voyage from New Orleans to Philadelphia.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 202-205</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-30-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0216T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Advice for sailing down the Mississippi; clothes and deportment in New Orleans and Philadelphia; slave trade in Louisiana; conditions of voyage from New Orleans to Philadelphia.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Durham Hall</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="04-28-1812">April 28 1812</date_mentioned></p>
<p>My Dear <person_mentioned>Son</person_mentioned></p>

<p>I had much to say to you before you left me but the fullness of my
heart and mind drove all most Every thing from my thoughts but<barker_pb n="203"/>
I must try to mend my recollections. In the first place I intended to
state to you some general rules to be observed in desending the 
<location_mentioned>Mississippia </location_mentioned>in opposition to every other advice do you observe the 
following rules—first never run late at Night but always make a landing
under a <location_mentioned>Willow Point</location_mentioned> in time, its always better to loose a few hours
than be exposed at Night. Never land under a high bank and large
timber When you Intend to land begin in time to pull your boat in
shore and always before the boat striks turn her stern down-Stream.
Never trust your boat to float unless you have a man on the look
out—lett this rule be always strictly observed, to much care cannot
be taken in Descending, this river, when you make your Boat fast at
Night see yourself that the Cable is properly made fast— Never
suffer any water to be in your boat a[t] Nigh[t] always put to land
in Winds I advise you always to Keep out from the <location_mentioned>bends of the
rivers</location_mentioned>, and, guard against <location_mentioned>Points of Islands</location_mentioned>, haveing observed this
much I must committ you to the Care of that being that govern
us all.</p>

<p>I have given you letters to <person_mentioned>Mr. William Kenner <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>Mr Andrew Price</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Mr Dunn</person_mentioned>— I have left them open that you
may see what I have said and conduct yourself accordingly in the
Instructions You will see the State of my business and govern 
yourself thereby. By <person_mentioned>William Bates</person_mentioned> I shall transmitt up a Cargo more
and at all times when I can Command a Hundred Dollars I am 
determened to transmitt it by land my Exertions will be to place you
and your Dear <person_mentioned>Mother </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Sister </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>in a happy situation as I
can, its the first consideration of my Sole and the sum of my 
happiness—make Every Exertion to obtain the money from <person_mentioned>A C Dunn</person_mentioned>
and Examin Well the situation of <person_mentioned>Negro <hi rend="italic">Will </hi></person_mentioned>and if you can have
that man pushed and made to pay—a Word to you about your own
Deportment a <person_mentioned>Young man</person_mentioned> must always remember that his apperance
is greatly Noticed by <person_mentioned>Strangers</person_mentioned>. You will therefore immedeately
on your arrival obtain in <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>such a Suite of Clothes as will be
agreeably to the place a Black Coat you will find not only in tast in
<location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>but also in <location_mentioned>Philadelphia </location_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>White Janes for 
Overhalls and Vest but in <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned> and <location_mentioned>Philadelphea </location_mentioned>they would be out
of the Order of Dress, and to avoid unnecessary Baggage and 
Expence provide only what will answer for your stay in <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>for you
will not use them in the <location_mentioned>Cities to the North</location_mentioned>, you have been so long in
the Woods that you will finde an Attention to your Dress 
indispensable this you will attend to—When you arrive in the <location_mentioned>City of
New York</location_mentioned> obtain lodgens at <person_mentioned>Mrs. Rumseys</person_mentioned> in <location_mentioned>Broadway </location_mentioned>near the
Custom hous its a respectable house and in a Genteel part of the
<location_mentioned>City</location_mentioned>—I have inclosed you a note to <person_mentioned>Mrs Rumsey</person_mentioned>—at <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>enquere<barker_pb n="204"/>
for <person_mentioned>Mr Masons</person_mentioned> its the house I staid at also your <person_mentioned>Mother </person_mentioned>and you and
<person_mentioned>Mr Bryan</person_mentioned> will finde the best companey at his <location_mentioned>House </location_mentioned>always informe
yourself of the rules of the table and conform to them these little
attention are absolutely Necessary, with out them you will be 
Deficient in breeding. Make you a small book and in it Keep an account
of every transaction that takes place so that you may account for all
the Expences of the Voyage this will be Necessary that you may
settle with <person_mentioned>James Bryan</person_mentioned> on your return With due attention you
may have your account in such order as not to give you any trouble
and as this is your first adventure be carefull how you manage it</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mr Dinwiddy</person_mentioned> will see you at <person_mentioned>Herculaneum </person_mentioned>with <person_mentioned>John Camp</person_mentioned>—I
have sent him over but I shall now State to you the situation of <person_mentioned>Jn°
Camp</person_mentioned> and what will be your and <person_mentioned>Mr Bryan</person_mentioned>s situation when you
arrive in the <location_mentioned>Territory of Orleans</location_mentioned> and have the business fully and
freely in your power—to act. as you think proper, sence you have left
me I have understood that a Law in the <location_mentioned>Territory of Orleans</location_mentioned> 
prohibits <person_mentioned>negroes </person_mentioned>to be sold or to remain in the <location_mentioned>Territory </location_mentioned>unless the
<person_mentioned>Seller </person_mentioned>of the <person_mentioned>Negro </person_mentioned>can give a Character of the <person_mentioned>negro </person_mentioned>favourable to
his former Conduct, and it must be stated that he has not—been
guilty of any crime what ever that has induced the <person_mentioned>Master </person_mentioned>to send
him into the <location_mentioned>low Country</location_mentioned>—this information has greatly deranged
me. What to do with the fellow I cannot tell, and should you be
brought into trouble with him after your arrival in the <location_mentioned>low country</location_mentioned>
It will be a disgrace as well as a detention, and at last be under
the necessaty of bringing him back again I am advised by <person_mentioned>Mr Heart</person_mentioned>
by <person_mentioned>Doct McGrady</person_mentioned> and Others not on any account to send him that
you may be placed in a disagreeable situation and not unlikely much
Injured I have however sent him by <person_mentioned>Mr Dinwiddy</person_mentioned> and leave it
intirely to yourself and <person_mentioned>Mr Bryan</person_mentioned> how to act in the business If you
think proper to take him you will do—so, and make the most of him
if not then in that case I have spoken to <person_mentioned>Mr Dinwiddy</person_mentioned> and he has
agreed to make <person_mentioned>John </person_mentioned>Beleive that he has bought him and so let him
remain untill I can sell him <person_mentioned>Doct Mcgrady</person_mentioned> thinks that a <person_mentioned>Capt Waters</person_mentioned>
will purchase him for Lead, he says that <person_mentioned>Waters </person_mentioned>is a man that has
been in that way of business, and may be induced to take <person_mentioned>John Camp</person_mentioned>-
as I understand he has <person_mentioned>Negroes </person_mentioned>to take to the <location_mentioned>Spanish Settlements</location_mentioned>
on <location_mentioned>Reel River</location_mentioned> however I leave the business entirely to you if you
think proper to take him do so if not send him back with <person_mentioned>Mr 
Dinwiddy</person_mentioned> and I will do the best I can with him, I am unwilling you
should undertake any thing that would Injure your reputation or
embarres you in your Voyage—you are young and must be carefull
how you injure your reputation should you take <person_mentioned>Jn°</person_mentioned> and Cannot do 
better it will be best to leave him with <person_mentioned>Mr Ab Dunn</person_mentioned>—but the object
is to turn him into Cotton—if you cannot obtain money—I have sent<barker_pb n="205"/>
the small box and trunk by <person_mentioned>Mr Donnal</person_mentioned>—I never mentioned nor
thought about bead clothes you will therefore take with you a Buffalo
Roab and two Blanketts from <location_mentioned>Herculanum</location_mentioned>—I have a pr of cotton
Sheets at <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Mrs Ellise</person_mentioned>s</location_mentioned> take one of the Sheets you will want the Sheet
on the Voyage you must have bead Clothes or you must purchase at
<location_mentioned>Orleans</location_mentioned>, you must purchase a Mattress at <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>that you will want
on your return also some things to cook in on your Voyage a small
kettle and a small oven with each man a tin Cup, an Ax and a Saw
and <hi rend="italic">Auger </hi>you must have on board also a Buckett these things you
cannot do with out</p>

<p>In taking your passage for <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned>—be carefull to examin the
ship, and Capt whether he is acquanted with the Voyage an <person_mentioned>Old
trader</person_mentioned> will make his—passage in nearly half the time and if likely for
war, Ship on board of a fast saleing Vessell if you give more freight
everything of this kind is of the utmost moment in a Voyage of such
risque and length you ought to minutely examen Every thing With
Care—If <person_mentioned>John Camp</person_mentioned> should Not go you must have three hands 
besides yourself if you are obliged to give an Extra price beeing short
Maned will—indanger you greatly its troublesum in Landing and
keeps you always uneasy therefore obtain an other hand by all
means—and lastly Write me when Ever you can that I may hear
from you by every oppertunety. Recommending you to the favour
of our great author and Heavenly farther I leave you</p>

<p>My <person_mentioned>son </person_mentioned>to Events to come and am
With Warm affection Your <person_mentioned>Fath[er]</person_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>M Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Mr Stephen F Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Herculaneum</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
