
<TEI.2 id="APB0378">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>02-03-1821</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 381-382</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Moses Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Felix Trudeau</document_recipient>
<document_title>Moses Austin to Felix Trudeau, 02-03-1821</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Nachitoches, LA</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Kirkham's relations with illicit traders.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Autograph copy by Moses Austin in "Common Place Book," in file of August 1, 1791.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 381-382</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-10-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0378T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Kirkham's relations with illicit traders.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>Copy of Declaration handed to <person_mentioned>Mons. Trudo Spanish Agent at
<location_mentioned>Nachitoches</location_mentioned>.</person_mentioned></p>

<p><date_mentioned n="02-03-1821">Feby 3 Year 21</date_mentioned></p>

<p>After leaving <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned> in Company with <person_mentioned>James Kirkham</person_mentioned> the
following circumstances transpired, a development of which I 
consider it my duty to make to you [to] exonerate me from any blame
or reproach that might be attached to me in Consiquence of my 
being in Company with <person_mentioned>James Kirkham</person_mentioned> whose unguarded conduct may
have drawn down disgrace on himself and indangered my 
Reputation.</p>

<p>The day before I left <location_mentioned>Sant Antonio</location_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Kirkham </person_mentioned>mentioned to me that
five <person_mentioned>Spaniards </person_mentioned>would leave the <location_mentioned>City </location_mentioned>with us, for <location_mentioned>Nachitoches </location_mentioned>but
did not say that they had an intention to leave in a Clandestine
manner or to commit any act in violation of the orders of the 
Governor or Society   Nor was their intentions made known to me until<barker_pb n="382"/>
after our arrival at the <location_mentioned>River St. Marks</location_mentioned>. When <location_mentioned>Kirkham </location_mentioned>
mentioned that the five <person_mentioned>Spaniards </person_mentioned>had made a brake on the <person_mentioned>King</person_mentioned>s Yard
of Mules and Horses and Stolen ten or twelve and had made there
escape and would come up with us at the <location_mentioned>River Colorado</location_mentioned> at which
place he had agreed to detain for them and had told them he would
purchase there Mules and give them a safe conduct into the <location_mentioned>United
States</location_mentioned>. I at the same time learned from him that the <person_mentioned>Spaniards</person_mentioned>
had communicated to some of there <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>at <location_mentioned>St. Antonio</location_mentioned> before
they made theft of the Mules that <person_mentioned>Kirkham </person_mentioned>and the other <person_mentioned>American</person_mentioned>
was to detain for them and give them a safe conduct into the <location_mentioned>United
States</location_mentioned> I Expostulated with him for giving them any 
encouragements to bring out Mules in as much as he knew it to be against the
orders of the <person_mentioned>Governor</person_mentioned>, he then said that he had not given them
any encouragement except, that if they brought Mules-he would
purchase, them. I again stated to him how unwise it was to have
held out the least inducement to these men to commit a theft the
consequences of which might turn on his own head and that I should
take the earliest moment to Exonerate myself from any 
participation in the whole matter in as much as my name had been called in
question it is however Clearly to be understood that I do not charge
<person_mentioned>Kirkham </person_mentioned>with having Covenants with the <person_mentioned>Spaniards </person_mentioned>for the mules
or of having been guilty of any act or Crime further than may be
attached to the Offers he made the <person_mentioned>Spaniards </person_mentioned>to Purchase the Mules
this statement therefore is made in Exoneration of myself. What
ever agreement <person_mentioned>Kirkham </person_mentioned>may have made with the <person_mentioned>Spaniards</person_mentioned>, if any,
is unknown to me—and I do most solemnly declare that. What
ever conversation might have takin place between <person_mentioned>Kirkham </person_mentioned>and
the <person_mentioned>Spaniards </person_mentioned>touching the Mules they are unknown (to me) as are
also the men themselves with whom I never had a conversation
directly or indirectly—</p>

<p>[Moses Austin.]</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
