
<TEI.2 id="APB0480">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>02-15-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 479-480</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Robert D. Dawson</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Robert D. Dawson to Stephen F. Austin, 02-15-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Madrid</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Introducing brother-in-law. "Pecuniary distress in every section of this State" [Missouri]. "Unparalleled change in the quantity and quality of our circulating medium."</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Printed in Texas History Teacher's Bulletin, November, 1917.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 479-480</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0480T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Introducing brother-in-law. "Pecuniary distress in every section of this State" [Missouri]. "Unparalleled change in the quantity and quality of our circulating medium."</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New Madrid, Mri.</location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="02-15-1822"> Feby 15th 1822</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Dr. Sir.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>bearer </person_mentioned>hereof <person_mentioned>Mr Federal Walker</person_mentioned> a<person_mentioned> brother in law</person_mentioned> of mine,
being incited by several letters of yours (published in most of the
<location_mentioned>Western Newspapers</location_mentioned>) to visit the <location_mentioned>province of Texas</location_mentioned> and 
particularly that part of it in which you preside as <person_mentioned>Civil Magistrate</person_mentioned> or
<person_mentioned>commandant</person_mentioned>, has furnished me with an opportunity of gratifying
a wish to renew with you a friendly acquaintance, long since dormant
from the diversity of our pursuits and the distance of our residence
and also to present to you my <person_mentioned>brother in Law</person_mentioned>, who from a long and
intimate acquaintance I feel myself authorised in saying is a young
man of strict fidelity and probity and of unblemished Moral 
Character, the substance of which is certified by the <person_mentioned>Judge of the 
Circuit</person_mentioned> and the <person_mentioned>Justice of the County Court</person_mentioned> for this <location_mentioned>county </location_mentioned>where <person_mentioned>Mr
Walker</person_mentioned> was raised and has resided for a number of years.</p>

<p>And as he proposes if pleased with the <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>to make the 
<location_mentioned>province of Texas</location_mentioned> his future residence, I must beg to recommend him to
your friendly notice and attention.</p>

<p>Your letters as well as information derived from other sources
have strongly tempted me to visit your country also, but the claims
of a young and growing <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>, together with some little 
embarrassment of a pecuniary kind in which the unparalleled change in the
quantity and quality of our circulating medium has thrown me,
together with the thousands of others, has rendered the gratification
of such a wish impossible at least for some time to come. But as it is
quite probable that at some future period I may do so, I should feel
greatly obliged to you for any information relating to the climate,
soil, production, state and form of <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>etc.
etc. which you may deem interesting and important to those who may
wish to visit you.</p>

<p>I have nothing interesting to communicate to you, My private
concerns have so completely occupied my attention for the last two
years that I have not had leisure to attend to what has been passing
in the country generally—I only know that there is a great deal of
pecuniary distress in every section of this state and I have not a
sufficiency of sagacity to be able to say at what period it will 
probably cease, not I fear until there is a very general change of
property.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Robt D Dawson  </person_mentioned>  [Rubric]</p>

<p>P. S. As I am so little acquainted with the nature and form of
your government, as to be incapable of addressing you by the Titles<barker_pb n="480"/>
which your situation may entitle you to I must beg to be excused
for omiting Titles altogether</p>

<p><person_mentioned>RDD</person_mentioned></p>
<p>[Addressed:]  <person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin Esquire Civil Commandant of
<location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned>.</person_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
