
<TEI.2 id="APB0881">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-07-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 917-922</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Littleberry Hawkins</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Littleberry Hawkins to Stephen F. Austin, 10-07-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Lexington, KY</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Brazos, TX</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Review of his trading ventures in Texas in 1822. Character of the public men.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 917-922</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-18-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0881T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Review of his trading ventures in Texas in 1822. Character of the public men.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Lexington</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="10-07-1824">7 October 1824</date_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>My Dear Sir The death of our dear <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>has left his
<person_mentioned>Wife </person_mentioned>and five <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>destitute and dependent on this ungratful
world I have four <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>and my situation desperate the 
balance of our old endorsement debts hanging over us to amount of
$6000 I have nothing left am working as clerk at a Cellery 
[salary] of $600 to enable me to get on and keep from actual want mv
<person_mentioned>Brothers family</person_mentioned> and my own the <person_mentioned>wife of my Brother</person_mentioned> is at this
place intends opening a <location_mentioned>boarding house</location_mentioned> to enable her to support her<barker_pb n="918"/>
self and three younger <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>I have the two eldest at the 
<location_mentioned>Beardstown College</location_mentioned> If this was not my particular situation I would
come without hesitation to the <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>the suffering and 
privation to me I was near four months on the <location_mentioned>Mexican Coast</location_mentioned> examining
the mouths of the <location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>Guadaloope </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>St Antonio
</location_mentioned>I was the first person that took a vessel to the <location_mentioned>landing of Guadalope
</location_mentioned>and the <location_mentioned>Bay of Musquittoes</location_mentioned> the <location_mentioned>mouth of the San Antonio River</location_mentioned> 
before I landed in the <location_mentioned>province</location_mentioned>. After all my toils and privation and
seperation from my <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>fifteen months I have been swindled out
of all that I sent out of the Country by <person_mentioned>John Hanna</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Issurael
Massie</person_mentioned> the two persons that I took into partnership in the Mule and
Horse business When I met with <person_mentioned>John Hanna</person_mentioned> at <location_mentioned>Labordee </location_mentioned>[La
Bahia] he was in bad health and had but $14 left in the world It is
believed in the Country in which <person_mentioned>Hanna </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Massie </person_mentioned>lives that they
sold the Mules and Horses and divided the Money out of 260 head
of Horses and 75 Mules 4 Jacks and 6 jinneys I have never Received
one single dollar, the principal part of the fund was advanced by
my self and <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>that made that purchase the Mules and Horses
put in the hands of A <person_mentioned>Mr Pettus</person_mentioned> by <person_mentioned>John Hanna</person_mentioned> to have taken to
the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> which he sold and used the money that he received
for them was principally Mine <person_mentioned>Massie </person_mentioned>had no Interest in that drove
Independent of the Capital that I put in I loaned <person_mentioned>Hanna </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Massie</person_mentioned>
$850 that I received for freight at the Mouth of the <location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>and at
<location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned> to enable the Company to get the Mules and Horses to
the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> Independent of that I advanced to favor <person_mentioned>Phillip
T Dimmit</person_mentioned> about $350 which <person_mentioned>John Hanna</person_mentioned> assumed the payment of.
he was in <person_mentioned>Dimmit</person_mentioned>s debt all the Money that <person_mentioned>Dimit </person_mentioned>has collected since
I left the Province is gone with the rest at the time we heard of
<person_mentioned>Jennings </person_mentioned>death I was sick at <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned> and employed <person_mentioned>Hanna </person_mentioned>to go
to <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Jennings </person_mentioned>encampment</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>25 Miles above the mouth of the Colorado</location_mentioned> to
get possession of the things in his hands and those of Poore <person_mentioned>Harrison</person_mentioned>
he received money of the two deceased to the amount of $150. and
used their clothing that was worth any thing their riphles and out fit
which was Considered loaned money of which I have Never received
of him One Dollar. Independent of those things Named I put in his
and <person_mentioned>Massie</person_mentioned>s hands 11 of the Best Mules and 4 of the finest horses of
the Country purchased with my <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned>s money with instructions
When they arrived in the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> to deliver them to my <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned>
I sent them to him as a sample of the Stock of the <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>they
Never delivered him One mule or Horse When I crossed the 
<location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>Coming to the <person_mentioned>United States</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Judge Cummins</person_mentioned> sent me word
that he had collected some money for me for salt that was brought
from the <location_mentioned>mouth of the River</location_mentioned>, the principal part of the articles that
was taken from the encampment by those <person_mentioned>Americans </person_mentioned>that Com-<barker_pb n="919"/>
milted the robery belonged to us, and are among the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Nelson</person_mentioned>
knows them <person_mentioned>Nelson </person_mentioned>is acquainted and apprised that I made the
principal advances to enable <person_mentioned>Hanna </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Massie </person_mentioned>to get on and he was
at <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned> when I started the last mules under the care of <person_mentioned>Massie</person_mentioned>
hurder [?] I takeing them to the Main Caney <location_mentioned>ford on the Colorado
</location_mentioned>or <location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned>I wish you distinctly to understand that the Two <person_mentioned>Negroes</person_mentioned>
given up to <person_mentioned>Isurael Massie</person_mentioned> and put in the hands of <person_mentioned>Bell </person_mentioned>the late <person_mentioned>alcalde</person_mentioned>
that <person_mentioned>Pettes </person_mentioned>gave them up to <person_mentioned>Hanna </person_mentioned>and my self to pay for a part of
the Mules and horses put in the hands of his <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>which he had
sold and used the proceed thereof by all means get possession of
them and retaine it I am prossecuting <person_mentioned>Hanna </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Massie </person_mentioned>but shall
never get a Cent they have Conveyed their property as Cirtain
as their is a god in heaven We have never received one Cent from
<person_mentioned>Pettes </person_mentioned>on account of the drove of Mules and Horses that he sold 
belonging principally to my self do [not] let those <person_mentioned>Petteses </person_mentioned>deceive you
I know them from experiment to be bad men particularly that one
that gave up those <person_mentioned>Negroes </person_mentioned>I had a fair trial with him at the <location_mentioned>mouth
of the Brassos</location_mentioned> he lay sick at my <location_mentioned>encampment </location_mentioned>Three weeks I
waited on him night an day gave him my Medicines my every thing
After that I had a chance of knowing him again the man that has
not gratitude put him down as a scoundrel and you are not often
deceived, rest assured what I say to you soon or later you will
verify my remark as to that <person_mentioned>Maj Pettes</person_mentioned>, I have sent you a Compleat
power of Attorney do for me as you would do for your self I had
many unhappy Moments as to the transaction with <person_mentioned>Don Manuel
Allouri</person_mentioned> I had made on the mind of <person_mentioned>Citizens of <location_mentioned>San Antonio</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> a good
impression <person_mentioned>Barron de Bastropp</person_mentioned> persuaded me to purchase that 
property and stated to me that it had sold for $5000 and that it was low
at $750 which I paid for it when I left <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned> there was due
to me at least $800 and the stock of articles on hand $2 to 300 I
had in the hands of <person_mentioned>dravilo </person_mentioned>4 Mules had I any right under those
Circumstances to expect that <person_mentioned>Dimmit </person_mentioned>Could Not at any time pay
the $250 due to <person_mentioned>Facco </person_mentioned>also the House and Lot that Consider worth
at the lowest rate $1500 and Actually Rented for $20,00 the quarter
I consider <person_mentioned>Allouri </person_mentioned>and the <person_mentioned>Landlord of James E B Austin</person_mentioned> were
among 10.000 also <person_mentioned>Mosquis </person_mentioned>and<person_mentioned> Don Victor Blanco</person_mentioned> told me that If
<person_mentioned>Modeira </person_mentioned>did Not pay that freight that they would pay it and <person_mentioned>Don
Victor Blanco</person_mentioned> offered to do it before he started to <location_mentioned>Monclover </location_mentioned>I
have an exalted oppinion of both of those men however it is 
dificult to judge of that Nation of people you know them better than
I do I am at times determined to run to the Country to sink or swim
with you and if my poor <person_mentioned>Brothers family</person_mentioned> were provided for would
do it without hessitation Since my arrival to the <location_mentioned>united States</location_mentioned> I
have paid the <person_mentioned>Heirs of Harrison</person_mentioned> that excellent man that died at the<barker_pb n="920"/>
<location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Jennings</person_mentioned> Encampment</location_mentioned> $150 for his guns Clothing and Money that
<person_mentioned>John Hanna</person_mentioned> used</p>

<p><person_mentioned>James E. B. Austin</person_mentioned> says in the letter from <location_mentioned>Herculanium </location_mentioned>that
<person_mentioned>Trespalacious </person_mentioned>has deceived me, I made it a rule to Consult <person_mentioned>Baron de
Bastropp</person_mentioned> in all Cases particularly in the Two grants of land received
from him my Money and services was always at the command of
the <person_mentioned>Baron </person_mentioned>he was the <person_mentioned>interpreter </person_mentioned>as I did not speak the language
If I have been deceived it is not my fault it was the implicit 
confidence placed in the <person_mentioned>Baron </person_mentioned>he told me that the <person_mentioned>Governor</person_mentioned>s title was
good as a title Coming from the head of department and that he was
Compleatly authorized to Convey to any One five Miles square he
procured the grants and promised to have them properly recorded It
was understood that I had the ellection in my power after seeing the
land granted If it did not meet my Expectations that I would change
them I took one on the West or south side of the <location_mentioned>Gaudaloope </location_mentioned>the
other on the west side of <location_mentioned>Trinity </location_mentioned>including the improvement and
ferry both at the upper <location_mentioned>Crossing of those Rivers</location_mentioned> I wished to have
them changed to this side of the <location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned>or laid at any point that
you may think best I presume that they Cannot be laid or located
in your boundary <person_mentioned>John Botts</person_mentioned> is living on <location_mentioned>Red river in Louisianna</location_mentioned>
raiseing Cotton Recollect that I appropriated to the benefit of the
<person_mentioned>Troops of the <location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> $2500 worth of Tobacco and 
established a <location_mentioned>Tin factory at St antonio</location_mentioned> that was the Consideration for
those grants <person_mentioned>Baron de Bastropp</person_mentioned> knows that that amount of the
article was seized and put in the <location_mentioned>publick Stank 
[estanco=warehouse] </location_mentioned>the <person_mentioned>citizens of <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> know the same uppon those grounds
I presume the grants will be ratified by the government do on it
what you think best, please write me often from the exalted terms
in which I have heard my <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>speak of you I have full 
Confidence <person_mentioned>George </person_mentioned>has the same and it [is] her wish that you should be
her <person_mentioned>Agent </person_mentioned>and do for her what you think best I will have her
Power of Attorney forwarded to you by the first chance please
state to me Candidly if it would [be] prudent to take afamily to the
settlement or not. I am anxious that <person_mentioned>Allouri </person_mentioned>should be paid he
treated all the <person_mentioned>Americans </person_mentioned>kindly that came to the place and was
very kind to me I have an exalted opinion of him you Certainly
Can Compele <person_mentioned>Modeira </person_mentioned>to pay the Claim against him, had you a
<person_mentioned>wife </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>would you take them to the <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>at this time
particularly those that never have known what it was to undergo
hardship or exposure in your letters answer this queary Candidly.
I can bring some good <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>particularly from <location_mentioned>Louisiana </location_mentioned>I have
lately seen the <person_mentioned>Brother of Mr. Ingram the surveyor</person_mentioned> that resides
at <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> he speaks of removing to the Country say to his<barker_pb n="921"/>
<person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>that he is in good health and present him <person_mentioned>Castleman </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Nelson</person_mentioned>
and the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>that may ask after me my respects I am sorry that
I ever quit the Country [if] I had remained I could have been 
Comfortable recollect that what is done is [for] the benefit of the 
dessolate <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>of our departed friend he always made it a rule to
divide his last dollar with me and it [is] my determination to [do]
no less with his <person_mentioned>children </person_mentioned>I am st[r]aining to get them in a situation
to live so soon as I can accomplish that I will Come to the Country,
I am pleased to learn that your <person_mentioned>sister </person_mentioned>is about to be well settled
again <person_mentioned>Hosa Murrah [José Maria Carbajal?] </person_mentioned>is well and going to
<location_mentioned>schoole </location_mentioned>learning fast inclosed is a letter from <person_mentioned>George Anna Hawkins
</person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Doct Holley</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>is well and desire to be spoken of to you
and your <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>James E B Austin</person_mentioned> that formerly Boarded with
them <person_mentioned>John H Morton</person_mentioned> Holds a draft of <person_mentioned>James </person_mentioned>on your self he
says for Boarding I will endeavor to take it up in this year if I can
please say if it ought to be paid I could not say on paper all that I
wish to communicate in a week excuse my scrawl the Mail is just 
closeing I fear that my letters may miss <person_mentioned>James </person_mentioned>if he sets out as soon as
he contemplated god bless and prosper your wishes health and 
Hapiness I find my <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>has advanced $2,850 to the vessels and cargoes
sent to the <location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Pro[vince]</location_mentioned> etc that is the statement of his
account in the hands of <person_mentioned>N Cox of <location_mentioned>N Orleans</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, please write my
<person_mentioned>Brothers wife </person_mentioned>[as] often as in your power dont let any Prejudices
or ill tales that you git from the <location_mentioned>settlers </location_mentioned>influence your mind as to
my self <person_mentioned>John T Hawkins</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>John Hanna</person_mentioned> had a dispute and the 
Circumstance of my taking <person_mentioned>Hanna </person_mentioned>into partnership dissatisfied <person_mentioned>John
Hawkins</person_mentioned> with me and he does every thing in his power to injure me
among them I did not meet with him the truth is that every man
appeared to think that all that came to the Country was free 
property and at their Command and Commenced cabbaging and using
accordingly whare ever they could find it</p>

<p>Your friend                                                         <person_mentioned> L. Hawkins</person_mentioned></p>

<p>When I left the <location_mentioned>Mouth of the Colorado</location_mentioned> I had stored there 
everything that suited farming purposes and took nothing round to sell
that I expected the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>would want. I left all the salt, hoes axes
Broad axes chains, grubbing hoes hand, Cross, and Whip saws
planes drawing Knives. <person_mentioned>Mr. Ingram</person_mentioned> can prove this I left them
under his care and in his room I had to purchase provisions of the
<person_mentioned>passengers </person_mentioned>On board of the Only <person_mentioned>Son </person_mentioned>at the <location_mentioned>Bay of St. Joseph</location_mentioned> for the
<person_mentioned>hands <location_mentioned>on Board</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> of the three vessils that I took to the <location_mentioned>mouth of
Guadaloupe</location_mentioned>, Still I was charged with having taken away the 
provissions that out [ought] to have been left for the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>and Many<barker_pb n="922"/>
other things as absurd I must stop all those that don any thing
in Boating or rendered any other services I paid them high Wages all
those that Came to either of my <location_mentioned>encampments </location_mentioned>lived as I did I never
did charge them for eating or drinking the rule was to divide to the
last cake with them the provisions that was eat at the <location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned>and on
the <location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned>if sold would have brought $500. ask little who was at
the <location_mentioned>encampment</location_mentioned>, that I know was prejudiced against me. ask 
<person_mentioned>Nelson </person_mentioned>who made many tripps up the <location_mentioned>Brassos</location_mentioned>, [ask] that <person_mentioned>Maj. Pettus
</person_mentioned>and his friend <person_mentioned>Kirkpatrick </person_mentioned>That lay sick at my <location_mentioned>encampment </location_mentioned>at the
<location_mentioned>mouth of the Brassos</location_mentioned> what kind of treatment they received without
paying One Cent, they [had] Chocolate Tea Coffee Brown and
Loaf sugar Bacon Beeff Pork Crackers ham Brandy Whiskey all
did not satisfy they still complained of me it shows the base 
ingratitude of the people of this world I took to the Country 10 young
men that I furnished with Riphles provisions everything they Could
want still paid their passage divided with them to the last and all
did not suffice <person_mentioned>Beard </person_mentioned>got offended with me for not purchasing a
watch and Riphle at <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned> when had a first rate One laying
on the <location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned>I took five good Riphles to the Country all was given
away except the one <person_mentioned>Hanna </person_mentioned>sold <person_mentioned>Nelson </person_mentioned>I came out of the Country
with 3 mules two Horses 1 Riphle and $250 in Money to pay the
Expences of three persons to <location_mentioned>Kentucky </location_mentioned>that is all that I have ever
have received out of the whole trip, my prayers for your good
health and Happiness please speak of me to <person_mentioned>Baron de Bastrop</person_mentioned> 
affectionately I became much attached to that man looked up to him
as a <person_mentioned>guardian </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>did nothing without Consulting him solicit
his aid in geting those grants in my name on this side of the 
<location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned>if possable speak of me to <person_mentioned>Don Erasmore and family</person_mentioned> I believe
him worth in principle all the whole possy No such man at <location_mentioned>St
Antonio</location_mentioned> as himself I have often regreated that every thing that
was thrown away on the <person_mentioned>scoundrels </person_mentioned>in the <location_mentioned>province </location_mentioned>had [not] been
put in his hands it [would] have saved many hundreds I have 
attempted to take leave of you twenty times since I commenced it
appears to be hard to do <person_mentioned>Iterbede </person_mentioned>is shot shortly after his landing
the <person_mentioned>French Troops</person_mentioned> left in <location_mentioned>Spain </location_mentioned>have been latly dreadfully butchered
by the <person_mentioned>Spaniards </person_mentioned>thank god I hope they will massacre the whole of
them.</p>

<p>Sincerely Your friend                                         <person_mentioned>L. Hawkins</person_mentioned></p>

<p>I regret that I cannot send you papers for six month Reading that
you might know what the Balance of the world is doing.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Stephen F Austin Esq</person_mentioned>. <location_mentioned>Phillipe De. Austin Brassos
Province of Texas</location_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
