
<TEI.2 id="APB0495">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-10-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 491-493</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Maria Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Maria Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 04-10-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Hazel Run, MO</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Austin, TX</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Families preparing for Texas. News.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Original in possession of Mrs. Emmett L. Perry.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 491-493</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0495T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Families preparing for Texas. News.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p><location_mentioned>Hazel run</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="04-10-1822">Aprill the 10—1822</date_mentioned></p>
<p>I am happy in meeting with So good an opportunity as now 
presents by <person_mentioned>V. Ally</person_mentioned>—of writing to my dear absent <person_mentioned>Sons </person_mentioned>and to tell them
how very anxious I am to hear from them I had flatterd myself I
should have had that pleasure before this time by the return of some
of the Gentlemn that went to <location_mentioned>texas </location_mentioned>in the <date_mentioned n="Fall-1821">fall </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="Winter-1821">winter </date_mentioned>Some of
whome promissed to call on us, nothing, except the pleasure of 
Embraceing my dear <person_mentioned>Sons</person_mentioned>—could give me So much Satisfaction as that
of seeing those who have visited your <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>and conversed with
you boath, every incident related by those who had Seen you, would
be Interesting to your anxious <person_mentioned>mother</person_mentioned>—the rage for emigration
still continues and a great number of <person_mentioned>famaly</person_mentioned>s boath from this State
and the <location_mentioned>Ill[inois]</location_mentioned> are prepareing for <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>without going to view the
country—a number of letters addressed to you from all quarters
has been taken out of the <location_mentioned>office </location_mentioned>by <person_mentioned>Mr Brian</person_mentioned> all of which he has
answerd we theirefore think it not necessary to forward them to<barker_pb n="492"/>
you I hope the people by this time knows you are not in this 
<location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>and will for the future direct their letters to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>your <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>
within my knowledge are well, your <person_mentioned>aunt Austin </person_mentioned>has another fine
<person_mentioned>Son</person_mentioned>, theay call him <person_mentioned>Elick</person_mentioned>, I toll them theay will have to Send their
<person_mentioned>Sons </person_mentioned>to the <location_mentioned>Spanish Country</location_mentioned> to get land—<person_mentioned>Moses </person_mentioned>talks of going
Sometimes, but your <person_mentioned>Uncle </person_mentioned>is averse to it—<person_mentioned>G Hammond</person_mentioned> returnd
from <location_mentioned>Georgey </location_mentioned>a Short time past, as poor as when he went on in
Short he is compleatly broak up and is not worth a dollar and your
<person_mentioned>Uncle </person_mentioned>has to Support his <person_mentioned>famaly</person_mentioned>— he talks of mackeing you a
visit—if he Should I hope you will have but little to do with him,
he has never manifested any friendship to our <person_mentioned>famaly </person_mentioned>and from his
treatment to your deceased <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>he well knows he is not intitled
to any favours from you or any of us—I feel Sorry for <person_mentioned>Eliza </person_mentioned>and
hur little <person_mentioned>children</person_mentioned>—I expect to go to <location_mentioned>Herculaneum </location_mentioned>in a few days I
have some property their which I must do something with I have
thought it would be best to Send my pot mettel to <location_mentioned>new Orleans</location_mentioned> to
the care of <person_mentioned>Mr Hawkins</person_mentioned> provided the freight was not two high,
you may recollect my <person_mentioned>Son</person_mentioned>, what a quantity of bucks horns was taken
in, nothing has been don[e] with them, but as <person_mentioned>Fletcher </person_mentioned>now occupys
the place and theay being in his way, Something must be done with
them and I have Concluded to Send them down the <location_mentioned>river </location_mentioned>to you or
your friend <person_mentioned>H[awkins]</person_mentioned>—perhaps may Sell them for Something—I
Shall also Send Some plough Shares, your poor <person_mentioned>father </person_mentioned>was very
particular in geting, the Iron of a pecular good quallity it requirs
no Steel, oh how I regret that the great distance that Seperates us,
deprives me of the pleasure of hereing from my dear <person_mentioned>Sons </person_mentioned>as oft as
I wish, I hope my dear <person_mentioned>Brown </person_mentioned>will not omit writing to his <person_mentioned>mother</person_mentioned>
or <person_mentioned>Sister </person_mentioned>by every Opportunity and let us know how he is pleased
with the country and Climate, we have had a very cold hard <date_mentioned n="Winter-1821">winter</date_mentioned>
and even now we are apprehensive of looseing all the fruite by
sevear frost—we are all disireous of leaveing this changeable climate
and shall rejoice when the time of our departure arrives—I wish my
dear <person_mentioned>Sons </person_mentioned>to be particular in writing and adviseing us, what to tacke
with us.<person_mentioned> Mr B,</person_mentioned> expects to have all businiss arranged by <date_mentioned n="10-xx-1822">October </date_mentioned>but
I shall still flatter myself it will be in my dear <person_mentioned>Stepn </person_mentioned>power to visit
<location_mentioned>Missouri </location_mentioned>before the <date_mentioned n="Fall-1822">fall</date_mentioned>. I expect to receive some money from 
<location_mentioned>Jersey </location_mentioned>this <date_mentioned n="Summer-1822">Summer </date_mentioned>and have made an arrangement with <person_mentioned>Mr S Perry</person_mentioned>
to get the money for me he and his <person_mentioned>lady </person_mentioned>has gown on to <location_mentioned>Philadela</location_mentioned>
I have wrote him to make use of the three hundred dollars if he
wished So to do and allow me 20 persent for the use of the money—
if I get this it will be in my power to pay of [f] Some of my <person_mentioned>son B</person_mentioned>
debts contracted in <location_mentioned>Kentuckey </location_mentioned>and wish him to let me know who to
pay it too—your little <person_mentioned>Nephfews </person_mentioned>are all fine <person_mentioned>Children </person_mentioned>in good health
and often speak of their <person_mentioned>Uncles</person_mentioned>, our little <person_mentioned>guy </person_mentioned>is the beauty of the<barker_pb n="493"/>
<person_mentioned>famaly</person_mentioned>, we expect an Increas about the <date_mentioned n="07-01-1822">first of July</date_mentioned>, your <person_mentioned>Sister</person_mentioned>
joines me in affectionate love to you boath Sincearely praying that
god may guard, protect and prosper you in all your just and 
laudable exertions—preserve you in health and happyniss and finally
bring us together and injoy each others Society in peace, as long as
we remain in this world and never ending felicity in the <location_mentioned>kingdom of
heaven</location_mentioned> is the prayr of your affectionate <person_mentioned>Mother</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mary Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>P S—I procurd another register of your <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned>s Baptism which
I now Inclose together with a letter for <person_mentioned>B</person_mentioned> from some of his 
<person_mentioned><location_mentioned>Kentuckey </location_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>—which I hope may reatch him in Safety—<person_mentioned>Bryant </person_mentioned>Sent
the lost Certificate by a<person_mentioned> Mr Witeing</person_mentioned>, aliso two barrels of flower for
your one use—let us know if flower and Whiskey will sell well, it
tis Said provisions of all kinds is high and Scarse, but this does not
frighten the people from going. I am only fearfull you will not
have as much land as the great number of <person_mentioned>famalys </person_mentioned>will want, even
admitting that one half of the people goes that talks of moveing,
and at the Same time reserve as much for your Self and <person_mentioned>famaly </person_mentioned>as
will pay you for all your trouble. I beg my dear <person_mentioned>Son </person_mentioned>will not let
his Generousity go So far—as to injure himself, but Secure a 
Sufficient quantity of land to place his fallen <person_mentioned>famaly </person_mentioned>in their former
State of Independance, truly my beloved <person_mentioned>Sons</person_mentioned>, this <location_mentioned>grant </location_mentioned>of land
was bought with a price—even the precious life of your dear <person_mentioned>Father</person_mentioned>,
for I am Sertain it was oing to fatigue and hardship that deprived
him of his health and finally ended in death, at the moment when he
thought he was about to receive a reward for all his exertions and
sevear tryals, but the lords will be done. I have good reason to
think your dear <person_mentioned>Father </person_mentioned>will receive his reward in <location_mentioned>heaven</location_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Mr alley
</person_mentioned>is waiting for this letter he has promesd to deliver it himself, once
more adieu my dear <person_mentioned>Sons</person_mentioned>, may god forever bless you</p>

<p><person_mentioned>MA</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p>[Addressd:] <person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin Esqr</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Austin <hi rend="italic">Provence of Texas</hi></location_mentioned>
Attention <person_mentioned>Mr. Thos V. Alley</person_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
