
<TEI.2 id="APB0950">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-22-1824</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 996-1002</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Public</document_status>
<document_type>Memorial</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Legislature</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Legislature, 12-22-1824</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Memorial by Austin to the Legislature of Coahuila and Texas: (1) Wants copy of law concerning settlement of estates of deceased persons. (2) Law concerning debts contracted before entering colony. Thinks law should exempt them from prosecution for 12 years. (3) Law concerning deeding and conveying lands. Describes the method he has been following.
(4) Asks whether English and French may be used in deeds and records. Has used Spanish consistently, but not "one in a hundred" of the colonists understands Spanish. (5) Asks how to procure sealed paper for 1825. (6) Asks instructions for punishment of thieves, robbers, etc. Position on frontier exposes settlement to rogues of both nations. (7) Argument for establishment of mail service as far as the Sabine; United States would establish a line to connect with the Mexican route. (8) Repeats request for permission to settle additional families and asks about slaves. (9) Instructions for treatment of fugitive slaves from the United States, and for the punishment of kidnappers of free negroes who bring the negroes to Texas. (10) Has Austin authority to punish counterfeiters of Louisiana bank paper who circulate it in Texas? (11) Is he authorized to establish provisional regulations if laws on certain subjects are not available? (12) Suggests appointment of superior judge and his own relief from judicial duties. (13) Toleration for Protestant preaching
and worship.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 996-1002</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-18-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0950T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Memorial by Austin to the Legislature of Coahuila and Texas: (1) Wants copy of law concerning settlement of estates of deceased persons. (2) Law concerning debts contracted before entering colony. Thinks law should exempt them from prosecution for 12 years. (3) Law concerning deeding and conveying lands. Describes the method he has been following.
(4) Asks whether English and French may be used in deeds and records. Has used Spanish consistently, but not "one in a hundred" of the colonists understands Spanish. (5) Asks how to procure sealed paper for 1825. (6) Asks instructions for punishment of thieves, robbers, etc. Position on frontier exposes settlement to rogues of both nations. (7) Argument for establishment of mail service as far as the Sabine; United States would establish a line to connect with the Mexican route. (8) Repeats request for permission to settle additional families and asks about slaves. (9) Instructions for treatment of fugitive slaves from the United States, and for the punishment of kidnappers of free negroes who bring the negroes to Texas. (10) Has Austin authority to punish counterfeiters of Louisiana bank paper who circulate it in Texas? (11) Is he authorized to establish provisional regulations if laws on certain subjects are not available? (12) Suggests appointment of superior judge and his own relief from judicial duties. (13) Toleration for Protestant preaching
and worship.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>The<person_mentioned> Empresario Stephen F Austin</person_mentioned> respectfully solicits in behalf
of the <location_mentioned>Colonists </location_mentioned>settled by him in this <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>that the 
<person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>will be pleased to forward Copies of the Laws and particularly
relative to the following points.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">first</hi>—The Law relative to the settlement of the estates of 
<person_mentioned>deceased persons</person_mentioned> and the mode of settling Where the <person_mentioned>Heirs </person_mentioned>or a part
of them live out of this <location_mentioned>Nation</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">second</hi>—The Law relative to the Collection of debts Contracted
by the <location_mentioned>Colonists </location_mentioned>out of this <location_mentioned>Nation </location_mentioned>previous to their removal here—
This is very important for if the <person_mentioned>Settlers </person_mentioned>can be sued and their
property taken here for debts due in the <location_mentioned>U. States of North America
</location_mentioned>before they have time to establish themselves and make any thing
they will be totally ruined. They have some of them spent all they
had to move and settle themselves in this <location_mentioned>uninhabited Country</location_mentioned>, they
will however be able by Cultivating Cotton to pay all their Debts
if time is given them, but if their Land and property can be taken
for those debts it will ruin them and be of more injury to the 
improvement of this Country than any thing that Could happen—I<barker_pb n="997"/>
therefore take the Liberty of respectfully suggesting whether the
interest of the <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>would not be greatly promoted by protecting
the new <location_mentioned>Emigrants </location_mentioned>from all old foreign debts for at least Twelve
Years—Many very good Men are unfortunate in business and 
become involved in Debt by misfortune, some such have removed here
and endured all the fatigues, and dangers and losses of settling a
<location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>with the hope of bettering their situation and being
able in time to pay off all their Debts, and they are now looking to
the <person_mentioned>Government of the State </person_mentioned>as to a father who will interpose its
parental Authority to save them and their <person_mentioned>wives </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Children </person_mentioned>from
the Cruel and merciless persecution of unfeeling <person_mentioned>Creditors </person_mentioned>who may
follow them from the <location_mentioned>U. States</location_mentioned>.—I am not in favor of extending too
much protection to any who have defrauded their <person_mentioned>Creditors </person_mentioned>but it
appears to me that sound policy and the dictates of Justice and
Humanity certainly would justify affording the most ample 
protection to every honest but unfortunate <person_mentioned>debtor </person_mentioned>whose hard fate 
elsewhere has driven him to seek an asylum in the <location_mentioned>Mexican Republic</location_mentioned>.
Therefore if the Laws do not already afford sufficient protection, I
think the Legislature would promote the prosperity of the Country
and do an act of humanity and justice by giving at least Twelve
years for all who remove and settle in this State to pay their old
debts Contracted before they removed here.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Third</hi>—The Law relative to the Sale and Deeding or Conveying
of Lands between the <location_mentioned>Settlers</location_mentioned>—This is also of much importance,
most of the <person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>have relations and friends in the <location_mentioned>United States
</location_mentioned>who they Wish to remove here and settle along side of them on their
Lands, and to do this they wish to divide the Lands granted to them
by the <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>into several parts in order to establish their <person_mentioned>Relations</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>near them, and as it is a matter of great importance that
there should be no irregularity or illegality in the mode of Making
their sales and Deeds I wish to know the Law on the subject and to
have the form of makeing Deeds and acknowledging them, this is
very important to the prosperity of the Country for by each <person_mentioned>Colonist</person_mentioned>
dividing his Land amongst his relations and friends the Land will
be much Better Cultivated and more produce made than if it was held
by the Individual to whom it was originally granted—Many such
sales have already been made and I have caused those who gave the
Deed to come before me as the <person_mentioned>Judge of the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and acknowledge
or Execute the Deed in my presence with witnesses and have made a
Record of the Act of Sale in a Record Book kept for that object and
delivered the original to the owner—This is the mode used in the
<location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> and is most satisfactory to the <person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>as they are
all accustomed to it, and this mode has been approved of by the most
Excellent Deputation of this <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>who also directed that a <person_mentioned>Sec-<barker_pb n="998"/>
retary</person_mentioned> should be appointed for the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>who should Register all
such Deeds and Mortgages between the <person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>under my 
inspection and responsability and who should be paid by the interested
party Agreeably to the old Spanish Arancel on the subject—
accordingly I have appointed <person_mentioned>Mr Samuel M Williams</person_mentioned> the <person_mentioned>Secretary </person_mentioned>and
have proceeded to execute and Record all sales of Lands by the
<person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>in the manner above stated, and Should it meet the 
Aprobation of the Government of the State I think that this mode will be
more satisfactory to the Colonists than any other that could be
adopted for by this means a Complete record is kept in the <location_mentioned>Archives
of the Colony</location_mentioned> of every sale and transfer of Land, which can always
be refered to in case the original Deed is lost, and also it will prevent
fraud because a reference to the Records will always shew whether
the Land had been sold or mortgaged before and the Complete state
of the Title in every respect will appear at all times on record.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">fourth</hi>—Whether Deeds of Sale must all be made and 
acknowledged and Recorded in Spanish or whether they Can be legally
executed and Recorded in the English or French Languages—I
have in all cases directed all the <person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>to make their Deeds of
Conveyance in Spanish as the only legal language, but as not one
in a hundred of them understand that language it would afford them
a great accomadation if the Law would permit them to Deed Lands
and make all their Written Contracts in the English or French and
permit them to be recorded in those Languages.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">fifth</hi>—The <person_mentioned>Political Chief of this <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> ordered me to seal
or habilitate all the Sealed paper which the <person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>might need
in the Transactions of their business and I have done so and the
<person_mentioned>Alcalde of the <location_mentioned>District of St Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> was appointed to
Collect it—but as that order only authorised me to seal the paper
for the Year <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824 </date_mentioned>I wish to know how we are to procure sealed
paper for the Year <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1825">1825 </date_mentioned>and Whether I am authorised to Continue
as I have done to seal it.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Sixth</hi>—I wish for particular instructions relative to the 
apprehending prosecuting and punishing of <person_mentioned>Criminals </person_mentioned>such as <person_mentioned>Theives</person_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>Robbers</person_mentioned>, Murderers, <person_mentioned>Disturbers of the peace</person_mentioned> etc, etc,—-Our Situation
so near the <location_mentioned>frontiers of two Nations</location_mentioned> and remote from the <location_mentioned>seat of
Government of the State</location_mentioned> renders us liable to great hazard from
the depredations of <person_mentioned>Rogues </person_mentioned>from both <location_mentioned>Nations </location_mentioned>in their transit from
the <location_mentioned>Territory </location_mentioned>of one to the other. I have so far taken prompt 
measures to order out of the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>all Men of Notoriously bad and
infamous Character who Come into it and by this method have
succeeded in protecting the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>from them, and since my 
return from <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>there has been not one instance of Murder and
only one of stealing which latter was punished by sending the Man<barker_pb n="999"/>
with his <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>and all Concerned in the transaction back over the
<location_mentioned>Sabine River</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">seventh</hi>—A Number of Gentlemen of high respectability living at
<location_mentioned>Nachitoches</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Rapide</location_mentioned>, and other parts of <location_mentioned>Louisiana </location_mentioned>have written to
me requesting any information in my power to give whether the
<person_mentioned>Mexican Government</person_mentioned> would probably establish a mail as far as the
<location_mentioned>River Sabine</location_mentioned>—They inform me that if such a thing was done there
was no doubt the [Govt.] of the <location_mentioned>United States of North America
</location_mentioned>would order the Mail on that side to meet the one from this at the
<location_mentioned>Sabine</location_mentioned>—I beg leave most respectfully to suggest to the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>. that
many benefits might probably arise to the whole <location_mentioned>Mexican Nation
</location_mentioned>as well as to this <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>if an arrangement of this kind Could be 
effected once a Month or even once in two Months.</p>

<p>1st. It would afford the means of Conveying the Correspondence
between the <person_mentioned>Mexican Government</person_mentioned> to their <person_mentioned>Minister at <location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
the whole distance by Land without the hazard of delay or 
miscarriage incident to the transportation of documents by sea.</p>

<p>2d. It would open a Certain, regular and direct Channel for the
Conveyance of letters and <location_mentioned>Newspapers </location_mentioned>from every part of either
<location_mentioned>Nation </location_mentioned>to every part of the other, thereby affording great facilities
to <person_mentioned>Merchants </person_mentioned>on either side in their Commercial Communications,
and presenting an opportunity for the mutual exchange of 
<location_mentioned>Newspapers </location_mentioned>and the dissemination of foreign intelligence recd at the <location_mentioned>ports
of the United States of the North</location_mentioned> through the <location_mentioned>United States of 
Mexico</location_mentioned> in the event of any interruption by <person_mentioned>Beligerants </person_mentioned>of the 
Communication by sea with our <location_mentioned>ports</location_mentioned>: and perhaps it might in some degree
tend to draw Closer the bands of fraternity and Confidence which
every <person_mentioned>Philanthropist </person_mentioned>must desire to see cemented and perpetuated
between the <location_mentioned>two great Republics of North America</location_mentioned>, by affording
to the <person_mentioned>Citizens </person_mentioned>of each the opportunity of a frequent and Mutual
interchange of sentiments as well by private letters as through the
medium of public Journals</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Eighth</hi>—I have received a number of Letters from respectable and
<person_mentioned>wealthy people</person_mentioned> from the States of <location_mentioned>Louisiana </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Mississippi </location_mentioned>asking
for information whether they would be allowed to remove and settle
in this <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>and to bring such property as they needed for their
own use particularly their <person_mentioned>Slaves</person_mentioned>—I answered them that I could not
inform them on the subject but would represent to the <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>
and accordingly sent on a petition some time since praying for
authority to settle <person_mentioned>Three hundred families</person_mentioned> more on the <location_mentioned>Trinity
River</location_mentioned> and round the <location_mentioned>Bay of Galveston</location_mentioned>—I respectfully request 
information relative to my petitions that I may inform those 
applicants what they have to expect—their reason for wishing to move
here is the unhealthiness of that Country and the inundations of the<barker_pb n="1000"/>
<location_mentioned>Mississippi   </location_mentioned>they are all men of honor industry and property and
Would greatly promote the prosperity of this Country</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Ninth</hi>—As we are near the <location_mentioned>frontiers of Louisiana</location_mentioned> some <person_mentioned>Negro
Slaves</person_mentioned> of that state may run away from their <person_mentioned>owners </person_mentioned>and Come to
this <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>—What am I authorised to do in such a Case? If the
<person_mentioned>runaway </person_mentioned>remains here, he is a nuisance to the Country—if his <person_mentioned>owner</person_mentioned>
claims him and he is not given up it will destroy all harmony 
between the <person_mentioned>Citizens </person_mentioned>of that State and this—Also if a <person_mentioned>free man</person_mentioned> steals a
<person_mentioned>Negro </person_mentioned>from that State and brings him here how is the Crime to be
punished? This is certainly a very high Crime and I think that
Justice requires it should be punished to the utmost extent—and that
those who bring stolen <person_mentioned>Negroes </person_mentioned>into this State ought to be chastised
by Whipping heavy fine and imprisonment to hard Labour but I
submit the subject to the Consideration of the Government and
solicit their instructions.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Tenth</hi>—Our Proximity to <location_mentioned>Louisiana </location_mentioned>also makes the Bank paper
of that state Current to a small extent here and we may therefore
be greatly imposed on by <person_mentioned>Counterfeiters </person_mentioned>how am I authorized to
punish a Man Who brings a quantity of Counterfeit Bank paper into
the Country to defraud the innocent <person_mentioned>Inhabitants </person_mentioned>who are not a judge
of such money-</p>

<p>I have made provisional regulations relative to some of these 
subjects which have as yet fully protected us—but it would be more
proper and satisfactory to receive the orders of [that] Government—
Also I respectfully wish to know whether I am authorised to make
any more temporary or provisional municipal regulations for the
preservation of good order and good government in the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>in
Cases where We have not received the Laws and are unable to 
procure them with translations—</p>

<p>Villa de <location_mentioned>San Felipe Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="12-22-1824">22 de Deciembre de 1824</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Estevan F. Austin</person_mentioned>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Part of another draft of this document, in Austin's hand, is 
endorsed by him:] Copies of representation sent to the <person_mentioned>Baron de
Bastrop deputy in the Legislature of this State</person_mentioned>, to be translated and
presented to the <person_mentioned>Governor of the <location_mentioned>State of Quahuila and Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>[In this partial draft, which perhaps represents the first stage of
the memorial, Austin wrote, and then deleted, two additional 
paragraphs :]</p>

<p>7—In as much as I have so many other occupations to attend to in
keeping good order—watching and pursuing hostile <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>—and
finally arranging all the business of the Colony, and also being 
uninformed as to the laws of the nation and the state I wish if possible
that a <person_mentioned>Juez de letras</person_mentioned> might be appointed to decide appeals etc from<barker_pb n="1001"/>
the Alcaldes—one <person_mentioned>Juez de letras</person_mentioned> could do for the whole <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned>,
I am ready and willing to act in any capacity in which the <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>may
deem me useful in this Colony and that without any pay or salary
whatever as I have heretofore done and am willing to continue
as I have done to manage the civil and militia affairs of the Colony
and the keeping of records etc., but if it can be otherwise arranged
I do not wish to have anything to do with Judicial proceedings
for I think that a man learned in the Mexican laws ought to be 
appointed for that purpose, though if this colony was divided into
as many partidos as are necessary and one Alcalde elected by the
people for each partido from whose decission there should be an
appeal to the <person_mentioned>juez de letras</person_mentioned> of the <location_mentioned>Province </location_mentioned>I think it would very
much tend to promote good order, and it certainly would be in the
highest degree satisfactory and gratifying to me as I should then
be releived from the most responsible and disagreeable part of my
duties—[In margin:]    Not sent.</p>

<p>8—A number of <person_mentioned>preachers of the Christian Religion</person_mentioned> in the 
English language have applied to me for liberty to preach and 
establish their mode of worship in this <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, I have informed them,
in conformity with the 4 article of the acta Constitution and in
complyance with the verbal instructions of the <person_mentioned>Political chief of
the <location_mentioned>Province</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> that it was contrary to law and if they come here to
preach publically they would be liable to be punished If the 
Constitution and laws of the nation or those of the state could permit
any relaxation on this point it would greatly promote the 
prosperity of this part of the country and as I conceive could not do
any injury as the object of those preachers who wish to come in is
solely to promote good morals without wishing to attempt making
converts from the Catholic Religion—Any indulgence that could be
extended to these <location_mentioned>settlers </location_mentioned>on this subject will be most thankfully
reced and gratefully remembered, as they are now totally destitute
of any spiritual aid whatever and must so continue for a long time
as they are all unacquainted with the Spanish language, and 
cannot therefore receive that instruction from the cura who we have
been expecting which a subject of such great importance requires—
I therefore submit the subject for the consideration of the <person_mentioned>Honorable
State Legislature</person_mentioned> in the full hope that, that honorable and 
enlightened Body will be pleased to extend to these inhabitants all the 
indulgence relative to public worship and preaching in the English
language, which they may deem consistent with the laws or with
the general interests of the nation. And under the full belief, that
the permiting a few enlightened well educated Judicious and 
reasonable <person_mentioned>preachers of the Gospel</person_mentioned> of the christian religion in the Eng-<barker_pb n="1002"/>
lish language would be attended with the most happy results to the
<person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>individually and would greatly promote the Genl, prosperity
good order morality and improvement of this part of the State-
in margin of this section:] deemed a dangerous subject to touch
and therefore not sent.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
