
<TEI.2 id="APB0531">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>08-06-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 535-536</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Joseph H. Hawkins</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Joseph H. Hawkins, 08-06-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Mexico City, MX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Political conditions in Mexico.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From the <hi rend="italic">Cincinnati Western Spy and Literary Cadet</hi>, October 19, 1822 (Wisconsin
Historical Society Collections), quoting from the <hi rend="italic">Louisiana Advertiser</hi>, no date. Copied
by the editor.
Both Bourbonists and Republicans resented the coronation of Iturbide, and plots and
counter-plots were numerous during July and August.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 535-536</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0531T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Political conditions in Mexico.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p><location_mentioned>City of Mexico</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="08-06-1822">Aug. 6, 1822</date_mentioned>.</p>
<p>Dear Sir—I wrote you a few days since by <person_mentioned>Mr. De Armos</person_mentioned> who
accompanied <person_mentioned>Col. Erwin</person_mentioned> through by land.   At the time I wrote that<barker_pb n="536"/>
letter, some strange rumors were in circulation as to the state of 
affairs here; but I am happy in assuring you they turned out to be
entirely false. Things are more tranquil; the <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>progressing
in their deliberations, and appearances justify the conclusion, that
whatever be the collision arising from difference in opinion as to
the course this government should pursue it is gradually gaining
strength, and will, I trust, ultimately secure the end of all 
government, the happiness of the people. As I mentioned in a former 
letter, business was all suspended for the ceremonies of the most 
splendid coronation which perhaps any age has furnished. <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>have
resumed their labors with some asciduity. The colonization law is
now printing and will be finally discussed and disposed of in eight
or ten days. I will forward a copy the moment it passes. There is
a section in it which embraces my case, and without some unexpected
opposition or difficulty, I hope to have my claim fully confirmed, and
be on my way to the <location_mentioned>settlement </location_mentioned>at all events in fifteen or twenty days,
I shall however, not leave this until my <location_mentioned>land claim</location_mentioned> is finally 
adjusted ; and although I am aware the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>have experienced much
inconvenience by my absence, still in the end my visit here will not
be without advantages to the settlement.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin.</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
