
<TEI.2 id="APB0500">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-16-1822</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 496-497</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>R. C. Bruffey</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F. Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>R. C. Bruffey to Stephen F. Austin, 04-16-1822</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>St. Antonio, TX</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Austin, TX</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Disappointment at not seeing Austin. Uneasy about constitution and "restrictions."  Austin's debts.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>The <hi rend="italic">Lively</hi>. See above, November 11, 1821, note.
Bruffey was a preacher. The "restrictions" which he most feared were probably religious.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 496-497</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB0500T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Disappointment at not seeing Austin.   Uneasy about constitution and " restrictions."   Austin's debts.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="04-16-1822">16th April 1822</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I left home and arrived at this place <date_mentioned n="06-15-1822">yesterday </date_mentioned>I left <location_mentioned>Home </location_mentioned>the
<date_mentioned n="01-22-1822">22nd January </date_mentioned>and have had a Tedious Journey as you will see by the
date I was mortified to hear of your vessell not having arrived on
the <location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned>I saw Messrs <person_mentioned>Foster </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Burnet </person_mentioned>who stated that your
articles were Landed at the <location_mentioned>mouth of that River</location_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Foster </person_mentioned>was then on
his way to the <location_mentioned>place of Landing</location_mentioned> and stated that he would Remain
by the goods Report says that yours and two other vessels had fitted
out for the same <location_mentioned>coast </location_mentioned>that is yours a second time I felt considerably
Shagrined when I heard that you had gone to <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>but it was no
doubt Necessary—I am pleased with the country on <location_mentioned>Brassos </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned>
and <location_mentioned>Guadalupe </location_mentioned>but particularly the Former I am sorry I cannot
see you as I can do nothing the <person_mentioned>Governor </person_mentioned>Refers me to you and
I am in doubt how to act more especially as the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>is not
compleately Organized consequently I know not what the 
constitution will be or whether the settlement will be circumscribed to a
particular number or not nor what the Result of those other Restric-<barker_pb n="497"/>
tions will be all of which seams to defeat my expectations could
I do anything profitable I would stay untill I knew the Result but I
fear I shall be forced to Return home and there it may end as Relates
to myself and I fear it may prevent others as numbers of Respectable
<person_mentioned>citizens from <location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> would have moved to the country had or
could I give them encouragement should I not stay I wish to hear
from you particularly on the subject on your Return your Relatives
were well as were my own family when I left <location_mentioned>Missouri </location_mentioned>I recd both your
letters of <date_mentioned n="11-15-1821">Novr 15th </date_mentioned>from <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>with the Receipts and money by
<person_mentioned>Mr Honey</person_mentioned> which was a Timely Relief—I am without money and
your <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>has let me have his watch to Take me home the price
we will settle when we meat if ever—Colletts exn [execution] amts
to 229$ and whatever cost and interest may be on it hereafter -I have
paid <person_mentioned>Guyard </person_mentioned>290 dollars including the money you sent me 200$ which
is the whole amount I showed your <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>the papers he can Give
you all the information you may want on the subject as soon as you
can please give me Relief</p>
<p>Yours affectionately</p>

<p><person_mentioned>R C Bruffy</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Stephen. F. Austin Esqr</person_mentioned> care of <person_mentioned>Mr J. E. B. Austin</person_mentioned></p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
