
<TEI.2 id="APB1071">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-04-1825</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1065-1067</document_citation>
<document_language>Englsih</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F. Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Governor Rafael Gonzales</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F. Austin to Governor Rafael Gonzales, 04-04-1825</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>First contract for 300 families filled. Three hundred more anxious to come. Many petitions from Louisiana, 
Mississippi, and Alabama. Some already arrived, and some on the road. Has expelled some bad characters from the colony, and they have spread damaging reports about the colony. Government will not be deceived. Petition for permit to settle 500 additional families. Argument: (1) The 300 families already settled too weak for adequate defense against Indians—need reinforcements; (2) vacant lands between settlers in his colony should be distributed by himself to avoid conflicting claims; (3) if the port of Galveston is opened,
the settlers can not get full advantage from it without additional colonists;(4) the country can only be enriched by foreign trade, and must have more population in order to produce enough commerce to attract foreigners. Suggests that new settlers be allowed to bring slaves and keep them and their descendants as slaves. Otherwise the immigrants will be confined to the poorest class and development of the province will be much delayed.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Translation from Record of Empresario Contracts, 1825-1835, pp. 48-50. General Land Office of Texas.  There is a Spanish copy in Austin's Blotter, in file of Auguest 26, 1824.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1065-1067</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-02-2010</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB1071T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>First contract for 300 families filled. Three hundred more anxious to come. Many petitions from Louisiana, 
Mississippi, and Alabama. Some already arrived, and some on the road. Has expelled some bad characters from the colony, and they have spread damaging reports about the colony. Government will not be deceived. Petition for permit to settle 500 additional families. Argument: (1) The 300 families already settled too weak for adequate defense against Indians—need reinforcements; (2) vacant lands between settlers in his colony should be distributed by himself to avoid conflicting claims; (3) if the port of Galveston is opened,
the settlers can not get full advantage from it without additional colonists;(4) the country can only be enriched by foreign trade, and must have more population in order to produce enough commerce to attract foreigners. Suggests that new settlers be allowed to bring slaves and keep them and their descendants as slaves. Otherwise the immigrants will be confined to the poorest class and development of the province will be much delayed.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">
<p><person_mentioned>Citizen Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Lieut. Colonel of the National Militia</person_mentioned>,
of the <location_mentioned>river Brazos</location_mentioned> and <location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Judge ad interim for the administration of justice, and Empresario of this Colony</person_mentioned>.—Most 
respectfully represents to your <person_mentioned>Excellency</person_mentioned>, that:</p>
<p>having already completed the settlement of the three hundred<person_mentioned>
families</person_mentioned> which the <person_mentioned>Supreme Government of Mexico</person_mentioned> authorized me
to introduce into this <location_mentioned>Province of Texas</location_mentioned>. Application is made to
me daily to receive and settle more <person_mentioned>families</person_mentioned>, as <person_mentioned>colonists</person_mentioned>, some of
which have already arrived here, others are on the road, and have
written to me, besides a number amounting to nearly three 
hundred, who have applied to me from <location_mentioned>Louisiana</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Mississippi</location_mentioned>, and 
<location_mentioned>Alabama</location_mentioned>. The only reply I have made at present to them, is, that I
would make their applications known to the Supreme Government
of the State, Stating to them, that it is out of my power to grant
them license or permission to occupy or appropriate any land 
whatever, in the <location_mentioned>district</location_mentioned> under my charge, until the resolution of the
Government should be known. Among the applicants, are some
few of bad repute, these I have ordered to depart forthwith out
of the limits of this <location_mentioned>Jurisdiction</location_mentioned>; a measure of Executive Police
which circumstances required me to take, to preserve good order,
and tranquility among these worthy <person_mentioned>Colonists</person_mentioned>, in consequence of
which, that class of people are very much irritated against me, and<barker_pb n="1066"/>
under the excitement, disseminating infinite calumnies, and raising
false reports, relative to my conduct and authority; but I feel 
perfectly secure under the conviction, that the <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>, taking into
consideration the great injury which would result from the 
introduction of such <person_mentioned>characters</person_mentioned>, will approve the course I have pursued
in this instance; thereby preventing such <person_mentioned>persons </person_mentioned>from 
incommoding these <person_mentioned>Colonist</person_mentioned> hereafter; and at the same time, promote the
progress of this section of the State generally.—I request the
<person_mentioned>Supreme Government of the <location_mentioned>State of Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, in its
acknowledged goodness to authorize me to settle the additional 
number of five hundred<person_mentioned> families</person_mentioned> on the <location_mentioned>lands which remain vacant upon
the rivers San Jacinto, Brazos, and Colorado</location_mentioned>, and their <location_mentioned>tributaries</location_mentioned>,
and <location_mentioned>on the Island and Bay of Galveston</location_mentioned>, with full power to expel
from this jurisdiction, all <person_mentioned>persons </person_mentioned>of notoriously bad character,
who in future may immigrate hither. The arguments I offer in
support of this petition are:</p>

<p>1st—The number of <person_mentioned>three hundred families</person_mentioned> already legally settled
is very small to sustain itself against the Savage <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>, who 
surround us.</p>

<p>2nd—It is important that the settlement of the <location_mentioned>vacant lands </location_mentioned>
contiguous to, and adjoining those already distributed, should be effected
through the same <person_mentioned>Empresario</person_mentioned>, or <person_mentioned>authority </person_mentioned>who surveyed and 
distributed the lands to the present <person_mentioned>Colonists</person_mentioned>, in order to prevent all
clashing or dispute between the <person_mentioned> new and oldColonists</person_mentioned>, with regard
to their <location_mentioned>lines and boundaries</location_mentioned>; likewise, by these means, to form in
this <location_mentioned>town </location_mentioned>a general and minute Record of all the lands distributed
within this jurisdiction; a matter of the greatest importance in
 preventing hereafter, even the possibility of doubts, or disputes, in 
relation to titles.</p>

<p>3rd—Should the National <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned> make a <location_mentioned>port of entry</location_mentioned> of 
<location_mentioned>Galveston</location_mentioned>, the advantages of sales which would result therefrom, will
not be realized from it unless <person_mentioned>Colonists</person_mentioned> settle there, and in its 
immediate <location_mentioned>neighborhood</location_mentioned>, and inasmuch as I was the first who proposed
this matter to the <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>, I entreat the <person_mentioned>Government of the
State</person_mentioned> to do me the honor of effecting its settlement, and 
completing its establishment.</p>

<p>4th—Nothing but foreign commerce, particularly the exportation
of cotton to <location_mentioned>Europe</location_mentioned>, can enrich the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>of <location_mentioned>this section of the
State</location_mentioned>; and this cannot be expected without an increase of population,
and physical force; for without this, <person_mentioned>Capitalists</person_mentioned> will not undertake
to enter into it, with vessels of sufficient size, for <location_mentioned>European</location_mentioned> 
Commerce ; and to obtain these great benefits to the full extent that would
indubitably result to the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, by the enterprise and industry of<barker_pb n="1067"/>
these new <person_mentioned>colonists</person_mentioned>, it is in my opinion a matter of the greatest 
importance, to authorize the <person_mentioned>emigrants</person_mentioned> to bring in their <person_mentioned>Slaves</person_mentioned> and 
<person_mentioned>Servants</person_mentioned> ; and that the right of property in these <person_mentioned>servants</person_mentioned> so introduced,
as well as their <person_mentioned>descendants</person_mentioned>, be guaranteed to them by law; for 
with-out this security, we cannot expect <person_mentioned>colonists</person_mentioned> with large and 
competent means, nor can we have hands for the cultivation of Cotton
or Sugar; and consequently these <location_mentioned>fertile lands</location_mentioned>, instead of being
occupied by <person_mentioned>wealthy planters</person_mentioned>, will remain for many years, in the
hands of mere <person_mentioned>shepherds</person_mentioned>, or poor <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>, who will scarcely raise a
sufficiency for the sustenance of their <person_mentioned>families</person_mentioned>, without any 
over-plus of sufficient importance to give an impulse to active <location_mentioned>foreign </location_mentioned>
commerce.—Therefore, I pray the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>of the <location_mentioned>State of Coahuila
and Texas</location_mentioned>, to grant me authority to settle Five hundred <person_mentioned>families
</person_mentioned>more, at the places above mentioned.</p>
<p><location_mentioned>Town of San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned>,<date_mentioned n="04-04-1825"> 4th April 1825.</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Most Excellent Sir,</p> 
<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin.</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
