
<TEI.2 id="APB4975">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-21-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 201-202</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Philip Dimmitt</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Philip Dimmitt to Stephen F Austin, 10-21-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Fort Goliad, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Sending information derived from a Mexican from Bexar</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 201-202</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>05-23-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4975T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Sending information derived from a Mexican from Bexar</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Fort Goliad</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="10-21-1835">Oct. 21st 1835</date_mentioned></p>
<p>To <person_mentioned>Gen. S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<p>Sir,</p>

<p>This is dispatched to give you intelligence of the intended movements of
the <person_mentioned>Enemy</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>By information recd. from a <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-21-1835">early this morning</date_mentioned>, who says he
is only two days from <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>, we are informed that <person_mentioned>Cos </person_mentioned>is fortifying
rapidly—that <person_mentioned>500 men</person_mentioned> were to arrive there <date_mentioned n="10-21-1835">today </date_mentioned>from the <location_mentioned>interior</location_mentioned>; and
that, as soon as they should arrive, he intended sending a strong <person_mentioned>force</person_mentioned>
here, to retake this <location_mentioned>post</location_mentioned>. I inclose you intercepted letters on the same 
subject. They speak for themselves.</p>

<p>Our effective <person_mentioned>force </person_mentioned>is still <person_mentioned>50 men</person_mentioned>. By the <person_mentioned>express </person_mentioned>which left here 
<date_mentioned n="10-20-1835">yesterday morning</date_mentioned> for <location_mentioned>Head Quarters</location_mentioned>, I wrote to <person_mentioned>Capt. Alley</person_mentioned>, urging the 
necessity of his joining me with his <person_mentioned>command</person_mentioned>, as speedily as possible; but 30
odd hours have elapsed, and no answer, nor have I any reason to expect
one or to see him, unless he is ordered to return by the <person_mentioned>Gen</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>We have done all we could in the way of repairing arms, and are still
doing. About 50 pikes and bayonets are handled. All the breaches in the
outer wall are repaired, and the bastions will be done <date_mentioned n="10-22-1835">tomorrow</date_mentioned>.
Some of the <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>are sick—but all are in good spirits. But 50 men,
against an <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned>, in so large a field as this, leaves too many blanks, too
many points unprotected; in case of an attack by a <person_mentioned>large force</person_mentioned>, to promise
success. Your orders are solicited. They are expected. Of the little
band that entered this place on the <date_mentioned n="10-09-1835">night of the 9th., inst</date_mentioned>., many have 
returned <location_mentioned>home</location_mentioned>, and others say they will go in a few days. Inform me what
I shall do in this matter? How shall I keep the <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>together? Or, shall
I permit them to go and come as they please?</p>

<p>I will now add more fully to the above, of the information given by
the <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-21-1835">this morning</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>He says, all the <location_mentioned>squares of Bexar</location_mentioned> are fortified that works,are raised at
every angle for the effective use of their artillery.</p>

<p>I am decidedly of the opinion from all that I can learn, that the day is
gone by for the present when that place can be taken by storm without a
great and disheartening loss of valuable men. Starvation by siege, 
presents itself to my mind as the cheapest, most certain, and most efficient<barker_pb n="202"/>
mode of operating at that point under the present state of things allowing
my information to be correct.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>P. Dimitt </person_mentioned>[Rubric]</p>

<p>Commanding</p>

<p>P.S. Since writing the above, I have again conversed with the <person_mentioned>Mexican</person_mentioned>
above Spoken of—He says that he was sent <person_mentioned>ex</person_mentioned>. to <person_mentioned>Cos </person_mentioned>by <person_mentioned>Zenteno</person_mentioned>, with a
full statement of the force here and of every thing connected with our
situation. <person_mentioned>Cos</person_mentioned>, therefore, knows as well as we do, what ever was known
to the <person_mentioned>Collector</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] To <person_mentioned>Gen. Stephen F. Austin Com. in Ch. of the Army of
the People.</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
