
<TEI.2 id="APB4705">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-07-1834</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 32-35</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>James F. Perry</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>James F. Perry to Stephen F Austin, 12-07-1834</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Peach Point, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Local political movements in Texas. Austin's enemies</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>October 28, 1834, above.
For this movement to organize a state government, see Barker, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Stephen F. Austin</hi>, 468-469.
Ayuntimento of Brazoria to Congress, July 31, 1834. Omitted from this publication.
November 9, 1834, above.
See, Concerning Robertson's Colony, July 2, 1834, and Barker's <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>, Chapter XI.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 32-35</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>02-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4705T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Local political movements in Texas. Austin's enemies</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Peach Point</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="12-07-1834">7th Decr. 1834</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Dear <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned></p>

<p>We fondly hoped that long ere this we would have been enjoying your
society at <location_mentioned>home </location_mentioned>but from your letter of the <date_mentioned n="08-25-1834">25th Aug</date_mentioned>., one to <person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>of
the <date_mentioned n="09-07-1834">7th September</date_mentioned> also a letter recd from <person_mentioned>Mr. Grayson</person_mentioned> a few days after
his arrival in the <location_mentioned>city </location_mentioned>leaves everything in uncertainty, but still we hope
that ere this you have been released and you with our good <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Messrs
Grason</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Jack </person_mentioned>are on your return and will soon meet your numerous
<person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>once more in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. Who will meet you with unfained pleasure,
with regard to <person_mentioned>famaly </person_mentioned>matters, nothing new has occured since <person_mentioned>Mr. Grason</person_mentioned>
left. <person_mentioned>Emily </person_mentioned>has had the fever a great part of the time for the last season,
she has not had it for two weeks, and I hope will now enjoy her health
once more Now for political affairs, a short time before I recd your letter
of the <date_mentioned n="08-25-1834">25th August</date_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Henry Smith our Political Cheaf</person_mentioned> (he who had his head
graised at <location_mentioned>Velasco</location_mentioned>)—came out in our <location_mentioned>Brazoria paper</location_mentioned> with a very urgent
address to the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> recommending a convention and a <person_mentioned>state
Govt</person_mentioned> this address had hardly got dry from the press untill he recd from
<person_mentioned>Judge Chambers</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Oliver Jones</person_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>Bascas [Vasquez]</person_mentioned> the other member
of <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>for <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>a plan of calling a convention together with a request
from the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> for <person_mentioned>delegates </person_mentioned>to be elected in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to meet in
convention at <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>on <date_mentioned n="11-15-1834">15th Nov.</date_mentioned> a few days before the election an address<barker_pb n="33"/>
from the <person_mentioned>central committee</person_mentioned> in reply to the <person_mentioned>cheaf</person_mentioned>s first address came out
in hand bills which was in direct opposition to the opinions of the <person_mentioned>cheaf</person_mentioned>
which had its influence, and in fact the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>are heartily tired of high
handed and revolutionary measures and almost with one voice opposed
the measure in toto I have not heard of any elections being held anywhere
but within this <location_mentioned>jurisdiction </location_mentioned>and only in three <location_mentioned>electorial district</location_mentioned> here viz.
<location_mentioned>Brazoria </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>Columbia </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Velasco </location_mentioned>at <location_mentioned>Brazoria </location_mentioned>there was 57 against a 
convention and 16 for it at <location_mentioned>Columbia </location_mentioned>24 against and 23 for at <location_mentioned>Velasco </location_mentioned>there
was actually not more than from 7 to 10 legal votes to be given but at
the time of the election there was two or three vessels lying there with their
<person_mentioned>crews </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>passengers </person_mentioned>and to accomodate I supose <person_mentioned>Mr Wharton</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Dct
Archer</person_mentioned> they all went forward and voted for there <person_mentioned>candidate </person_mentioned>and I have
been told there was between 50 and 60 votes taken there when there was
not more than ten in the <location_mentioned>precinct </location_mentioned>but it all availed them nothing as they
were completely headed and broke down and so I hope they will remain.</p>

<p>Your letter of <date_mentioned n="11-25-1834">25th</date_mentioned> came to hand a very short time before this election
was to take place I showed it to <person_mentioned>McKinney</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Williams</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Bell </person_mentioned>and several
others of your <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>and they all concured in urging the publication of it
and accordingly it was, and has been widely circulated both in the paper
and handbills and all who I have conversed with it on the subject say they
think it has had and will have a good effect, the <person_mentioned>tryo </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Chambers </person_mentioned>and
<person_mentioned>Whartons </person_mentioned>are now as politically dead as if they were buried. <person_mentioned>Chambers</person_mentioned>
has been at <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned> but has not attemted to enter on his duties as a
<person_mentioned>judge </person_mentioned>I hear he has gone back to <location_mentioned>Monclova</location_mentioned>, he met with the coldest
kind of a cold reception in the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and I expect he was glad to get out
of it again. Since I commenced this I saw your letter of the <date_mentioned n="10-08-1834">18th Oct</date_mentioned> to
<person_mentioned>McKinney </person_mentioned>I am sorry you are so much deceived with regard to the
<person_mentioned>Whartons </person_mentioned>conduct towards you. you are more decieved than ever if you
think one of the <person_mentioned>tryo </person_mentioned>has the least good feeling toward you or that they
ever had. no it is far from their remotest thoughts I saw the paper that
<person_mentioned>Waller </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Wharton </person_mentioned>signed it was nothing but a statment of facts which
neither of them could or dare deny it was drawn up at the request of
<person_mentioned>McKinney </person_mentioned>and myself by <person_mentioned>W. H. Jack</person_mentioned> and their willingness to sign it was not
from any kind feelings towards you. their motives were widely different
they discovered that your cituation was causing a strong a very strong
excitement throughout the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Whartons</person_mentioned>, only motive
was to go with the current to gain popularity and to check the warm<barker_pb n="34"/>
excitement felt on your a/c at the same time he was taking every 
opportunity to caluminate and abuse you all this we knew when we got him to
sign the memorial but never dreamt that you could be deceived by such a
manuever <person_mentioned>Spencer Jack</person_mentioned> knew his motives he can inform you. None of
your conciliatory centiments towards such fellows shall ever be published
by [me] nor will they by <person_mentioned>McKinney </person_mentioned>on this subject I know his centiments
these fellows are not deserving of an[y] friendly sentiment from yourself
and I hope may never make another advance towards a reconciliation I
dont wish to quarl with but hold them at a distance as you would tainted
meat they are not deserving of confidence or one good feeling from you
or those who are your sincere well wishers these are my opinions I have
always thought that I was of as forgiving a disposition [as] any person
ought to be but a man or set of men who would persecute me as they
have you I never could meet them on terms of friendship. <person_mentioned>W. H. Wharton</person_mentioned>
took great offense at your letter and came out in a very violent card
against you but I believe before he got them printed he got ashamed of it
himself and tryed to suppress it a few of the proof sheets got out and I
am told his best friends decountenance it.</p>

<p>There is a great reaction in public opinion since you left crops throught
[throughout] the <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>has been very good this season (with the 
exception of this imediate <location_mentioned>neighbourhood </location_mentioned>our crops here was about ruined with
the worm not more than a third made) everything is prospering a 
considerable emigration is coming in both by land and water and the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>
apear well contented without any more conventions. <person_mentioned>McKinney </person_mentioned>is now in
<location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> of which I expect he has informed me. he is a man of entire
worth <person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>says he is going to <location_mentioned>Montclova </location_mentioned>very soon I have not
offered any of your land for sale as I have not seen any necessity for
selling there was a small claim against you which was pressed but 
<person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>with a little aid I gave him has settled it so he informs me. <person_mentioned>Sterling
C. Robinson</person_mentioned> is cavolting about in the <location_mentioned>upper colony</location_mentioned> at a great rate he is
taring up all that was done by <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Williams</person_mentioned>, he will hardly let the
hills and rivers stand that they happened to have crossed with a chain.
While <person_mentioned>Chambers </person_mentioned>was up the country he wrote an expose for <location_mentioned>Robinson</location_mentioned>
which has been published in which he makes heavy charges against you—
but all these things are now prety generally understood and if <person_mentioned>Williams</person_mentioned>
goes on and has that business straightened all these assertions will go back
on themselves writh double force</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Capt Henry Austins family</person_mentioned> was all well a few days since, he gets along
but badly in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. I had a letter from <person_mentioned>Mr. Learning</person_mentioned> a few days since
he says the <person_mentioned>Fox </person_mentioned>suit is still <location_mentioned>in court</location_mentioned> and hopes it will come to an ishue this<barker_pb n="35"/>
<date_mentioned n="12-xx-1834">month </date_mentioned>he sent you a new <location_mentioned>map </location_mentioned>of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>a second edition of the one you
furnished he had heard you had got <location_mentioned>home </location_mentioned>and wishes you to write to him
What was the situation of your a/c with <person_mentioned>Jno Austin</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Wm T. Austin</person_mentioned> as
adm.r of his <person_mentioned>Brother </person_mentioned>has been selling notes which was in his brothers
possession of yours one I know of against <person_mentioned>Thomas Westall</person_mentioned> for 611$ this
I presume was only logd with <person_mentioned>John </person_mentioned>for collection if so it ought not to be
paid to the <person_mentioned>assignee of his admr</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>[James F. Perry]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
