
<TEI.2 id="APB4962">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-18-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 191-192</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>R R Royall</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>R R Royall to Stephen F Austin, 10-18-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Activities of the permanent council. Rangers. Negotiations with Indians. Supplies and reinforcements</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 191-192</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>04-04-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4962T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Activities of the permanent council. Rangers. Negotiations with Indians. Supplies and reinforcements</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="10-18-1835">18th October 1835 (Sunday</date_mentioned>)</p>
<p><person_mentioned>Genl Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>Some <person_mentioned>members </person_mentioned>have been aded to day to our <person_mentioned>Council </person_mentioned>by late Arrivals
to the <person_mentioned>Consultation </person_mentioned>and some have obtained leave of absence. Our <person_mentioned>Present
Members</person_mentioned> are about 16.</p>

<p>We have taken upon us in the present times (Pregnant as they are with
Emergencies) some Responsibilities, <person_mentioned>agents from the <location_mentioned>upper settlements</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>,
have arrived and we have dispatched them with Commissions, and 
Instructions, to three <person_mentioned>Captains </person_mentioned>one to act as <person_mentioned>Ranger </person_mentioned>with <person_mentioned>ten men <location_mentioned>east of Trinity
</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>one with <person_mentioned>25 <location_mentioned>between the Brazos and Trinity</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and one with <person_mentioned>25 <location_mentioned>between the
Colorado and Brazos</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> offering $1.25 pr day to each <person_mentioned>Ranger </person_mentioned>till Otherwise
Provided by the <person_mentioned>Consultation</person_mentioned>. We will dispatch to <location_mentioned>N.</location_mentioned> and <location_mentioned>Ayish Bayou
</location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-19-1835">tomorrow </date_mentioned>a delegation to, the <person_mentioned>Chiefs of the Indians</person_mentioned> and the <person_mentioned>American 
setters</person_mentioned> with <location_mentioned>Circulars </location_mentioned>Printed for their Information and signed by the whole
<person_mentioned>House</person_mentioned>, in these we declare an opposition to the Great land speculation etc.
tell them our true situation and urge them to turn out. On the part of the
<person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>we Delegate to our <person_mentioned>Commissioners </person_mentioned>the Power to council with them
and give Pledges of the Public faith to Respect their rights to <location_mentioned>land </location_mentioned>with
assurances, that the <person_mentioned>convention </person_mentioned>will conform. This I am confident is at
least as far as was Intended to be delegated to us, but the times seem to
require it, as to the part the <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>will act the <person_mentioned>Com.</person_mentioned> are Instructed to 
assertain and be Governed by Circumstances, we hear Rumours here of there
being only <person_mentioned>40 men</person_mentioned> coming from that <location_mentioned>Quarter </location_mentioned>and of threats from the 
<person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>but it is only Rumour The <person_mentioned>Chiefs</person_mentioned> have not arrived nor are they
heard of. I have been urged to go myself But I believe it will be over
ruled as I think is best, and <person_mentioned>Esqr. Garrett of the <location_mentioned>Red Lands</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Mr Hood</person_mentioned> and
<person_mentioned>Mr Menard</person_mentioned> will be apointed it will be disposed of this <date_mentioned n="10-18-1835">evening</date_mentioned>, the
cannon is here and perhaps <date_mentioned n="10-17-1835">tomorrow </date_mentioned>we will be able to get two yoke of
Oxen to take it on <person_mentioned>Capt Wm. Hall</person_mentioned> left <date_mentioned n="10-18-1835">today </date_mentioned>to go to <location_mentioned>Gonzales </location_mentioned>or 
<location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>to forward corn Meal to <location_mentioned>head quarters</location_mentioned>. You should I think be more
full about supplies for a long time and say how much—<person_mentioned>Members from
Cow Bayou and that Quarter</person_mentioned> say there will be <person_mentioned>40 men</person_mentioned> from that way 
<date_mentioned n="10-18-1835">tonight </date_mentioned>or in a few days. On the subject I wrote you relative to <person_mentioned>Jno 
Williams</person_mentioned> I would think—on reflecting more, had best be well matured before
we act and the present press for .men and uncertainty every where of 
Immediate success it may be best not to proceed as I proposd or not till the
<person_mentioned>convention </person_mentioned>meets but be that with you.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Prisioners </person_mentioned>are here and I think it Doubtfull yet whether the 
<person_mentioned>Council </person_mentioned>will consent to the <person_mentioned>Captains </person_mentioned>release unless by request of <person_mentioned>Capt Collins-<barker_pb n="192"/>
worth</person_mentioned> as they say he would be reasonably, mortified and that If they get
liberty and the like occur On us we can not effect an Exchange but would
be Imprisoned. They have the liberty of the <location_mentioned>town</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>If you still desire it please write again or a word from <person_mentioned>Capt C.</person_mentioned> or your
statement of his,wish, the subject will be submitted <date_mentioned n="10-19-1835">tomorrow </date_mentioned>to the <person_mentioned>house</person_mentioned>.
<person_mentioned>R. R. Royall President of Council</person_mentioned></p>

<p><date_mentioned n="10-19-1835">19th Octr 1835</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Some <person_mentioned>troops </person_mentioned>have arrived from the <location_mentioned>Trinity </location_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Col Pettus</person_mentioned> says, he will
be able to forward the cannon to day. 5 Wagons have been dispatched
from <location_mentioned>Columbia </location_mentioned>and 2 from here with provisions Arms and Amunition
under charge of <person_mentioned>Geo. Huff</person_mentioned> with a <person_mentioned>Guard of 10 men</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Genl Briscoe</person_mentioned> has 
arrived from <location_mentioned>Mississippi </location_mentioned>Via <location_mentioned>Nacog</location_mentioned>. he says he counted <person_mentioned>80 men leaving
<location_mentioned>Nacog</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. but <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>Generally said 150 as also <person_mentioned>John Dust</person_mentioned> stated the same.
<person_mentioned>Esqr Garrett</person_mentioned> thinks he will be abble to turn out more of this you can be
informed by <person_mentioned>Gentlemen from that <location_mentioned>Quarter</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> who know him and his 
associates <person_mentioned>Hood </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Menard </person_mentioned>they are alive to the cause and will do their
Best. <person_mentioned>Genl Briscoe</person_mentioned> States that <person_mentioned>Jno Dust</person_mentioned> said he had talked with the
<person_mentioned>Cherokees </person_mentioned>and other <person_mentioned>associate tribes</person_mentioned> and they Intended to be neutral also
that his opinion was that If we were Vanquished they would turn against
us. that at Present some of their <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>are gone out Hunting appearing
Entirely Indifferent. It will be one or two days before our <person_mentioned>Commissioners</person_mentioned>
can leave on act. of not being able to get the Printing done sooner, since
my last a few days ago I find the <person_mentioned>members </person_mentioned>here by being kept Buisy are
More Contented and will Probably continue so and depart only with leave
till those in the army may find it advisable to return. But I think it will
be necessary for you to state the wish of those in camp how far we may
consistently with their Views go in matters necessary to the forwarding of
our Views to cause protection of the <person_mentioned>Army </person_mentioned>and security of the <location_mentioned>frontier</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>R. R. Royall</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Some days since I wrote to <location_mentioned>Matagorda </location_mentioned>to <person_mentioned>Fisher the Present Chairman
of Com.</person_mentioned> to forward 10 sacks coffee some shugar 5 Sacks salt and what
Powder they could spare from the place—I hope he will attend to it.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>R. R. R.</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
