
<TEI.2 id="APB4958">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-16-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 188-189</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>R R Royall</document_author>
<document_sender>Major Whiting</document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>R R Royall to Stephen F Austin, 10-16-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Head quarters, Texas Volunteers, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Necessity of arresting John A. Williams with company of 58 to aid the enemy. Lacks authority</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 188-189</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>04-04-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4958T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Necessity of arresting John A. Williams with company of 58 to aid the enemy. Lacks authority</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>San. Felipe</location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-16-1835"> 16th 1835</date_mentioned>—</p>
<p><person_mentioned>Col S F Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>For a long time there has been a great many things spoken of
Th[r]oughout our <location_mentioned>community </location_mentioned>about One <person_mentioned>John A Williams (Judge 
Williams)</person_mentioned> as having taken a very active Part against the Acts of the <person_mentioned>Colonists</person_mentioned>
and advocating the measures persued by the <person_mentioned>Mexican Government</person_mentioned>, for a
long time I thought from report (for I dont know the man) his oposition
arose from misconceived Ideas But it has been Impressed upon the 
<person_mentioned>Council </person_mentioned>and Particularly today that his conduct deserved the attention of that<barker_pb n="189"/>
Body and that he has arrayed himself with <person_mentioned>58 followers</person_mentioned> already enrolled
against out military movements and with a View of offering facilities to the
<person_mentioned>Enemy </person_mentioned>with whoom he is in Regular Correspondence—having Prepared a
Boat for the accomodation etc. Now from these facts coming from so 
respectable an authority the <person_mentioned>Council </person_mentioned>in secret session with <person_mentioned>Henry Smith Esqr</person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>John D. Newell</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Wm- P Harris</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Saml Whiting</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Mr Menifee</person_mentioned> 01 have thought the circumstances would Justify an
Immediate arrest and the safe keeping of said <person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>till he should be
tried and Disposed of by a proper tribunal. But considering the Delicate
situation of this <person_mentioned>Council </person_mentioned>being Representatives from a <location_mentioned>minority of the 
municipalities </location_mentioned>only Have recommended that the <person_mentioned>commander in chief</person_mentioned> associated
with his <person_mentioned>staff </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>confidential officers</person_mentioned> Invite those <person_mentioned>members </person_mentioned>acquainted
with the circumstances and Ishue their request or Order to this Body for
their complyance.</p>

<p>I cannot see but such a proceeding is consistant in times like these when
we are surrounded by Warr and our <person_mentioned>Citizens </person_mentioned>are afraid to leave their
<location_mentioned>Homes </location_mentioned>lest their <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>be destroyed by the means and facilities afforded
by those within our own Bosom it is times of Warr and military rules
must Prevail in some Extent till otherwise Provided. If you advise 
anything to be done in this matter it is necessary to be done with secrecy and
Dispatch—If you come to any conclusion of active measures in this matter
please dispatch it by <person_mentioned>Express </person_mentioned>and it is well to have the names associated
with you signed to the Order and for the Execution of the Order I 
particularly recommend <person_mentioned>Majr Whiting</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>R. R. Royall Presdt</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] Private <person_mentioned>Col. S. F. Austin</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Head Quarters Texas</person_mentioned> 
<person_mentioned>Volunteers </person_mentioned>favr by <person_mentioned>Majr Whiting</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
