
<TEI.2 id="APB4854">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>08-23-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 105-107</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Public</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>D. C. Barrett</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Citizens of Mina</document_recipient>
<document_title>D. C. Barrett to Citizens of Mina, 08-23-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Antonio, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Political advice. Means of reconciliation with Mexico</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Barrett with Gritten had undertaken a mission to General Cos at Matamoras to
try to convince him that the Texans were peaceably inclined. They were stopped at
San Antonio by Colonel Ugartechea, who declared that Cos would not listen to them
until the colonists surrendered the leaders of the war party. During Barrett's absence
from Bastrop on this mission the alcalde granted an attachment against some of his
property to satisfy a judgment of $100. Several pages of protest by Barrett are
omitted.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 105-107</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>03-11-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4854T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Political advice. Means of reconciliation with Mexico</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><date_mentioned n="08-23-1835">August 23 1835</date_mentioned></p>
<p>To the <person_mentioned>Citizens of <location_mentioned>Mina</location_mentioned></person_mentioned></p>
<p>When at the call of the <person_mentioned>Political Chief</person_mentioned>, by and with the advice of his
<person_mentioned>counsel</person_mentioned>, then in session, I submitted to undertake a hazardous Mission in
behalf of my <location_mentioned>adopted Country</location_mentioned>. I did not give a full consent, until I had
consulted your "<person_mentioned>Committee of Safety</person_mentioned>" and obtained their approbation. . . . </p>

<p>I wish now to give you a brief account of the occurrences connected with
my public duties since the letters of <person_mentioned>Mr. Gritten</person_mentioned> and myself by Messrs.
<person_mentioned>Drown </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Turner</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>United States Government [of Mexico]</person_mentioned> have through their <person_mentioned>officers
at <location_mentioned>Matamoras </location_mentioned>and<location_mentioned> this place</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, fully recognized the objects of the Mission,
and the public character of your <person_mentioned>agents</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p><date_mentioned n="08-23-1835">Augt. 25 1835</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I have just heard from <person_mentioned>Mr. Gritten</person_mentioned> by <person_mentioned>express</person_mentioned>, he is at <location_mentioned>Goliad</location_mentioned>, where
he expected to have met me, on this day, several late communications<barker_pb n="106"/>
from the <person_mentioned>supreme Government</person_mentioned>, through <person_mentioned>Genl. Cos</person_mentioned>, demanding certain 
persons, in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, <hi rend="italic">especially <person_mentioned>Mr Zavalla</person_mentioned></hi>, of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, whose surrender, or 
positive evidence, of his not being in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, is made a "sine que non" to all
further negotiations, and I regret to say, that the next upon the list 
demanded is<hi rend="italic"> <person_mentioned>W. B. Travis Esq</person_mentioned>,</hi> the next in order are <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Robt M Williamson</person_mentioned></hi>
and <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Mosely Bakqr Esqs</person_mentioned></hi>.- together with the individuals concerned in "abusing"
the <person_mentioned>Government Messengers</person_mentioned>, and "Violating" their dispatches the next
in order demanded, is <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>S M Williams </person_mentioned></hi>Esq. and <person_mentioned>Judge Johnson</person_mentioned>, All the
<person_mentioned>North Americans</person_mentioned> above named, were <hi rend="italic">first </hi>demanded by the <person_mentioned>Comdt </person_mentioned>here
in a letter sent <hi rend="italic">here </hi>from "<location_mentioned>San Felepe</location_mentioned>", signed <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>J H. C Miller</person_mentioned></hi> urging the
prompt demand of these individuals, <person_mentioned>Co. U [Ugartechea] </person_mentioned>in consequence
of such pressing advice, anticipated the order which should have <hi rend="italic">originated</hi>
from <person_mentioned>Genl. Cos,</person_mentioned> to<person_mentioned> Col U</person_mentioned> promptly communicated this act to<person_mentioned> Genl. Cos</person_mentioned>,
asking his <hi rend="italic">approbation </hi>which he as <hi rend="italic">promptly </hi>received. The worst features
in this, to me painful state of things, have arisen <hi rend="italic">since </hi><person_mentioned>Mr. Gritten</person_mentioned> <hi rend="italic">left </hi>here,
especially the <hi rend="italic">"sine qua non"</hi> or condition precedent to all pacific 
negotiations, between <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>, also the positive order from
the <person_mentioned>Supreme Government</person_mentioned> to <person_mentioned>Col U</person_mentioned>, on <hi rend="italic">non compliance</hi>, forthwith to march
with <hi rend="italic">all </hi>his <person_mentioned>cavalry</person_mentioned>, into <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and in this way execute the order himself,
a reply to this demand is hourly expected, by <person_mentioned>express</person_mentioned>, from <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned>,
I have therefore, with the advice of <hi rend="italic">our </hi><person_mentioned>American friends </person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">here</hi>, in which
<person_mentioned>Col. U</person_mentioned>. decidedly concured. concluded to send for my colleague <person_mentioned>Mr. Gritten</person_mentioned>,
without whose knowledge and assistance I cannot advance, a step further.
Copies of <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the correspondance of your <person_mentioned>commissioners</person_mentioned>, have been and
will be, faithfully preserved. This will prove that in all our negotiations
for <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, we have been governed by <hi rend="italic">prudence </hi>and an unchangeable regard
for the honor and justice of her <person_mentioned>citizens</person_mentioned>. Upon this subject, our last letter,
the knowledge of <person_mentioned>Mr. Drown</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Mr. Turner</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Mr- Pease</person_mentioned> will fully satisfy
you. I will here add, that I am firmly of opinion, that if the mission be
persevered in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>will receive a speedy modification of the tariff, and
a new <location_mentioned>Post Office</location_mentioned> organization, in this opinion I am sustained, by the
most respectable and intelligent people here. I should <hi rend="italic">now </hi>return to <location_mentioned>Mina</location_mentioned>
but for the strong advice of our <person_mentioned>American friends</person_mentioned> here, <hi rend="italic">not </hi>to do so at
present.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Judge Hood</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Mr. Milton</person_mentioned> have been with me, for a number of days,
and will be able to give you many interesting details. I have received much
support from the <person_mentioned>Judge </person_mentioned>in all matters of public concernment.</p>

<p>Again the want of <person_mentioned>commissioners </person_mentioned>for making titles for <location_mentioned>lands</location_mentioned>, to 
unprovided <person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>is severely felt. The law passed upon this subject last
<date_mentioned n="Spring-1834">spring</date_mentioned>, has made the most ample and liberal provision in these cases. No
<person_mentioned>commissioner </person_mentioned>has ever been appointed under this law. I have procured
copies of this and several laws unknown in our municipality yet very 
important to <person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>land holders</person_mentioned>. These laws among other provisions,<barker_pb n="107"/>
provide for the appointment of a <person_mentioned>commissioner </person_mentioned>in each <location_mentioned>department of Texas</location_mentioned>.
The present <person_mentioned>Governor </person_mentioned>will appoint them on application from 
<person_mentioned>Ayuntamientos</person_mentioned>, through the <person_mentioned>Political chief</person_mentioned>, or your <person_mentioned>commissioners</person_mentioned>, of this I have
ample assurances. Who would be suitable men for these <person_mentioned>officers</person_mentioned>? I will
venture to <hi rend="italic">suggest </hi>my <hi rend="italic">own </hi>opinion, of two unexceptionable men, well 
qualified, unconnected with <person_mentioned>Texas parties</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Mr. Padilla </person_mentioned>well known as a 
republican and an honorable man. The other my friend and colleague <person_mentioned>Edward
Gritten Esq</person_mentioned>. whose good report among you, too recent, to require any
remark from me. These gentlemen are <hi rend="italic">both </hi>intimate <person_mentioned>friends of the acting
Governor</person_mentioned>, who will only wish to know that they will be approved of in
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, when he will promptly appoint them, for the two departments, I
am but <hi rend="italic">one </hi>in the matter, shall therefore leave the subject to the <person_mentioned>People</person_mentioned>.
It may be proper to add, that <person_mentioned>Mr. Padilla</person_mentioned> I have consulted, <person_mentioned>Mr. Gritten</person_mentioned>
I have not. <person_mentioned>Mr. Padilla</person_mentioned> is too honest to be rich, and too poor to support
himself and <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>, without some productive employment,—and as he
wishes some pretext to take himself and <person_mentioned>family </person_mentioned>to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>forever, he will if
the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>approve gladly accept the office. He desires his best respects
to the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Mina</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> generally, and <hi rend="italic">especially </hi>his gratitude to <person_mentioned>Capt. Sims</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>Capt. Moore</person_mentioned> for past acts of friendship. I am happy to be sustained
in my opinion by the highest <person_mentioned>legal authorities</person_mentioned> in the country, that the
law intending to affect the contracts of <person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>or <person_mentioned>Williamson</person_mentioned>, in the
settlemant of their <location_mentioned>colonies</location_mentioned>, is ineffectual in its operation For the sake
of my good old friend <person_mentioned>Col Chambers</person_mentioned> I rejoice that I am able to give this
statement. . . .</p>

<p><person_mentioned>D C Barrett </person_mentioned>[Rubric]</p>

<p><location_mentioned>San Antonio</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="08-28-1835">28th 1835.</date_mentioned></p>

<p>P. S.</p>

<p>It is said that a plan for the consti[tu]tion of a <person_mentioned>central Government</person_mentioned> has
been got up, and is now debating. Should any thing certain be made
known, <hi rend="italic">you </hi>will be apprised of it as speedily as possible</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
