
<TEI.2 id="APB4907">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-04-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 153-156</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Domingo de Ugartechea</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Domingo de Ugartechea to Stephen F Austin, 10-04-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Bexar, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Urging him to use his influence to quiet the colonists and induce them to surrender the cannon at Gonzales </barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From Lamar Papers, Texas State Library.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 153-156</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>03-24-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4907T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Urging him to use his influence to- quiet the colonists and induce them to surrender the cannon at Gonzales </p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-04-1835">4th Oct 1835</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin Esqr</person_mentioned>-</p>
<p>My worthy friend,</p>

<p>I have just received your letter of the <date_mentioned n="09-15-1835">15th ult</date_mentioned>. and am glad to learn your
happy arrival at <location_mentioned>S Felipe</location_mentioned>; the more so, as I believe that your presence,
and the direct influence, which as a good <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>you should exercise in
the affairs of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, will cause them to be managed with the skill and 
circumspection required by the present delicate circumstances, which have
been rendered important by the excitements of the <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>of order, whose
proceedings with which I believe you are well acquainted, have induced
the <person_mentioned>supreme Government</person_mentioned>, who abounds in resources, to adopt measures fit
to procure a permanent and firm peace in that interesting <location_mentioned>part of the 
Republic</location_mentioned>, without leaving unfinished— crimes and abominations. In the
understanding therefore that you are well acquainted with the events that
have happened previous to your arrival. I shall only give a sketch of the
principal ones, that you may be convinced of the necessity and justice of
the measures which have caused so much alarm and given rise to sinister
interpretations.</p>

<p>You cannot be ignorant of the outrage committed at <location_mentioned>Anahuac </location_mentioned>against
the <person_mentioned>detachment </person_mentioned>placed there under the orders of <person_mentioned>Capt. Antonio Tenorio</person_mentioned>, of<barker_pb n="154"/>
which the <person_mentioned>force </person_mentioned>was so small as to be barely sufficient to fulfil its object of
preventing the smuggling, which to the notorious prejudice of the national
revenue and with such frequency was carrying on at <location_mentioned>Galveston </location_mentioned>measures
which ought not to have caused the <person_mentioned>Colonist </person_mentioned>to entertain apprehensions of
another nature. Neither can you be ignorant that when the <person_mentioned>State 
Legislature</person_mentioned> was dissolved, those who are discontented with the <person_mentioned>present 
Government</person_mentioned>, or rather, the <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>interested in the Decree for alienating <location_mentioned>400
leagues of Texas</location_mentioned>, proceeded to the <location_mentioned>interior (Texas)</location_mentioned> there propagating
alarming reports for the purpose of kindling the torch of discord and in
a direct manner bringing about in <location_mentioned>San Felipe </location_mentioned>[rebellion] against public
faith and all right, the intercepting opening and publishing of the official
and very confidential correspondence addressed to said Capt. Tenorio,
after having arrested, molested outraging the <person_mentioned>soldiers </person_mentioned>who were the <person_mentioned>bearers</person_mentioned>.
If such proceeding were to remain unpunished, it would be believed that
the <location_mentioned>Mexican Nation</location_mentioned> is unjust, or perhaps that she wanted force and energy
sufficient to make herself respected. She therefore considered herself in
the necessity of proving the contrary and of adopting with regard to the
<person_mentioned>delinquents </person_mentioned>and only with regard to them, measures, which by no means
made connexion with the good and peaceable <person_mentioned>inhabitants of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. This
has been repeatedly manifested to them by myself and the <person_mentioned>Commandant
General</person_mentioned> to the <person_mentioned>political Chiefs of <location_mentioned>Nacogdoches </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Brazos</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> although 
unhappily without effect, on the contrary it appears that such manifestations
have been viewed with contempt, without viewing the <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>are 
patient of suffering, but valient, full of honor and capable of making their
<person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>be respected then the <person_mentioned>Commandant General</person_mentioned> suspended the
march of <person_mentioned>troops </person_mentioned>in order to do away with apprehension and show that he
had no distrust of the good sentiments of the <person_mentioned>Colonists </person_mentioned>provided the 
<person_mentioned>delinquents </person_mentioned>were delivered up for trials by the <person_mentioned>competent authority</person_mentioned>, fresh 
motive occurs for supposing that there exists strong intention of provoking a
disastrous war, which it is important in time to prevent. When the 
<person_mentioned>authorities of <location_mentioned>Gonzales</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> were repulsed by this <person_mentioned>Political Chief</person_mentioned> to deliver the piece
of artillery lying there, as it had been lent to the "<person_mentioned>empresario</person_mentioned>" of that
<location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>by my <person_mentioned>predecessor </person_mentioned>and it belongs to this <location_mentioned>military jurisdiction</location_mentioned>,
those <person_mentioned>authorities </person_mentioned>not only refuse to deliver it up but say they will give it
up to force only. Such conduct placed me under the necessity of sending
a <person_mentioned>party of 100 men</person_mentioned> to exact their delivery and I gave orders to the 
<person_mentioned>Commander </person_mentioned>to send a new communication to the <person_mentioned>Alcalde of <location_mentioned>Gonzales</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, 
manifesting to him the injustice of wishing to detain an article which does not
belong to that <location_mentioned>municipality</location_mentioned>, and that if against expectation he did not 
deliver up the gun, the said <person_mentioned>commandant </person_mentioned>was then to employ force, Either
from fear or malice, the <person_mentioned>Alcalde of <location_mentioned>Gonzales</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> aware that it was an outrage
to arrest the <person_mentioned>corporal </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>soldiers </person_mentioned>who were the first <person_mentioned>bearers </person_mentioned>of the 
communication from the <person_mentioned>political Chief</person_mentioned>, caused the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>residing on<barker_pb n="155"/>
<location_mentioned>this side of the river</location_mentioned> to leave their <location_mentioned>houses</location_mentioned>, allarmed the <person_mentioned>Citizens </person_mentioned>and in
order to impede the passage of the <person_mentioned>troops </person_mentioned>withdrew to the <location_mentioned>other side the
ferry</location_mentioned> in canoes, so that when the <person_mentioned>commander of the party</person_mentioned> arrived <location_mentioned>on the
banks of the river</location_mentioned> he was met by that obstacal, Notwithstanding which,
he solicited an interview—with the <person_mentioned>Alcalde </person_mentioned>but in vain altho he was 
informed that within three hours he would come, not being in <location_mentioned>town</location_mentioned>, when
that time expired the next <person_mentioned>Regidor </person_mentioned>made his appearance and made known
that he had to consult with the <person_mentioned>Political Chief of the <location_mentioned>Brazos</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and without
his sanction he could not, nor would not deliver up the cannon, I was
informed of this occurrence and then ordered the <person_mentioned>commandant of the party
</person_mentioned>to withdraw, in the belief that on the <person_mentioned>political Chiefs</person_mentioned> answer the gun would
be delivered up, so far from that however, the <person_mentioned>inhabitants of the <location_mentioned>town</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> 
acting on the wrong belief that the <person_mentioned>troops </person_mentioned>retired thro fear came out, pass the
<location_mentioned>river </location_mentioned>and committing the outrage of attacking the <person_mentioned>party </person_mentioned>and intimating
surrender to the <person_mentioned>Commandant</person_mentioned>. A report was made to me of that event and
that besides the <person_mentioned>Citizens of <location_mentioned>Gonzales</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>300 men from <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> had collected
and as I did not wish to see that small <person_mentioned>force </person_mentioned>compromitted, I ordered it to
withdraw, and shall march <date_mentioned n="10-05-1835">tomorrow</date_mentioned>
 with the knowledge of the 
<person_mentioned>Commandant General</person_mentioned> with a force of every discription of arms, sufficient to
prove that the <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>can never suffer themselves to be insulted.</p>

<p>There are in the <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>some <person_mentioned>individuals</person_mentioned>, who, like yourself know me
to be frank in my proceedings, and also that I possess the character and
energy characteristic of my <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. I may therefore assure you that if
you make use of your influence with the <person_mentioned>political Chief</person_mentioned> to have the gun
delivered up to me, wherever it may meet me, from that spot I will return
immediately, if not I will act militarily and the consequence will be a war
declared by the <person_mentioned>Colonists</person_mentioned>, which shall be maintained by the <person_mentioned>Government
of the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> with corresponding dignity.</p>

<p>I know you are right to complain of <person_mentioned>Thompson</person_mentioned>s proceedings, which I
do not approve much less as they are arbitrary, and having no authority
for acting in such a manner but some sacrifice is requisite in favor of
peace, which, if it disappear from <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, will be caused only by the
oposition of the <person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>to what is just, and I am convinced of your good
sentiments in favor of your <location_mentioned>adopted Country</location_mentioned>, notwithstanding your 
sufferings and have not doubt that in favour of this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>you will continue
to make fresh sacrifices and cooperate effectually in removing the evils
which threaten, for which important purpose you may rec[k]on upon me
for the use of my influence with the <person_mentioned>Supreme Government</person_mentioned> and with the
<person_mentioned>Commandant General</person_mentioned>, and I can assure you if peace should be sincerely
established and unalterably so, the introduction of <person_mentioned>troops </person_mentioned>into those 
<location_mentioned>departments </location_mentioned>will be dispensed with,</p>

<p>I am your <person_mentioned>friend </person_mentioned>likewise a <person_mentioned>friend </person_mentioned>to the <person_mentioned>Colonist</person_mentioned>, if I have been 
sometimes obliged to fight with them, it was an absolute fulfilment of my duty,<barker_pb n="156"/>
but in personalities I have always treated them like a Gentleman, both
before and after fighting with them, I have observed the same conduct
with as many as have entered into this city, where they still remain, 
notwithstanding they have not behaved well in <location_mentioned>Gonzales </location_mentioned>towards the
<person_mentioned>Mexicans</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>In a P. S. to your letter which I now answer you say you enclose a
paper, which I have not received, I know that the said paper is in 
<location_mentioned>circulation </location_mentioned>in your <location_mentioned>department</location_mentioned>, and that in it you strongly recommend peace
and due gratitude to the <person_mentioned>Supreme Government</person_mentioned> avail yourself of some
opportunity for forwarding it to me and in the mean while</p>

<p>I remain your attached Friend etc</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Domingo de Ugartechea</person_mentioned></p>

<p>A true copy of the original, which I certify <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-04-1835">4th Oct 1835</date_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
