
<TEI.2 id="APB4912">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-04-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 159-160</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Unknown</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Unknown, 10-04-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Committee Room, San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Austin recommends establishment of Post Office Department.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 159-160</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>03-25-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4912T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Austin recommends establishment of Post Office Department.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>During the present interesting period in the affairs of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, it is very
evident that <location_mentioned>facility of communication</location_mentioned> between the different sections of the
country is all important; indeed it is always so, but at this time the best
interest of the cause of the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>clearly requires, that there should be a
regular mail between <location_mentioned>this country</location_mentioned> and the <location_mentioned>United States frontier</location_mentioned>, by way of
<location_mentioned>Harrisburg</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Liberty </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Nacogdoches</location_mentioned>, as well for the purpose of 
communication with the <person_mentioned>people of the latter places</person_mentioned>, as also for that of 
informing our <person_mentioned>friends and brethren in the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, of the interesting events
now passing in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—events which can not fail to enlist the moral and
physical aid of the free and magnanimous of <location_mentioned>all nations</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Mail routes to <location_mentioned>Velasco</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Matagorda</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Bastrop</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Gonzales </location_mentioned>and
other places are equally important, and are also recommended to be 
established as soon as the funds of the <person_mentioned>department </person_mentioned>will be sufficient to defray
the expenses.</p>

<p>Animated by these considerations of public good, the <person_mentioned>committee of 
Vigilence of <location_mentioned>Austin</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> recommend.</p>

<p>1st. The establishment of a <person_mentioned>provisional post Office department</person_mentioned>, and that
<person_mentioned>John Rice Jones</person_mentioned>, whose well known integrity and long experience as <person_mentioned>post
master in the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, eminently qualifies him for such a station, be
placed at the head of it.</p>

<p>2nd. That a general subscription be opened and put in circulation
under the superintendance of said <person_mentioned>director</person_mentioned>, to raise funds to defray the
expenses of carrying weekly mails, Commencing with that to the <location_mentioned>Sabine</location_mentioned>
above mentioned, and extending it to other places as soon as the resources
of the <person_mentioned>department </person_mentioned>will permit.</p>

<p>3rd. That, in order, to insure system, and a correct <person_mentioned>administration </person_mentioned>of this
important <person_mentioned>department</person_mentioned>, the director be invested with full powers to make
provisional rules and regulations, and fix the rate of Postage on letters and
papers, that are not on public service; and to appoint such <person_mentioned>post masters</person_mentioned><barker_pb n="160"/>
at the different places where they may be necessary. But such 
appointments are always to be made in conformity with the recommendation of
the <person_mentioned>committee of Correspondence</person_mentioned> of said places.</p>

<p>4th. That it be the duty of said <person_mentioned>director </person_mentioned>to keep an exact account of all
the receipts and disbursements of the <person_mentioned>department </person_mentioned>and to make all contracts
for carrying the mail, and generally to superintend and direct everything
connected with the <person_mentioned>department</person_mentioned>—he being liable always to render an 
account of his acts to the competent authority when one is established by the
<person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. It being understood that the private subscriptions are to
be refunded whenever the funds of the <person_mentioned>department </person_mentioned>will permit.</p>

<p>5th. That said <person_mentioned>director </person_mentioned>correspond with <person_mentioned>all the committees of safety of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> on this subject without delay; requesting their co-operation, and
transmitting to them, copies of this proceeding</p>

<p><location_mentioned>Committee Room</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="10-04-1835">Oct 4th 1835</date_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
