
<TEI.2 id="APB4781">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-29-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 68-69</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Samuel M Williams</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 04-29-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Mexico</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Monclova, Coahuila</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Butler's machinations to injure him. Butler's unpopularity in Mexico. Does not understand Mexican politics. Nobody does; just waiting. The four hundred league law</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>See Austin to Williams, April 15, and May 6, 1835</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 68-69</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>02-23-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4781T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Butler's machinations to injure him. Butler's unpopularity in Mexico. Does not understand Mexican politics. Nobody does; just waiting. The four hundred league law</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">


<p>[From the Williams Papers. Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Texas.]</p>

<p><location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="04-29-1835">April 29 1835</date_mentioned></p>

<p>My friend</p>

<p>Recd. yours of <date_mentioned n="04-08-1835">8 instant</date_mentioned> and the letters and papers enclosed— The
letter from <person_mentioned>Butler </person_mentioned>to you of <date_mentioned n="05-07-1834">7 May [1834]</date_mentioned> explains to me a circumstance
that occured a few days previous to that when I was in the inquisition—
on the <date_mentioned n="05-10-1835">10th </date_mentioned>I was put in communication, and I think on the <date_mentioned n="05-15-1835">15th</date_mentioned> or <date_mentioned n="05-14-185">14th</date_mentioned>
I was told by a <person_mentioned>friend of Butler</person_mentioned>s that he, <person_mentioned>Butler</person_mentioned>, had just recd a letter from
you from which it was quite evident that you was my <person_mentioned>enemy</person_mentioned>, and I was
acquainted with it so as to be on my guard etc— Now at this same time
he writes to you in a way to try and influence you against me— The object
of all this is very plain— It was no doubt hoped that the information
communicated to me would cause irritation in me, and induce me to write
to you under those feelings and thus it was expected an irritable state of
feelings might perhaps be produced between you and me— This is the
only solution I can give to the affair, and I am the more induced to construe
it in this way because <person_mentioned>Butler </person_mentioned>has tried to irritate me, all he can against
<person_mentioned>Mason </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Hotchkiss</person_mentioned>, and I presume he tried to irritate them against me—
I have never in all my life known so bad a man— He left here to day
for the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> and as he was the only <person_mentioned>enemy </person_mentioned>I had in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>I believe I
shall be at liberty to leave here for <location_mentioned>Monclova </location_mentioned>in two weeks— Is it not
strange that the only man in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>who is not anxious for my complete
liberation should be the representative of my <location_mentioned>native country</location_mentioned>?— This bad
man had succeeded in irritating me very much against <person_mentioned>Mason </person_mentioned>but I have
now entirely suspended my opinion as to <person_mentioned>Mason </person_mentioned>for I do not believe
[what] <person_mentioned>Butler </person_mentioned>has said about <person_mentioned>Hotchkiss</person_mentioned>' enmity to me—his object evidently
has been to envolve and entangle me all he can</p>

<p>I have never known so bad and base a man— Should he find that
his enmity to me is unpopular in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, he will then try and make <person_mentioned>Mason</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>Hotchkiss </person_mentioned>the <person_mentioned>scapegoats</person_mentioned>— he has not one friend in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>amongst
the <person_mentioned>foreigners </person_mentioned>and is dispised by most of the <person_mentioned>Mexicans</person_mentioned>—</p>

<p>I thank the <person_mentioned>Legislature </person_mentioned>for their kindness. I am fully comprehended in
the Amnesty, if it ever passes, and I now think it will—my <hi rend="italic">only </hi><person_mentioned>enemy </person_mentioned>is
gone—</p>

<p>I say nothing about politics— I do not understand those of the day—
who does? Keep quiet and still in that state—look on—matters will go in
<hi rend="italic">masse</hi>, one way or the other before long—at present everybody is looking
on, for something—no one knows what— <person_mentioned>Almonte </person_mentioned>goes to the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned>
<date_mentioned n="04-30-1835">tomorrow </date_mentioned>he is truly a good man and <person_mentioned>friend </person_mentioned>to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— I most sincerely
thank my good friends <person_mentioned>Johnson </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Peebles </person_mentioned>for their welcome letters, and<barker_pb n="69"/>
also <person_mentioned>Carbajal</person_mentioned>. Show them this and remember me to them very 
particularly— I hope I shall arrive soon to go home with you all— a few days
will show the result of <person_mentioned>Tony</person_mentioned>s absence— I think it will be favourable—</p>

<p>I do not write home by this mail—you can inform them that I am alive—</p>

<p>[Rubric]</p>

<p><person_mentioned>D. V. [Don Victor Blanco]</person_mentioned> has informed you all of the evils produced
by the impolitic 400 league law its results are bad enough but nothing
in [com]parison to what I at first expected—it produced] a great 
excitement here [ve]ry great indeed it has injured me, altho it [oug]ht not—
but so it [is] I have to bear many sins not my own—</p>

<p>[Addressed:] (Coahuila) <person_mentioned>D. Samuel M. Williams</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Monclova</location_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
