
<TEI.2 id="APB4866">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>09-08-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 116-119</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Public</document_status>
<document_type>Speech</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>People of Texas</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to People of Texas, 09-08-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Delivered at Brazoria, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to></sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Reporting conditions in Mexico, Santa Anna's determination to abolish the federal system, and necessity of convention in Texas to enable Texans to determine on their attitude toward the change.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From a clipping of the <hi rend="italic">Telegraph and Texas Register</hi></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 116-119</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>03-11-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4866T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Reporting conditions in Mexico, Santa Anna's determination to abolish the federal system, and necessity of convention in Texas to enable Texans to determine on their attitude toward the change.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>speech of colonel austin</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Delivered on the <date_mentioned n="09-08-1835">8th of September, 1835</date_mentioned>, at a public dinner in <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>,
given in honor of his return to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></hi>.</p>

<p>I cannot refrain from returning my unfeigned thanks for the flattering
sentiments with which I have just been honored, nor have I words to express
my satisfaction on returning to this my more than <location_mentioned>native country</location_mentioned>, and
meeting so many of my <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>companions </person_mentioned>in its settlement.</p>

<p>I left <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="04-xx-1833">April, 1833</date_mentioned>, as the <person_mentioned>public agent of the people</person_mentioned>, for the
purpose of applying for the admission of this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>into the <location_mentioned>Mexican
confederation</location_mentioned> as a state separate from <location_mentioned>Coahuila</location_mentioned>. This application was
based upon the constitutional and vested rights of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and was sustained
by me in the <location_mentioned>city of Mexico</location_mentioned> to the utmost of my abilities. No honorable
means were spared to effect the objects of my mission and to oppose the
forming of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>into a <location_mentioned>territory</location_mentioned>, which was attempted. I rigidly adhered
to the instructions and wishes of my <person_mentioned>constituents</person_mentioned>, so far as they were 
communicated to me. My efforts to serve <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>involved me in the labyrinth
of Mexican politics. I was arrested, and have suffered a long persecution
and imprisonment. I consider it my duty to give an account of these events
to my <person_mentioned>constituents</person_mentioned>, and will therefore at this time merely observe that
I have never, in any manner, agreed to any thing, or admitted any thing,
that would compromise the constitutional or vested rights of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. These
rights belong to the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>, and can only be surrendered by them.</p>

<p>I fully hoped to have found <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>at peace and in tranquility, but regret
to find it in commotion; all disorganized, all in anarchy, and threatened
with immediate hostilities. This state of things is deeply to be lamented;
it is a great misfortune, but it is one which has not been produced by any
acts of the <person_mentioned>people of this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>: on the contrary, it is the natural and<barker_pb n="117"/>
inevitable consequence of the revolution that has spread all over <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>,
and of the imprudent and impolitic measures of both the <person_mentioned>general and state
governments</person_mentioned>, with respect to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. The <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>here are not to blame, and
cannot be justly censured. They are <person_mentioned>farmers</person_mentioned>, cultivators of the soil, and
are pacific from interest, from occupation, and from inclination. They
have uniformly endeavored to sustain the constitution and the public peace
by pacific means, and have never deviated from their duty as <person_mentioned>Mexican 
citizens</person_mentioned>. If any acts of imprudence have been committed by <person_mentioned>individuals</person_mentioned>, they
evidently resulted from the revolutionary state of the whole <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, the
imprudent and censurable conduct of the <person_mentioned>state authorities</person_mentioned>, and the total
want of a <person_mentioned>local government in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. It is, indeed, a source of surprise and
creditable congratulation, that so few acts of this description have occurred
under the peculiar circumstances of the times. It is, however, to be 
remembered that acts of this nature were not the acts of the people, nor is
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>responsible for them. They were, as I before observed, the natural
consequences of the revolutionary state of the <location_mentioned>Mexican nation</location_mentioned>; and <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
certainly did not originate the revolution, neither have the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>, as a
people, participated in it. The consciences and hands of the <person_mentioned>Texians </person_mentioned>are
free from censure, and clean.</p>

<p>The revolution in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>is drawing to a close. The object is to change
the form of government, destroy the federal constitution of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date_mentioned>, and
establish a <person_mentioned>central or consolidated government</person_mentioned>. The <location_mentioned>states </location_mentioned>are to be 
converted into <location_mentioned>provinces</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Whether the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> ought or ought not to agree to this change,
and relinquish all or a part of their constitutional and vested rights under
the constitution of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date_mentioned>, is a question of the most vital importance; one
that calls for the deliberate consideration of the people, and can only be
decided by them, fairly convened for the purpose. As a <person_mentioned>citizen of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
I have no other right, and pretend to no other. In the report which I
consider it my duty to make to my constituents, I intend to give my views
on the present situation of the country, and especially as to the 
constitutional and natural rights of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and will, therefore, at this time, merely
touch this subject.</p>

<p>Under the <person_mentioned>Spanish government</person_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>was a separate and distinct local
organization. It was one of the <location_mentioned>unities </location_mentioned>that composed the general mass of
the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, and as such participated in the war of the revolution, and
was represented in the constituent congress of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, that formed the
constitution of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date_mentioned>. This constituent congress, so far from destroying
this unity, expressly recognized and confirmed it by the law of <date_mentioned n="05-07-1824">May 7th
1824</date_mentioned>, which united <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>with <location_mentioned>Coahuila </location_mentioned><hi rend="italic">provisionally</hi>, under the especial
guarantee of being made a <location_mentioned>state of the Mexican confederation</location_mentioned>, as soon as
it possessed the necessary elements. That law and the federal constitution
gave to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>a specific political existence, and vested in its <person_mentioned>inhabitants</person_mentioned><barker_pb n="118"/>
special and defined rights, which can only be relinquished by the <person_mentioned>people
of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, acting for themselves as a <location_mentioned>unity</location_mentioned>, and not as a part of <location_mentioned>Coahuila</location_mentioned>,
for the reason that the union with <location_mentioned>Coahuila</location_mentioned>, was <hi rend="italic">limited</hi>, and only gave
power to the <location_mentioned>state of Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned> to govern <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>for the time
being, but <hi rend="italic">always subject to the vested rights of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></hi>. The <location_mentioned>state</location_mentioned>, 
therefore, cannot relinquish those vested rights, by agreeing to the change of
government, or by any other act, unless expressly authorized by the <person_mentioned>people
of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to do so; neither can the <person_mentioned>general government of <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>legally
deprive <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>of them without the consent of this <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>. These are my
opinions.</p>

<p>An important question now presents itself to the <person_mentioned>people of this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.
The federal constitution of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824 </date_mentioned>is about to be destroyed, the system of
government changed, and a central or consolidated one established. Will
this act annihilate all the rights of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and subject this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>to the
uncontrolled and unlimited dictation of the new government?</p>

<p>This is a subject of the most vital importance. I have no doubts the
federal constitution will be destroyed, and a <person_mentioned>central government</person_mentioned> established,
and that the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>will soon be called upon to say whether they agree to
this change or not. This matter requires the most calm discussion, the
most mature deliberation, and the most perfect union. How is this to be
had? I see but one way, and that is by a general consultation of the people
by means of <person_mentioned>delegates </person_mentioned>elected for that purpose, with full powers to give
such an answer, in the name of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, to this question, as they may deem
best, and to adopt such measures as the tranquility and salvation of the
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>may require.</p>

<p>It is my duty to state that<person_mentioned> general Santa Anna</person_mentioned> verbally and expressly
authorized me to say to the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, that he was their <person_mentioned>friend</person_mentioned>, that
he wished for their prosperity, and would do all he could to promote it;
and that, in the new constitution, he would use his influence to give to the
<person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> a special organization, suited to their education, habits,
and situation. Several of the most <person_mentioned>intelligent and influential men in
<location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and especially the <person_mentioned>Ministers of Relations and War</person_mentioned>, expressed 
themselves in the same manner. These declarations afford another and more
urgent necessity for a general consultation of all <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, in order to inform
the <person_mentioned>general government</person_mentioned>, and especially <person_mentioned>general Santa Anna</person_mentioned>, what kind of
organization will suit the education, habits, and situation of this people.</p>

<p>It is also proper for me to state that, in all my conversation with the
<person_mentioned>president </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>ministers </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>men of influence</person_mentioned>, I advised that no <person_mentioned>troops</person_mentioned>
should be sent to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and no cruisers<location_mentioned> along the coast</location_mentioned>. I gave it as my
decided opinion, that the inevitable consequence of sending an <person_mentioned>armed force
</person_mentioned>to this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>would be war. I stated that there was a sound and correct
moral principle in the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, that was abundantly sufficient to
restrain or put down all turbulent or seditious movements, but that this<barker_pb n="119"/>
moral principle could not, and would not unite with any <person_mentioned>armed force</person_mentioned> sent
against this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>; on the contrary, it would resist and repel it, and
ought to do so. This point presents another strong reason why the <person_mentioned>people
of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> should meet in general consultation. This <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>is now in
anarchy, threatened with hostilities; armed vessels are capturing every thing
they can catch<location_mentioned> on the coast</location_mentioned>, and acts of piracy are said to be committed
under cover of the Mexican flag. Can this state of things exist without 
precipitating the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>into a war? I think it cannot, and therefore believe
that it is our bounden and solemn duty as <person_mentioned>Mexicans</person_mentioned>, and as <person_mentioned>Texians</person_mentioned>, to
represent the evils that are likely to result from this mistaken and most
impolitic policy in the military movement.</p>

<p>My <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>, I can truly say that no one has been, or is now, more anxious
than myself to keep trouble away from this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. No one has been, or
now is more faithful to his duty as a <person_mentioned>Mexican citizen</person_mentioned>, and no one has 
personally sacrificed or suffered more in the discharge of this duty. I have
uniformly been opposed to have any thing to do with the family political
quarrels of the <person_mentioned>Mexicans</person_mentioned>. <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>needs peace, and a <person_mentioned>local government</person_mentioned>: its
<person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>are <person_mentioned>farmers</person_mentioned>, and they need a calm and quiet life. But how can
I, or any one, remain indifferent, when our rights, our all, appear to be
in jeopardy, and when it is our duty, as well as our obligation as good
<person_mentioned>Mexican citizens</person_mentioned>, to express our opinions on the present state of things,
and to represent our situation to the government? It is impossible. The
crisis is such as to bring it home to the judgment of every man that 
something must be done, and that without delay. The question will perhaps
be asked, what are we to do? I have already indicated my opinion. Let all
personalities, or divisions, or excitements, or passion, or violence, be
banished from among us. Let a general consultation of the <person_mentioned>people of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> be convened as speedily as posible, to be composed of the best,
and most calm, and intelligent, and firm men in the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, and let them
decide what representations ought to be made to the general government,
and what ought to be done in future.</p>

<p>With these explanatory remarks I will give a toast—<hi rend="italic">The constitutional
rights and the security and peace of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—they ought to be maintained;
and jeopardized as they now are they demand a general consultation of
the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>.</hi></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
