
<TEI.2 id="APB4681">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-06-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 1-6</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>James F Perry</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 10-06-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Mexico</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Judicial procedure in Mexico. Vague charges against him make defense difficult, even if his case could get to trial. Rumored in Mexico that he has many enemies in Texas. Almonte's investigation of Texas may lead to its transfer to the United States—in fact, he believes that it will be transferred within two years</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>For Austin's imprisonment see Barker, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Stephen F. Austin</hi>, 438-459
For Almonte's mission to Texas, see Ibid., 462-468; and for his report see the translation by Carlos E. Castaneda in <hi rend="italic">Southwestern Historical Quarterly</hi>, xxviii, 177-222.
"Even if they could" deleted.
See Austin to Rafael Llanos, January 14, 1834.
Austin to the Ayuntamiento of Bexar, October 2, 1833.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 1-6</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>02-09-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4681T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Judicial procedure in Mexico. Vague charges against him make defense difficult, even if his case could get to trial. Rumored in Mexico that he has many enemies in Texas. Almonte's investigation of Texas may lead to its transfer to the United States—in fact, he believes that it will be transferred within two years</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>[From the Williams Papers. Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Texas.]</p>
<p><location_mentioned>Prison of the Deputation</location_mentioned>, or <location_mentioned>Carcel de Ciudad</location_mentioned>,</p>
<p><date_mentioned n="10-06-1835">October 6 1834</date_mentioned>—</p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Confidential</hi></p>
<p>Dr <person_mentioned>Brother</person_mentioned>.</p>
<p>I was removed to this <location_mentioned>prison </location_mentioned>on the <date_mentioned n="09-19-1835">19th ultimo</date_mentioned>, and for the first time
since my arrest, <date_mentioned n="0-xx-1835">more than nine months</date_mentioned>, an investigation of my case has<barker_pb n="1"/>
commenced. All I know about it is what little I can infer from the
questions asked me, and the vague information or reports of <person_mentioned>persons who
visit</person_mentioned> me— You will understand that the mode of proceeding here is to
collect and arrange all the evidence against an <person_mentioned>accused </person_mentioned>ex-parte, he knows
nothing about it, nor what he has to answer to, untill the evidence against
him is all collected, the case is then delivered to him, and not before, to
make his defence and exhibit proofs to disprove or do away the evidence
against— It is evident that under such a system a suit may be protracted
indefinitely at the will of <person_mentioned>accusers</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>prosecutors </person_mentioned>etc. etc. The only place
I can procure proofs is in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. It may be six months or more before
it is considered that all the evidence is collected against me, and then I
must send to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>for evidence on my part— So far as I can judge, all
seem to agree that my letter of <date_mentioned n="10-02-1834">2d. October</date_mentioned> to the <person_mentioned>Ayto. of <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> was
nothing more than an imprudent opinion, but not a criminal act in the eye
of the law, because it was merely an opinion, unaccompanied by any overt-
act—but, as I am informed, for I know nothing certain, the intention is to
try and convict me of a design to separate <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>from <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and unite
it to the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> and that letter is used as an incident, or link in the
plot which it is pretended there was. All this is utterly false— All <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
can acquit me and I have no doubt would do so unanimously of any such
design or plot—nothing of the kind has ever existed in me, or in any one
else in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>that I ever heard of— But I am of the opinion that my
innocence will avail me nothing— There seems to be a net wove around
me which I cannot understand, and of course cannot resist— Everything
I have said or done with pure intentions and in good faith— All my honest
and republican frankness in explaining to the <person_mentioned>govt</person_mentioned> the true situation of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, every thing that has passed in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>since I went there in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date_mentioned>—
All the events of the last four years— All that is said there now and
since my imprisonment— All that has been published about <location_mentioned>my colony</location_mentioned>
in <location_mentioned>newspapers </location_mentioned><location_mentioned>books </location_mentioned>etc even the population and advancement of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in
agriculture, arts, exports, and resources—in short every thing seems to
be construed and perverted against me—nothing comes from <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in my
favor, and much (as it is said) against me. This however I doubt— I
have but few <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>here very few indeed, they have complained at the
injustice done me by so much delay— It is however said in reply that all
my own <location_mentioned>countrymen </location_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>are against me, and as a proof that they
are, nothing comes from there, no representations in my favor— Some
even doubt whether I was ever appointed the <person_mentioned>agent of these people</person_mentioned>, for it is
said, that it is not reasonable to suppose that they would abandon me, as
they seem to have done etc for my part I do not believe all this, and I
doubt very much whether any thing in my favor sent to the <person_mentioned>present minister<barker_pb n="2"/>
of relations Francisco Lombardo</person_mentioned>, will ever reach me or the <person_mentioned>judge</person_mentioned>— I am
of this opinion because I am told by many that he is the most bitter <person_mentioned>enemy</person_mentioned>
I have—he was violently opposed to the repeal of the 11 Article of the
law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6 April 1830</date_mentioned>, and blamed me for getting that measure through—it
is probable he will never forgive me for it— Under these circumstances,
a <person_mentioned>foreigner </person_mentioned>and a <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>North American</person_mentioned></hi> by birth, shut up in <location_mentioned>prison</location_mentioned>, almost destitute 
of <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>and money, far removed from all resources, and in the
midst of <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>with the <person_mentioned>Minister of relations Lombardo</person_mentioned> at their head,
what have I reasonably to expect except a long imprisonment and
perhaps total ruin? I have no doubt that the <person_mentioned>President Genl. Santana</person_mentioned> is
friendly to me and to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. I also have confidence in the <person_mentioned>judge </person_mentioned>who has
charge of my case <person_mentioned>Don Martinez de Castro</person_mentioned>— I believe he is an honest and
honorable man, but what can the <person_mentioned>President </person_mentioned>or the <person_mentioned>judge </person_mentioned>do against a host
of <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>persecutors</person_mentioned>, when no one appears in my favor <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>is
silent—the <person_mentioned>State Govt</person_mentioned>- the same—this all say is even worse than if they
openly accused me, for it shows a contemptuous indifference—</p>

<p>The sum and substance of the whole matter is that you must look upon
me as <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>, for a long time to come—this is the only reasonable opinion I
can form on the subject. I wrote you in <date_mentioned n="05-xx-1835">May </date_mentioned>that everything depended
on the report of <person_mentioned>Almonte </person_mentioned>who was sent to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and I presume is now
there— I wish you or some true <person_mentioned>friend </person_mentioned>of mine to go and see him in
person— My <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>I am told have been very active in that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>and
at <location_mentioned>Monclova</location_mentioned>, tho I must confess frankly that I do not believe the hundredth
part of what is said about the efforts of my <person_mentioned>enemies in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to ruin me.
That I have <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>is a mere matter of course—it is in fact an honor to
me, for none but a most miserable and contemptable poor devil could
have had as much to do with public matters as I have in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, without
making <person_mentioned>enemies</person_mentioned>— I admit that I have them, but I also have the charity
to believe that they are honorable and noble minded <person_mentioned>enemies</person_mentioned>, and would
not, try to ruin me and perpetuate my imprisonment, by taking a mean
and base advantage of my present persecutions and misfortunes— I acquit
them in my heart of any such design or any such efforts, and I begin to
think, that most of what is said about their efforts to ruin me comes from
persons who are either blinded by passion or prejudice or who are real
<person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>of mine and of every body else who lives in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and that the
real object is to try and darken the North American character-</p>

<p>I send this by <person_mentioned>H. J. Offutt</person_mentioned>— All my other letters have gone by mail,
either direct to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, or by <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned>, and very likely have been opened or
intercepted, for even that mode has been resorted to, to try and ruin me—
a mode as base as the object intended and worthy of my <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>perse-<barker_pb n="4"/>
cutors</person_mentioned>—worthy of <person_mentioned>F. Lombardo</person_mentioned>. In <date_mentioned n="01-xx-1836">Jany next</date_mentioned> I presume there will be
a complete change in political matters, and I hope that <person_mentioned>D. Lucas Alaman</person_mentioned>
will come into power again, it is believed he will and in that event I shall
probably be set at liberty at once— In short this is my pirncipal hope
at present. <person_mentioned>Alaman </person_mentioned>has talents. The main defect in him is that he is too
honest and too honorable for the <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>taste. <person_mentioned>Santana </person_mentioned>I believe is fully
convinced of <person_mentioned>Alaman</person_mentioned>'s merits and I hope will employ him in the <location_mentioned>Ministry</location_mentioned>—
I again repeat, that I have confidence in <person_mentioned>Santana</person_mentioned>'s friendly disposition
towards me.</p>

<p>I was interrupted in my letter by a <person_mentioned>Mexican friend</person_mentioned>, who has just left—
he called to inform me that a packet had been recd. from <person_mentioned>Almonte </person_mentioned>against
me, which was calculated to do me great harm and that I need not be
surprised if the rigors of my imprisonment were increased— Whether this
be a fact or not, I doubt—it has been hinted to me more than once that
a sum of money, say $50,000, would stop my <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>and set me at
liberty—all I have on earth would not bring that sum, nor the half of it
in cash, but it has been reported here that I have many millions in the
<location_mentioned>banks of the U. S</location_mentioned>.—now all these reports about my <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>may be nothing
more than management to try and draw out cash. I cannot think that
<person_mentioned>Almonte </person_mentioned>would try to ruin me You and my other <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>can investigate
this matter, and if he is playing an unjust game, you will know how to treat
him as he, or any one else in such a case deserves— <person_mentioned>Noriega </person_mentioned>is here and
says publically that I ought to be shot</p>

<p>I sent you duplicate powers of attorney to sell any of my land and
settle all my business—call on <person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>for all notes due me, and do
what you can to save my property, every honest and <person_mentioned>good man in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
will assist you in so doing, I have no doubt.</p>

<p>My imprisonment has been very severe, it has cost me very dear— I
have suffered very much, but I now believe it will have a great influence
in the transfer of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to the <location_mentioned>U. S</location_mentioned>. by treaty, for it has caused an investigation as to the affairs of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, that is beginning to convince all me[n]
of judgment, that what I said to the <person_mentioned>vice president Gomez Farias</person_mentioned>, was true,
that i[s] that if the <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>did not provide for the welfare of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, the
people there would do it of themselve[s] <hi rend="italic">and were able to do so</hi>— I also
said in a paper which I wrote to a <person_mentioned>Mexican friend</person_mentioned> in this <location_mentioned>city </location_mentioned>that it was the
duty of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to separate from <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>if there was no other mode of
saving that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>from ruin—this paper is now filed as the main evidence against me, and my letter to the <person_mentioned>Ayto. of <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned></person_mentioned> etc. etc. are brought
in as corroborating testimony Men of sence now say that these opinions
of mine are true and well founded, but that I used an imprudent and blunt
frankness that is unknown in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, and would ruin any one who made
use of it— I was taught to speak the truth from my infancy and am too
old to learn new habits— I wished to get remedies that would satisfy
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and prevent its separation However whether my <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>have been
active or not, my <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>ought to be so, if they wish to relieve me, and
they ought therefore to go and see <person_mentioned>Almonte </person_mentioned>in person— Great surprise
has been expressed at the silence of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>about me— All seem to think
that a very respectfull, mild, but frank and manly representation in my
favor from the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> stating in substance— That I did no more
than to represent their true wishes and opinions as they were when I left
there in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1833">1833</date_mentioned>, as it was my duty to do as an <person_mentioned>agent</person_mentioned>—that there never was
any design in me, or in those people to separate from <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, but at the
same time they believed in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1833">1833</date_mentioned>, and <hi rend="italic">still believe</hi>, that under the first law
of nature they have the right, as all people have, to provide for their safety
and salvation from ruin by any means in their power, <hi rend="italic">in the extreme case</hi>
that there was no other remidy left them, and that they not only consider
this to be a right, but also a duty which as men they owe to themselves and
to their <person_mentioned>families</person_mentioned>. That the desire to form a <location_mentioned>state</location_mentioned> separate from <location_mentioned>Coahuila</location_mentioned>,
grew out of the want of a competent <person_mentioned>local government</person_mentioned>, and not from any
design to separate from <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>—that if the <hi rend="italic">mode </hi>that was adopted, and
the interpretation given by the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and by me, to the law of
<date_mentioned n="05-07-1824">7 May 1824</date_mentioned>, were erronious, it was a mere error in judgement, and not
a design to violate the law, or the constitution—that there were strong
opinions in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1833">1833</date_mentioned>, in favor of an organization <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>, and that I was
opposed to that measure (This is a fact, and a very important one for me to
establish, very important indeed)—that the discontent in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>was quieted
by the repeal of the 11 article of the law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6 April 1830</date_mentioned> and by the
remedies that were applied by the <person_mentioned>State Govt</person_mentioned>- <date_mentioned n="Winter-1834">last winter</date_mentioned> in the local
administration, and that those people were faithful to the Mexican Constitution, and finally requesting my release, in as much as I had only acted
as their <person_mentioned>agent </person_mentioned>and if any blame was to be attached, it must fall on the
<person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and not on their representative, and that those people were
at all times ready <hi rend="italic">to meet the responsability and in any manner</hi> etc. etc.—</p>

<p>The representation should be in the most respectful and mild terms—
the strongest kind of ideas and principles are better expressed in mild polite
and even <hi rend="italic">flattering </hi>language, than in any other way, and such language
never gives offence or mortifies self dignity or self pride— No kind of
harm can come to the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> from such a representation for
the very plain reason that they are far beyond the reach of harm—and it
may save me, and do much good in other matters for it will tend very much
to convince every body that this govt- must satisfy <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>or expect unpleasant consequences or sell it— I say to you frankly that I am of the
opinion that <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>will be transfer[red] to the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> by treaty in less than
two years— I may be sacrificed and not live, or not be in a situation to
enjoy the prosperity that would result from that measure but you all in
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>will. Men who pretend to be acquainted with the secrets of Govt-
here are tryin[g] to buy up <location_mentioned>Texas lands</location_mentioned>— I am of the opinion it is the
best way money can be employed—</p>

<p>I have been much more faithfull to the <person_mentioned>Govt. of my <location_mentioned>adopted country</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>,
and much more frank and honest than my own interest or wellfare required,
and I begin to think, more than this Govt. deserved— What a recompense
am I now receiving for all my fidelity to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, all my labors to advance
its prosperity, to settle its wilderness, to keep peace and tranquility in
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>? Do I deserve such treatment? No—in place of imprisonment I
deserve rewards from the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>- The only consolation I have is that I
have done my duty— My conscience is clear— I am certain the <person_mentioned>people
of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> will do me ample justice— If I am sacrificed unjustly by the
machinations of <person_mentioned>enemies</person_mentioned>, those people will I have no doubt, revenge my
ruin as justice requires.</p>

<p>[S. F. Austin]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
