
<TEI.2 id="APB4685">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-18-1834</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 10-13</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Thomas F McKinney</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Thomas F McKinney, 10-18-1834</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>City Prison, Mexico</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Deeply grateful for mission of Grayson and Jack in his behalf. Asks destruction of a letter written October 6. Robertson Colony</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>See Barker, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Stephen F. Austin</hi>, 447-450.
See Austin to Perry, August 25. See William H. Wharton's "Caid," November 9,
1834.
July 31, 1834, Austin Papers. Omitted from this publication.
McKinney had been elected Suplente.
"The Robertson colony. See Robertson's Statement, July 2, 1834. For the history of
the Robertson Colony, see Barker, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Stephen F. Austin</hi>, Chaptere XI.
See Barker's <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>, 466.
Henry Smith, recently appointed political chief of the Department of the Brazos.
David G. Burnet had been appointed judge under the new judiciary act for Texas.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 10-13</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>02-11-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4685T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Deeply grateful for mission of Grayson and Jack in his behalf. Asks destruction of a letter written October 6. Robertson Colony</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-18-1834">October 18. 1834</date_mentioned>.—in the <location_mentioned>city prison</location_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>T. F. McKinney</person_mentioned>,</p>

<p>My much esteemed <person_mentioned>friend</person_mentioned>. It is difficult for me to express to you the
satisfaction I have derived from the arrival of Messrs. <person_mentioned>Grayson </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Jack
</person_mentioned>on the <date_mentioned n="10-14-1834">14 instant</date_mentioned>—2 You must have experienced the desolate situation of a
long imprisonment far removed from your <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>, with even a doubt that
some of them had forgotten you or were indifferent as to your situation,
to be sensible of the pleasure I have recd from hearing from you all in
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and knowing that I still occupy a place in your remembrance, and
in your regard. I sincerely thank you all— No new ties were needed to
bind my heart and affections to the<person_mentioned> people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, I can however never
forget this last act of kindness—it came at an interesting moment I had
borne all with calm fortitude up to the beginning of this month. At that
time I heard so many unfavourable rumors, and one in particular, that my
<person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>at home (except my own <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned>), were careless about me and were
indifferent as to my fate that my spirits began to sink The idea of being
cast off contemptuously by those whom I had, at least, <hi rend="italic">tryed </hi>to serve faithfully was worse than death. I am now entirely relieved from that idea—
and am in better spirits than since my arrest Nothing could have depressed
them but the above idea</p>

<p>I hope the representations brought by <person_mentioned>Grayson </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Jack </person_mentioned>will have a
favourable effect The only objection is that they are in the English 
language Nothing should be sent in that language It does great harm I
think I now understand the rumors that have reached me of unfavourable
impressions against me in the <location_mentioned>cabinet</location_mentioned>, on account of <person_mentioned>representations from
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> Those Impressions were made, but they proceeded from 
communications that were intended to benefit me, and had quite a contrary effect
owing to the high toned and inflamatory language used. I am convinced
that no representations have been made against me, and no unfair means<barker_pb n="11"/>
used against me by any <person_mentioned>persons </person_mentioned>who belong to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and I acquit all
persons of such a suspicion I say this because in my letter to my <person_mentioned>brother
in [law]</person_mentioned> of <date_mentioned n="08-26-1834">26 August</date_mentioned> I expressed a doubt on the subject I regret that
I entertained any such doubt I was induced to believe amongst other
things that the <person_mentioned>minister of relations Lombardo</person_mentioned> was personally hostile to
me, and that <person_mentioned>Col. Almonte</person_mentioned> had made a very unfavourable report about me
and <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— all this I now find to be quite incorrect <person_mentioned>Almonte</person_mentioned>'s report
was <hi rend="italic">favourable</hi>, and the <person_mentioned>minister </person_mentioned>is not my <person_mentioned>enemy</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Under all these false impressions I wrote on the <date_mentioned n="10-06-1834">6 of this month</date_mentioned> by
<person_mentioned>Capt. Offutt</person_mentioned> on the subject of representing All those letters were written
under erroneous impressions made by false information, and I wish <person_mentioned>Mr. P.
[Perry]</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>W. [Williams]</person_mentioned> to destroy all my letters of <date_mentioned n="08-06-1834">6 October </date_mentioned>and
not to show them to any one whatever</p>

<p>How much difficulty have I been involved in by the excitements in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
You know how much I have been opposed to most of the events of the
last two years It will be a lesson to me for the future, and I hope that
hereafter the people of that country will not abuse or suspect me or any
one else, who advises, <hi rend="italic">Fidelity to Mexico, and opposition to violent men</hi>
and measures—which has always been and now is my motto, and I hope
will in future be the motto of all <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></p>

<p>I am pleased with the representation from <location_mentioned>Brazoria </location_mentioned>or <location_mentioned>Colombia </location_mentioned>signed
by <person_mentioned>Waller </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Wharton</person_mentioned>. I shall return to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, as a <person_mentioned>farmer </person_mentioned>determined
to have nothing more to do with the public matters of this, or any country
for I wish for harmony This is too important a matter for individual
and public happiness and prosperity to be suspended or jeopardized by
stickling etiquette, and under this view I am the first to say that no obstacles
to personal harmony with all men will be raised by me on account of the
past political events, altho I am the only one who has suffered by them
The <person_mentioned>Whartons </person_mentioned>have heretofore taken a hostile attitude, or at least an 
unfriendly one towards me They never had any cause, as I think, to do so.
However be it that <person_mentioned>W. H. W. [Wharton]</person_mentioned> is a friend or foe, the 
representation above mentioned is calculated to benefit me and was evidently intended
to do so and I therefore thank him so far as he had any agency in it, and
authorize you to tell him so—and also that I look on that measure as a
<hi rend="italic">step </hi>on his part towards personal harmony, if he intended, it as such, I
meet it with corresponding feeling, and if we do not shake hands as friends
in future it will be his fault not mine <person_mentioned>John [Wharton]</person_mentioned> is of course 
included in these remarks.</p><barker_pb n="12"/>

<p>I am weary of a troubled life I wish for a calm and quiet one on a
<location_mentioned>farm </location_mentioned>along side of my <person_mentioned>sister </person_mentioned>and her <person_mentioned>flock of little ones</person_mentioned> The society of
<location_mentioned>new countries</location_mentioned> is thin and bad at best—why should it be made worse by
dissentions that separate <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>who might enjoy each others society as
<person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>neighbors </person_mentioned>and thus cast a rose or two upon the thorny path of
human life? I am weary of such things—if I know myself I am made
for social intercourse and enjoyment of <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>neighbors</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Show this to <person_mentioned>P. and W. [Perry and Williams] </person_mentioned>without any delay that
they may know my wishes as to my letters of <date_mentioned n="10-06-1834">6 October</date_mentioned> and distroy them.
Remember me to<person_mentioned> Mrs. McKinney</person_mentioned> and to <person_mentioned>Col Groce </person_mentioned>and all his <person_mentioned>children</person_mentioned>
and to my <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>in genl.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned> [Rubric]</p>

<p>7 oclock at night</p>

<p>just as I had sealed this and was about sending it to the <location_mentioned>post office</location_mentioned>
I rec.d the oficio of the <person_mentioned>chief of that department</person_mentioned> informing me of my 
election as a <person_mentioned>member of the state legislature of <location_mentioned>Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. No event
of my life has afforded me more gratification, not because I desire office,
or to have anything to do with public matters, far from it— I sincerely
wish to avoid them—but situated as I now am I should be worse than cold
hearted and insencible not to feel the greatest degree of gratitude and
thankfulness for this distinguished and unequivocal evidence of the 
confidence and esteem of my fellow <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>and fellow <person_mentioned>laborers</person_mentioned>, because it is
a vindication of what is dearer to me than life or liberty—of <hi rend="italic">my reputation</hi>
I thank them I hope it may be in my power to thank them by some act,
some service more substantial than these words This hope is all that can
diminish my repugnance to entering again into the confused and entangled
public matters of our <location_mentioned>adopted country</location_mentioned> I believe however by the laws my
election is nulo because I have a causa pendiente and I think it quite 
doubtful whether I shall be at liberty before <date_mentioned n="01-xx-1835">January </date_mentioned>or <date_mentioned n="01-xx-1835">February </date_mentioned>My case is
before the <person_mentioned>judiciary</person_mentioned>, and the executive cannot interfere with it I have no
doubt the <person_mentioned>president Santana</person_mentioned> is friendly to me and to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>I therefore
advise you to prepare to go to <location_mentioned>Monclova </location_mentioned>so as to be there by the <date_mentioned n="01-01-1835">first of
Jany-</date_mentioned> or before.</p>

<p>I rec.d <person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>letter—cannot answer it or the <person_mentioned>chiefs</person_mentioned> by this mail which
will close in an hour and so will my <location_mentioned>prison </location_mentioned>for the night U. debe visitar a
mi <person_mentioned>hermana </person_mentioned>amenudo, y debe ser mas prudente y mucho menos estremoso
en todo—lo digo como <person_mentioned>amigo</person_mentioned>. qe le ha dada bastantes preuvas qe lo soy
verdaderamte—basta</p>

<p>Many strange things have occured during the last year of revolutions
<location_mentioned>all over Mexico</location_mentioned> which deserve the name of <hi rend="italic">Anarchical phynomina</hi> The<barker_pb n="13"/>
<person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>business may be classed in the number <person_mentioned>W</person_mentioned>. should go to 
<location_mentioned>Monclova </location_mentioned>in person. He should collect all the oficios of <person_mentioned>Teran </person_mentioned>and the <person_mentioned>Govr- of
the state</person_mentioned> by which <person_mentioned>R</person_mentioned>. was banished I saved him and those who came with
him from those orders—these in addition to the <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">April law</date_mentioned> rendered it 
impossible for the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>- to regrant that <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>to him or extend the time to
the <person_mentioned>Nashville comp</person_mentioned>.y <person_mentioned>Secretary Santiago del Valle</person_mentioned> I presume will recollect
that he was much hurt at me for requesting that the time should be extended
to the <person_mentioned>Nashville Co</person_mentioned>. for he said I knew it was impossible as they were all
<person_mentioned>citizens of the U. S</person_mentioned>. and the <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">April law</date_mentioned> was then in force It could not
be granted to <person_mentioned>R</person_mentioned>. or extended to the <person_mentioned>Nashville Co.</person_mentioned> this was impossible
I enquired if it could be done and gave offense by making the enquiry
It was applied for by a <person_mentioned>french Co</person_mentioned>. and others and would have been granted
to some one, had I not procured it just as I did I thought it was my duty
to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to try and keep it out of the hands of those <person_mentioned>foreign companies</person_mentioned>, for
they have only done harm or at least as yet have not contributed <hi rend="italic">much </hi>to
settle the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. They would have had no sympathy for the <person_mentioned>old settlers
</person_mentioned>my object was to settle that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>so as to form a barrier against the
<person_mentioned>hostile indians</person_mentioned> My intentions were good and had the genl good in view
Why am I now abused for doing what it really was my duty to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to do
<person_mentioned>Chambers </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>both know the history of all that matter. The
fact is I deserve the thanks of the people instead of their abuse, as to the
<location_mentioned>upper Colony</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I am of the opinion that the the rough answer given to <person_mentioned>Noriega </person_mentioned>and some
<hi rend="italic">other </hi>things of like character that I never knew anything about untill a
week or so ago, have or will prolong my imprisonment six months at least,
beyond what it would have been under a different course Thus I suffer
for the hot headed acts' of others as I have done in many instances my
general character is mildness and I have pursued conciliation as a system—
but at moments I have been goaded into <hi rend="italic">impatience </hi>and even <hi rend="italic">passion</hi>
Is it not rather strange that <hi rend="italic">those moments</hi>, and they are few, are never
forgotten all my mildness and prudence is over looked and merged in
the recollection of some one or two rash expressions or an isolated act
that of itself may appear intemperate, without knowing all the circumstances This is not just <person_mentioned>Ben Franklin</person_mentioned> or Job wd. have had their moments
of ruffled temper in some situations I have been placed [in]
Remember me to the <person_mentioned>chief H. Smith</person_mentioned>, I hope he will not take it amiss
if I advise him to sign <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Enrique </person_mentioned></hi>and not <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Henry </person_mentioned></hi>I am pleased with his appointment and <person_mentioned>Burnett</person_mentioned>s—give <person_mentioned>Burnett </person_mentioned>and the good <person_mentioned>Dr. Miller</person_mentioned> a shake
of the hand for me—in fact to all—all—everybody—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. A.</person_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
