
<TEI.2 id="APB4851">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>08-21-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 101-103</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Mary Austin Holley</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Mary Austin Holley, 08-21-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Orleans, Louisiana</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Texas must become a slave state and ultimately ought to belong to the United States. Desires a great immigration</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Copy by Mrs. Holley</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 101-103</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>03-11-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4851T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Texas must become a slave state and ultimately ought to belong to the United States. Desires a great immigration</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="08-21-1835">August 21, 1835</date_mentioned>.</p>
<p>My Dear <person_mentioned>Cousin</person_mentioned>,</p>
<p>I am, as you will see by my date, once more in the <location_mentioned>land of my birth</location_mentioned>, and
of <hi rend="italic">freedom</hi>— a word I can well appreciate. I shall leave here in a day
or two for <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. I wished to have taken a trip <location_mentioned>up the river</location_mentioned>, and thence
<location_mentioned>to the north</location_mentioned> but shall have to defer it until <date_mentioned n="Spring-1836">spring</date_mentioned>. I have been so long
absent from <location_mentioned>home</location_mentioned>, that my affairs there are behind hand, and require my
attention.</p>

<p>The situation of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>is daily becoming more and more interesting, so
much so, that I doubt whether the <person_mentioned>Government of the <location_mentioned>United -States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, or that
of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, can much longer look on with indifference, or inaction. It is
very evident that the best interests of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> require that <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
should be effectually, and fully, <hi rend="italic">Americanized</hi>—that is—settled by a 
population that will harmonize with their <person_mentioned>neighbors on the <location_mentioned>East</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, in language,
political principles, common origin, sympathy, and even interest. <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned><barker_pb n="102"/>
must be a <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>slave </person_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. It is no longer a matter of doubt.</hi> The interest
of <location_mentioned>Louisiana </location_mentioned>requires that it should be, a population of fanatical 
<person_mentioned>abolitionists </person_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>would have a very pernicious and dangerous influence on
the overgrown <person_mentioned>slave </person_mentioned>population of that state. <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>must, and ought to
become an <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>out work</hi> on the west</location_mentioned>, as <location_mentioned>Alabama </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Florida </location_mentioned>are on the <location_mentioned>East</location_mentioned>,
to defend the key of the <location_mentioned>western world</location_mentioned>—the <location_mentioned>mouths of the Mississippi</location_mentioned>.
Being fully <hi rend="italic">Americanized </hi>under the <location_mentioned>Mexican</location_mentioned> flag, would be the same thing
in effect, and ultimate result, as coming under the <location_mentioned>United States </location_mentioned>Flag. A
gentle breeze shakes off a ripe peach. Can it be supposed that the violent
political convulsions of <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>will not shake off <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>so soon as it is
ripe enough to fall All that is now wanting is a great immigration of
good and efficient <person_mentioned>families</person_mentioned>, this <date_mentioned n="Fall- 1835">fall </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="Winter-1835">winter</date_mentioned>. Should we get such an
emigration, especially from the western states—all is done—the peach
will be ripe. Under this view: and it is a correct one, <person_mentioned>every man of 
influence <location_mentioned>in the western States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, who has the true interests of his <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>at heart,
ought to use every possible exertion to induce such an immigration. They
can get lands; <hi rend="italic">now is the accepted time,</hi> and none too soon. The door
is still open for them to come in legally. The <person_mentioned>government of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> can
not complain—it has invited immigration.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Gen: Sant[a] Anna</person_mentioned> told me he should visit <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="09-xx-1835">next month</date_mentioned>—<hi rend="italic">as a <person_mentioned>friend</person_mentioned>.</hi>
His visit is uncertain—his friendship much more so. We must rely on 
ourselves, and prepare for the worst. A large immigration will prepare us,
give us strength, resources, everything. I do not know what may be the
state of public feeling in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, but presume they mean to avoid all collision
with <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>if possible to do so, and be also ready to repel attacks should
they come. This is my opinion. A great immigration from <location_mentioned>Kentucky</location_mentioned>,
<location_mentioned>Tennessee </location_mentioned>etc, each man with his rifle or musket, would be of great use
to us—very great indeed. If they go by sea, they must take passport from
the <person_mentioned>Mexican Consul</person_mentioned>, comply with all the requisites of the law, and get
legally into the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, so long as the door is legally open. Should it be
closed it will then be time enough to force it open—if necessary. <hi rend="italic">Prudence,</hi>
and<hi rend="italic"> an observance of appearances</hi> must therefore be strictly attended to
for the present. Here, I figure to myself, you start, and exclaim, "Dios
mio; my  <person_mentioned>cousin Stephen </person_mentioned>has become a very <person_mentioned>Mexican politician in 
hypocrisy</person_mentioned>." not so; there is no hypocrisy about it. It is well known that my
object has always been to fill up <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>with a <person_mentioned>north American population</person_mentioned>;
and, besides, it may become a question of <hi rend="italic">to be</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">not to be</hi>. And in that
event, the great law of nature—self preservation—operates, and supersedes,
all other laws.</p>

<p>The cause of philanthrophy and liberty, also, will be promoted by
<hi rend="italic">Americanizing </hi><location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. I am morally right, therefore, to do so by all 
possible, honorable, means.</p><barker_pb n="103"/>

<p>In all <location_mentioned>countries</location_mentioned>, one way or another, <person_mentioned>a few men</person_mentioned> rule society. If those
few were convinced of the great benefits that would result to the western
world by <hi rend="italic">Americanizing <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></hi>, they would exert their influence to promote
that object, and in so doing use such arguments as would best effect it,
without letting anything transpire in the public prints to alarm the <person_mentioned>Mexican
Government</person_mentioned>, or place that of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> in the awkward necessity
of taking any steps, as a <person_mentioned>friend of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, under the treaty etc.</p>

<p>If there was any way of getting at it, I should like to know what the <person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">wise
men</hi> of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> think the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> ought to do. The
fact is, we must, and ought to become a part of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>. Money
should be no consideration. The political importance of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to the
great <location_mentioned>Western world</location_mentioned>, from the influence it may one day have on <location_mentioned>Louisiana</location_mentioned>,
is so great, that it can not fail to have due weight on all reflecting men,
and on <person_mentioned>Gen Jackson</person_mentioned> and the <person_mentioned>Senate</person_mentioned>, in particular. The more the <person_mentioned>American
population of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> is increased, the more readily will the <person_mentioned>Mexican 
Government</person_mentioned> give it up, also, the more the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> <hi rend="italic">seem </hi>to oppose a
separation from <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, the less tenacious will they be to hold it. This
seems paradoxical, but will cease to appear so when you consider that
strange compound the Mexican character. If <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>insisted on separating,
and it should be given up in consequence, it would appear as if they
yielded to force, or fear, and their national pride would be roused. They
are a strange people, and must be studied to be managed. They have high
ideas of National dignity should it be openly attacked, but will sacrifice
national dignity, and national interest too if it can be done in a <hi rend="italic">still </hi>way,
or so as not to arrest public attention. "Dios Castiga el escandolo mas
que el crimen," (God punishes the exposure more than the crime) is their
motto. This maxim influences their morals and their politics. I learned
it when I was there in 1822, and I now believe that if I had not always
kept it in view, and known the power which <hi rend="italic">appearances </hi>have on them, even
when they know they are deceived, I should never have succeeded, to the
extent I have done in Americanizing <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>To conclude—I wish a great immigration this <date_mentioned n="Fall-1835">fall </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="Winter-1835">winter </date_mentioned>from
<location_mentioned>Kentucky</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Tennessee</location_mentioned>, <hi rend="italic">every where</hi>, passports, or no passports, <hi rend="italic">any how</hi>.
For fourteen years I have had a hard time of it, but nothing shall daunt
my courage or abate my exertions to complete the main object of my
labors—<hi rend="italic">to Americanize <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></hi>. This <date_mentioned n="Fall-1835">fall</date_mentioned>, and <date_mentioned n="Winter-1835">winter</date_mentioned>, will fix our fate—a
great immigration will settle the question.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S F Austin</person_mentioned>.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
