
<TEI.2 id="APB4877">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>09-21-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 128-129</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Circular letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Columbia Committee</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Columbia Committee, 09-21-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Columbia, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Reconciliation hopeless. Advises preparation for resistance</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>This is a manuscript copy but it was also printed in handbill form and by the
<hi rend="italic">Texas Republican</hi>. It was issued as a circular letter to all districts under date of
September 21, with the following postscript:
Information was received last night by express that Genl. Cos landed at
Copano with 400 men arms and ammunition
An Expedition is now raising in the lower country to take the field at once.
They are called upon to rendezvous at Leagues old place on the Colorado on
the 28th of this month.
Every man in Texas is called upon to take up arms in defence of his
country and his rights. Those who can join the expedition on the 28th are
requested to do so; or they can join it at James Kerrs on the Lavaca which
will be the principal rendezvous. A Corpse of reserve will be formed to
march on and sustain the advance. Those who can not join the advance are
requested to unite with the reserve, and report themselves to the Committee
of Safety in this place.
It is expected that each man will supply himself with provision arms and
ammunition to march with.
Arrangements will be made for permanent supplies as soon as possible.
Austin Sept 21st 1835</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 128-129</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>03-20-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4877T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Reconciliation hopeless. Advises preparation for resistance</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>CIRCULAR from the <person_mentioned>committee of safety of the <location_mentioned>Jurisdiction of Austin</location_mentioned></person_mentioned></p>

<p>Information of the most important and decisive character has just been
received from <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>from unquestionable authority which in the opinion
of this <person_mentioned>committee </person_mentioned>calls for the prompt attention of the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The substance of this information is that <person_mentioned>Genl. Cos</person_mentioned> was expected at <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>
on the <date_mentioned n="09-16-1835">16th of this month</date_mentioned> with more <person_mentioned>troops</person_mentioned>, that he intended to make an
immediate attack on the <location_mentioned>colonies</location_mentioned>, that there was a plan to try and foment
divisions and discord among the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>, so as to use one part against the
other, and prevent preparation—and that the real object is to destroy and<barker_pb n="129"/>
break up the<location_mentioned> foreign settlements</location_mentioned> in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— This <person_mentioned>committee </person_mentioned>have no doubt
of the correctness of this information and therefore recommend—</p>

<p>That the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>should maintain the position taken by them at their
primary meetings— to insist on their rights under the federal Constitution
of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824 </date_mentioned>and law of <date_mentioned n="05-07-1824">7th May of that year</date_mentioned> and union with the <location_mentioned>Mexican
Confederation</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>That <location_mentioned>every district</location_mentioned> ought to organize its <person_mentioned>militia </person_mentioned>where it is not already
done, and have frequent musters, and that the <person_mentioned>Captains of Companies</person_mentioned> make
a return without delay to the <person_mentioned>political Chief of this Department</person_mentioned> of the force
of his <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>the arms and amunition, in order that he may lay the same
before the <person_mentioned>general consultation of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>— <person_mentioned>Volunteer Companies</person_mentioned> are also
rec ommended—</p>

<p>This <person_mentioned>Committe </person_mentioned>deems it to be a duty to say that in its opinion all kind
of conciliatory measures with <person_mentioned>Genl. Cos</person_mentioned> and the <person_mentioned>military at <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> are 
hopeless, and that nothing but <hi rend="italic">ruin </hi>to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>can be expected from any such
measures— They have already and very properly been resorted to without
effect.</p>

<p>WAR is our only resource—there is no other remedy but to defend our
rights, our <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>ourselves </person_mentioned>by force of arms— To do this we must
be united, and in order to unite, the <person_mentioned>delegates of the people</person_mentioned> must meet in
general consultation and organize a system of defense and give organization
to the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>so as to produce concert—</p>

<p>UNTILL some <person_mentioned>competent authority</person_mentioned> is established to <hi rend="italic">direct </hi>all that can be
done is to recommend this <person_mentioned>Committee </person_mentioned>therefore earnestly recommends
this subject and advises <person_mentioned>every man in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to prepare for war and lay
aside all hopes of conciliation.</p>

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="09-19-1835">September 19 1835</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin chairman of the Comm.</person_mentioned> [Rubric]</p>
<p>Please to send copies to <location_mentioned>Matagorda </location_mentioned>and over the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>.—</p>
<p><person_mentioned>Committee of Safety</person_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Columbia</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
