
<TEI.2 id="APB4991">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-27-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 213-214</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Philip Dimmitt</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Philip Dimmitt to Stephen F Austin, 10-27-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Port of Goliad, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Head Quarters, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Karankawa Indians stopped from destruction of cattle. Has made a flag, which he describes</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>In Austin's Order Book, as cited, p. 27.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 213-214</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-07-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4991T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Karankawa Indians stopped from destruction of cattle. Has made a flag, which he describes</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Port of Goliad</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="10-27-1835">Oct. 27th 1835</date_mentioned></p>
<p>9 o. c. in the morning.</p>
<p>To <person_mentioned>Gen. S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Com. in Ch. of the Army of the People</person_mentioned>,</p>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>Yours of the <date_mentioned n="10-23-1835">23d</date_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>exs</person_mentioned>. [express] by hand of <person_mentioned>Mr. Bracken</person_mentioned>, was duly
recd, <date_mentioned n="10-26-1835">last evening</date_mentioned> The information it gives is both cheering and 
stimulating. But whilst our mutual congratulations are called for by a 
rhetrospect of the past, whilst we indulge bright visions of the future, permit me
to express to yourself, the lively sympathy felt by every one here, for their
fellows, suffering so many privations, whilst contending for their rights.
We have done, are doing, and shall continue to do, every thing in our
power, to supply your wants, and diminish your privations—</p>

<p>It was confidently anticipated when <person_mentioned>Majr. Collinsworth</person_mentioned> left for your
<location_mentioned>camp</location_mentioned>, that, the teams could have been put in motion <date_mentioned n="10-26-1835">yesterday</date_mentioned>—but we
found it impossible. The teams and carts below, and especially those at
the <location_mentioned>Mission</location_mentioned>, had been sent to <location_mentioned>Guardeloupe </location_mentioned>with the <location_mentioned>women </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>children</location_mentioned>;
and we have had to send there for them. However, we have succeeded in
mustering 8 carts and waggons—all of which, will be dispatched today,
with full freight, and the corresponding List transmitted by hand of <person_mentioned>Maj.
Southerland</person_mentioned>, the <person_mentioned>Bearer </person_mentioned>of this letter.</p><barker_pb n="214"/>

<p>I much regret that it becomes my duty to inform you, that, the report of
<person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Toole </person_mentioned>having been dispatched <person_mentioned>prisoners of war</person_mentioned> to 
<person_mentioned>Matamoros</person_mentioned>, from the <location_mentioned>Garrison of Le Panteclan</location_mentioned>, is now but too well confirmed,
to admit of a doubt. They were sent off, a <date_mentioned n="10-18-1835">week ago last Sunday</date_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Toole</person_mentioned>
was in very bad health, and in preference to transportation to a distant 
<location_mentioned>dungeon</location_mentioned>, there to linger out a mere fragment of existence, requested that he
might be dispatched at once. The confirmation of this news, after the lenity
shown to the <person_mentioned>prisoners </person_mentioned>taken here, could not fail to create a lively, and a
strong excitement.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>men under my command</person_mentioned> are clamorous for retaliation, either by
clothing with suits of iron, those in <hi rend="italic">our</hi> power; or by marching immediately
against the <location_mentioned>garrison</location_mentioned>, and reducing it to unconditional submission, or 
putting it to the sword.</p>

<p>I have had a <hi rend="italic">flag </hi>made—the colours, and their arrangement the same
as the old one—with the words and figures, "Constitution of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date_mentioned>," 
displayed on the <hi rend="italic">white</hi>, in the centre.</p>

<p>Regular rations of flour, sugar and Coffee, have been ordered to be issued
to the <person_mentioned>poor</person_mentioned>, of the <person_mentioned>families from the <location_mentioned>Mission at Guardeloupe</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Measures are taken to procure the earliest information of any important
occurrence at <location_mentioned>Copano</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I have great satisfaction in communicating the intelligence of our having
succeeded in calling the <person_mentioned>Karankawa Indians</person_mentioned> in from the work of 
destruction which they had commenced among the stock, on the <location_mentioned>Navidad </location_mentioned>and
<location_mentioned>Guardeloupe</location_mentioned>. We have engaged them to remain neutral during the present
contest, and to retire to the <location_mentioned>Banks of the Sn. Antonio</location_mentioned>, till the pleasure of
the <person_mentioned>Com. in Ch.</person_mentioned> shall have been communicated to them, in such manner as
he may dictate. I enclose herewith for your perusal and gratification, 
several letters from <location_mentioned>Monterey</location_mentioned>, and an anonymous paper by<person_mentioned> Dr. Grant</person_mentioned>, to the
<person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>; all delivered to me <date_mentioned n="10-26-1835">last evening</date_mentioned>, by <person_mentioned>Sen Jose Abendano</person_mentioned>,
of that City. The earliest intelligence of every thing important with you,
will greatly releive, and oblige, Sir,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>P. Dimitt Comd </person_mentioned>[Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <hi rend="italic">No. 1.</hi> To <person_mentioned>Gen. S. F. Austin Com. in Ch. of the Army of
the People</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Head Quarters</location_mentioned>.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
