
<TEI.2 id="APB4718">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>01-15-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 39-40</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>James F. Perry</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Lastraps and Desmare</document_recipient>
<document_title>James F. Perry to Lastraps and Desmare, 01-15-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Peach Point, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Loss of goods on vessel. Insurance. Cotton crop </barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 39-40</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>02-16-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB4718T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Loss of goods on vessel. Insurance. Cotton crop </p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Peach Point Near Brazoria Texas</location_mentioned></p>
<p><date_mentioned n="01-15-1835">Jany 15th 1835</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Messrs. Lastraps and Desmare [New Orleans]</person_mentioned></p>
<p>Gentlen</p>

<p>Your Favour of <date_mentioned n="11-28-1834">28th Nov</date_mentioned> enclosing bills of articles shipd- pr Schooner
Helin Mar, was duely recieved and you have no doubt been informed of the
fate of that vessel, the vessel and cargo was all most a total loss, the
greater part of the Goods which came to shore was stolen the articles sent
to me were all lost I beleave except 11 BB1 Flour and 1 do Mackeral. A
<person_mentioned>Mr. Andrews</person_mentioned> will inform you more particularly; who will forward you
the necessary vouchers to recover the insurance I hope they were inshured.
having but lately commenced opening a <location_mentioned>farm </location_mentioned>I had put Little land in
cotton last season and the worm distroyed the greater part of that Little
as well as all the cotton in my <location_mentioned>emedeate neigbourhood</location_mentioned>. there was scarce
one third of a crop made. It was my intention to have shiped you what
Little I made but on enquiry I found unless the dueties amounted to 200$
the money would have to be paid to the <person_mentioned>collector</person_mentioned>: I concluded it would
be more trouble to you than proffit and I got one of my <person_mentioned>neighbours </person_mentioned>to
ship it with his crop it went up in the S[chooner] Brazoria and sold for
16c. It was some disapointment the loss of the articles you sent me. but
I hope you will recover the inshurance on them. The cotton crops in this
county was verry fine with the Exception of some 5 or 6 <location_mentioned>plan[ta]tions</location_mentioned> in<barker_pb n="40"/>
my <location_mentioned>neighbourhood </location_mentioned>which was destroyed by the worm since <date_mentioned n="03-xx-1834">last march</date_mentioned>
we have generally and verry fine wether the <date_mentioned n="Fall-1834">fall </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="Winter-1834">winter </date_mentioned>so
far has been verry much pleasant and dry. <person_mentioned>Mr. Somervell</person_mentioned> returned
from <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned> in the <location_mentioned>San Felepe</location_mentioned> in <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1834">nov</date_mentioned>. but I am sorry to say that he
has not got near all his goods to <location_mentioned>San Felepe</location_mentioned> yet. he might have got them
up in the steapi[boat] Cayuga which went up but his <person_mentioned>partner </person_mentioned>was not 
willing to risk it. The boat however got up without any accident he tarryed
at least one month too long in <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned> for his benefit please inform me
whether you have recovered the inshurance on the Empress also the lost
on the Helin Mar</p>

<p><person_mentioned>J F Perry</person_mentioned> [Rubric]</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
