
<TEI.2 id="APB5059">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-02-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 265-267</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>William H Wharton</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Branch T Archer</document_recipient>
<document_title>William H Wharton to Branch T Archer, 12-02-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Declining mission to United States because he believes nothing short of a declaration of independence by the Texans will get aid from the United States</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From a broadside.  Wharton subsequently changed his mind and accepted the appointment.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 265-267</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-15-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5059T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Declining mission to United States because he believes nothing short of a declaration of independence by the Texans will get aid from the United States</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>To the <person_mentioned>Editors of the Telegraph</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Gentlemen,</p>

<p>I herewith transmit to you, for publication, a copy of an official letter
which I addressed to <person_mentioned>Wm. H. Wharton</person_mentioned>, together with his answer. 
Inasmuch as the latter contains matter worthy of general consideration, I hope
you will lay it before the <person_mentioned>public</person_mentioned>, without delay.</p>

<p>Very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>B. T. Archer</person_mentioned></p>

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="12-02-1835">December 2, 1834 [1835]</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p><location_mentioned>Convention Hall, San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned>,</p>

<p><date_mentioned n="11-13-1835">Nov. 13, 1833 [1835]</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mr. Wm. H. Wharton</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Sir,—By a resolution of the <person_mentioned>Consultation of the chosen Delegates of all
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, in <person_mentioned>General Convention</person_mentioned> assembled, it was made the duty of its 
<person_mentioned>president </person_mentioned>to inform you that you are elected by that body, a <person_mentioned>commissioner to
the <location_mentioned>United States of the North</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, to act under the advice and instruction of
the <person_mentioned>Provisional Government</person_mentioned>; and that you be requested, as speedily as is<barker_pb n="266"/>
convenient to report your acceptance or refusal to the <person_mentioned>Governor of the
Council</person_mentioned>, that your commission and the proper instructions be given to you,</p>

<p>Your obedient servant,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>B. T. Archer, President</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>P. B. Dexter, Sec'ry</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>B. T. Archer, Esq., President of the Convention</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Sir,—In answer to your letter announcing my election by the 
<person_mentioned>Convention</person_mentioned>, as <person_mentioned>commissioner to the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, I have to say, that, under 
existing circumstances, I decline the appointment. The declaration of the 
<person_mentioned>Convention</person_mentioned>, and the attitude assumed by that body, appear to me to be too
indefinite to induce <person_mentioned>foreign governments</person_mentioned> or <person_mentioned>capitalists </person_mentioned>to lend us their aid,
either of a pecuniary or other nature. Understand me; I do not blame the
<person_mentioned>Convention </person_mentioned>for their declaration. They were not empowered, as I 
conceive, to make any other. A declaration of independence was not in the
contemplation of those who elected them. It was thought, and I, among
others thought, that a declaration in favor of the federal Constitution of
<date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date_mentioned> would be the most prudent and politic course that could be pursued
by the <person_mentioned>Convention</person_mentioned>. It was thought that such a course would neutralize, or
enlist the sympathies and assistance of the <person_mentioned>federal party of the <location_mentioned>Interior</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> in
our favor; and also that, under such declaration, we could obtain the 
requisite loans etc. etc., from the <person_mentioned>capitalists of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. Of late, I
have been forced to conclude that <person_mentioned>both parties of the <location_mentioned>Interior</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> will unite
against us, whatever be our declaration, believing, or pretending to believe
it an attack upon the "integrity of the republic." And moreover, I believe,
under any declaration short of absolute independence, we will receive no
efficient or permanent aid, or pecuniary assistance, from the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>,
they believing it an internal domestic quarrel, about which they feel but
little interest. So that, situated as we are, we encounter all the evils of a
declaration of independence, without reaping one tenth of the advantages
of such declaration.</p>

<p>Again, many honestly differ in regard to the power of the <person_mentioned>late 
Convention</person_mentioned>. Some believe them to have been purely recommendatory Others say
that not one fifth of the people voted for <person_mentioned>representatives</person_mentioned>, not anticipating
the present crisis; and various others find various other objections. We
know mankind well enough to know that every cavil, objection, or cause
of excitement will be greedily embraced, magnified, and circulated, for the
purpose of poisoning and prejudicing the public mind, which would be a
result that could not be too much avoided and deprecated, in our present
infant and unorganized condition.</p>

<p>Those, of course, acting with authority from a <person_mentioned>body of dubious powers</person_mentioned>,
would necessarily have a delicate and difficult task to perform We truly,<barker_pb n="267"/>
do as we will, "walk upon fires covered with deceitful ashes." In order
to obviate these efvils, and give universal satisfaction, I would respectfully
suggest that the present Provisional Governor immediately order an 
election throughout Texas, 0n the <date_mentioned n="01-01-1836">1st of January</date_mentioned>, for <person_mentioned>members to a Convention</person_mentioned>,
to meet on the <date_mentioned n="01-15-1836">15th of the same month</date_mentioned>. Let it be fully announced, that this
Convention is called to ascertain the will of the <person_mentioned>majority</person_mentioned>, in regard to a
declaration of independence, to sell the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>to the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>, if 
practicable and desirable, to form a constitution for <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, to take prompt
measures to prosecute the present war with vigor, to fix the <location_mentioned>seat of 
government</location_mentioned>, and also the <location_mentioned>seats of justices</location_mentioned> for the different <location_mentioned>municipalities</location_mentioned>, to 
appoint a <person_mentioned>board of commissioners</person_mentioned> to adjudicate and settle our land titles on
a solid and secure basis, to resolve themselves into a <person_mentioned>legislature</person_mentioned>, if 
necessary; in short, let it be clearly understood, that this <person_mentioned>Convention </person_mentioned>will meet
to do whatever, in their opinion, the good of the country requires, and
that they exercise all the powers which the people themselves possess in
their radical and original capacity. In this way, the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> will
vote wirh their eyes open; the will of the <person_mentioned>majority </person_mentioned>will be clearly 
ascertained and carried into effect, which, in my estimation, will redound much
indeed to the prosperity and quiet of our adopted, and at present 
disorganized and distracted country.</p>

<p>Allow me to assure you that the course herein recommended would
meet the views of a great <person_mentioned>majority of the army</person_mentioned>, and also of those <person_mentioned>citizens</person_mentioned>
with whom I have met since my return from <location_mentioned>camp</location_mentioned>. A conscientious 
conviction of the importance, correctness, and indeed indispensability of it,
induces me to decline acting as <person_mentioned>commissioner</person_mentioned>, under present circumstances.
I understand that arrangements have been made to borrow one hundred
thousand dollars, which, with the other aid in the power of the <person_mentioned>Governor</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>Council </person_mentioned>to bestow, will be amply sufficient to sustain the <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned>, and
provide for all other emergencies, until a new <person_mentioned>Convention </person_mentioned>can meet. In
conclusion, allow me to say, that I believe the sustaining of the present <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned>
is more important than every thing else put together; and that I hope and
recommend that no pains be spared to give them all the comfort and 
support within the powers of the <person_mentioned>provisional government</person_mentioned>. A belief of the
importance of sustaining the army, will induce me to return to it 
immediately, with all the recruits I can possibly muster.</p>

<p>Very respecfully yours,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Wm. H. Wharton</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>P. S. The <person_mentioned>army </person_mentioned>is much in want of coffee, sugar, flour, tobacco, 
clothing, etc., and if not furnished as soon as possible, great and just 
dissatisfaction will ensue.</p>

<p>Please communicate as much of this as is necessary, to the <person_mentioned>Provisional
Governor</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Council</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p><date_mentioned n="11-26-1835">November 26, 1835</date_mentioned>.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
