
<TEI.2 id="APB5169">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>05-04-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 344-348</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Senator L F Linn</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Senator L F Linn, 05-04-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New York, New York</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Appealing for aid for Texas from the United States.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From the <hi rend="italic">St. Louis Commercial Bulletin</hi>, June 3, 1836, in Collections of the Wisconsin Historical Society. The <hi rend="italic">Bulletin </hi>gives credit to the<hi rend="italic"> Baltimore Republican</hi> for the letter. Linn was United States Senator from Missouri.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 344-348</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-01-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5169T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Appealing for aid for Texas from the United States.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="05-04-1836">May 4, 1836</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Hon. L. F. Linn</person_mentioned>:</p>

<p>Dear Sir:</p>

<p>Yours of <date_mentioned n="05-01-1836">1st. instant</date_mentioned> I received to-day on my return from <location_mentioned>Philadelphia</location_mentioned>,
(where I went, at the solicitation of a <person_mentioned>committee </person_mentioned>from there,) in 
conjunction with my <person_mentioned>colleagues</person_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Archer </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Wharton</location_mentioned>, to attend a <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>meeting
on the <date_mentioned n="05-02-1836">2d</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I presume you have seen in the <location_mentioned>Philadelphia papers</location_mentioned> the result of the
meeting— (see the <location_mentioned>Pennsylvania Inquirer</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>U. S. Gazette,</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Ledger</location_mentioned>, etc.) It
was very enthusiastic and ardent in the cause of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and was held in a<barker_pb n="345"/>
<location_mentioned>wing of that Temple of Liberty</location_mentioned> where, in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1776">'76</date_mentioned>, those principles were 
proclaimed which have ever since been a beacon-light to the benighted and
enslaved of <location_mentioned>all nations</location_mentioned>. The <hi rend="italic">spirit </hi>of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1776">'76</date_mentioned> was there. <hi rend="italic">That </hi>spirit, and <hi rend="italic">hearts</hi>
of the vast multitude, told them what to do. No cold or selfish influence of
policy or of party cast its chilling breath over that meeting.</p>

<p>You ask me what can be done in favor of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>? Ask your heart, my
<person_mentioned>friend </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>fellow-citizen</person_mentioned>, (for such you are in feeling, although an 
invisible line separates our domicils— ask the noble spirit of your and my
<person_mentioned>fathers</person_mentioned>— ask every <person_mentioned>freeman</person_mentioned>, every <person_mentioned>philanthropist on earth</person_mentioned>— ask every man
<hi rend="italic">who is not a <person_mentioned>politician</person_mentioned></hi>, and who acts from the warm and honest impulses
of a patriotic heart, and you will receive a satisfactory answer.</p>

<p>A war of extermination is raging in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—a war of barbarism and of
despotic principles, waged by the <person_mentioned>mongrel Spanish-Indian</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Negro </person_mentioned>race,
against civilization and the <person_mentioned>Anglo-American</person_mentioned> race.</p>

<p>For fifteen years I have been laboring like a slave to <hi rend="italic">Americanize</hi>
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—to form a nucleus around which my <person_mentioned>native countrymen</person_mentioned> could 
collect and grow into a solid body that would forever be a barrier of safety
to the <location_mentioned>southwestern frontier</location_mentioned>, and especially to the outlet of the <location_mentioned>western
world</location_mentioned>—the <location_mentioned>mouth of the Mississippi</location_mentioned>—and which would be a beacon-light
to the <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>in their search after liberty.</p>

<p>But the <person_mentioned>Anglo-American</person_mentioned> foundation, this nucleus of republicanism, is to
be broken up, and its place supplied by a population of <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Mexicans</person_mentioned>,
and <person_mentioned>renegadoes</person_mentioned>, all mixed together, and all the natural enemies of white
men and civilization.</p>

<p>What I have been the means of effecting towards the Americanism of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, is of more real service to the protection of <location_mentioned>Louisiana</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Arkansas</location_mentioned>, and
<location_mentioned>Missouri</location_mentioned>, than the expenditure of <hi rend="italic">thirty millions of dollars</hi> on the 
fortifications of that <location_mentioned>frontier</location_mentioned>; yes, more than a standing army of <person_mentioned>10,000 men
</person_mentioned>there would be; and yet it is to be broken up, because the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
have too much of the spirit of their fathers to lay down beneath the feet of
military despotism, and debase and damn their blood and their education;
it is to be broken up, because it will not do for the <person_mentioned><location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> 
government</person_mentioned> to interfere with a usurper, a base, unprincipled, bloody monster,
who sets the laws of civilization and of humanity at defiance, who 
desolates <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>under the bloody flag of a <person_mentioned>pirate</person_mentioned>, and whose avowed intention
is to excite the <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>negroes</person_mentioned>, and crimson the waters of the 
<location_mentioned>Mississippi</location_mentioned>, and make it the eastern boundary of Mexico, (for such an intention
has been avowed.) No. This <person_mentioned>monster </person_mentioned>cannot be interfered with, because
a treaty was made with the <location_mentioned>federal republic of Mexico</location_mentioned>, <hi rend="italic">which republic no
longer exists.</hi></p>

<p>Oh! spirit of our fathers, where are you? Just and omnipotent God,
where is thy influence? Where is the fatherly care and protection of a wise<barker_pb n="346"/>
and watchful government that applies <hi rend="italic">cheap </hi>and <hi rend="italic">prompt </hi>preventives 
beforehand, in preference to the expenditure of <hi rend="italic">millions </hi>for remedies, after an
evil has occurred?</p>

<p>But you ask, What <hi rend="italic">preventive </hi>can be applied? The answer is plain—Let
an <person_mentioned>army of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> march into <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and say to the pirate <person_mentioned>Santa
Anna</person_mentioned>, "Stop:" a great and philanthropic and <person_mentioned>free people</person_mentioned> will not stand
tamely by and see justice, constitutional right, and humanity, wantonly
violated at her door—nor can a paternal government tolerate a state of
things on its most vulnerable and important <location_mentioned>frontier</location_mentioned>, that will, and <hi rend="italic">must</hi>
bring the bloody tide of savage war and the horrors of <person_mentioned>negro </person_mentioned>insurrection
within its limits.</p>

<p>It is madness and folly—it is deceiving yourselves and your constituents
to believe that the <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>war is not a war of extermination against 
<hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Anglo-Americans</person_mentioned></hi> and <hi rend="italic">their principles</hi> and <hi rend="italic">interests</hi>. The <person_mentioned>republican party in
<location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> are now subdued and crushed: they, by their own acts and 
misplaced confidence in <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned>, have put the sword into <hi rend="italic">his </hi>hands to cut
their own throats. He has acquired all his power by deceiving the <person_mentioned>federal
republican party of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and by making blind instruments of them. He
is now continuing the same policy, for he has united all the influence and
resources of <hi rend="italic">that party</hi> against <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. <hi rend="italic">He </hi>and the <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>monarchial party</person_mentioned></hi> now in
power, who have overturned the federal constitution of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1834">1824</date_mentioned>, know very well
that to expect any thing like tranquility, or even comparative security in the
enjoyment of their usurpations, they must keep out <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Anglo-American </person_mentioned>
republicanism</hi>, and stop the <hi rend="italic">moral invasion</hi> that was spreading over the <location_mentioned>eastern
and internal states (now military provinces) of Mexico</location_mentioned>. How is this to be
done? By exterminating the <person_mentioned>American population in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and filling that
country with <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>negroes</person_mentioned>, who (as he thinks) will form an 
impenetrable barrier from the <location_mentioned>Sabine river</location_mentioned> to the <location_mentioned>Rio del Norte</location_mentioned>, and thus restore
the old Spanish policy, which was <hi rend="italic">"to prevent even a bird from crossing
the <location_mentioned>Sabine river</location_mentioned> if possible"</hi></p>

<p>And the <person_mentioned><location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> Government</person_mentioned> are to stand by with its hands folded,
over <hi rend="italic">scruples </hi>about interposing in the holy cause of humanity, philanthropy,
of liberty, and of protection to its own exposed <location_mentioned>frontier</location_mentioned>! Oh! I cannot—do
not—will not believe it. Of one thing <hi rend="italic">I am certain</hi>, the people, the <person_mentioned>freemen
of this <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, <hi rend="italic">will not</hi> permit, nor will they tolerate the barbarities and
usurpations of a <person_mentioned>Mexican tyrant</person_mentioned>. No—they will obey the dictates of their
hearts, and fly to the rescue of their <person_mentioned>countrymen </person_mentioned>and of free principles.
They will, of their own accord, save the bulwark of the whole <location_mentioned>Southwestern
frontier</location_mentioned>, and <location_mentioned>Arkansas </location_mentioned>from the greatest peril that has ever threatened any
portion of the <location_mentioned>United States territory</location_mentioned> since it became a nation. I do not
mean the peril of <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>invasion—it would be an insult to the <person_mentioned>people of
the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to <hi rend="italic">call </hi>that a peril— I mean the peril of an <person_mentioned>Indian </person_mentioned>and<barker_pb n="347"/>
servile war—the murder of <person_mentioned>women </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>children</person_mentioned>, and the loss to civilization (at least for some time) of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I have seen the communication you speak of in the ****. That 
<location_mentioned>newspaper </location_mentioned>seems to lean towards scruples, or party interests, or perhaps to 
<person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>influence. I do not read or look at any papers of that character. I am,
however, willing to believe that they do not properly understand the 
ORIGIN, PRINCIPLES and OBJECTS of the <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>war, and are acting under
<hi rend="italic">Mistaken views,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">not from want of principle, or even the common 
impulses of justice and humanity.</hi></p>

<p>I must, however, say that it looks very badly for men to condemn a whole
people who are struggling for <hi rend="italic">self-preservation</hi>, before they understand the
subject, and analyze it sufficiently to judge of its Moral as well as Political
merits.</p>

<p>Let such men take up the history of <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>misrule in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and all
over <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>; let them inquire into the present state of things in that 
important nation; let them ascertain whether the present consolidated 
despotism which exists there, has or has not been established by <hi rend="italic">revolutionary
means</hi>, by <hi rend="italic">force, fraud,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">violence</hi>; whether the federal social compact of
<location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, to which the <person_mentioned>People of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> bound their allegiance, is not illegally
dissolved; whether the <person_mentioned>People of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> did or did not oppose this illegal
dissolution of their <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>, as they were bound by their oaths to do,
and whether they did not grimly adhere to THEIR duty and obligations as
<person_mentioned>Mexican citizens</person_mentioned>, under the Constitution, so long as it existed. Let them
read an exposition of the <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>war, made by me at <location_mentioned>Louisville, Kentucky</location_mentioned>,
on <date_mentioned n="03-07-1836">7th March last</date_mentioned>, that made in this city by <person_mentioned>W. H. Wharton, Esq</person_mentioned>. on the
<date_mentioned n="04-26-1836">26th ult</date_mentioned>. and other documents on this subject. In short, let them 
<hi rend="italic">understand</hi> the question, before they attempt to approve or condemn, and I am
confident they can form but ONE OPINION, which is, that the <person_mentioned>Texians </person_mentioned>are
RIGHT, and that under similar circumstances all <person_mentioned>freemen </person_mentioned>ought to, and
would have done as they have.</p>

<p>An expression of opinion in <person_mentioned>Congress</person_mentioned>, or by the Executive favorable to
<hi rend="italic">the cause of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></hi>, would settle this matter and end this war; it would be a
<hi rend="italic">preventive </hi>which will cost nothing, and violate no treaty or other obligation,
no more than the Greek Revolution did; <hi rend="italic">and it will save the expenditure of
millions hereafter, and the loss of thousands of lives.</hi> It will do this, 
because such an expression of opinion would inspire confidence, and thus open
the ice-bound chests of <person_mentioned>money lenders</person_mentioned>, and enable <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to procure funds.
Men she can get in thousands. The <location_mentioned>chivalrous <hi rend="italic">West</hi></location_mentioned>, and the <location_mentioned>warm-hearted,
high-souled <hi rend="italic">South </hi></location_mentioned>will furnish them; but they must be fed and provided
with arms and ammunition, etc.</p>

<p>Pardon me for occupying so much of your time by so long a letter; my
heart and soul, my all, and, as I think, the best interests of my <location_mentioned>native 
country</location_mentioned>, and the great principles of liberty, are deeply involved in this subject.<barker_pb n="348"/>
I have, in times past, had more kind and charitable feelings for the 
<person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>in general, and have been much more faithful to them than they
merited. I acted from a sound and honest principle—that of mutually 
benefiting my native and <location_mentioned>adopted country</location_mentioned>, by <hi rend="italic">Americanizing </hi><location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and securing
to liberal principles in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>a <hi rend="italic">support </hi>and a <hi rend="italic">guide </hi>in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and at the
same time serving my native country by a population there, that would 
harmonize with their neighbors. But sad and dear bought experience has 
convincd me that it is in vain to hope for any good from <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>institutions,
or <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>justice. I am, therefore,<hi rend="italic"> for the independence of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></hi>, and I
am so from the soundest principles that move the human heart—those of
<hi rend="italic">liberty, justice, humanity</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">self-preservation</hi>.</p>

<p>Respectfully, your most obedient servant,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned>.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
