
<TEI.2 id="APB5131">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>02-22-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 316-317</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Thomas F McKinney</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Thomas F McKinney to Stephen F Austin, 02-22-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Orleans, Louisiana</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Cannot follow Austin in support of independence. Has lost all confidence in him</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>The blank is McKinney's.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 316-317</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-27-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5131T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Cannot follow Austin in support of independence. Has lost all confidence in him</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="02-22-1836">Feby 22nd. 1836</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Col S. F. Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned></p>

<p>Dr. Sir</p>

<p>I have intended answering your letter to me from <location_mentioned>N. Orleans</location_mentioned> but have
realy been at a loss how to begin finding from circumstances which I will
satisfactorily or at least clearly explain to you if ever again we should<barker_pb n="317"/>
meet that you and I must sever totaly in any thing of a political character
and having always shown to you my partialities for you and your opinions
from my conduct toward you I shall be equaly frank in saying to you that
my confidence in you is I think for ever at an end I am not your <person_mentioned>enemy</person_mentioned>
and trust never will be but at the same time I am now fully convinced
that you can not be any thing else but an injury to your <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>where
you have influence. I have warned you of dangers which were preparing
for you but shall never again raise my voice in your defence or warn you
of any thing which may come to my knowledge against you If you are
ruined it shall not be my fault nor will I ever be found to take any part in
your fate or your fortune all the diffculty I have ever had in that 
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>has been on your account. I do not intend to say you are dishonest
no Sir but you are from your nature useless in any thing like a public
capacity and your illusions and remarks in that letter to me from <location_mentioned>N.
Orleans</location_mentioned> are_____</p>

<p>You will verry probably find yourself unsustained in your pledges for
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>declaring Independence</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Thos. F McKinney</person_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
