
<TEI.2 id="APB5065">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-03-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 275-279</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>D C Barrett</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to D C Barrett, 12-03-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Strong statement of reasons for calling a new convention</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>This is from a printed copy in <hi rend="italic">The Telegraph and Texas Register.</hi> There is in
the collection an autograph draft of most of the letter.
Thomas Jefferson Chambers.
See "Land Speculation as a Cause of the Texas Revolution," by the editor, in
<hi rend="italic">Quarterly </hi>of the Texas State Historical Association, X, 76—95.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 275-279</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-25-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5065T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Strong statement of reasons for calling a new convention</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="12-03-1835">Dec. 3, 1835</date_mentioned>.</p>
<p>To <person_mentioned>D. C. Barrett, Esq.</person_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>I have just received your note of <date_mentioned n="12-03-1835">this date</date_mentioned>, in which you request my
opinion, as to calling a convention, without delay, on the plan of equality
of representation, as nearly as practicable.</p>

<p>In two communications, which I have made to the <person_mentioned>provisional 
government</person_mentioned>, under date <date_mentioned n="10-30-1835">30th ult</date_mentioned>. and <date_mentioned n="12-02-1835">2d inst</date_mentioned>., I took a view of the present political
situation of the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, which has a close connection with the subject of
your enquiry. I refer you to them, as those communications were of an
official character; the object of which was to state facts, as I understood<barker_pb n="276"/>
them. I gave no opinion as to <hi rend="italic">when </hi>the convention should be called, 
believing it to be more proper to leave the <person_mentioned>provisional government</person_mentioned> to draw
its own conclusions.</p>

<p>The present communication is of a different character: I am directly
called upon to give an opinion. I should comply with this request with
great diffidence, did I not believe that the prudence and better judgment of
the <person_mentioned>council </person_mentioned>(to which you say it will be submitted by you, as <person_mentioned>chairman of
the committee</person_mentioned> on state affairs,) will detect any inacuracies or false 
positions it may contain.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>general consultation of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> was elected at a time when the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>
was distracted by popular excitements, produced by the diversity of 
opinions which naturally resulted from the disbelief of some that the federal
system would be destroyed, or was even attacked, the excited and 
intemperate zeal of others, and the general want of certain information in all.
It could not be reasonably expected that a body elected under such 
circumstances, would be entirely free from the conflicting opinions that prevailed
amongst their <person_mentioned>constituents</person_mentioned>, or that a clear and positively definite position
would be taken by it. The <person_mentioned>majority of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, so far as an opinion can be
formed, from the acts of the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>at their primary meetings, was 
decidedly in favor of declaring in positive, clear and unequivocal terms, for
the federal constitution of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date_mentioned>, and for the organization of <person_mentioned>local 
government</person_mentioned>, either as a <location_mentioned>state of the Mexican confederation</location_mentioned>, or provisionally, until
the <person_mentioned>authorities of the <location_mentioned>state of Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> could be restored. This
measure was absolutely necessary to save the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>from anarchy; for it
was left without any government at all, owing to the dispersion and 
imprisonment of the <person_mentioned>executive</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>legislative authorities</person_mentioned>, by the 
unconstitutional intervention of the <person_mentioned>military power</person_mentioned>. Some <person_mentioned>individuals </person_mentioned>were also in
favor of independence, though no public meeting whose proceedings I have
seen, expressed such an idea.</p>

<p>We have seen the consequence of these conflicting opinions, in the 
declaration made by the <person_mentioned>consultation</person_mentioned>, on the <date_mentioned n="11-07-1835">7th of the last month</date_mentioned>. It is not 
entirely positive and definite in its character. Whether or not the crisis in
which <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>is now placed, can be met and sufficiently provided for, by a
position which admits of construction in its application, is a matter of
opinion; as for myself, I believe it cannot.</p>

<p>The character of the struggle in which <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>is engaged, is now clearly
developed; it evidently is one of life or death, "to be, or not to be." It is
no longer a mere question about the forms of political institutions; it is
one of self-preservation. <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>is menaced with a war of extermination:
the <person_mentioned>government of Mexico</person_mentioned> has so proclaimed it. The <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>now 
understand their situation, and consequently are much better prepared to elect
<person_mentioned>public agents</person_mentioned> to provide against such a danger, than they were at the time<barker_pb n="277"/>
of the last election. At that time the form of government was not changed
by any act which had the influence or the character of law; it now is by
the decree of the <date_mentioned n="10-03-1835">3rd of October last</date_mentioned>. At that time the <person_mentioned>state government </person_mentioned>
existed; at this, no such thing as a state exists, not even in name. The decree
of the <date_mentioned n="10-03-1835">3rd of October</date_mentioned> has converted them into <hi rend="italic">departments</hi>, without any
legislative powers whatever, and entirely subject to the orders of the 
<person_mentioned>president </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>central government in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Again, the representation in the <person_mentioned>consultation </person_mentioned>was very unequal, a 
principle that should be cautiously avoided, so far as practicable, in a body
that is to settle the political destinies of a <location_mentioned>community </location_mentioned>where all are equally
interested.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>consultation</person_mentioned>, foreseeing that such a crisis as the present might 
arrive, has very wisely provided for the calling a convention by the 
<person_mentioned>provisional government</person_mentioned>; and I am clearly of opinion it ought to be done with
the least possible delay.</p>

<p>Another weighty reason in favor, is that the <location_mentioned>world </location_mentioned>are not yet sufficiently
informed or enlightened on the causes or the merits of the present conflict.
The <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> have been, and now are accused of being ungrateful
<person_mentioned>rebels</person_mentioned>, who have repaid the favors and bounties of the <location_mentioned>nation </location_mentioned>with 
ingratitude and rebellion. This accusation is unfounded and unjust. That 
<person_mentioned>individuals </person_mentioned>have committed imprudences and even excesses, and by so doing,
have injured the character and the best interests of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, by giving a 
pretext to our <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>to confound the whole of the people with those 
<person_mentioned>individuals </person_mentioned>may be true; but when the causes of such excesses are sought for,
they will be found to have proceeded from bad government, bad legislation,
bad administration, or no government at all. Is this the fault of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>?
Whenever the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>here have tried to get a local organization of 
government, in order to correct and punish such excesses, they have been treated
as <person_mentioned>rebels</person_mentioned>; so that the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>are denounced because the want of <person_mentioned>local 
government</person_mentioned> produces anarchy; and when ever they attempt to apply a remedy,
they are treated as ungrateful <person_mentioned>rebels</person_mentioned>! This <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>has been redeemed
from the <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>by the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>who now live in it, and without any cost
to the <person_mentioned>general government</person_mentioned> or to the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>. The <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>were stimulated to
persevere and to overcome the most appalling difficulties, by the express
guarantees of a liberal system of government, and of the right of 
self-government in their internal affairs, as a <location_mentioned>state of the Mexican confederation</location_mentioned>.
The <location_mentioned>lands </location_mentioned>thus received were granted and sold by the <location_mentioned>state of Coahuila and
Texas</location_mentioned>, and not by the <person_mentioned>general government</person_mentioned>, (except a few <location_mentioned>old grants</location_mentioned>, 
previous to the establishment of the federal system) ; and it is worthy of notice,
that one of the crimes attributed to the <person_mentioned>authorities of <location_mentioned>Coahuila and Texas
</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>by the <person_mentioned>general government</person_mentioned>, as justification for its military intervention, was
a granting of their <location_mentioned>lands</location_mentioned>; and yet the <person_mentioned>general government</person_mentioned> claims all the<barker_pb n="278"/>
merit of having given them away to the <person_mentioned>Texians</person_mentioned>! These <location_mentioned>lands </location_mentioned>and this
<location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, at the commencement of the <location_mentioned>settlement</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1821">fourteen years ago</date_mentioned>, were
valueless, and so considered by the <person_mentioned>general government</person_mentioned>, they became the sole
property of the <location_mentioned>state of Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned>, and the <location_mentioned>state </location_mentioned>alone had the
power to dispose of them. The <person_mentioned>state authorities</person_mentioned> have always considered
them to be valueless; a proof of which is the manner in which they have
been disposed of, given away for nothing to <person_mentioned>native Mexicans</person_mentioned>, in <location_mentioned>eleven
league tracts</location_mentioned>, and sold to them and to the <person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>(for all the land 
acquired by <person_mentioned>foreign settlers</person_mentioned> was sold to them by the <location_mentioned>state</location_mentioned>,) at from thirty to
one hundred dollars per <location_mentioned>square league</location_mentioned>. In 1833, <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>thirty square leagues</location_mentioned> of
</hi>land were voted by the late <person_mentioned>legislators</person_mentioned>, to a young man (who had previously
received a grant of <location_mentioned>eleven leagues</location_mentioned>), as pay for <hi rend="italic">one years salary, for his
services</hi> as <person_mentioned>judge</person_mentioned>! Some <location_mentioned>eight hundred square leagues</location_mentioned> were sold by these
<person_mentioned>legislators</person_mentioned>, in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1834">1834 </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1835">1835</date_mentioned>, to <person_mentioned>speculators</person_mentioned>, principally <person_mentioned>foreigners</person_mentioned>, and to
themselves; for the same <person_mentioned>legislators </person_mentioned>who passed the law for a part of this
sale, were <person_mentioned>purchasers</person_mentioned>, at from about fifty to seventy-five and a hundred
dollars per <location_mentioned>square league</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>It is not my intention to cast any censure on the <person_mentioned>legislators of <location_mentioned>Coahuila</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>,
or on the <person_mentioned>individuals </person_mentioned>who purchased; the object of the former was to raise
funds out of the sale of <location_mentioned>Texas lands</location_mentioned>, to replenish the state treasure which
was empty—the latter were <person_mentioned>speculators</person_mentioned>, whose object was to take 
advantage of any law or circumstance that favored their views. I have 
mentioned this subject to prove more clearly the fact that all the legislation of
both <person_mentioned>general and state governments</person_mentioned>, on the subject of <location_mentioned>Texas lands</location_mentioned>, has
been based on the full belief that they were <hi rend="italic">valueless</hi>, and that the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>
and the <location_mentioned>state </location_mentioned>were great gainers by getting this <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>settled, so as to
have a barrier against <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>, without any cost whatever to the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, on
the contrary, with the gain of from thirty to one hundred dollars per <location_mentioned>square
league</location_mentioned>. There never has been any kind of organization in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, that
merits even the <hi rend="italic">name </hi>of a governmnt, at least not since the year <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1827">1827</date_mentioned>. The
moral principle of the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>governed them, and kept the country quiet.
Peace prevailed in this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, until <date_mentioned n="05-xx-1835">last May</date_mentioned>; in that month, a 
revolutionary ball was thrown into it by the <person_mentioned>state authorities of <location_mentioned>Monclova</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, all
<hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>valient Mexicans</person_mentioned>;</hi> and since then, not a month, indeed scarcely a week has
passed, without some act on the part of the <person_mentioned>general government</person_mentioned> or its
<person_mentioned>authorities</person_mentioned>, to increase the irritation, and hurry this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>into 
revolution, or into anarchy and ruin, so as to involve it in a war, to which they
give the character of a national one against <person_mentioned>foreign adventurers</person_mentioned>. And yet,
according to the <person_mentioned>general government of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> alone<barker_pb n="279"/>
are to be blamed for every thing, and deserve death. It is something like
the fable of the wolf, who devoured a sheep for muddying the water of a
brook in which they were both drinking at the same time, the wolf some
hundred yards <hi rend="italic">above </hi>the sheep. That some acts have been committed in
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, which I have always disapproved, and still disapprove, is well
known. They were reprobated and disapproved by the great mass of the
<person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>. But that these individual acts were of the <hi rend="italic">rebel </hi>character, which
the <person_mentioned>government of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> says they are, or that all <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>should be 
condemned to ruin on this account, is as false a pretext as that of the wolf for
eating the sheep. The truth is that liberal and free principles must be 
banished from <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, as they have been, or perhaps will be, from all <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>,
to suit the views of the <person_mentioned>central party</person_mentioned>. To do this, the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> must
be annihilated; and some reasons must be given to the world, for so harsh
a measure. The rumors circulated by my <person_mentioned>enemies</person_mentioned>, that I was instructed,
[interested] or in any way concerned in these large land sales and 
speculations, is false. This specimen of the ruinous legislation of <location_mentioned>Coahuila</location_mentioned>, as to
<location_mentioned>lands</location_mentioned>, is a fair specimen of their legislation for <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, in all other matters.
A <location_mentioned>large portion of this country</location_mentioned> has thus been thrown away into the hands of
<person_mentioned>speculators</person_mentioned>, and entangled by conflicting claims. And are the <person_mentioned>people of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to be blamed for all this? Was it <hi rend="italic">their </hi>acts that involved this 
country in a perplexing land labyrinth, and in anarchy and revolution? No, it
was the acts of native born <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Mexican legislators</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>revolutionists</person_mentioned></hi>. ThSs
subject, and all other matters connected with <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, ought to be fully 
explained in a manifesto from the <person_mentioned>representatives </person_mentioned>of the people. This is
therefore another reason why a convention ought to be called. The fact is
now evident that <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>is engaged in a struggle for existence, against great
numerical strength and resources; and she must supply her physical 
weakness, by the justice of the cause. If she cannot do this, she deserves to fall.</p>

<p>For the reasons expressed, I am of opinion a convention should be called,
without any delay, to meet as soon as possible to hold the elections and
convene the <person_mentioned>members</person_mentioned>. This is also the decided opinion of the <person_mentioned>citizen
volunteers of the army</person_mentioned>, as expressed to me very generally, before I left the
<location_mentioned>camp</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>provisional government</person_mentioned> will, of course, continue in full force, until
changed by the convention. Their labors, in my opinion, have been directed
by the purest desire to promote the general good, and merit the approbation
of the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned></p>.

<p>I remain, very respectfully, your most obedient servant,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned>.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
