
<TEI.2 id="APB5349">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>[xx-xx-1844]</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 484-487</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Public</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>James F Perry</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Public</document_recipient>
<document_title>James F Perry to Public, [xx-xx-1844]</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unknown</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Preparation to gather material for a biography of Austin</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>This was probably issued about 1844</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 484-487</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-31-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5349T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Preparation to gather material for a biography of Austin</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned></hi>.</p>

<p>To the friends of <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>A sacred duty is yet to be performed,— A noble trust is yet to be 
committed,— a patriot's gratitude is yet to be given to the <person_mentioned>biographer </person_mentioned>of
<person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned>,—the <person_mentioned>father of his country</person_mentioned>,— Him! the first great
"pioneer of pioneers," who founded, who suffered, who <hi rend="italic">died </hi>for his 
<location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. Wonderful man! Rising superior, far beyond common thought and
human passion,—casting from him, in the service of the state, the feelings
of the private man, for the sake of <hi rend="italic">union </hi>in a common cause,—for his 
country's good. "This first of patriots, and best of men," forgot injury, in-<barker_pb n="485"/>
gratitude, contumely,—forgave his bitter <person_mentioned>enemies</person_mentioned>, and with them, labored
for his country's triumph. Such, and more, was <person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned>: One
of the brightest examples of human enterprise and virtue,—a man that
should be known to every <person_mentioned>Texian </person_mentioned>Upon his <person_mentioned>countrymen </person_mentioned>we rely for aid
in our present undertaking. From a sense of duty, and at the solicitation
of our friends, we have commenced the task of collecting material for the
life of <person_mentioned>Genl. Austin.</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Having in our family all of his public and private papers in his 
possession, at the time of his death; with the information gained from his <person_mentioned>sister</person_mentioned>,
(his only near relative) the playmate of his childhood,—the companion of
his youth, we already have more than a nucleus around which we hope to
collect much information important to the <person_mentioned>future historian of Austin and
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. But for this information we must mainly rely upon gratitude,
friendship and public spirit.</p>

<p>Before it is too late we wish to collect the information that the <person_mentioned>pioneers</person_mentioned>
and <person_mentioned>old settlers</person_mentioned> alone can give, which may be, unless now obtained, ere
long, buried in the silence of the grave. We appeal then, to those who
braved, with the <person_mentioned>patriarch of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, the <location_mentioned>wilderness</location_mentioned>; to go back to the time
when they thirsted and hungered,—fought the savage, and drove him from
his haunts. Survivors of the <person_mentioned>old "Three Hundred</person_mentioned>" we appeal to you.
We appeal to the <person_mentioned>old settlers</person_mentioned> for justice to the memory of <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>. Yes,
once more enact the scene of other days; once more under <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>'s banner
march and do good service for his, and your name,— A service due to
yourselves,—to posterity, to your worthy and beloved chief.</p>

<p>We do not seek information from the <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>old settlers</person_mentioned></hi> alone; but look to
every <person_mentioned>Texian</person_mentioned>, whether he be an old, or a <person_mentioned>new settler</person_mentioned>, to communicate 
anything of interest he knows of <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">now </hi>is the property of the
<hi rend="italic">whole </hi>country: no particular portion of the Community.can claim him;
no section of <location_mentioned>Country </location_mentioned>can appropriate him.</p>

<p>In the language of the good and chivalrous <person_mentioned>Lamar</person_mentioned>, in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1837">1837</date_mentioned>, we would
further present the claims of <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>, upon the <person_mentioned>patriot </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>true Texian</person_mentioned>.
"The claims of <person_mentioned>General Austin</person_mentioned> upon the affections of the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
were of the strongest kind. He was not only the founder of our republic;
but there is scarcely a blessing which has flowed to the country that may
not fairly be attributed to his untiring efforts for its welfare; whilst almost
every calamity and misfortune which have befallen it, might have been
averted by an adherence to his wise and prudent councils. The world has
afforded but few examples of superior intelligence and sagacity; and as
for disinterested and extended philanthropy, his long sufferings for the
weal of others,—, his patient indurance under persecution,—his generous
forgiveness of enemies—and his final sacrifice of health, happiness and life
in the service of his <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>,—all conspire to place him without a modern<barker_pb n="486"/>
rival, amongst the first of <person_mentioned>patriots</person_mentioned>, and the best of men. Now that he lives
no more to serve us by his counsels, or to receive the reward of his labors,
let us manifest our gratitude by doing justice to his memory. Let us make
a full and faithful record of his good works, and following the example of
his own generosity, give each venial error to the stream of Lethe. To pay
due tribute to departed excellence is a pleasing performance to the 
generous mind; and not to do it,—to deny just homage to exalted worth,
evinces a sad insensibility to virtue. Surely, no one who casts his eyes over
our broad and beautiful <person_mentioned>prairies</person_mentioned>, and reflects that he has come to the
bright inheritance through the toils and afflicting vicissitudes of one whose
home, for our benefit, has been the <location_mentioned>wilderness </location_mentioned>and the <location_mentioned>dungeon</location_mentioned>, can for a
moment, refuse his small contribution toward erecting a monument to the
memory of the noble <person_mentioned>benefactor</person_mentioned>? And of what shall that monument 
consist? Of Marble? No: The best and purest superstructure which can be
reared to the honor of <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>, is the record of his actions,—the history of
his life; and he who shall contribute to this object by preserving any 
anecdote and interesting fact illustrative of his character, will not only render
service to the cause of truth and justice; but will be making some small
return for the many blessings which we are all enjoying from his labors.</p>

<p>"The labors of Austin were extensive, and important: So intimately
connected with all the interesting events of his times, that a faithful 
account of his life must necessarily embrace a large portion of the history
of our <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. It will be perceived, therefore, that the materials 
appropriate to such a work, will not be limited to any particular epoch; but will
include whatever relates to past wars—to the <person_mentioned>aborigines</person_mentioned>,—to the 
settlement of the province by <person_mentioned>North Americans</person_mentioned>,—to the thrilling events of our
revolutionary struggle for independence; and indeed, to every object and
circumstance in anywise connected with this country, and worthy to be
remembered in its annals. As <person_mentioned>Boswell </person_mentioned>said of <person_mentioned>Doctor Johnson</person_mentioned>, we ought
not to <hi rend="italic">'lose one drop of our immortal friend'</hi>; and it is to be hoped, that
the early followers of <person_mentioned>Austin</person_mentioned>—the hardy <person_mentioned>adventurers </person_mentioned>who blazed their way
through the bottom of the <location_mentioned>Brazos</location_mentioned>, will not permit the soul stirring scenes
of former days to fade from memory, or go unchronicled before the wit-
nesses are called upon to follow their faithful <hi rend="italic">Pioneer </hi>to other, and more
beautiful prairies of the spirit land."</p>

<p>It may be asked by <person_mentioned>Austin friends</person_mentioned>, What will be done with this material
when collected? We reply that it will be placed with the matter we have
already obtained, and carefully preserved for the future <person_mentioned>historian of
Austin and <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>In order to facilitate our means of obtaining the information which
may be contributed, the following gentlemen will please act as our <person_mentioned>agents</person_mentioned>
in receiving communications and transmitting the same by safe hands to<barker_pb n="487"/>
the undersigned, or to <person_mentioned>James F, Perry</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Wm- J. Bryan</person_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Peach Point,
Brazoria Country.</location_mentioned></p>

<p><location_mentioned>Austin</location_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>J. H. Kuykendall</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Wm Pettus </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Col. L. W. Groce</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Oliver
Jones</person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Horatio Chrisman</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>E. Roddy Editor of <location_mentioned>Vindicator</location_mentioned></person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Montgomery</location_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Dr. Charles B Stewart Rankin</person_mentioned>.</p>
<p>Harris Stephen Richardson, Hon D G Burnet Editor of Telegraph</p>
<p><location_mentioned>Liberty</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>W and F Hardin</person_mentioned>.</p>
<p><location_mentioned>Fort Bend</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>J. B. Miller</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Randall Jones</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>J. P. Borden</person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Col. Wm. T. Austin</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Thaddeus Bell</person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Matagorda</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Judge T. M. Duke</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>I. R. Lewis Esq. Editor of <location_mentioned>Despatch</location_mentioned></person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Jackson</location_mentioned>.<person_mentioned> Genl A Sommervell</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Geo Sutherland</person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Victoria</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Rev. Mr. Blair</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Maj David Murphree</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Jno. Linn</person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Gonzales</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>T. J. Pilgrim</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Andrew Ponton</person_mentioned>.</p>
<p><location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>J. W. Smith</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Mr. Maverick </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Erasmo Seguin</person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Bastrop</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Genl. Burleson</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>B. Sims</person_mentioned>.</p>
<p><location_mentioned>Travis </location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Col. Cazneau</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Capt. Hornsby</person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Fayette</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>A. and T. Rabb.</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Rev. Mr. Richardson and Editor of the <location_mentioned>Lagrange Intelligencer</location_mentioned></person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>A Alley</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Maj Montgomery</person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Galveston </location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Saml. M. Williams</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Gail Borden</person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>Nacogdoches </location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Gen. T. J. Rusk</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Col. Sterne</person_mentioned></p>
<p><location_mentioned>San Augustine</location_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Editor of <location_mentioned>Red Lander</location_mentioned></person_mentioned></p>
<p>Communications addressed to the undersigned will be directed to 
<location_mentioned>Brazoria Brazoria Co</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
