
<TEI.2 id="APB5105">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>01-15-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 305-306</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>D C Barrett</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to D C Barrett, 01-15-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Orleans, Louisiana</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Advising declaration of independence and giving reasons</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From a newspaper clipping</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 305-306</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-22-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5105T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Advising declaration of independence and giving reasons</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><hi rend="italic">Copy of a Letter to Col. D. C. Barrett.</hi></p>

<p><location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="01-17-1836">Jan. 17, 1836</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p><location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>stands high all over this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. We have effected a loan for
<hi rend="italic">two hundred thousand</hi> dollars and expect to procure another for 40 or
50,000. The enclosed contract contains the terms of the first loan, it will
no doubt be ratified by the <person_mentioned>Convention </person_mentioned>as stipulated. The credit and 
prospects of the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>will be totally ruined if it is not. The last news from
<location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned> and <location_mentioned>Tampico </location_mentioned>is, that the <person_mentioned>Federal Party </person_mentioned>had united with <person_mentioned>Santa
Anna</person_mentioned> against <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. This leaves us but one course, which is an absolute
Declaration of Independence. Such a measure is expected and called for
by the <person_mentioned>people of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, from one end of this union to the other.
We could not have obtained the loan here except on the firm belief by the
<person_mentioned>lenders </person_mentioned>that a Declaration of Independence would be made in <date_mentioned n="03-xx-1836">March next</date_mentioned>
by the <person_mentioned>Convention</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The negotiation that is now pending for another loan has been 
embarrassed by a rumor that there has been a <person_mentioned>mob at <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to destroy the
<person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>, and restore the old state of things under <location_mentioned>Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned>.
I do not believe there has been any such thing. <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>must be united and
act together and in harmony and never recede one inch. It may perhaps
be necessary to stop and rest a while on the way, but never to retrace our<barker_pb n="306"/>
political march. It must be <hi rend="italic">forward</hi>. The <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>has rested a short time
under the declaration of <date_mentioned n="11-07-1835">7th November</date_mentioned>, in order to look around and gain
a little more strength and a little more information as to the road yet to be
traveled over—and we are now ready for another move and a final one.
Whatever difference of opinion there may have been as to the time for this
move, I hope there will be none now. The <location_mentioned>whole nation</location_mentioned> of all <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>are
against us; they have left us but one [course]—INDEPENDENCE— It
is now necessary as a measure of self defence. The <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned> as a
people are ready to sustain it—we shall sink in their estimation if we do
not adopt it.</p>

<p>My health is greatly improved— I wish it had been as good in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— I
should then have been more active and followed my- own impulses and
judgment, both of which are sufficiently indicated by my communications
of <date_mentioned n="11-30-1835">30th November</date_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="12-02-1835">2nd December</date_mentioned> and letter to you about that time.
I shall try to be at <location_mentioned>home </location_mentioned>by the <date_mentioned n="03-xx-1836">first week in March</date_mentioned> and preach 
Independence.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin.</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
