
<TEI.2 id="APB5028">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-08-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 244-247</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>John P Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>John P Austin to Stephen F Austin, 11-08-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New York, New York</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>General interest throughout the United States and disposition to aid Texas. Meeting in New York. Land interest</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>John P. Austin was the brother of Henry Austin, the cousin of Stephen F. Austin</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 244-247</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-12-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5028T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>General interest throughout the United States and disposition to aid Texas. Meeting in New York. Land interest</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="11-08-1835">November 8. 1835</date_mentioned></p>

<p>My dear <person_mentioned>Cousin</person_mentioned>,</p>

<p>I embrace the first opportunity, of <person_mentioned>Mr. Williams</person_mentioned>, to Congratulate you,
as I most sincerely do, on your Safe return to your <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>. Which 
Welcome news reached me a Short time Since through <person_mentioned>brother Henry</person_mentioned> and of
the flattering reception you met with from all <person_mentioned>parties</person_mentioned>, and although but a
just tribute for your long suffering and exertions in their behalf. It
must have proved to you highly gratifying to find them so united on your
appearing again among them. You may be assured it was most fortunate
your getting away from <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>when you did for I have little doubt and
is the opinion of <person_mentioned>Mr. Dale</person_mentioned> that had you been delay'd until the receipt of
the news from <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>(shortly after your departure) You would not have
been permitted to leave, therefore not only fortunate for yourself but
equally so for the welfare of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>your being at home at the present 
important Crisis, requiring of all others your presence to unite the people and
direct their Councils, the late movements there and of <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> to
bring the <person_mentioned>Texians </person_mentioned>under his immediate subjection excite a general and 
increased interest throughout the <location_mentioned>U. States</location_mentioned> in your favor with a disposition
to render you prompt and efficient aid—a proof of which you have in the
Spirited Meetings at new <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Mobile</location_mentioned>. A Meeting has also been
held at <location_mentioned>Boston </location_mentioned>and quite an enthusiastic One here an Evening or two Since
got up at very Short notice. Appointed a <person_mentioned>Committee </person_mentioned>of <person_mentioned>twenty of Our
Most respectable Citizen</person_mentioned>s and adjourned to meet on <date_mentioned n="11-12-1835">thursday Evening of
this week</date_mentioned> when I have no doubt it will be fully attended with an unanimous
response in favor of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— the landing of <person_mentioned>Genl. Cos</person_mentioned> with his <person_mentioned>400 Men</person_mentioned><barker_pb n="245"/>
was the latest news up to <date_mentioned n="11-07-1835">yesterday </date_mentioned>we got the cheering and glorious news,
if it be but true of the <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>being- repulsed at <location_mentioned>Gonzales </location_mentioned>and of the
<person_mentioned>Texians </person_mentioned>taking quiet possession of <location_mentioned>St Antonio</location_mentioned>, under <person_mentioned>Genl. Houston</person_mentioned>, the
<person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>retiring without Making any opposition Both accounts however
want Confirmation, not that it is thought there would be any difficulty in
such a result but the want of time which would not allow it to take place
at so early a date— All the <person_mentioned>Texians </person_mentioned>now here, and there are a number 
anxious to join their <person_mentioned>companions in Arms</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Williams</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>White</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Sayre</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Morgan</person_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>Yates</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Allen </person_mentioned>etc etc, agree that united you have nothing to fear for the
result of your present difficulties, but [will be] able to cope with any force
<person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> Can send against you and that there is little doubt in Case of
need you will receive timely aid from your <person_mentioned>neighbours</person_mentioned>—The excitement
here is however great and late news sought after with the greatest avidity—
Some 8 or 10 Vessels have cleared from here within a short time, 
Coastwise and direct—destination <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—to touch in at the <location_mentioned>mouth of the 
Mississippi river</location_mentioned> for information and to proceed thence together that their
united Strength may protect them in Case of need, being mostly Armed—
was it practicable nothing Could give me more pleasure than to join you
at the present interesting moment and regret Circumstances put it out of
my power. You have however my most Sincere prayers for your welfare
and the success of your Cause, as you will ever have any services that may
be in my power to render you. I would here beg leave to tender you my
best thanks for your very kind and friendly letter of <date_mentioned n="06-23-1835">23d. June</date_mentioned> from
<location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>—the more Gratifying to my feelings as it confirmed my previous
expressed opinion with regard to <person_mentioned>Mr. Meigs</person_mentioned> withholding from me the
perusal of your letters, or at least proving that it was not for the want of
Confidence on your part, which I could not Credit at this time Although
<person_mentioned>Mr. Meigs</person_mentioned>' manner went far to justify Such a Conclusion. I wish I was
deserving of half the Compliment you are pleased to bestow upon me,
but be that as it may I trust you will never find me ungrateful or the 
betrayer of Confidence. You Say if I will state wherein I am interested in
<location_mentioned>Texas lands</location_mentioned>, you will give me your opinion with regard to them. I wish
I was so interested but my sole interest lies in the Success of your 
enterprise and Welfare of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. If I except a small Share in the purchase of
<location_mentioned>Cloppers Point</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Galveston Bay</location_mentioned>—by <person_mentioned>Jas Morgan</person_mentioned> associated with a few 
<person_mentioned>Gentlemen </person_mentioned>Mostly of this <location_mentioned>City</location_mentioned>, in which our Mutual friend <person_mentioned>Dale </person_mentioned>has also an
interest, two Vessels have just Sailed for the point with full Cargoes to
touch in at the <location_mentioned>Mouth of the Mississippi</location_mentioned> where <person_mentioned>Mr. Morgan</person_mentioned>, who goes over
land, is to join them— He has laid out a site for a town to be called <location_mentioned>New
Washington</location_mentioned>, and is intended to run one or both Vessels between there and
<location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned>. All of which Can but tend to benifit your own possessions
as I hold to be the Case of any improvement in the <location_mentioned>Neighbourhood</location_mentioned>. Often<barker_pb n="246"/>
have I regretted that I could not take advantage of <person_mentioned>Henry </person_mentioned>being on the Spot
to secure land in your <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>as Suggested by him—by Clearing out and
assure you nothing but the power to do so from the want of means has 
prevented and not the disposition I now look upon those <location_mentioned>lands </location_mentioned>as soon to
become very valuable—whether by Independence, Cession to the <location_mentioned>United
States</location_mentioned>, or a More Settled and Substantial form of Government under that
of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>—In my letter to <person_mentioned>Henry </person_mentioned>I mentioned, what I here repeat in 
Confidence, that there is little doubt but our <person_mentioned>Charge de affaires Col. Butler</person_mentioned> has
gone out with instructions to treat with regard to purchase and was to have
reported in time for <person_mentioned>Genl. Jackson</person_mentioned>'s Message to <person_mentioned>Congress</person_mentioned>— There is 
however little chance of his arriving out in time to accomplish the latter object,
from his taking this route, I understand he has, through <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>(no doubt
on Motives of present interests) and which will make him not the more
popular with the <person_mentioned>Mexican Government</person_mentioned>— <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> may however from
the fear of loosing <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>altogether imbrace the opportunity to secure the
best offer he Can as the last and only alternative— Last and late advices
from <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>give every indication of an other revolution as being near at
hand and hint at <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned>'s joining the <person_mentioned>liberal </person_mentioned>or <person_mentioned>Strongest Party</person_mentioned> as the
only Chance of Securing his popularity and by so doing it is thought he
may succeed—He Changes too often for either <person_mentioned>party </person_mentioned>to have any 
Confidence in him—I am some time without letters from our friend <person_mentioned>Dale </person_mentioned>as I
got none pr last packet, but hope to be more fortunate by the next—<person_mentioned>Col.
Almonte</person_mentioned> is Still here—He favored us with several friendly Calls at the
<location_mentioned>House</location_mentioned>, prior to the late news from <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—which I presume occupies most
of his time to Counteract as far as may be in his power the popular feeling
in your favor. Says he regrets the Steps you have taken or to find you in
opposition to his <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>— I met a <person_mentioned>Gentleman </person_mentioned>last evening direct from
<location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned>—an old and intimate <person_mentioned>friend </person_mentioned>of <person_mentioned>President Jackson</person_mentioned>—who says
the <person_mentioned>President </person_mentioned>has no disposition to interfere with any present aid given
you by <person_mentioned>Citizens of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</</location_mentioned>person_mentioned> provided they do not openly Violate the laws
of Nations—and that the <person_mentioned>Mexican Government</person_mentioned> will not be permitted to
press our Merchantsmen for the purpose of transporting their <person_mentioned>Troops</person_mentioned>
Also that orders have been Sent to <location_mentioned>Pensacola </location_mentioned>for the <person_mentioned>Men of War</person_mentioned> to Cruise
in the <location_mentioned>Gulf of Mexico</location_mentioned> and a Sloop of War is fitting out with all possible
dispatch at <location_mentioned>Philadelphia</location_mentioned>, to Sail in week or ten days to Cruise <location_mentioned>between
Tampico and the Mouth of the Mississippi</location_mentioned>—which will be Very much in
your favor and a great protection to Vessels bound into any of your ports—
<person_mentioned>Mrs Holley</person_mentioned> writes me She has made arrangements for publishing in 
<location_mentioned>Lexington</location_mentioned>, an other <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—to be out in about Six weeks, with a request that
I send her 2000 Copies of the <location_mentioned>Map</location_mentioned>, to her first with some additions she has
suggested— She was not then aware of your troubles, which when she hears
it may delay her book—I had a Visit from <person_mentioned>brother Charles</person_mentioned> a Short time<barker_pb n="247"/>
Since who takes a great interest in your affairs. So that I can report all
friends well— I should be happy to hear from you since your return, but
know I ought not to look for it when you must have so many Calls upon
your time—<person_mentioned>Mrs Austin</person_mentioned>'s best regards</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Jno. P. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
