
<TEI.2 id="APB5039">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-13-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 249-251</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Philip Dimmitt</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Philip Dimmitt to Stephen F Austin, 11-13-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Goliad, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Head Quarters, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>His refusal to receive the Governor officially produced insubordination. General conditions</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 249-251</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-14-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5039T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>His refusal to receive the Governor officially produced insubordination. General conditions</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Fortress of Goliad</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="11-13-1835">Nov. 13th. 1835</date_mentioned></p>

<p>To <person_mentioned>Gen. Stephen F. Austin</person_mentioned>,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Com. in Ch. of the Army of the People</person_mentioned>,</p>

<p>Sir, Yours of the <date_mentioned n="11-08-1835">8th. inst</date_mentioned>. by <person_mentioned>express </person_mentioned>was duly recd, on the <date_mentioned n="11-10-1835">night of
the 10th</date_mentioned> and would have been answered much sooner had not events here,
which it required time to control, prevented. Your request relative to the
<person_mentioned>Volunteer Greys</person_mentioned>, was promptly complied with; and this <person_mentioned>corps </person_mentioned>will proceed
immediately to <location_mentioned>Head Quarters</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>As to the <person_mentioned>force </person_mentioned>under my command, recent proceedings of a few 
disaffected <person_mentioned>individuals </person_mentioned>here, borrowing assurance from events which cannot
long favour their views, but on which they rely for the moment, prevent
an immediate movement of any portion of it in the direction of <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mr. Augustin Viesca the former Executive of this State</person_mentioned>, arrived here
<date_mentioned n="11-09-1835">day before yesterday</date_mentioned>, accompanied by <person_mentioned>Doctors, Grant</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Cameron</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Col.
Gonzales</person_mentioned>, and others. On being informed of their approach, I ordered an
<person_mentioned>escort</person_mentioned>  of <person_mentioned>four Americans</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>two Mexicans</person_mentioned>, to meet, receive, and conduct,
<person_mentioned>Citizen Viesca</person_mentioned> and suit, to the <location_mentioned>quarters </location_mentioned>provided for his accommodation.
This order was directed to <person_mentioned>Capt. Morris</person_mentioned> of the <person_mentioned><location_mentioned>N. O.</location_mentioned> Volunteers</person_mentioned>, and was
executed.</p>

<p>As I did not conceive myself duly authorised to receive this <person_mentioned>Gentleman</person_mentioned>
in an official capacity, no such reception was either given or intended. On<barker_pb n="250"/>
being applied to for orders to give him a different reception, and on my
refusing to grant it, a strong, but by no means general excitement arose,
and opposition to good order was immediately developed. Part of this
opposition was made <location_mentioned><hi rend="italic">within </hi>the fortress</location_mentioned>—but it originated <hi rend="italic">without</hi>; and
from this <location_mentioned>quarter</location_mentioned>, an attempt was made to carry the purpose of the 
discontented into effect. These occurrences transpired <date_mentioned n="11-11-1835">evening before last</date_mentioned>.
One of my men refused when <location_mentioned>on parade</location_mentioned>, (and had engaged others to follow
his example,) to bring his gun to a shoulder when the order was given,
steped out of the ranks and commenced a harangue to the <person_mentioned>Company</person_mentioned>. I 
instantly ordered him under <person_mentioned>guard</person_mentioned>. Immediately after he was marched off,
another of the disaffected, (one of those who followed <person_mentioned>Irwin </person_mentioned>in the late
movement which resulted in the loss of a valuable young <person_mentioned>officer</person_mentioned>,) came
from the <location_mentioned>house of <person_mentioned>Western</person_mentioned></location_mentioned>, (the <location_mentioned>abode of the <person_mentioned>disaffected</person_mentioned></location_mentioned>,) to the door of
the room where his <person_mentioned>associate </person_mentioned>had just been confined, threatened to release
him, and drew a pistol on the <person_mentioned>guard</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I met the <person_mentioned>mutiny </person_mentioned>by detailing <person_mentioned>15 men</person_mentioned>, under command of <person_mentioned>Leuit. Bordon</person_mentioned>,
to proceed to the <location_mentioned>house of <person_mentioned>Western</person_mentioned></location_mentioned>, where the self styled <person_mentioned>liberator </person_mentioned>of the
man under <person_mentioned>guard </person_mentioned>had fled for protection, (and where too the physical force
of the <person_mentioned>friends of the mutiners</person_mentioned> was then concentrated,) with orders to take
the <person_mentioned>fugitive </person_mentioned>and put him under <person_mentioned>guard</person_mentioned></p>

<p>This order was executed by <person_mentioned>Leuit. Bordon</person_mentioned> with a promptness, firmness,
and coolness, which does both him and the men under his command, the
highest honour.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>occupants of the <location_mentioned>house</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> refused to surrender the <person_mentioned>fugitive</person_mentioned>, or to open
the doors for the entrance of <person_mentioned>Bordon</person_mentioned>; and a threat that the "first man who
entered should be killed", was distinctly heard without. The order was
then given to force the door. Whilst carrying this into effect, the door was
opened and the <person_mentioned>mutiner </person_mentioned>surrendered.</p>

<p>During the absence of <person_mentioned>Luiet. Bordon</person_mentioned> from the <location_mentioned>fortress</location_mentioned>, and whilst he
was before the <location_mentioned>house of <person_mentioned>Western</person_mentioned></location_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Adjutant West</person_mentioned> over was ordered to 
reinforce <person_mentioned>Bordon </person_mentioned>with a <person_mentioned>detachment of 10 men</person_mentioned>. He refused to obey this
order in <hi rend="italic">presence </hi>of the <person_mentioned>Compy</person_mentioned>-, when I informed him that I considered
him no longer an <person_mentioned>officer</person_mentioned>. He retired. During these proceedings, the 
<person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>under my command behaved in a manner highly creditable, both to
themselves and the service— All, excepting <person_mentioned>Westover</person_mentioned>, were ready to 
maintain order, and obey the command of their <person_mentioned>officers</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The proceedings, of which the foregoing is but a brief outline, viewed
in connection with the Character, influence and known exertions of <person_mentioned>several
individuals</person_mentioned>, to encourage insubordination, diffuse discontent, and excite a
spirit of opposition, both <hi rend="italic">in </hi>and <hi rend="italic">out </hi>of the <location_mentioned>fort</location_mentioned>, imposed on this 
commandancy the hard necessity of placing the <location_mentioned>Town </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>environs of Goliad</location_mentioned>,
under martial law—This measure has accordingly been adopted, and a
copy of the order is herewith enclosed.</p><barker_pb n="251"/>

<p>The <person_mentioned>detachment </person_mentioned>sent to the <location_mentioned>Nuecis</location_mentioned>, of which I informed your Excellency
in a former communication, returned on the <date_mentioned n="11-10-1835">10th inst</date_mentioned>. The Cannon, arms
and ammunition at that <location_mentioned>post </location_mentioned>were taken—7 of the <person_mentioned>enemy </person_mentioned>were <person_mentioned>killed</person_mentioned>, and
12 or fourteen <person_mentioned>wounded</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Sixty five of the enemy</person_mentioned> were engaged—and only
14 of our <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>were brought into the action. <person_mentioned>Savriago </person_mentioned>put off, during the
action for <location_mentioned>Matamoros</location_mentioned>. Among the wounded of the <person_mentioned>enemy</person_mentioned>, are all the
<person_mentioned>Members of the Ayun°. of <location_mentioned>San Patricio</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, the <person_mentioned>Judge</person_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>Sheriff of that
<location_mentioned>jurisdiction</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>One only of our men, was <person_mentioned>wounded</person_mentioned>,—<person_mentioned>William Bracken</person_mentioned>—none killed—
All returned that went out. <person_mentioned>Bracken </person_mentioned>lost three fingers off his right hand.
The <person_mentioned>enemy </person_mentioned>retreated, and, we are informed, in the direction of <location_mentioned>Matamoras</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>As to the particulars of this engagement, I am sorry to inform you, that,
all I have here stated, is founded on the verbal statements of the men on
the ground. Altho' again and again requested to report, the <person_mentioned>officer </person_mentioned>in
command, has made no report in writing. If the information of several
of the men placed under his command can be relied on, <person_mentioned>Westover </person_mentioned>obeyed
no part of the order under which he acted. I reserve the particulars of
this affair, so dishonourable to the <person_mentioned>commanding officer</person_mentioned>, so gallantly 
contested, and so [successfully] terminated by the brave <person_mentioned>men </person_mentioned>under his 
command, for the subject of a future communication.</p>

<p>I have dispatched <person_mentioned>Maj. Collinsworth</person_mentioned> to <location_mentioned>Matagorda </location_mentioned>for a supply of 
Blankets and winter clothing for the <person_mentioned>company</person_mentioned> under my command, for Buck
shot, musket flints, etc—and in the event of his failure to procure the 
articles <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, he is instructed to proceed to <location_mentioned>Columbia</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>, and <location_mentioned>Velasco</location_mentioned>.
To aid him in the prosecution of his commission, he was furnished with
communications addressed to the <person_mentioned>Committees of Safety</person_mentioned> of all those <location_mentioned>Towns</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I have pressed into the service a <person_mentioned>caballardo </person_mentioned>on the way from the <location_mentioned>Interior</location_mentioned>
to the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>, consisting, of 40 to 50 animals, said to belong to one
<person_mentioned>Bartolo Pajas</person_mentioned>, have had them valued, and distributed among the 
<person_mentioned>Volunteers</person_mentioned>—The '<person_mentioned>Greys</person_mentioned>" have participated in this distribution, many of whom
are still unprovided with horses.</p>

<p>Please instruct me on whom the command of the <location_mentioned>post, on the Nuecis</location_mentioned>,
recently reduced, now devolves. I am <hi rend="italic">informed</hi>, inofficially, that the 
<person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>there, have declared for the Constitution of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">'24</date_mentioned>, and are now under
arms in the cause of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. Should you think proper to place this <location_mentioned>post</location_mentioned>
under my command, it will afford me pleasure to provide for its defence.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>P. Dimitt Comd</person_mentioned> [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] No. 1 <hi rend="italic">By <person_mentioned>Express</person_mentioned></hi> To <person_mentioned>Gen. Stephen F. Austin Com. in Ch.
of the Army of the People</person_mentioned>— <location_mentioned>Head Quarters</location_mentioned>.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
