
<TEI.2 id="APB5294">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-30-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 441-444</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Joseph Ficklin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Joseph Ficklin, 10-30-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Peach Point, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Conditions in Texas. Explaining why no more volunteers are needed</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 441-444</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-28-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5294T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Conditions in Texas. Explaining why no more volunteers are needed</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Peach Point</location_mentioned> near <location_mentioned>Brazoria </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="10-30-1836">Oct. 30th 1836</date_mentioned></p>
<p><person_mentioned>Jos. Ficklin</person_mentioned></p>
<p>My dear Sir</p>
<p>I have recd, several letters from you, and I fear you have accused me of
neglect in not answering them sooner, As an apology I have to say that
on my arrival at <location_mentioned>Velasco</location_mentioned>, (<location_mentioned>mouth of Brazos</location_mentioned>) on <date_mentioned n="06-27-1836">27 June </date_mentioned>I was called up the
country on important business, and was in motion the whole of <date_mentioned n="07-xx-1836">July </date_mentioned>and
<date_mentioned n="08-xx-1836">August</date_mentioned>— The <date_mentioned n="08-30-1836">last of August</date_mentioned> I was taken sick, with fever, at the <location_mentioned>head
quarters of the <person_mentioned>Army </person_mentioned>at Victoria on Guadalupe</location_mentioned> and with difficulty reached
this place (the residence of my <person_mentioned>brother in law</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Mr James F. Perry</person_mentioned>) I have
had a severe attack, but am now convalescent, tho dispeptic to a great 
degree, and so debilitated that I am barely able to get about—</p><barker_pb n="442"/>

<p>There have been some few local or isolated excitements produced 
principally by the various constructions that were put upon some of the acts of
the march Convention, which have no doubt been greatly magnified abroad,
but they have all terminated— The <person_mentioned>administration of Genl. Houston</person_mentioned> has
entered upon its duties under the most favorable auspices, and the utmost
harmony, and union prevails in all the <person_mentioned>departments </person_mentioned>and also in the 
community at large— The <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> excitement (as it was called) I believe
is <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>—when I arrived in June it was at its extreme point, and there was
a strong disposition to take him to the army and <hi rend="italic">court martial</hi> him— I
opposed this measure by every means in my power, and in consequence soon
drew upon myself the hatred of most of the <person_mentioned>army </person_mentioned>and the ill will of a large
portion of the community— All that however was temporary—it has
passed away. What might be considered an act of retributive justice, <hi rend="italic">at the
time <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> was taken, on the field of battle, before</hi> The <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>was
compromised by receiving him as a <person_mentioned>prisoner of war</person_mentioned>, and treating with him;
would evidently have been quite the reverse <hi rend="italic">afterwards</hi>— This at least
was the view I took of it, and this is the view which <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>and the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>
now take of it— That dreadful excitement consequently entirely subsided
The <person_mentioned>volunteer </person_mentioned>excitement as it was called, has also entirely subsided, so
that we have union and harmony in <location_mentioned>all quarters</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>I pass to another subject which is purely individual and only interesting
to myself— On my arrival in <location_mentioned>Orleans </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="06-xx-1836">June </date_mentioned>on my way home I met with
Messrs <person_mentioned>Collinsworth</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Grayson</person_mentioned>, the <person_mentioned>new commissioners or 
representatives of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to <location_mentioned>washington City</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>— These gentlemen were direct from
<location_mentioned>Velasco</location_mentioned>, the then <location_mentioned>seat of Government</location_mentioned> and stated that in all probability there
would be no more hostilities in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>until late in the <date_mentioned n="Fall-1836">fall</date_mentioned>, that provisions
and supplies were scarce, that it was doubtful whether <person_mentioned>volunteers </person_mentioned>would
be needed immediately, that the sickly season was coming on etc. What
these gentlmen said, they believed to be <hi rend="italic">facts </hi>and subsequent events have
positively proved that they <hi rend="italic">were facts</hi>, for altho a report came on afterwards
of the advance of the <person_mentioned>Mexican army</person_mentioned> and the <person_mentioned>govt</person_mentioned>, here acted upon it, and
called out the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned><hi rend="italic">en masse</hi>, it was erroneous, the <person_mentioned>mexican forces
</person_mentioned>never moved from <location_mentioned>Matamoros </location_mentioned>towards <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and have not been able to
move—</p>

<p>Under these circumstances I was asked by some of the <person_mentioned>volunteers in 
<location_mentioned>Orleans</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and amongst the rest by some from <location_mentioned>Lexington</location_mentioned>, what was the news
from <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— I of course, could only state what the above named 
<person_mentioned>commissioners </person_mentioned>direct from their <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, stated I did so, as it was my duty to do
if I said anything, and for so doing I have understood I have been censured,
and accused of <hi rend="italic">discouraging </hi>the <person_mentioned>volunteers </person_mentioned>etc. My motives and those of
<person_mentioned>Collinsworth </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Grayson </person_mentioned>have been misconstrued,—our object, clearly
and evidently was to <hi rend="italic">benefit </hi>the <person_mentioned>volunteers</person_mentioned>, by informing them of the true<barker_pb n="443"/>
situation of things in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, to avoid disappointment and discontent when
they reached there. In all my acts and conversations while in the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> I
endeavored to be very cautions in holding out high or exaggerated 
inducements of immediate profit, or personal comforts to <person_mentioned>volunteers</person_mentioned>— I 
considered it to be a matter of consciencious duty to do so, in order not to
excite expectations—which I had no doubts would not be fully realized—
I recollect that I was asked some where (either at <location_mentioned>Louisville </location_mentioned>or <location_mentioned>Lexington</location_mentioned>
I believe) whether <person_mentioned>volunteers </person_mentioned>would receive league <location_mentioned>tracts of land</location_mentioned>, besides
their bounty, and that I replyed, I had no instructions or authority as 
<person_mentioned>commissioner</person_mentioned>, to promise any thing of the kind, which was the fact— my 
uniform rule has been to state <hi rend="italic">facts </hi>the plain truth so far as I was informed,
and to try and operate upon the <hi rend="italic">judgement </hi>and the <hi rend="italic">sound moral principles</hi>
of the heart rather than upon the passions, or any momentary excitement or
a mere passing enthusiasm, which, altho wild and unbounded for a time,
too often ends in the oposite extreme of disappointment, disgust and even
hostility— I have [been] censured for pursuing this course I feel I
should have <hi rend="italic">deserved </hi>censure, had I pursued a different one, for besides the
evils that would result to the <person_mentioned>volunteers </person_mentioned>themselves from too sanguine
hopes, those which this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>would suffer from a large body of 
disappointed and enraged men, would be incalculable as what has already 
transpired on a small scale has sufficiently demonstrated— such evils in fact
are more to be dreaded [than] our common <person_mentioned>enemy </person_mentioned>I have also been told
I have been accused of not treating our <person_mentioned><location_mentioned>Lexington </location_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned> with sufficient
attention etc— This has mortified me very much for I do not merit it—
I have no house, not a roof in all <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, that I can call my own— The only
one I had was burnt at <location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned> during the late invasion of the <person_mentioned>enemy</person_mentioned>,
I make my home where the business of the country calls me There is none
here at the farm of my <person_mentioned>brother in law</person_mentioned> who only began to open this place
three years ago, and is still in the primitive log cabbins and wild shrubbery
of the forest— I have no farm, no cotton plantation, no income, no money,
no comforts— I have spent the prime of my life and worn out my 
constitution in trying to colonize this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. Many persons boast of their
300 and <location_mentioned>400 leagues</location_mentioned> acquired by speculation without personal labor or the
sacrifice of years or even days, I shall be content to save <location_mentioned>twenty leagues</location_mentioned>
or about nineteen [ninety] thousand acres, <hi rend="italic">acquired very hard and very
dear indeed</hi>. All my wealth is prospective and contingent upon the events
of the future, what I have been able from time to time to realise in active
means, has gone as fast as realised, and much faster (for I am still in debt
for the expences of my trip to <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>in <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1833">1833</date_mentioned> -<date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1834">34 </date_mentioned>and <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1835">35</date_mentioned>) where my health
and strength and time have gone, which is in the service of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and I am
therefore not ashamed of my present poverty. In this situation what 
attentions could I have offered to any one? I only saw <person_mentioned>Capt. Poslethwaite</person_mentioned> for<barker_pb n="444"/>
a moment and expected to see him again at the <location_mentioned>head quarters of the <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned></location_mentioned>
where I was just starting and understood he was going, I met him coming
out of <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>President Burnett</person_mentioned>s office</location_mentioned>, and offered him my services if they could
be useful. I never saw <person_mentioned>Col Wilson</person_mentioned>— I held no office; had no office, had
no power, and was then unpopular with the <person_mentioned>army </person_mentioned>and many others, on 
account of the <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> excitement etc I mention these things to you—
they are not for publication, far from it my only object is to inform my
old and esteemed and dearly cherished friends of the <hi rend="italic">facts </hi>so far as relates
to myself— As to other matters I have nothing to say, for I have had no
participation in them— I must say however that great injustice has been
done to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in some respects—no doubt from misconceptions— 
Denunciations of a bitter and abusive character, especially when made against a
whole community and that too under very peculiar circumstances, 
generally carry upon their face, a sufficient and satisfactory answer I deeply
most deeply regret that any difficulty or dissatisfaction should have 
occured with the <person_mentioned>volunteers</person_mentioned>— it is a misfortune, but it ought not, and 
certainly cannot injure the cause of this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. Please to remember me to
my old <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>. I hope before <date_mentioned n="03-xx-1837">March </date_mentioned>the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> flag will wave all over
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, God grant it may</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>A Copy. <person_mentioned>M A Bryan</person_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
