
<TEI.2 id="APB5347">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>01-14-1837</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 480-482</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Mary Austin Holley</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Mary Austin Holley to Stephen F Austin, 01-14-1837</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Lexington, Kentucky</sent_from>
	<sent_to>New Orleans, Louisiana, to be forwarded to Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Account of the passage of resolution by the Kentucky Senate requesting recognition of Texan independence</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Original in possession of Mrs. E. L. Perry.
They had led Kentucky troops to Texas after the battle of San Jacinto and were much offended because President Burnet declined to accept their services.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 480-482</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-31-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5347T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Mary Austin Holley to Austin, Lexington, January 14, 1837. Account of the passage of resolution by the Kentucky Senate requesting recognition of Texan independence</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Lexington</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="01-14-1836">Jany 14, 1837</date_mentioned></p>
<p>Dear <person_mentioned>Cousin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>I have been again to <location_mentioned>Frankfort </location_mentioned>to get the <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>resolutions through the
<person_mentioned>Senate</person_mentioned>. I wrote you of their passage in the <person_mentioned>House</person_mentioned>. After the recess for
the Christmas Holidays, the weather being excessively cold I could not
immediately get back, and when I arrived had the mortification to learn<barker_pb n="481"/>
they had been brought up, before all the <person_mentioned>members </person_mentioned>returned, and had been
<hi rend="italic">laid on the table till <date_mentioned n="06-xx-1836">June</date_mentioned>.</hi> Could I have got home the same night I should
have done so without showing myself. I had to stay, however, and learned,
from conversation with my <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>among the <person_mentioned>senators</person_mentioned>, that probably a
vote of reconsideration might be obtained. On motion it proved to be the
fact; and after a very animated and interesting discussion, for which I 
furnished the chief matter, such ignorance prevails on the subject, the 
Resolutions were carried, but with very considerable amendments, growing out
of <hi rend="italic">prudential </hi>motives. Old men are excessively prudent, as if there could
be danger in requesting <person_mentioned>congress </person_mentioned>to recognize when they see reason for so
doing. The amendments are rather in the phraseology than in the sense.
<person_mentioned>Mr Wiggington</person_mentioned> seemed displeased and doubted if the <person_mentioned>House </person_mentioned>would concur.
I shall have to go again to see about it. The success of these Resolutions—
They are called my resolutions—is ascribed entirely to the presence of the
<person_mentioned>ladies</person_mentioned>. The seats were crowded by my influence and example. The <person_mentioned>ladies</person_mentioned>
call out the eloquence—and they electioneer well in the <location_mentioned>lobbies </location_mentioned>and in
<location_mentioned>society</location_mentioned>. Our friends in the senate are Mesrs <person_mentioned>Carter</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Willes</person_mentioned>—Dixon—
<person_mentioned>Barnet</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Young</person_mentioned>. All were eloquent. <person_mentioned>Willes </person_mentioned>most elaborate. I gave him
a book—and numbers of the <location_mentioned>Telegraph</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Fergurson </person_mentioned>drew up his brief, and
assisted him by hints as he spoke. He was very useful and devoted. They
doubted the ability of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to <hi rend="italic">maintain her Independence</hi>, which was a
clause left out by the amendments. With the alterations they had every
vote but two. One of the <hi rend="italic">no </hi>was the <person_mentioned>Uncle of young Woolley</person_mentioned> who 
returned with <person_mentioned>Wilson </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Postletwhaite</person_mentioned>. Those bad men did incalculable
mischief. Nothing can do away [with] the impression The <person_mentioned>President</person_mentioned>'s
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>message, arriving while the Resolutions were pending, had its effect
to retard. 'He knows better than we,' they would say. <person_mentioned>Wharton</person_mentioned>s foolish
speech did mischief by giving plausibility to the argument of our 
<person_mentioned>opponents </person_mentioned>that the <person_mentioned>Texian </person_mentioned>battles were fought by <person_mentioned>adventurers </person_mentioned>from the <location_mentioned>United
States</location_mentioned> rather than by <location_mentioned>Texans</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Mr Burrel of the Senate</person_mentioned>, arrived direct from
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>while the discussion was going on, and had he been more of a man
he might have aided us much by a speech in point, as I urged. He is not
much of a talker, and I suspect, though I could not find out, that he was
not altogether pleased. He spoke of the excitement caused by <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned>'s
release, and of <person_mentioned>Houston</person_mentioned>'s intemperance and unpopularity. He said he had
been with you some days. He only voted with us—said nothing. I saw in
<location_mentioned>Frankfort </location_mentioned>an old friend of yours—<person_mentioned>Mrs Ramsey</person_mentioned>. She told me to speak to
you of <person_mentioned><hi rend="italic">Martha Lockwood</hi>—of <location_mentioned>St. Louis</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. She said she had led many a
dance with you. I replied, no doubt she would again, for she is going to
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to reside, being a <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>widow</person_mentioned></hi>, and having a <person_mentioned>sister </person_mentioned>there, living in <location_mentioned>Nacog-<barker_pb n="482"/>
doches</location_mentioned>. We were attracted to each other simply by <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>sympathy—
sitting together during the debates.</p>

<p>I wish I could go on to <location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned>, now I see how much I could do.
If the money comes soon enough I shall do so. All care will be necessary
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>has <person_mentioned>enemies</person_mentioned>. Unless the mission of <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> should effect all.
He is nearly there by this time. He was sick here a week, as you were—
through severe cold. As soon as able he took carriages from <location_mentioned>Wheeling</location_mentioned>,
the river being frozen—to be there in ten days. It is now the tenth. Then
he would take stage. He has been heard from at <location_mentioned>Chilacothe</location_mentioned>—doing well.
<person_mentioned>Gen. Jackson</person_mentioned> is reported doing well also—they will therefore meet before
many days. While here he was not very accessible to <person_mentioned>visitors</person_mentioned>— I saw
and conversed with him in his room—found in him all the urbanity of the
perfect gentleman. Could not discover in him the <hi rend="italic">cloven foot</hi>—or talk of
monster any more. He spoke of you as his <hi rend="italic">amigo</hi>. Complimented us a
good deal—said he had seen my book etc: said <person_mentioned>Henrietta </person_mentioned>did not much
resemble the <person_mentioned>ladies </person_mentioned>he saw in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— I replied he could not have seen
many there—they had to <hi rend="italic">fly before</hi> him etc: He laughed at all I said was
very pleasant, as was <person_mentioned>Almonte</person_mentioned>. They promised to pass an even'g at my
<location_mentioned>house </location_mentioned>with some <person_mentioned>Kentucky ladies</person_mentioned>. They did not however give me a chance.
They produced quite a sensation. Our lamented friend <person_mentioned>Charlton Hunt</person_mentioned> was
buried with military honors the day they arrived, which caused a concourse
in the streets. He was frightened at the sight of Military supposing him-
[self] the object of attention. Reports of him have gone ahead of him
all the way—and people, tired of the cry of wolf, suffered him to pass
unmolested. God speed him and <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.— I wrote you about <person_mentioned>Fergurson</person_mentioned>.
You did not get the letters in season— <person_mentioned>Wharton </person_mentioned>passed while he was
busy at <location_mentioned>Frankfort</location_mentioned>. He will probably return to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. Ever yours</p>

<p><person_mentioned>M A H</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Since writing—I have a letter from <person_mentioned>Henry</person_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="12-09-1836">9 Dec</date_mentioned>: Some hope of the
money glad affairs go on so well. <person_mentioned>Henrietta </person_mentioned>and I will go to <person_mentioned>Washington</person_mentioned>
rather than <location_mentioned>N Orleans</location_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Emily </person_mentioned>has returned from <location_mentioned>N York</location_mentioned>— We are all
very well. Have an approv'g letter from <person_mentioned>Edwards teacher</person_mentioned>— Best love to
cousin <person_mentioned>Emily</person_mentioned>. <person_mentioned>Girls </person_mentioned>send theirs also to her and you—</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>S F Austin Texas</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Care of <person_mentioned>Messrs Toby and Brothers</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
