
<TEI.2 id="APB5239">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>07-27-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 405-406</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>James Ramage</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>James Ramage to Stephen F Austin, 07-27-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Orleans, Louisiana</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Texas free of danger from Mexico. International aspect of the situation</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>Declaring that Texas ought to be recognized when the Government of the United
States was assured that it had in operation a de facto government capable of fulfilling
its obligations.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 405-406</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-15-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5239T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>James Ramage to Austin, New Orleans, July 27, 1836. Texas free of danger from Mexico. International aspect of the situation</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="07-27-1836"> 27th July 1836</date_mentioned></p>

<p>My Dear Sir</p>

<p>I avail myself of the departure of <person_mentioned>Mr Wm. Bryan</person_mentioned> to forward you some
public Documents and papers which I hope and trust may wile away a
leisure hour—</p>

<p>I have much to say to you that cannot well be included within the narrow
limits of a letter— I must however congratulate you on the Prospect before
you, never in my opinion has <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>stood upon the same high ground in
the estimation of <location_mentioned>civilized nations</location_mentioned> that she does at this Moment— Another
revolution in <location_mentioned>Mex</location_mentioned>. must inevitably be the result of the recent struggle in
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, <hi rend="italic">that</hi>, will ward off any immediate apprehension of Danger from 
invasion ; the great and glorious resolutions of the <person_mentioned>Senate and H of R</person_mentioned> will have
in a moral point of view a greater bearing on your fate, than all which has
preceded it; add to this the interest which the <person_mentioned>Press in <location_mentioned>England </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>has taken
in your cause and the whole will I think justify the remark above Made—
that you now stand on higher ground than you ever have done before.—
Yet my dear Sir, I have my doubts and fears—and they arise not from your
external foes but from your <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>within— You have had from strong
necessity a class of people thrown among you, who when the excitement
ceases which collected them, will exhibit the evils attendant on ill organised
minds and unbridled passions.</p>

<p>I know of nothing that would be so favourable for <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>at this moment
as the election of yourself as <person_mentioned>Presdt of the <location_mentioned>Republic</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>— I not only give this
as my own opinion but I have it corroborated by some of the best 
authorities in <location_mentioned>Washtn</location_mentioned>- That such an election would hasten the proclamation of
the <person_mentioned>President</person_mentioned>, acknowledging your Independence is VERY CERTAIN.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mr Bryan</person_mentioned> who will deliver you this has been shamefully treated by the
<person_mentioned>existing government of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. The Current of public opinion runs strongly
in his favour here and against the intrigues and Maneouvers which 
appointed his <person_mentioned>succesor</person_mentioned>. On this subject however you are well informed— I
tell you from my personal Knowledge that <person_mentioned>Mr Bryan</person_mentioned> stood by your cause
in its gloomiest moments while his successor proved recreant to it.</p><barker_pb n="405"/>

<p>In conclusion I again congratulate you upon what I consider a happy
state of your affairs</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Jas Ramage</person_mentioned></p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Honble S. F. Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></p>

<p>P. S. I saw nothing of <person_mentioned>A—r</person_mentioned> when he was here and but little of <person_mentioned>W—n—</person_mentioned>
indeed I felt no inclination to see either—upon you and the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>
now depends your salvation.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] The <person_mentioned>Honble S. F. Austin</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>by <person_mentioned>Mr. Bryan</person_mentioned>.</p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
