
<TEI.2 id="APB5195">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>06-16-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 366-367</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>R Salmon</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>R Salmon to Stephen F Austin, 06-16-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Orleans, Louisiana</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Reciting his work for two years past in furthering interest of Western New York in Texas. Many settlers wish to emigrate, and want land</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 366-367</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-12-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5195T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Reciting his work for two years past in furthering interest of Western New York in Texas. Many settlers wish to emigrate, and want land</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="10-16-1836">June 16th 1836</date_mentioned></p>

<p>My Dear Sir:—</p>

<p>I have diligently sought an interview with You, during your short stay
here:—but, not having been so fortunate as to find You at leisure,—even
for a few Moments permit me to use my Pen, and briefly lay before you
the following facts, etc relative to my intended Location and Settlement in
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>:—And, <hi rend="italic">first</hi>, my <hi rend="italic">efforts </hi>for the benefit of that <location_mentioned>Country</location_mentioned>, 1.—Thro
the medium of the <location_mentioned>News-Papers</location_mentioned>, I have re-published all the most valuable
and interesting Matter which has appeared relative to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—together with
many original Articles, for the space of 2 Years past, especially thro' the
<location_mentioned>Middle and Western parts of the State of New York</location_mentioned>; by which a very 
general and ardent interest has been excited in its behalf, so that, besides the
small Colony which I bring with me, there are more than <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>100 Families</person_mentioned></hi> in
<location_mentioned>Onondaga </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>adjacent Counties</location_mentioned>, many of them being quite independent
as to Property, who, if <hi rend="italic">we (pioneers) succeed</hi> in effecting our Location,<barker_pb n="367"/>
and send back a <hi rend="italic">good report,</hi> will immediately follow us into <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>;—
2 I have been the cause of a number of <person_mentioned>Families emigrating to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, who
have resided there for some time,— 3.—Also of sending a number of
hardy <person_mentioned>Volunteers </person_mentioned>(15 or 20 at least) to aid her in the great and glorious
struggle for Independence. 4. I wish to settle in your fine <location_mentioned>Country</location_mentioned>,
on account of the <hi rend="italic">health </hi>of my <person_mentioned>Family</person_mentioned>—to make myself useful as a 
<person_mentioned>Missionary</person_mentioned>—and intend, that the <person_mentioned>Families </person_mentioned>I take with me shall constitute my
first <person_mentioned>Congregation</person_mentioned>. The only difficulty, of moment, with which we now
have to contend, is, our long and expensive delay, and especially in a 
climate where Neither our healths nor lives are <hi rend="italic">safe</hi>, should we be obliged
to remain many weeks beyond the present time:—Moreover, I have only
about <hi rend="italic">one fourth the means</hi> necessary to transport these <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>;
and, having no <hi rend="italic">certainty </hi>and obtaining remittances from <location_mentioned>N. York, </location_mentioned>sooner
than abt 7 or 8 Weeks hence; I am therefore obliged <hi rend="italic">to remain here until</hi>
those remittances <hi rend="italic">arrive</hi>—or until I can, <hi rend="italic">myself succeed</hi> in raising the
requisite means to take my People on.— This has been a sad delay for Us
all.— I trust we shall be enabled to go on soon, and be permitted to Locate,
where at least we shall be enabled to preserve both our Healths and our
Lives;— My present plan—As soon as I can get ready—to take our people
on to the <hi rend="italic"><location_mentioned>Nachez Bluffs</location_mentioned></hi>, and let them remain there for a time, upon the
<location_mentioned>Lands of <person_mentioned>A. C. Allen </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>E. A. Baldwin Esqr</person_mentioned>s</location_mentioned>, and occupy a number of
<location_mentioned>Buildings </location_mentioned>belonging to them there.—Should —(finally) the interest which
I have so long and so warmly taken in the welfare of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>be so 
considered by yourself and the <person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>, as to expedite our Location, I shall
be very glad, and shall have renewed cause to extend my labors and 
exertions in so good a cause.— Permit me again to solicit your kind aid and
influence in our behalf:— I am, Dr. Sir, with great Respect</p>

<p><person_mentioned>R. Salmon</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>To <person_mentioned>Genl S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
