
<TEI.2 id="APB5300">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-07-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 448-452</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Henry Meigs</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Henry Meigs, 11-07-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Columbia, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>New York, New York</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Suggesting methods for negotiation with Santa Anna to quiet the Mexican claim to Texas and make way for annexation. Views on Texan boundary with Mexico</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 448-452</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-28-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5300T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Suggesting methods for negotiation with Santa Anna to quiet the Mexican claim to Texas and make way for annexation. Views on Texan boundary with Mexico</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Columbia, Texas</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="11-07-1836">Novr. 7th 1836</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Henry Meigs Esq.</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned> (Confidential)</p>

<p>My dear Sir</p>

<p>I have not written to you since my return from the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> for various 
reasons— I arrived the <date_mentioned n="06-27-1836">29th [27th] June</date_mentioned> and went up the country and out to<barker_pb n="449"/>
the <person_mentioned>army on <location_mentioned>Guadalupe</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, was taken sick in <date_mentioned n="08-xx-1836">august</date_mentioned>, and confined all 
<date_mentioned n="09-xx-1836">September </date_mentioned>and part of <date_mentioned n="10-xx-1836">Oct</date_mentioned>., and am now barely able to get about— I have
just entered upon the office of <person_mentioned>secretary of state</person_mentioned>, a station which I sincerely
hope I shall be relieved from by the speedy annexation of this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>to
the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> or by some other final settlement of the affairs of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— My
constitution and health are worn out, and I wish to nurse what little 
remnant the sixteen years of exposure and labor in this country has left me—</p>

<p>I am truly happy to inform you that our internal affairs are getting on
well— <person_mentioned>Houston </person_mentioned>has entered into the office under favorable auspices—all
party excitements have already subsided, and public opinion has settled
down upon one all absorbing point, which is <hi rend="italic">annexation to the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>
without delay—</hi> The <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>, at the late general election have sanctioned
this measure by almost an unanimous vote, and I think will not be very
tenacious, as to the <hi rend="italic">mode </hi>of effecting this object, provided our equitable
and just, as well as legal rights, are properly secured. Probably <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>
will not refuse to treat with the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned> for a quit claim, or a final adjustment
of limits, and thus give to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>what she wants, without compromising her
pride or prejudices by treating direct with <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—or the same results may
be attained by means of the mediation of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> which <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> has
solicited from <person_mentioned>Genl. Jackson</person_mentioned>— Could not <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> be used in this
matter? and if he can, why not use him? I am convinced he is satisfied
<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>cannot reconquer <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, nor retain it, and that it is the interest of
<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>to get rid of this troublesome <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>as soon as possible and on
the best terms she can— I believe he would act on this basis were he in a
situation to do so with effect— His political position in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>may 
enable him to do much with proper management. The men now in power I
believe are his <person_mentioned>enemies </person_mentioned>and have proscribed him—<person_mentioned>Tornel</person_mentioned>—<person_mentioned>Valencia</person_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Bravo</person_mentioned>,
<person_mentioned>Canalizo</person_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>Bustamante's friends</person_mentioned>, and some of the other <person_mentioned>generals</person_mentioned>, seem
to be struggling for power, and are jealous of each other and wish <person_mentioned>Santa
Anna</person_mentioned> detained here as a <person_mentioned>prisoner </person_mentioned>or shot, and would do anything they could
to induce the <person_mentioned>Texans </person_mentioned>to destroy him, at the same time keeping up 
appearances and opperating on the <person_mentioned>subalterns </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>soldiers </person_mentioned>by appeals in favor of
the captive who is popular with that class— On the other hand the 
<person_mentioned>federalists </person_mentioned>are courting <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> and have attempted to make overtures to him
(which have not yet reached him) to use his influence in favor of that party
by writing from here to his known and faithful personal <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>
but it is also known that the <person_mentioned>leaders of that party</person_mentioned> are opposed to the release
of <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> and to his return to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>— From this it appears that
both parties <hi rend="italic">fear </hi>him, and either would receive him as a leader rather
than see him join the opposite side, and carry the <person_mentioned>army </person_mentioned>or a large portion
of it with him, and rekindle the civil war again—<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>needs peace and
a stable order of things, and the nation in mass are clamorous for it and<barker_pb n="450"/>
dread another civil war and will be more likely to unite upon <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned>,
than to split up into factions under a dozen or more local or <person_mentioned>party leaders</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Under these circumstances <hi rend="italic">suppose </hi>that <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> should go to 
<location_mentioned>Washington city </location_mentioned>and have an interview with the <person_mentioned>President of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> come to
a definitive conclusion as to the <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>question on the basis of recognition
of our independence or on that of annexation to the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> (as he is willing
to bind himself to do) and should from there go to <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned>, or operate
in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>as circumstances may require to terminate the <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>war and
all other matters He distinctly and positively declares that the basis on
which he will act, is to terminate the <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>war, because this country is
lost to <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and consequently the true interests of the latter requires that
the dispute should end without more delay or more sacrifices That the
mode of terminating the matter is greatly facilitated by the recent 
declaration of the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, of their desire to be annexed to the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> in as
much as it removes all embarrassments, so far as the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> are
concerned to an arrangement between <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> relative to 
annexation etc. <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> is useless to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>so long as he is detained as
a <person_mentioned>prisoner </person_mentioned>here, and may possibly be of service if permitted to go to 
<location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned>— <person_mentioned>both parties in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> would be well satisfied if he were to be
shot and either would make hostile demonstrations against <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, if by so
doing his life would be jeopardized— This I believe to be pretty nearly
the state of things in regard to this subject—the best interests of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>,
and of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> as well as of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned><hi rend="italic">demand </hi>a termination of the war and
the annexation of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned>— Protracted hostilities will inevitably
ruin all the eastern parts of the <location_mentioned>Mexican states</location_mentioned> or provinces of <location_mentioned>Tamaulipas</location_mentioned>,
<location_mentioned>Nuevo Leon</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Coahuila</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Chihuahua</location_mentioned>, etc, for this <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, will be compelled to
send her <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned>, which is accumulating, to the <location_mentioned>other side of the Rio Bravo</location_mentioned>
to keep them employed— The <person_mentioned>indians </person_mentioned>will go, of their own accord to
plunder- such a war will also place the <location_mentioned>S. W. frontier of the U. S</location_mentioned>. in
such a situation as regards the <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>that it will be a source of trouble
and expense— The opening of the <location_mentioned>Mexican ports</location_mentioned> to <location_mentioned>Spain</location_mentioned>, is another
reason why the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> should interpose to stop this war in order to 
counteract the <person_mentioned>Spanish </person_mentioned>influence amongst the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> against all 
<person_mentioned>Americans </person_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>American </location_mentioned>commerce—</p>

<p>The <location_mentioned>Rio Bravo</location_mentioned> ought to be the line— If that cannot be obtained it 
certainly should be a <hi rend="italic">sine qua non</hi> to include all the <location_mentioned>valley of the Nueces river</location_mentioned>
up to its head thence westwardly along the hills or mountains to the <location_mentioned>rio
<hi rend="italic">Puerco </hi>or <hi rend="italic">Pecos </hi></location_mentioned>(I believe it is called by the latter name high up, and by
the former lower down, tho some are of opinion that they are two 
distinct rivers, I believe however from good information that it is all one and
the same river) which enters the <location_mentioned>Bravo </location_mentioned>some<location_mentioned> 60 or 80 miles above the old
<hi rend="italic">Precidio of Rio Grande</hi></location_mentioned> situated at the <location_mentioned>crossing of the upper road from
Bexar to Monclova</location_mentioned>— The line should then run <location_mentioned>up this river Puerco or<barker_pb n="451"/>
Pecos, to its head</location_mentioned>, including in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>all its <location_mentioned>valley on both sides</location_mentioned>, and thence
to the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> line at the <location_mentioned>head of Arkansas River</location_mentioned> so as to include in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, all
the <location_mentioned>valley </location_mentioned>and waters of the <location_mentioned>Nueces </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Puerco</location_mentioned>, and all the waters of the
<location_mentioned>Guadalupe</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Brazos</location_mentioned>, and all <location_mentioned>Red River</location_mentioned> and all the waters of the
<location_mentioned>south side of Arkansas river west of Longitude one hundred</location_mentioned> (which is
the <person_mentioned>De Onis</person_mentioned> line) <location_mentioned>between Red and Arkansas rivers</location_mentioned>. Or in other words
make the ridge of high land the line which divides the waters of the <location_mentioned>Nueces</location_mentioned>
and <location_mentioned>Puerco </location_mentioned>from those of the <location_mentioned>Bravo</location_mentioned>, following said ridge or <location_mentioned>mountain
above the head of Puerco</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>to the head of Arkansas</location_mentioned>— I mention this line,
only in the event of there being serious embarrassments to the <location_mentioned>Bravo </location_mentioned>as the
line, as there may be, on account of dividing the populated parts of 
<location_mentioned>Tammaulipas </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Coahuila </location_mentioned>low down, and <location_mentioned>Chihuahua </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>New Mexico</location_mentioned> high
up— The other line will take no <person_mentioned>mexican </person_mentioned>population except what 
belongs to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, proper, such as, <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Goliad</location_mentioned>, etc Money should be no
object with the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> in this matter and <hi rend="italic">it is</hi> an object with <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>. Also
the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> might stipulate to keep the <person_mentioned>Comanche Indians </person_mentioned>quiet, who are
dessolating the state or province of <location_mentioned>Chihuahua</location_mentioned>— The <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>of that 
<location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>would if they could, <hi rend="italic">ask </hi>the protection of the U. S. for their own Govt
cannot protect them and they are in danger of total annihilation by the
<hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Comanches </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Apaches</person_mentioned></hi> A stipulation to keep those <person_mentioned>Indians </person_mentioned>quiet would
be popular in <location_mentioned>mexico </location_mentioned>and in conjunction with money satisfy them for
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>Where the interests of all <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>demand peace, as is the case with the
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>question, I cannot see why it should be delayed— I am informed
from a source on which I rely that <person_mentioned>Tornel the minister of war of mexico</person_mentioned>
has said that <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>was lost and that the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, so viewed it— <hi rend="italic">Pride and
remuneration</hi> for past losses, are all the stumbling blocks—a treaty with
the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> Satisfies the first, and a few millions the other—</p>

<p>I recommend this subject to you and hope you will do all you can to
procure annexation to the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> without delay</p>

<p>Remember me to <person_mentioned>cousin Julia </person_mentioned>and all your <person_mentioned>family</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p>A copy <person_mentioned>M Austin Bryan</person_mentioned></p>
<p>P. S. I think no time should be lost in terminating the question of 
annexation. Public opinion is now in favor of the measure but if it is not
done by <date_mentioned n="03-04-1837">4 march</date_mentioned> next, no calculations can be made as to the consent of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, for the reason that new and other views, will of necessity, govern
the policy and course of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— In short we cannot remain in suspense
longer than <date_mentioned n="03-xx-1837">March</date_mentioned>, and if the question of annexation is not settled by that
time we shall be compelled to go to work on the basis of a separate and<barker_pb n="452"/>
independent <location_mentioned>republic</location_mentioned>, and if that basis is once adopted by the <person_mentioned>people of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> it will never be abandoned— now is the time or never.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S F Austin</person_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
