
<TEI.2 id="APB5094">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>01-07-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 298-299</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Sam Houston</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Sam Houston, 01-07-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New Orleans, Louisiana</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Advising and giving reasons for declaration of independence.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From a newspaper clipping. The letter is printed in Brown, <hi rend="italic">History of Texas</hi>,
I. 470-472</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 298-299</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-13-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5094T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Advising and giving reasons for declaration of independence.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>New Orleans</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="01-07-1836">January 7, 1836</date_mentioned>.</p>

<p>To <person_mentioned>Gen. Sam Houston</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Dear Sir:</p>

<p>In all our <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>affairs, as you are well apprised, I have felt it to be my
duty to be very cautions in involving the <person_mentioned>pioneers </person_mentioned>and actual <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>of
that <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, by any act of mine, until I was fully and clearly convinced
of its necessity, and of the capabilities of our resources to sustain it. Hence
it is that I have been censured by some for being over cautious. Where the
fate of a whole people is in question, it is difficult to be over-cautious or
to be too prudent. Besides these general considerations, there are others
which ought to have weight with me individually. I have been, either
directly or indirectly, the cause of drawing many <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>; also,
the situation and circumstances in which I have been placed have given
considerable weight to my opinions. This has thrown a heavy 
responsibility upon me, so much so that I have considered it to be my duty to be
prudent, and even to control my own impulses and feelings; these have
long been impatient under the state of things which has existed in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>,
and in favor of a speedy and radical change. But I have never approved
of the course of forestalling public opinion by party or partial meetings,
or by management of any kind. The true course is to lay facts before the
<person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>, and let them judge for themselves. I have endeavored to pursue
this course.</p>

<p>A question of vital importance is yet to be decided by <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, which is a
declaration of independence. When I left <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>I was of opinion that it
was premature to stir this question, and that we ought to be very cautious
of taking any steps that would make the <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>war purely a national war,
which would unite all <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>against us, instead of it being a <person_mentioned>party </person_mentioned>war,
which would secure to us the aid of the <person_mentioned>federal party</person_mentioned>. In this I acted<barker_pb n="299"/>
contrary to my own impulses, for I wish to see <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>free from the 
trammels of religious intolerance and other anti-republican restrictions, and 
independent at once; and as an individual have always been ready to risk my
all to obtain it; but I could not feel justifiable in precipitating and 
involving others until I was fully satisfied that they would be sustained. Since
my arrival here, I have received information which has satisfied me on this
subject. I have no doubt we can obtain all and even much more aid than
we need. I now think the time has come for <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>to assert her natural
rights; and were I in the convention I would urge an immediate declaration
of independence. I form this opinion from the information now before me.
I have not heard of any movement in the <location_mentioned>interior </location_mentioned>by the <person_mentioned>federal party</person_mentioned>, in
favor of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, or of the constitution; on the contrary the information from
<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>is that all <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>are against us, owing to what has already been
said and done in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in favor of independence; and that we have nothing
to expect from that quarter but hostility. I am acting on this information.
If it be true, and I have no reason to doubt it, our present position in
favor of the republican principles of the constitution of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date_mentioned>, can do us no
good, and it is doing us harm by deterring those kind of men from joining
us that are most useful. I know not what information you may have in
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>as to the movements of the <person_mentioned>federal party</person_mentioned> in our favor, nor what 
influence they ought to have on the decision of this question, this being a
matter which the convention alone can determine; I can only say that, with
the information now before me, I am in favor of an immediate declaration
of independence. <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> was at <location_mentioned>San Luis Potosi</location_mentioned> according to the last
accounts, marching on rapidly with a large <person_mentioned>force </person_mentioned>against <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. We must
be united and firm, and look well to the month of <date_mentioned n="03-xx-1836">March</date_mentioned>—and be ready.
I shall try to be at <location_mentioned>home </location_mentioned>by that time. Yours, respectfully,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned>.</p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
