
<TEI.2 id="APB5126">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>02-14-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 314</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Henry Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Henry Austin, 02-14-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Nashville, Tennessee</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Great enthusiasm for independence of Texas</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From a copy of Extracts, in file of October 14, 1836</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 314</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>07-26-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5126T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Great enthusiasm for independence of Texas</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Nashville</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="02-14-1836">Feb'y 14th. 1836</date_mentioned></p>

<p>all goes on prosperously for <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in this part of the world— I have
never been in a place where I have met with more genuine hospitality and
enthusiastic patriotism—</p>

<p>We can get all the aid we need to sustain our independence and I think
it will not be difficult to procure the recognition of the <person_mentioned>U. S. Govt</person_mentioned>,— 
Nothing is wanted but union and concert of action and of purpose at home and
an unqualified declaration of independence at once— That of <date_mentioned n="11-07-1835">7th, Nov'r</date_mentioned>
has been made an absolute declaration of independence, by the acts of the
<person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>by submitting to centralism and of the <person_mentioned>Govt</person_mentioned>, in invading us, and
no act of that government for the sale or transfer of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, to any one, can
be or ought to be, in any manner valid, or obligatory on the <person_mentioned>people of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> -</p>

<p>- We all have the same great interest at stake, and the same
objects—which are the total separation of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>from <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, and our
independence as a new republic, or annexation to the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> under proper
guarantees— All we have to do is to keep this object in view and labor
solely with an eye to its accomplishment, and to the public good and 
general happiness, regardless of personalities, or parties, or anything
else-</p>

<p>- I had no idea before I left home of the deep and general
interest that is felt for the cause of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, or of the influence which my
opinions seem to have in this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>—had I known it sooner, I should
have been less cautions than I have been, about precipitating the <person_mentioned>people of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> into a declaration of independence— The responsibility, however,
would have been very great on me had I contributed to involve the <person_mentioned>settlers</person_mentioned>
whom I had been instrumental in drawing to that <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, before I was
certain they would be sustained. I am now confident they will be fully
and promptly sustained in their independence, and that the sooner such a
declaration is made the better— Besides, the reasons for leaving open any
door, however small, for a re-union with <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>have ceased, for all <person_mentioned>parties</person_mentioned>
have united against us—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. A.</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
