
<TEI.2 id="APB5005">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>10-31-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 223-224</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Public</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>R R Royall</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Volunteers at Bexar</document_recipient>
<document_title>R R Royall to Volunteers at Bexar, 10-31-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Head Quarters, Bexar, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Urging them to remain in the field and promising stores and munitions</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 223-224</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-08-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5005T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Urging them to remain in the field and promising stores and munitions</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe</location_mentioned>. <date_mentioned n="10-31-1835">October 31st. 1835</date_mentioned></p>
<p>To <person_mentioned>Genl. S. F. Austin</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Genl. Saml Houston</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Volunteers </person_mentioned>Generally
<person_mentioned>Friends </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Fellow Citizens</person_mentioned></p>

<p>We understand from <person_mentioned>persons from <location_mentioned>head Quarters</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> that much 
disatisfaction prevails in <location_mentioned>camp </location_mentioned>on account of being uncomfortable, we most 
earnestly hope you will not desert the Noble Enterprise so boldly and 
manfully Begun, will You leave our <location_mentioned>frontier </location_mentioned>to the Ravages of a <person_mentioned>cowardly foe</person_mentioned>
who dare not oppose you when <location_mentioned>In the Field</location_mentioned>, will you sacrifice <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and
the Fame you have already won for the sake of a little momentary comfort,
will you forsake the <location_mentioned>fine settlements to the West (Guadaloupe and La
Vaca.)</location_mentioned> only for the sake of a little Respite from the Inclemency of the
approaching <date_mentioned n="Winter - 1835">winter</date_mentioned>, thereby giving the <person_mentioned>Enemy </person_mentioned>confidence in themselves
and a contempt for us. We cannot believe it. You are still <person_mentioned>Americans</person_mentioned>
and will sustain your character as such Gentlemen and Friends. If you
desert <location_mentioned>San Antonio</location_mentioned> you will almost Ruin, <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. As for comforts you shall
want for none Wagons are <location_mentioned>on the Road</location_mentioned> with Corn meal shugar, coffee
and Bacon Flour some arms, canon and Ball. Blanketts tent cloth shoes
etc are also started from <location_mentioned>Columbia </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Brazoria </location_mentioned>our <person_mentioned>friends </person_mentioned>there Invite
you to send for what you want and nothing will be refused you If you
want Clothing a heavy stock has Just arrived in <location_mentioned>Brazoria</location_mentioned>, <location_mentioned>Quintana </location_mentioned>and
<location_mentioned>Matagorda</location_mentioned>, do but say and it shall be sent you without price or trouble on
your Part let each <person_mentioned>Capt </person_mentioned>Report his wants to the <person_mentioned>commander </person_mentioned>and this
<person_mentioned>council </person_mentioned>has provided means to fill every order nothing cant be Ordered
but what will be at your command we will send it on Pack Horses, If you
are in a hurry we can get an abundance of Warm Clothing Blanketts Shoes,
and Tents If you will but Just ask for it. <person_mentioned>Reinforcements </person_mentioned>are coming
from <location_mentioned>every Quarter</location_mentioned> and If you but Just hold on a little <location_mentioned>San Antonio</location_mentioned> must
fall Just at the sight as If it were of your superior numbers. If you or a<barker_pb n="224"/>
portion of you leave it will discourage and prevent the <person_mentioned>Reinforcements</person_mentioned>
now getting up in <location_mentioned>all parts of the Country</location_mentioned> <person_mentioned>75 men from <location_mentioned>N. Orleans</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, in
complete uniform have Just left <location_mentioned>Brazoria </location_mentioned>and will soon Join you an 
<person_mentioned>Express </person_mentioned>from <location_mentioned>Lake Creek</location_mentioned> says in a few days <person_mentioned>50 men from that <location_mentioned>Quarter </location_mentioned></person_mentioned>will
leave for <location_mentioned>head Quarters</location_mentioned> <person_mentioned>men from <location_mentioned>Nacogdoches</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> came in <date_mentioned n="10-31-1835">today </date_mentioned>and from
all accounts we Expect a Great many more from there in a few days. <person_mentioned>75</person_mentioned>
left <location_mentioned>N. Orleans</location_mentioned> by steam for <location_mentioned>Nachitoches </location_mentioned>destined for <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and will be
soon along, another vessel full is hourly expected at <location_mentioned>Velasco </location_mentioned>and from
<location_mentioned>cow Bayou</location_mentioned> some <person_mentioned>30 </person_mentioned>or <person_mentioned>50 </person_mentioned>more beside our letters from the <location_mentioned>U States</location_mentioned> In
form us of <person_mentioned>Companies </person_mentioned>being in readiness <location_mentioned>all along the Mississippi River
</location_mentioned>and from the Calls we have made Upon them we cannot fear but there will
be in a few weeks as many <person_mentioned>troops </person_mentioned>as we want when our <person_mentioned>Farmers </person_mentioned>may return
home and attend to their Bussiness. You must see that we have every thing
to expect and nothing to loose by holding on. you will be assuredly 
relieved in the meantime every comfort ever known in an <person_mentioned>Army </person_mentioned>shall be
afforded you If you will but ask for it.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Felow citizens</person_mentioned> we would Gladly Join you in the <person_mentioned>Army </person_mentioned>but there is but
a few of us and your necessities require that we stay here to forward 
supplies and take all other steps to advance the Cause you are fighting for.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Felow Citizens</person_mentioned></p>

<p>You are where the news of state of things dont Reach you we hear
from <location_mentioned>all parts of Texas</location_mentioned> and the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned>, of <person_mentioned>Reinforcements </person_mentioned>men and
money. As much As we want can soon be had We could not expect to
Rise up and conquer the <person_mentioned>Enemy </person_mentioned>in a few Weeks and If you but hold on a
little while all will be well</p>

<p>The 12 pounder is perhaps now at <location_mentioned>Colorado</location_mentioned></p>

<p>The 13 " is "	started from <location_mentioned>Columbia </location_mentioned>with 
considerable Powder and Ball I am shure these circumstances should 
encourage you If they afford no other advantage you can plant them where
they will knock a few of their <location_mentioned>Houses </location_mentioned>about their Ears, the Wagon from
<location_mentioned>Matagorda </location_mentioned>will cross the <location_mentioned>Colorado </location_mentioned>I suppose <date_mentioned n="10-31-1835">to day</date_mentioned> with shugar, coffee,
Iron for slugs etc etc the wagon with musketts is <location_mentioned>on the Road</location_mentioned> and also
Bacon We earnestly hope that the next we hear is you have determined
never to abandon your hold and Receive an Order for more tent Cloth
Blanketts Warm Clothing shoes etc etc. The things already <location_mentioned>on the Road</location_mentioned>
in the way of clothing is 300 Blanketts 250 prs shoes 600 yds tent cloth,
soap and candles. We Remain Very Respectfully</p>

<p><person_mentioned>R. R. Royall, Presd Genl Council.</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>A. Houston Secty</person_mentioned></p>

<p>N B. If you wish the <person_mentioned>Volunteers from <location_mentioned>N. O.</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to come to <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>send to
<location_mentioned>Goliad </location_mentioned>for them they will be there in a few days from this</p>

<p><person_mentioned>R. R. R.</person_mentioned></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Generals Austin and Houston</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Head Quarters Bexar</location_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
