
<TEI.2 id="APB5312">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-20-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 457-458</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Samuel Houston</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Andrew Jackson</document_recipient>
<document_title>Samuel Houston to Andrew Jackson, 11-20-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Columbia, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Release of Santa Anna. Annexation</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From Austin's letter book, in file of July 4, 1836. A copy.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 457-458</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-28-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5312T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Release of Santa Anna. Annexation</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>(Private)</p>	

<p><location_mentioned>Columbia Texas</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="11-20-1836">Nov. 20th 1836</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Genl. Santa Anna</person_mentioned> has been released and when liberated it is his wish to
go to <location_mentioned>Washington </location_mentioned>and there to consummate his pledges given to this 
<person_mentioned>Government</person_mentioned>. <hi rend="italic">He is free</hi> and will enjoy the desired escort of <person_mentioned>Col Hockley</person_mentioned>
<person_mentioned>Maj Wm H Patton</person_mentioned> (my <person_mentioned>former aid-de camp</person_mentioned>) and <person_mentioned>Col B. E. Bee</person_mentioned></p>

<p>That his great object is to enter into such an arrangement with the 
<person_mentioned>President of the <location_mentioned>U. States.</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> as will place <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in the position which is desirable
for her to enjoy I have no doubt.</p>

<p>I have dispatched an <person_mentioned>accredited agent</person_mentioned> or <person_mentioned>Minister plenipotentiary </person_mentioned>to you
which will doubtless arrive before <person_mentioned>Genl. Santa Anna</person_mentioned> can reach 
<location_mentioned>Washington</location_mentioned>. My great desire is that our country <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>shall be annexed to the
<location_mentioned>U. States</location_mentioned> and on a footing of Justice and reciprosity to the <person_mentioned>parties</person_mentioned>. It is
policy to hold out the idea (and few there are who Know to the contrary)
that we are very able to sustain ourselves, against any power, who are not
impotent, yet I am free to say <hi rend="italic">to you</hi> that we cannot do it Do not 
understand me as yielding to any unfounded apprehensions in behalf of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>—</p>

<p>Whenever I see that the crisis has arrived I will repair to the van of
danger and show to the world, that I can act, and fall as a man.</p>

<p>Whatever of unpleasant forebodings meet my view, is matter of great
distress. It is not my individual hazard or difficulties that of regard but it
is to contemplate a country so nearly redeemed that may be lossed by 
remissness in the <person_mentioned>friends of liberty</person_mentioned> or by the want of forecast in those who
are coordinate powers with me! To witness the fairest portion of the Globe
cast on the hazard, more uncertain than "a die" must awaken in the patriot<barker_pb n="458"/>
sensations of the most lively and painful character. I look to you, as the
friend and patron of my youth and the benefactor of mankind to interpose
in our behalf and save us.</p>

<p>Your wishes are regarded by every <person_mentioned>patriot </person_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and did I not believe
by liberating <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> I was acting in accordance with your wishes, I
might distrust the measure— as it is I feel no distrust in its propriety and
policy!</p>

<p>To you Sir, I confide the course and the measures so far as may be in
your power of making a free and happy people mingling I hope with our
<person_mentioned>kindred people of the <location_mentioned>United States</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Sam Houston</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Genl. A. Jackson</person_mentioned></p>



</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
