
<TEI.2 id="APB5327">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>12-01-1836 [approx]</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 463-470</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Draft</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>None</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to none, 12-01-1836 [approx]</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Unsent</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unsent</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Draft of Proclamation against Slave Trade.</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>This draft is by Austin. Houston touched the subject in his message of May 5, 1837.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 463-470</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-29-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5327T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Draft of Proclamation against Slave Trade.</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>[About December 1, 1836.]</p>

<p>Whereas the 9th section of the Constitution of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>prohibits the 
"importation or admission of <person_mentioned>Africans </person_mentioned>or <person_mentioned>negroes </person_mentioned>into this <location_mentioned>republic </location_mentioned>except
from the<location_mentioned> U. S. of A.</location_mentioned>" which article was published and promulgated to the
world by the proclamation of <person_mentioned>David G. Burnet president</person_mentioned> <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> of this<barker_pb n="464"/>
consent of the Government. When I was at <location_mentioned>Saltillo</location_mentioned>, the <location_mentioned>seat of 
<person_mentioned>government of the <location_mentioned>State</location_mentioned></person_mentioned></location_mentioned>, I procured the sanction of the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>to said
transfer, by a decree dated the <date_mentioned n="10-15-1827">15th of October 1827</date_mentioned>, and <person_mentioned>H. H. League</person_mentioned>
was made the <hi rend="italic"><person_mentioned>Empresario </person_mentioned></hi>or <person_mentioned>State Agent</person_mentioned>, he was also recognized as the
<person_mentioned>agent of the Nashville Company</person_mentioned>, and subject to their instructions. Thus
all doubts and embarrassments were removed, and the matter was placed
on the most favorable footing for the <person_mentioned>company </person_mentioned>for they were permitted to
go on with the contract with <person_mentioned>foreigners </person_mentioned>living <location_mentioned>out of the country</location_mentioned>. On that
occasion I did all I could to serve the <person_mentioned>Nashville Company</person_mentioned>, and saved the
contract of <person_mentioned>Leftwich </person_mentioned>from being forfeited by his transfer of it to the
<person_mentioned>company</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>It is a fact well known that in six years nothing was done by this 
company to settle the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, except to send an <person_mentioned>agent </person_mentioned>to explore it, and make
locations for persons who were not in the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. The plan was adopted
of selling <hi rend="italic">land scrip </hi>in the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned> a measure that was pernicious to the best
interests of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>It is a fact well known to me, and to all others who understand this 
subject, that the sale of <location_mentioned>Texas lands</location_mentioned> by means of scrip in the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> and the
imprudent advertisements and publications made in that <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>by the
<person_mentioned>agents of companies</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Empresarios</person_mentioned>, caused the first great alarm in
<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>as to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and produced the prohibition of emigration from the
<location_mentioned>U. S,</location_mentioned> by the 11th Article of the Law of <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6th of April 1830,</date_mentioned> and laid a 
foundation for all the restrictive measures against this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Some time in <date_mentioned n="11-xx-1830">November 1830</date_mentioned>, only about five months before the 
expiration of the said <person_mentioned>Leftwich</person_mentioned>'s contract, <person_mentioned>Maj. Sterling C. Robinson</person_mentioned> 
[Robertson] and <person_mentioned>Mr. Alexander Thompson</person_mentioned> arrived with a few <person_mentioned>families </person_mentioned>in my
<location_mentioned>colony</location_mentioned>. They were involved in a difficulty on passing <location_mentioned>Nacogdoches </location_mentioned>with
<person_mentioned>Col. Piedras the military commandant</person_mentioned>, in consequence of which, orders
were issued by <person_mentioned>General Teran</person_mentioned>, and by the <person_mentioned>Governor of the <location_mentioned>State</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, to all
<person_mentioned>military and civil authorities in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to expel them from the country by
force. I received one of these orders; it was however evaded until I had
time to procure a counter-order from <person_mentioned>Teran</person_mentioned>, and permission to receive
them as <person_mentioned>colonists </person_mentioned>under my contracts (see copies of <person_mentioned>Piedras</person_mentioned>' and <person_mentioned>Teran</person_mentioned>'s
letters marked A. B.). This affair cost me more difficulty, and perplexity,
than can well be conceived or explained at this time, and I risked involving
myself and <location_mentioned>colony </location_mentioned>with the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>by my interference in favor of
<person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>[Robertson] and his companions I, however, succeeded fairly,
and such of said families or persons who came with him, at that time, and
who applied for it, received a grant of land in my <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>. In this matter
therefore I served <person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>[Robertson] and his <person_mentioned>companions </person_mentioned>all in my
power, and at much hazard to the interests of my own <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>After this difficulty was all arranged and quieted I went to <location_mentioned>Saltillo </location_mentioned>to
attend the <person_mentioned>Legislature </person_mentioned>of which I was a <person_mentioned>member</person_mentioned>. Immediately on my ar-<barker_pb n="467"/>
rival there (about the <date_mentioned n="01-01-1831">first of January 1831</date_mentioned>) I spoke to <person_mentioned>Governor Jose M.
Viesca</person_mentioned> in relation to the <person_mentioned>Nashville Colony</person_mentioned>, for an extension of time for the
<person_mentioned>Company</person_mentioned>, or a new contract for <person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>[Robertson]. It is to be 
remembered that I was not the <person_mentioned>agent of the Company</person_mentioned>, nor of <person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>
[Robertson] and that all I did for them was gratuitous on my part, and proceeded
from a desire to serve them and promote the settlement of the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>My application in favor of <person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>[Robertson] displeased <person_mentioned>Governor
Viesca</person_mentioned> and the <person_mentioned>Secretary of State, Valle</person_mentioned>, very much, and produced 
considerable irritation against me for even having made such an application,
because they said I knew that it would be an open and direct violation of
the 11th Article of the national law of the <date_mentioned n="04-06-1836">6th April 1830</date_mentioned>, to grant it, and
make a Colonization Contract with <person_mentioned>citizens of the<location_mentioned> U. S</location_mentioned>.</person_mentioned> whose emigration to
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>was positively prohibited by said law, and consequently that it would
involve the <person_mentioned>Governor </person_mentioned>in a responsibility to both the general and <person_mentioned>State 
Governments</person_mentioned>, that, in the then excited situation of <person_mentioned>political parties</person_mentioned>, must have
totally ruined him. Besides which he said that I was interceding for a
man who had rendered himself notorious and obnoxious to the 
<person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>by the violence and abusive course he had pursued. In this matter
therefore I again endeavored to serve the <person_mentioned>Nashville Company</person_mentioned>, and 
<person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>[Robertson] in the most essential manner, and at the hazard of losing
all the influence I still had with the <person_mentioned>State Government</person_mentioned>, an influence which
was of vital import at that critical period to protect the interests of the
<person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>in my own <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>, and to ward off trouble from <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in General.</p>

<p>A majority of the then <person_mentioned>State Legislature</person_mentioned> were of the <person_mentioned>central party</person_mentioned> and
politics, and unfriendly to the progress of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and especially to 
<location_mentioned>Americans</location_mentioned>. The fact is that by interfering in favor of <person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>[Robertson] at
all, in the matter of <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>and politics, I lost sight of my duty to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
as its representative, for <hi rend="italic">that duty</hi> required that I should retain as much
influence with the <person_mentioned>Governor </person_mentioned>as possible and avoid creating excitements. I
knew that applications had been made to the <person_mentioned>State Government</person_mentioned> for 
Contracts to Colonize the <location_mentioned>sections of country formerly contracted to <person_mentioned>Leftwich</person_mentioned></location_mentioned>,
whose contract would expire on the <date_mentioned n="04-15-1831">15th of April 1831</date_mentioned>, also for the <location_mentioned>vacant
land remaining in my Colony</location_mentioned>, between <location_mentioned>Ten Leagues of the coast and the
San Antonio road</location_mentioned> and also for a <location_mentioned>section of country North of Nacogdoches</location_mentioned>.
On enquiring, the <person_mentioned>Governor </person_mentioned>informed me that one of these applications
was by <person_mentioned>Doct. Beale</person_mentioned> for an <person_mentioned>English Company</person_mentioned>, (the same that afterwards
obtained <person_mentioned>Milam's colony</person_mentioned> on the <location_mentioned>West of Colorado</location_mentioned>) and the're were two
applications by two <person_mentioned>frenchmen </person_mentioned>by the name of <person_mentioned>Villaveque</person_mentioned>, for <person_mentioned>French
companies in <location_mentioned>Paris</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>Governor </person_mentioned>expressed a disposition to give those applications the
preference, as they were made by <person_mentioned>Europeans</person_mentioned>, and consequently would not
interfere with the prohibitory law of<date_mentioned n="04-06-1830"> 6th April 1830</date_mentioned></p><barker_pb n="468"/>

<p>This was truly alarming and would have been pernicious to the best
interests of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. It is well known that nothing but injury to this 
country has resulted from the <person_mentioned>companies </person_mentioned>who have had colonization contracts
in <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>. They have uniformly made it a matter of illegal speculation by
selling "Land Scrip" and deceiving the ignorant and credulous in <location_mentioned>foreign
countries</location_mentioned>. The credit of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and all faith in any of our land titles has
been destroyed in the<location_mentioned> U. S.</location_mentioned> by such proceedings, and emigration has been
retarded rather than promoted by them. Besides this, it was very evident
that the <location_mentioned>upper Colony</location_mentioned>, if granted to a <location_mentioned>foreign Company</location_mentioned>, would be again
hung up for six years, as it had been by the <person_mentioned>Nashville Company</person_mentioned>, and thus
have left the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>in my <location_mentioned>Colonies </location_mentioned>below, exposed to the <person_mentioned>Indians</person_mentioned>; and
what would have been still worse, that nothing but anarchy and perhaps
civil war would have been produced within the limits of my <location_mentioned>old colonies</location_mentioned>,
if a <person_mentioned>Foreign Empresario</person_mentioned> or <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>were permitted to have anything to
do with the distribution of the <location_mentioned>vacant land </location_mentioned>remaining there. A single 
remark will be sufficient to bring this matter home to the understanding and
feelings of everyone who has any interest in this subject. <hi rend="italic">If at this time
some of our own <person_mentioned>citizens </person_mentioned>advocate the montsrous doctrine that all titles
are void and the land vacant, where each and all of the conditions and
minute formalities of the Colonization Laws have not been complied with
by the <person_mentioned>Settler</person_mentioned>: What could have been expected from a <person_mentioned>foreign Empresario</person_mentioned>
or <person_mentioned>Company </person_mentioned>whose only object would have been speculation and to have
had as much land forfeited as possible?</hi></p>

<p>Under these circumstances it was a solemn and paramount duty in me
to keep the land business within, and adjoining my <location_mentioned>Colonies</location_mentioned>, as much under
my own control as was possible. I should have failed in my obligations
to the <person_mentioned>Settlers </person_mentioned>if I had not done it, and should have merited censure from
them, and yet it seems that I have been, and am abused because I did do it.
Another consideratoin of great importance to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>influenced me. 
<person_mentioned>Governor Jose M. Viesca</person_mentioned> was, and uniformly had been friendly to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and
to its settlement by <person_mentioned>Americans</person_mentioned>. His term of office was to expire on the <date_mentioned n="03-01-1836">first
of March</date_mentioned>, and his successor <person_mentioned>Letona </person_mentioned>was known to be unfriendly to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
and hostile to <person_mentioned>Americans</person_mentioned>. Influenced by my duty to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and not by any
selfish motives of personal interest, I therefore applied to <person_mentioned>Governor Viesca</person_mentioned>
for a colonization contract to comprehend all the <location_mentioned>vacant lands remaining
within the limits of my former Colony</location_mentioned> (except the <location_mentioned>coast</location_mentioned>) and to extend
<location_mentioned>above the San Antonio road</location_mentioned> to include all that country. This application
succeeded with great difficulty, and by the influence of the <person_mentioned>leading men of
the Federal or liberal party</person_mentioned> then in <location_mentioned>Saltillo</location_mentioned>, for although <person_mentioned>Austin </person_mentioned>and 
<person_mentioned>Williams </person_mentioned>were <person_mentioned>Mexican Citizens</person_mentioned> and were not excluded by the law of the <date_mentioned n="04-06-1830">6th
April 1830</date_mentioned>, still the <person_mentioned>Governor </person_mentioned>had scruples because they were born in
the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned></p><barker_pb n="469"/>

<p>I have performed many services to the <person_mentioned>people of my <location_mentioned>Colonies</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and to
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in general, and I consider that few of them was of more essential and
vital importance, than this one of procuring this colonization contract, and
keeping off the <person_mentioned>foreign companies</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The above is a correct statement of facts, so far as I have had anything
to do in person with these transactions.</p>

<p>As to the acts of others performed during my absence from the <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>,
or without my knowledge, I have nothing to do with them, and am not
responsible for them.</p>

<p>I have been compelled to rely principally on my own recollection in
making the foregoing statements many of which are only sustained by my
own word. My unofficial correspondence with <person_mentioned>Genl. Teran</person_mentioned>, the <person_mentioned>Governor
of the State</person_mentioned>, the <person_mentioned>Political Chief of Bexar</person_mentioned>, and others would prove the most
of them, but my private papers were scattered, and many of them destroyed,
during the invasion, and I have not yet collected and arranged the 
fragments that have been saved. These matters were however so notorious at
the time they occurred that several persons were acquainted with them.</p>

<p>I therefore assert positively that so far from having injured or attempted
to injure the <person_mentioned>Nashville Company</person_mentioned>, or <person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>[Robertson] I have 
uniformly endeavored to serve them, and have served them more than any
other man living, in the most critical times, and even at the hazard of 
injuring myself and jeopardizing the best interests of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>When I was in <location_mentioned>Nashville </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="Winter-1835">last winter</date_mentioned> some of the gentlemen who were
<person_mentioned>members of the Company</person_mentioned> expressed to me their approbation of my conduct
towards them. The fact is the fault was in <hi rend="italic">them</hi>, in not settling the <location_mentioned>Colony</location_mentioned>
as they might have done from <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1825">1825 </date_mentioned>to <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1830">1830</date_mentioned>. Had they done only half as
much to settle the <location_mentioned>country above the San Antonio road</location_mentioned>, as I have done
below, (and their means were greater than mine ever were) the physical
strength of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and the situation of our <location_mentioned>frontier settlements</location_mentioned>, would have
been very different from what it now is.</p>

<p>Ever since <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1830">1830</date_mentioned>, I foresaw that an open breach with <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>was 
inevitable. It was, however, of the greatest important to keep it off as long
as possible, in order to gain time and strength. No one in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>was more
anxious than myself to have the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>settled, and especially the <location_mentioned>upper
Colony</location_mentioned>, for the safety of my <location_mentioned>Colonies </location_mentioned>below from <person_mentioned>Indian </person_mentioned>depredations 
depended upon it. I therefore never had any object in view in, procuring the
contract of <person_mentioned>Austin and Williams</person_mentioned> but the public good. The same principle
governs me still, and so far as my own personal interest is concerned, no
impediments will be thrown in the way by me to any adjustment of this
matter that <person_mentioned>Congress </person_mentioned>may deem equitable and necessary. But I have no
power to dispose of or in any manner compromit or relinquish the rights
and interests of others. For example amongst those who obtained authority<barker_pb n="470"/>
from <person_mentioned>Austin and Williams</person_mentioned> to locate <location_mentioned>grants </location_mentioned>made by the <person_mentioned>State Government
</person_mentioned><location_mentioned>above the San Antonio road</location_mentioned>, is <person_mentioned>Col. Francisco Ruiz</person_mentioned> now a <person_mentioned>Senator in 
Congress</person_mentioned>. This gentleman received a grant of ________ Leagues from the <person_mentioned>State</person_mentioned>,
and as a <person_mentioned>native Mexican</person_mentioned> has a preference by the Colonization Law of <date_mentioned n="03-24-1824">24th
March 1824 [1825]</date_mentioned> in locating it. He located ________ Leagues of it <location_mentioned>on the
Brazos</location_mentioned> <location_mentioned>above the road</location_mentioned> as above stated, this location is certainly valid, and
<person_mentioned>Ruiz</person_mentioned>'s title is unquestionable, and yet it is said that this same land has been
given to others under <person_mentioned>Robinson </person_mentioned>[Robertson]. This case of <person_mentioned>Ruiz </person_mentioned>will serve
as an example for all others who settled in that <location_mentioned>Colony </location_mentioned>under <person_mentioned>Austin and
Williams</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>As I observed in the commencement this statement is made to correct
many misrepresentations and erroneous impressions that have been 
circulated, in relation to these transactions, by which much confusion has been
produced in the public mind and great injustice done to me. This 
exposition may also be of service in elucidating the question now before 
Congress, as to what ought to be done with <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Robinson</person_mentioned>'s [Robertson's] Colony.</location_mentioned>
I therefore beg that you will lay it before the <person_mentioned>Senate</person_mentioned>. I have the honor to
remain,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin.</person_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
