
<TEI.2 id="APB5062">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>11-30-1835</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 269-273</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Provisional Government</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Provisional Government, 11-30-1835</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Views on subversion of Constitution of 1824. His policy has been to separate Texas from Mexican political squabbles by organizing local state government. Review of military history since October. Appreciation of the volunteer army</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>From the office of the Secretary of State of Texas, Vault No. 1, Vol. 3, pp. 159-164.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 269-273</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>06-15-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>

<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5062T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Views on subversion of Constitution of 1824. His policy has been to separate Texas from Mexican political squabbles by organizing local state government. Review of military history since October. Appreciation of the volunteer army</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>San Felipe de Austin</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="11-30-1835">Nov. 30 1835</date_mentioned></p>
<p>To the <person_mentioned>Provisional Government of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I have the honor to report to the <person_mentioned>Provisional Government</person_mentioned> that in 
obedience to the call of the <person_mentioned>Representatives of the people</person_mentioned> met in General 
consultation, appointing me a <person_mentioned>commissioner </person_mentioned>to proceed to the <location_mentioned>U. S. of America</location_mentioned>, I
left the <person_mentioned>volunteer army</person_mentioned> that is besieging <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>on the <date_mentioned n="11-25-1835">25</date_mentioned>, and arrived at
this place <date_mentioned n="11-29-1835">last night</date_mentioned> and am ready to leave the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>in the station which
has been assigned to me.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Col. Edward Burleson</person_mentioned> was elected by the <person_mentioned>volunteers </person_mentioned>comprising the <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned>
to succeed me in the<person_mentioned> chief command</person_mentioned>. I have the satisfaction to say that
the patriotism which drew together the gallant <person_mentioned>volunteers </person_mentioned>now in service 
before <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>and at <location_mentioned>Goliad </location_mentioned>is unabated. They left all the comforts and 
endearments of <location_mentioned>home </location_mentioned>to defend their constitutional rights and the Republican
principles of the Federal sistem and constitution of <date_mentioned n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date_mentioned>, and the vested
rights of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>under the law of <date_mentioned n="05-07-1824">7th May of that year</date_mentioned>. Their basis is the
Constitution and the Federal Sistem, but should these be destroyed in
<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and the decree of <date_mentioned n="10-03-1835">3d of October last</date_mentioned> passed by the <person_mentioned>Central party</person_mentioned> (a
copy of which is herewith presented) be carried into effect, and a central
and <person_mentioned>despotic government</person_mentioned> established where all the authority is to be 
concentrated in one person or in a few persons in the <location_mentioned>City of Mexico</location_mentioned>, sustained
by <person_mentioned>military </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Ecclesiastical </person_mentioned>power, the <person_mentioned>volunteer army</person_mentioned> will also im that
event do their duty to their <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>—to the cause of Liberty and 
themselves, as honor, patriotism, and the first law of nature may require.</p>

<p>That every people have the right to change their <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>is 
unquestionable: but it is equally certain and true, that this change [to] be morally
or Politically obligatory must be effected by the expression of the will of
the <person_mentioned>community </person_mentioned>and by legal and constitutional means: for otherwise the
stability of the <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>and the rights of the <person_mentioned>people </person_mentioned>would be at the
mercy of fortunate <person_mentioned>revolutionists</person_mentioned>, of violence or faction. Admitting 
therefore that a central and <person_mentioned>despotic strong government</person_mentioned> is best adapted to the<barker_pb n="270"/>
Education and habits of a portion of the <person_mentioned>Mexican people</person_mentioned>, and that they
wish it, this does not and cannot give to them the right to dictate, by 
unconstitutional means and force, to the other portion who have equal rights
and differ in opinion.</p>

<p>Had the change been effected by constitutional means or had a national
convention been convened and every member of the confederacy been fairly
represented, and a <person_mentioned>majority </person_mentioned>agreed to the change, it would have placed the
matter on different ground, but even then, it would be monstrous to admit
the principle, that a <person_mentioned>majority </person_mentioned>have the right to destroy a <person_mentioned>minority</person_mentioned>, for the
reason that self preservation is superior to all political obligations.</p>

<p>That such a <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>as is contemplated by the before mentioned 
decree of <date_mentioned n="10-03-1835">3d October</date_mentioned>, would destroy the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, must be evident to
all, when they consider its geographical situation, so remote from the 
contemplated centre of legislation and power, populated as it is by a people
who are so different in education, habits, customs, language, and local wants
from all the rest of the <location_mentioned>nation</location_mentioned>, and especially where a portion of the central
power, have manifested violent Religious prejudices and jealousies against
them. But no national convention was convened and the constitution has
been and is violated and disregarded.</p>

<p>The Constitutinal authority of the <location_mentioned>State of Coahuila and Texas</location_mentioned> solemnly
protested against the change of Government for which act they were driven
by <person_mentioned>military force</person_mentioned> from office and imprisoned. The <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> 
protested against it as they had a right to do for which they have been declared
<person_mentioned>rebels </person_mentioned>by the <person_mentioned>Government in <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>However necessary then the basis established by the decree of <date_mentioned n="10-03-1835">3d of 
Octobr</date_mentioned> may be to prevent civil wars and anarchy in other parts of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, it is
attempted to be effected by force and unconstitutional means. However
beneficial it may be to some parts of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, it would be ruinous to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>.
This view of the matter presents the whole subject to the <person_mentioned>people</person_mentioned>. If they
submit to a forcible and unconstitutional destruction of the social compact,
which they have sworn to support, they violate their oaths, if they submit
to be tamely destroyed they disregard-their duty to themselves and violate
the first law which God stamped upon the heart of man, civilized or savage,
which is the Law, or the right of self preservation,.</p>

<p>The decree of the <date_mentioned n="10-03-1835">3d October</date_mentioned> therefore if carried into effect evidently
leaves no remedy for <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>but resistance, secession from <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and a
direct resort to natural right.</p>

<p>Such I believe to be the view which the <person_mentioned>volunteer army</person_mentioned> late under my
command have taken of this subject, and such in substance the principles
they are defending and will defend. That they are sound and just and
merit the approbation of impartial men of all nations, I sincerely believe.</p>

<p>It may be out of place to speak of myself in such a communication as
this, but I deem it to be due to say that I have faithfully labored for years<barker_pb n="271"/>
to unite <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>permanently to the <location_mentioned>Mexican confederation</location_mentioned> by separating its
<person_mentioned>local government</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>internal administration</person_mentioned> so far as practicable from
every other part of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, and placing it in the hands of the <person_mentioned>people of
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, who are certainly best acquainted with their own local wants and
could best harmonize in legislating for them. There was but one way to
effect this union with any hopes of permanency or harmony, which was by
erecting <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>into a state of the <location_mentioned>Mexican confederation</location_mentioned>. Sound policy and
the true interests of the <location_mentioned>Mexican republic</location_mentioned> evidently required that this should
be done. The <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> desired it, and if process [proofs] were
wanting, but they are not, of their fidelity to their obligations as <person_mentioned>Mexican
citizens</person_mentioned> this effort to erect <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>into a <location_mentioned>State </location_mentioned>affords one which is conclusive
to any <person_mentioned>man of Judgement </person_mentioned>who knows anything about this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, for all
such are convinced that <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>could not and would not remain united to
<location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>without the right of self government as a <location_mentioned>State</location_mentioned>. The object of the
<person_mentioned>Texians </person_mentioned>therefore in wishing a separation from <location_mentioned>Coahuila </location_mentioned>and the erection
of their <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>into a <location_mentioned>state </location_mentioned>was to avoid a total separation from <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>by
revolution. Neither <location_mentioned>Coahuila </location_mentioned>nor any other portion of the <person_mentioned>Mexicans </person_mentioned>can
legislate on the internal affairs of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— It is impossible— This <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>
must either be a <location_mentioned>State of the Mexican confederation</location_mentioned> or must separate in to 
as an <location_mentioned>independent community</location_mentioned> or seek protection from some power that
recognizes the principles of self government. I can see no remedy between
one of these three positions and total ruin.</p>

<p>I must particularly call the attention of the <person_mentioned>provisional government</person_mentioned> to
the <person_mentioned>volunteer army</person_mentioned> now in the <location_mentioned>field</location_mentioned>. That their services have been and now
are in the highest possible degree useful and important to <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>is very
evident; had this <person_mentioned>army </person_mentioned>never crossed the <location_mentioned>River Guadaloupe</location_mentioned>, a movement
which some have condemned, the War would have been carried by the 
<person_mentioned>centralists </person_mentioned>into the <location_mentioned>colonies</location_mentioned>, and the <location_mentioned>settlements on Guadaloupe and La vaca
</location_mentioned>would probably have suffered and perhaps been broken up. The Town of
<location_mentioned>Gonzales </location_mentioned>had already been attacked and many of the <person_mentioned>settlers </person_mentioned>were about to
remove. What effect such a state of things would have had upon the moral
standing and prospects of the <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>altho' a matter of opinion, is worthy
of mature consideration: and more especially when it is remembered that
at that time the opinions of many were vacillating and unsettled, and much
division prevailed. The <person_mentioned>volunteer army</person_mentioned> have also parallized the force of
<person_mentioned>Gen. Cos</person_mentioned>, so that it is shut up within the <location_mentioned>fortifications of Bexar</location_mentioned> incapable
of any hostile movement whatever, <location_mentioned>outside the walls</location_mentioned>, and must shortly 
surrender or be annihilated. The <person_mentioned>enemy </person_mentioned>has been beaten in every contest
and skirmish, which has proven the superiority of the <person_mentioned>volunteers</person_mentioned>, and given
confidence to every one. Our undisciplind <person_mentioned>volunteers</person_mentioned>, but few of whom
were ever in the field before have acquired some experience and much 
confidence in each other and in themselves, and are much better prepared for
organization and to meet a formidable attack than they were before.</p><barker_pb n="272"/>

<p>The <location_mentioned>post at Goliad</location_mentioned> has been taken by the <person_mentioned>volunteers </person_mentioned>and the <person_mentioned>army </person_mentioned>
deprived of large supplies which were at that place, and of the facilities of
securing others by water thro' the <location_mentioned>port of Copano</location_mentioned> which is closed upon
them by the occupation of <location_mentioned>Goliad</location_mentioned>. The <person_mentioned>enemy </person_mentioned>has been driven from the
<location_mentioned>River Nueces</location_mentioned> by a <person_mentioned>detachment of the volunteers</person_mentioned> who garrison <location_mentioned>Goliad</location_mentioned>, and
by the <person_mentioned>patriotic sons of <location_mentioned>Ireland </location_mentioned>from <location_mentioned>Powers Colony</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. More than one hundred
of the <person_mentioned>enemy </person_mentioned>including many <person_mentioned>officers </person_mentioned>have been <person_mentioned>killed</person_mentioned>, a great many have
been <person_mentioned>wounded</person_mentioned>, others have deserted, one valuable piece of brass cannon a
six pounder has been taken and another preserved (the one that was at
<location_mentioned>Goliad </location_mentioned>[Gonzales?] from falling into the hands of the <person_mentioned>enemy</person_mentioned>, three 
hundred head of horses have been taken and the resources for sustaining an
<person_mentioned>army </person_mentioned>in <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>all destroyed or exhausted, so that an <person_mentioned>enemy </person_mentioned>in that place is
at this time more than three hundred miles from any supplies of bread stuffs
and many other necessary articles, all this has been effected by the 
<person_mentioned>volunteer army</person_mentioned> in a little more than one month, and with the loss of only one
man <person_mentioned>killed </person_mentioned>in Battle and one <person_mentioned>wounded</person_mentioned>, who has nearly recovered, before
<location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>, one <person_mentioned>wounded </person_mentioned>at <location_mentioned>Goliad</location_mentioned>, and one at <location_mentioned>Lipanticlon</location_mentioned> on <location_mentioned>Nueces</location_mentioned>. In short,
the moral and political influence of the campaign is equally beneficial to
<location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and to the sacred cause of the Constitution and of Liberty and 
honorable to the <person_mentioned>volunteer army</person_mentioned> [which] is composed principally of the most
intelligent respectable and worthy <person_mentioned>citizens of this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> and of <person_mentioned>volunteers
from <location_mentioned>Louisiana </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Alabama</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, of men who have taken up arms from 
principle, from a sense of duty and from the purest motives of Patriotism and
Philanthropy, they have bravely sustained the rights of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and the cause
of <person_mentioned>Mexican </person_mentioned>liberty and patiently borne the exposure and fatigue of a 
winters campaign during the most inclement wet and cold spell of weather
known in this <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>for many years. The most of them are <person_mentioned>men of
families</person_mentioned> whose loss would have made a fearful void in their 
<location_mentioned>community</location_mentioned>. They might have been precipitated upon the <location_mentioned>fortifications of Bexar</location_mentioned>
which were defended by seven or <person_mentioned>eight hundred men</person_mentioned> and a number of
cannon and taken the place by storm against superior numbers and <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>
might and in all probability would have been covered with mourning in
the hour of victory. On consultation with the <person_mentioned>officers in councils of war</person_mentioned>,
it was deemed most prudent not to hazard so much in the commencement
of the contest when a disaster would have been so materially injurious, and
the sistem was adopted of wasting away the resources and spirits and 
numbers of the <person_mentioned>enemy </person_mentioned>by a siege, the ultimate success of which seemed to be
certain, without any serious hazard on our part. That the fall of <location_mentioned>Bexar</location_mentioned>
within a short time will be the result and with very little loss, I have no
doubt.</p>

<p>I consider the <person_mentioned>volunteer army</person_mentioned> to be the main hope of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, at this time
and until a regular force can be organized, and I recommend that it be
sustained and provided for in the most effectual and efficient manner.</p><barker_pb n="273"/>

<p>Before closing this communication, I deem it my duty to recommend to
the consideration of the <person_mentioned>Provisional Government</person_mentioned> the situation of the 
<person_mentioned>inhabitants of <location_mentioned>Bexar </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Goliad</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>. The necessary and indispensable 
operations of the war, has compelled the <person_mentioned>army </person_mentioned>to make use of a considerable
amount of their property, particularly corn, beef, cattle, etc. So soon as
circumstances will permit I respectfully recommend that some sistem be
adopted to ascertain the amount of the property thus made use of, and to
provide for a Just compensation. This recommendation also extends to
horses and other property lost by the <person_mentioned>volunteers</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>I will present to the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>another report on a special subject of
importance and have the Honor to remain</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>




