
<TEI.2 id="APB5212">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>07-03-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 378-379</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>William S. Archer</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Stephen F Austin</document_recipient>
<document_title>William S. Archer to Stephen F Austin, 07-03-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Elk-Hill, Virginia</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Velasco, Texas</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Replying to invitation to emigrate to Texas</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 378-379</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-12-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5212T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Replying to invitation to emigrate to Texas</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Elk-Hill Va</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="07-03-1836">July 3d 1836</date_mentioned></p>

<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p>On my way from the <location_mentioned>south</location_mentioned>, a few days ago, I met <location_mentioned>on the Road</location_mentioned>, My 
Relative <person_mentioned>Doct. B. T. Archer</person_mentioned>, who informed me that you had been good enough<barker_pb n="379"/>
to unite with him, in a letter, to invite me to become an <person_mentioned>Emigrant </person_mentioned>to the
beautiful <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, with whose magnificent destinies, your name has become
associated as a <person_mentioned>Founder</person_mentioned>. This letter, owing to the wandering life I have
been lately leading, has not reached me, but the assurance that it has been
written, no less binds me, not only to due acknowledgments for the favor,
but to the expression of the gratification I have derived, from the evidence
it affords of favorable opinion of me. This evidence I assure you that I
appreciate highly—</p>

<p>Having seen a little, and heard a great deal from authentic sources, of
your splendid <location_mentioned>Region</location_mentioned>, I can not doubt that it is destined to become one of
the most desirable portions of the Globe, <hi rend="italic">provided always</hi> (as the Law
phrase is) that the <person_mentioned>government </person_mentioned>to be established, do not counteract the
physical advantages, as it is the tendency of all the <person_mentioned>Governments </person_mentioned>
established in our <location_mentioned>Western Country</location_mentioned> Eventually to do. Good Government can
only be set up in the infancy and outset of states, as it never retrogrades
from bad to good though it so often changes in the contrary directions.</p>

<p>You will be united I hope and think, very speedily, with our 
<person_mentioned>confederation</person_mentioned>, a result equally to be desired on your account and ours— But, the
character of the <person_mentioned>state government</person_mentioned> you may form, will be matter of far
more importance both to yourselves, and those who may be disposed to
come among you. I take the freedom of indulging this remark, because my
own determination in regard to Emigration will be much influenced by this
consideration.</p>

<p>I expect to be in <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned><date_mentioned n="Fall-1836">This Fall</date_mentioned>, and to have the opportunity of 
expressing in person my acknowledgments for the courtesy I have received from
you,</p>

<p><person_mentioned>Wm. S. Archer</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin Esqr</person_mentioned>.</p>
<p>[Addressed:] <person_mentioned>Stephen F. Austin Esqr</person_mentioned> <location_mentioned>Velasco Texas</location_mentioned></p>


</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
