
<TEI.2 id="APB5214">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>07-04-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 380-383</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>Andrew Jackson</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to Andrew Jackson, 07-04-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>Columbia, Texas</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Suggesting that Jackson give Texas guarantee that Santa Anna will strive for recognition of Texas by Mexico if released. Santa Anna anxious to do so, but only Jackson's guarantee will induce Texans to release him</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes>For the movement to obtain the intervention of the United States, see Barker, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Stephen F. Austin</hi>, 505—509.
Santa Anna's letter to Jackson may be found conveniently in Richardson, <hi rend="italic">Messages
and Papers of the Presidents</hi>, III, 274; and in Garrison, <hi rend="italic">Dip. Cor. Texas</hi>, as cited, I,
106-107.</barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 380-383</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-13-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5214T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Suggesting that Jackson give Texas guarantee that Santa Anna will strive for recognition of Texas by Mexico if released. Santa Anna anxious to do so, but only Jackson's guarantee will induce Texans to release him</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p><location_mentioned>Columbia Texas</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="07-04-1836">July 4—1836</date_mentioned></p>

<p>(<location_mentioned>On the Brazos river 12 miles above Brazoria</location_mentioned>—)</p>

<p><person_mentioned>President Andrew Jackson</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>The <person_mentioned>President of Mexico Genl Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna</person_mentioned>, at present
a <person_mentioned>prisoner of war</person_mentioned> at this place, has expressed to the <person_mentioned>President and Cabinet
of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and to <person_mentioned>Genls Samuel Houston</person_mentioned> and <person_mentioned>Thos J. Rusk</person_mentioned>, his full 
conviction that the true interest of <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>requires an immediate termination of
the war between <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, on the basis of a recognition of the
Independence of the former by the latter— He has also expressed the
same to me in the various conversations I have had with him since my
arrival here, The only difficulty is the <hi rend="italic">mode </hi>of effecting this desirable
object. <person_mentioned>Genl Santa Anna</person_mentioned> has written to you on this subject under this
date, soliciting your mediation, and I have the honor to Enclose to you
his letter.</p>

<p>Presuming that Messrs <person_mentioned>Grayson </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Collinsworth </person_mentioned>have explained all the
previous Transactions had with <person_mentioned>Genl Santa Anna</person_mentioned>, and the events connected
therewith—The public and private Treaty of <date_mentioned n="05-14-1836">14 May last</date_mentioned>, copies of which
are enclosed to you by <person_mentioned>Genl Santa Anna</person_mentioned>—the impediments which public
opinion interposed to the release of <person_mentioned>Genl Santa Anna</person_mentioned> etc etc— I deem
it unnecessary to occupy your time by a recapitulation of them
The grounds taken by <person_mentioned>Genl Santa Anna</person_mentioned> for his immediate release and
return to <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, are that without his presence and influence there, the
independence of <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>will not be recognised, and the war will be renewed
and prosecuted with redoubled vigor and acrimony; for the reasons that
neither the <person_mentioned>Govt </person_mentioned>or <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> are sufficiently informed of the 
Geographical situation and resources of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>— The Character of her 
<person_mentioned>inhabitants</person_mentioned>, and many other things, to Enable them to come to the conclusion
that <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>cannot retain <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and even if she could, that it would be at
a sacrifice which no good that could be reasonably calculated on would
justify making. He says he is fully convinced of these facts, and 
consequently, that it is his duty as a <person_mentioned>Mexican citizen</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>and patriot</person_mentioned>, and as the <person_mentioned>head
of that nation</person_mentioned> to say so frankly and avert farther evils from his <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>,
by terminating an expensive and useless war.</p>

<p>But that nothing could have convinced him but Experience and personal
observation, and that nothing but his own statements and influence in the<barker_pb n="381"/>
<person_mentioned>congress </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Cabinet of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> can or will convince them— That such
statements will be unavailing if made from here during his captivity, for
the reason of his being a <person_mentioned>captive</person_mentioned>, for want of minute explanations which
cannot be given in written communications, and also owing to the intrigues
and slanders of his <person_mentioned>enemies</person_mentioned>, and of party spirit, who would endeavor to
mislead public opinion, Excite national pride, and prejudice, and perhaps
attempt to impugn the purity of his motives etc. He also says that it may
Embarrass the great and magnanimous object he has in view, (I use his
own words) which—is a recognition of <person_mentioned>Texian </person_mentioned>independence, and to build
up a new <person_mentioned>nation </person_mentioned>here, with the cooperation of the <person_mentioned><location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> Govt</person_mentioned>, if the contents
of the secret treaty of <date_mentioned n="05-14-1836">14 May</date_mentioned> or of his letter to you of this date should be
published and reach <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>before he does, in as much as it might be used
by political parties to mislead public opinion, shake public confidence in
him or create erronious impressions,</p>

<p>He also says that the Elections for— <person_mentioned>President of Mexico</person_mentioned> come on in
<date_mentioned n="09-xx-1836">September next</date_mentioned>, and that <person_mentioned>Genl Bravo</person_mentioned> probably may be elected, if he, <person_mentioned>Santa
Anna</person_mentioned>, is detained here, that in this event there would be but little 
probability of accomadating the affairs of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, for the reasons that the new
<person_mentioned>President </person_mentioned>would probably consider it necessary to keep up the national 
Excitement on this subject by appealing to national pride, and doing all he
could to discredit his <person_mentioned>political enemy</person_mentioned> <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> etc These in substance
are the views taken by <person_mentioned>Genl Santa Anna</person_mentioned> on this subject</p>

<p>He entered into lengthy details to Explain his reasons for being in favor
of acknowledging the Independence of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, and the advantages that
would result to <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and to the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> from a termination of the war etc.
It would be extending this letter very much to repeat them all. They are
based (as I think) on a full knowledge of the subject, and an ardent and
patriotic desire to serve the true interest of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, and the cause of 
humanity by terminating an Expensive and useless war, His manner, and
his reasoning, evinced frankness, sincerity, and Magnanimity,— He drew
a very striking comparison between the obstinate silly, and impolitic course
pursued by <location_mentioned>Spain </location_mentioned>in refusing to acknowledge the Independence of <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>,
after all hopes of conquering it had ceased, and the good of <location_mentioned>Spain </location_mentioned>required
a termination of the war between them: and the prompt, frank and high
minded course of <location_mentioned>England</location_mentioned>, with the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> by terminating the war of 
Independence without delay, so soon as it was evident the public good required
it, He hopes the Example of the latter would be followed by <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>with
respect to <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, at the same time observing that if this liberal and 
magnanimous course was adopted by <location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned>, it would naturally be expected
that a similar one would influence <location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>in agreeing to some just and 
reasonable indemnity for the losses of <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>to be amicably arranged by
negotiations under the general mediation of the U. S. etc— These 
conversations were held with me as an individual.— I hold no office at this time<barker_pb n="382"/>
in this <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>. And as such they are detailed to you with the knowledge
of <person_mentioned>Genl Santa Anna</person_mentioned>, to whom I have communicated the substance of this
letter. On my part I could only reply by Expressing my desires to see the
war terminated on the basis of an acknowledgment of our Independence,
and that I had confidence in the sincerity and good faith of his declarations
on the subject, and would use any influence I might have to bring about a
permanent peace through the Mediation of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> which I considered a
decorous and safe mode of terminating the difficulty, both for <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and
<location_mentioned>Texas </location_mentioned>The step taken by the <person_mentioned>president and cabinet of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to liberate
<person_mentioned>Genl. Santa Anna</person_mentioned> and send him to <location_mentioned>Vera Cruz</location_mentioned> forthwith, was disapproved
of by public opinion, an excitement was the consequence and he was 
disembarked after he had embarked to sail for <location_mentioned>vera cruz</location_mentioned>. The cause of this
excitement was the want of confidence by the army and people in the 
professions and declarations of <person_mentioned>Gen. Santa Anna</person_mentioned>—the belief that the <person_mentioned>Cabinet</person_mentioned>
had been overreached and deceived by a misplaced confidence in him—the
want of information as to the nature of the secret treaty with him, which
was not published for the reasons before stated, and the want of guarantees
for the prompt fulfilment of his promise to acknowledge our independence,
and doubts as to his power and influence with the <person_mentioned>Congress and people of
<location_mentioned>Mexico</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> to effect this object etc etc. Also, the deep feeling produced by the
execution of <person_mentioned>Col Fannin's men</person_mentioned>, the loss of property, suffering of <person_mentioned>families</person_mentioned>
etc etc.</p>

<p>You have been called upon by the <person_mentioned>Govt, of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> through Messrs 
<person_mentioned>Grayson </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>Collingsworth</person_mentioned>, who went on for that purpose and are now called
upon by <person_mentioned>Gen Santa Anna</person_mentioned> to interpose your influence and mediation for the
purpose of terminating the war between <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>and <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>, on the basis of
the full establishment and recognition of the independence of the latter,
and I sincerely hope that these joint calls will be deemed sufficient to 
justify the intervention of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> as a mediator in this matter and that your
intervention will be prompt and directed at once of the object of a 
cessation of hostilities here. Your guarantee to the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> for the 
fulfilment of the offer made by <person_mentioned>Gen Santa Anna</person_mentioned> would <hi rend="italic">produce his immediate
release</hi>, and he says that this will end the war, as he then can exercise his
authority and influence to take back the <person_mentioned>Mexican Army</person_mentioned> and terminate the
whole matter by negociation before his and your terms of office expire.
I am myself convinced of <person_mentioned>Gen. Santa Anna</person_mentioned>'s sincerity and good faith in
this matter and I shall proceed to the <person_mentioned>Army of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> with the view of trying
to allay excitements and see, whether <person_mentioned>Gen. Urrea</person_mentioned> (in case there is any mode
of communicating with him officially by the command of our <person_mentioned>army</person_mentioned>) will by
a solemn and formal treaty agree to withdraw his army beyond the <location_mentioned>Rio
Bravo</location_mentioned> and obey the orders of <person_mentioned>Gen Santa Anna</person_mentioned> in the event of the liberation
of the latter and his arrival at <location_mentioned><person_mentioned>Urrea</person_mentioned>s head quarters</location_mentioned>, <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> on his
part giving such assurances and guarantees as will satisfy our army on the<barker_pb n="383"/>
subject and produce confidence. I doubt however whether anything can
be done untill <hi rend="italic">your </hi>guarantee is received here and made known. <person_mentioned>Gen.
Santa Anna</person_mentioned> has written to <person_mentioned>Gen Urrea</person_mentioned> expressing his wishes and requesting
him to make such an arrangement as before stated and I shall take this
letter to the commander of our <person_mentioned>Army </person_mentioned><person_mentioned>Gen M. B. Lamar</person_mentioned>, to be used by him
as he deems proper— I must however repeat the opinion that nothing will
be done definitely untill your guarantee is received for the reason that I
do not believe any thing else will satisfy public opinion here. If <person_mentioned>Gen
Santa Anna</person_mentioned> is sincere and acting in good faith, this want of confidence
which prevents his liberation is unfortunate, as it may be the means of
detaining him here, untill his influence in <location_mentioned>Mexico </location_mentioned>is lost by the election of
<person_mentioned>Bravo </person_mentioned>or other causes— If on the other hand he is not sincere and all his
promises and professions are hipocritical it would be an act of perfidy and
baseness which could not be justified on any pretext and cannot be 
supposed possible, nor do I believe it to be possible— It would justify the
<person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> in <hi rend="italic">any </hi>act of violence hereafter, and it would justify the
<person_mentioned><location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned> Govt</person_mentioned>, in enterposing <hi rend="italic">by force</hi> in favor of a people who had been thus
deceived, more especially when <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned>'s letter to you of this date is
considered and brought into public view as it would be in the event of his
treachery. For these reasons I shall act in this matter on the basis that he
is sincere and in good faith, and endeavor to stop the advance of <person_mentioned>Urrea </person_mentioned>and
procure a cessation of hostilities, altho I have but very little prospect of
success without your guarantee. If <person_mentioned>Urrea </person_mentioned>refuses to do as <person_mentioned>Santa Anna</person_mentioned> has
requested him in his letter, nothing of course will be done—</p>

<p>I arrived at <location_mentioned>Velasco</location_mentioned>, the<location_mentioned> present seat of Govt</location_mentioned>, on the <date_mentioned n="06-27-1836">27th ult</date_mentioned>. and at this
place on the <date_mentioned n="07-02-1836">2d instant</date_mentioned>. I found this subject very much entangled, as you
perceive—</p>

<p>Our <person_mentioned>Army </person_mentioned>is at <location_mentioned>Guadalupe </location_mentioned>near <location_mentioned>Victoria</location_mentioned>, The whole <location_mentioned>country </location_mentioned>is turning
out <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi> and I have no doubt the<person_mentioned> Mexican Army</person_mentioned> will be cut to pieces
should it advance.</p>

<p>It is not any doubts I have on this subject that influences me in wishing
to embrace the opportunity of ending the war. But the <person_mentioned>inhabitants </person_mentioned>are
suffering, they are all <location_mentioned>in the field</location_mentioned> or are going and a procrastinated war
will greatly injure them.— I have been thus lengthy in order to give you
all the information I can in regard to a matter in which you are called
upon by both <person_mentioned>parties </person_mentioned>to enterpose your mediation, and one which is of
deep interest to the <person_mentioned>people of the <location_mentioned>U. S.</location_mentioned></person_mentioned> And to the cause of liberty and
humanity, and hope that its importance will excuse me for occupying so
much of your time—</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S. F. Austin</person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
