
<TEI.2 id="APB5161">
<project_title>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</project_title>
<project_editor>Andrew J. Torget</project_editor>

<document_creation>04-23-1836</document_creation>
<document_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 338-339</document_citation>
<document_language>English</document_language>
<document_status>Private</document_status>
<document_type>Letter</document_type>
<document_author>Stephen F Austin</document_author>
<document_sender></document_sender>
<document_recipient>A J Yates</document_recipient>
<document_title>Stephen F Austin to A J Yates, 04-23-1836</document_title>
<document_location>
	<sent_from>New York, New York</sent_from>
	<sent_to>Unknown</sent_to>
</document_location>
<barker_notes>
	<barker_summary>Suspending purchase of steamboat</barker_summary>
	<barker_footnotes></barker_footnotes>
	<barker_citation>Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 338-339</barker_citation>
</barker_notes>
<document_digital_creation>08-01-2011</document_digital_creation>

<respStmt>
<resp>Project Director and Editor: </resp> 
<name>Andrew J. Torget</name>
<resp>Creation of XML version: </resp>
<name>Debbie Liles</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<text id="APB5161T">

<body>
<div1 type="summary">
<p>Suspending purchase of steamboat</p>
</div1>

<div1 type="body">

<p>(Copy)	<location_mentioned>New York</location_mentioned> <date_mentioned n="04-23-1836">April 23, 1836</date_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Mr. A. J. Yates</person_mentioned></p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>Your letter dated at <location_mentioned>Washington City</location_mentioned>, <date_mentioned n="04-01-1836">April 1st 1836</date_mentioned> containing a report
of your proceedings under our letters of Instruction of the <date_mentioned n="01-21-1836">21st</date_mentioned> and <date_mentioned n="01-22-1836">22nd
January last</date_mentioned>, has been received.</p>

<p>Your several previous letters to us transmitting important information
relative to the interests of our <location_mentioned>country</location_mentioned>, together with the efforts you have
made in her cause, not only meet our warmest approbation, but also entitle
you to the gratitude of the <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>We much regret to be under the necessity of discharging from further
consideration, the purchase of a Steam Boat for the <person_mentioned>Government of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>,
in consequence of its slender finances, and of the immediate and more 
important demands for money to be applied to sustaining the army already
<location_mentioned>in the field</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>The proposition to negotiate a loan in the <location_mentioned>City of New York</location_mentioned> which you
have presented to us at the <location_mentioned>City of Washington</location_mentioned>, cannot be acted on by us,
as it requires power with which we are not vested, and we must there fore
decline it.</p><barker_pb n="339"/>

<p>We wish you to send us a statement of the disbursements in the mission
in which you have been engaged, from the time of your leaving the <location_mentioned>City of
New Orleans</location_mentioned>, including your prospective expenses in returning to that <location_mentioned>City</location_mentioned>,
with the vouchers of the account for our examination, and we will 
endeavour to provide the means for your reimbursement, before we leave the
<location_mentioned>City</location_mentioned>.</p>

<p>We still desire to leave the amount of your compensation for services,
to be determined by the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>on your return, at the same time giving
both you and it, our assurances of unqualified approbation, at the manner
in which you have discharged the duties of the situation in which you have
been placed by us, and our earnest recommendation to the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>to
repay you in a liberal manner, for your exertions in behalf of the <location_mentioned>Country</location_mentioned>.
We are much gratified to learn of your active efforts to raise a <person_mentioned>joint stock
Steam Boat Company</person_mentioned>, and fit out a Steam Boat from this <location_mentioned>City </location_mentioned>for <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned>,
on the individual enterprise of your <person_mentioned>friends</person_mentioned>.</p>

<p>Permit us to express to you our great satisfaction for your zeal in those
efforts, and our earnest desire that you may succeed in accomplishing the
object, as we are fully convinced of the great advantages of such a 
communication to the <person_mentioned>Government </person_mentioned>and <person_mentioned>people of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned>, and we most ardently
wish for your success in the undertaking.</p>

<p><person_mentioned>S F Austin</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>Wm. H. Wharton</person_mentioned></p>

<p><person_mentioned>B T Archer</person_mentioned></p>	

<p><person_mentioned>Commissioners of <location_mentioned>Texas</location_mentioned></person_mentioned></p>

</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
