<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0108">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Albert Gallatin, 08-xx-1806</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-27">06-27-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Albert Gallatin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 115-122
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="Private "/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1806-08">08-xx-1806</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-27" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Describing conditions in Missouri; dissatisfaction with Gen. Wilkinson's administration a governor; complaints against the land commssioners; and suggesting amendment of the land law by Congress.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[About August, 1806?]</p>
<p>Sir</p>

<p>The embarrassed situation of the <persName>Inhabitants of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName></persName> together
with the distance of the <placeName>Territory </placeName>from the <placeName>seat of the American 
Government</placeName>, and, the unhappy party contencions, which prevail at this
moment, and have from the commencement of <persName>Genl. Wilkinson
Administration</persName> have induced me to address you this letter&#8212;</p>

<p>It is my intention to communicate such things, as I think the 
<persName>Legislators of the General Government</persName> ought to know, I have not a doubt,
but many communications have already been made, and that many
more will be made, it is not my wish to detract from, or depreciate, the
confidence those communications merit, yet I hope I shall be 
pardoned in saying that from the marked preference <persName>Govr. Wilkinson</persName>
has shewn for Spanish customs and useages&#8212;The little interest he has
appeared to take in the establishment and prosperity of this <placeName>Country</placeName>,
leads me to believe his Communications, to our <persName>Government</persName>, have
rather been calculated to destroy the reputation of <persName>Men in Office</persName>, not
submissive, to his will, than to inform the government of the real
situation in this <placeName>Territory</placeName>, and what measures are necessary to be
adopted to meet the wishes of the people, and at the same time answer
the views of the <persName>Government</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Not deeming an apology necessary for thus troubling you, I shall
commence my naritive of this Country as far back as <date n="xx-xx-1797">1797</date>, the year
I first visited it, and bring it down to the present day, in so doing I
shall endeavour to give you an ample Idea of the motives which 
induced the <persName>Americans </persName>to remove within the <placeName>Spanish limits</placeName>; with a
view of the situation of the <persName>settlers</persName>, when the changes of <persName>Government</persName>
took place. You will then have it in your power to judge of the 
propriety of the claims, the <persName>People </persName>have on the <persName>Government </persName>with more
correctness</p>

<p>In <date n="xx-xx-1797">1797 </date>I found this Country a <placeName>Wilderness </placeName>except on the <placeName>Banks of
the Mississippi</placeName> in the <placeName>district of St. Genevieve</placeName>, not an Establishment
of any kind, at a distance of more than twelve miles from the River,
<placeName>Cape Gerredeau</placeName> and <placeName>Madrid Districts</placeName>, began about, this time to
settle back. The commencement, of the <persName>American </persName>emigration may be
dated back from the <date n="Fall-1796">Fall of 96</date> and <date n="Spring-1797">Spring of 97</date>.</p>

<p>All the <placeName>cultivated Land</placeName>, was of consequence, confined to the <placeName>river
Bottoms</placeName>, and whenever the River overflowed its <placeName>Banks</placeName>, which it has
commonly done, about every Five or Six years, Beginning to rise,
about <date n="06-xx-xxxx">June </date>and continueing until <date n="08-xx-xxxx">August</date>, destroying the Crops of
every kind, and leaving the <persName>Inhabitants </persName>dependent on the <persName>King</persName>s
Bounty for Bread, on such Occasions, the <persName>King </persName>has been compeled
to open the <placeName>Public Magazenes of Provisions</placeName> and furnish the <persName>People</persName>
To remove this inconvenience which was found not only expensive
but a derangement of the Public Supplies which could only be 
replenished from the <placeName>United States</placeName>&#8212;It was therefore propos'd to give
encouragement to the <persName>Americans </persName>to settle within the <placeName>Province</placeName>&#8212;. To
effect so desirable an object hand Bills and Phamphlets, Printed in
the english Language were circulated throughout the <placeName>Western
Country</placeName> holding up great inducements to <persName>Emigrants</persName>, and in many
parts of the <placeName>Province </placeName>Farming Utensils and Provisions, for one year
were granted to <persName>Emigrants</persName>&#8212;The consequences were such as were to
be expected</p>

<p>A considerable Emigration took place in <date n="xx-xx-1797">97</date> which continued untill
<date n="xx-xx-1801">1801</date>, the <persName>Americans </persName>generally settled back from the River and
Cultivated, the high lands, Provisions soon became plenty and the
prices greatly reduced Such were the effects produced by 
Emigration, that Bacon brought from <placeName>Kentucky</placeName>, in <date n="xx-xx-1797">97 </date>sold at 20 to 25 
Dollars pr Hundred and Country Pork at 40 Cents pr. pound could in
<date n="xx-xx-1803">1803</date>, be bought at 3$50 4$ pr. hundred, the advantages arising from
the Emigration, became so evident that the <persName>Spanish Officers</persName> gave
every encouragement the <persName>Emigrants </persName>could desire&#8212;Those advantages.
were not confind, to the Cultivation of the Land only but as a 
safeguard against the <persName>Indians</persName>&#8212;This was verified in <date n="xx-xx-1802">1802 </date>An 
expedition was ordered to remove a party of <persName>Creek Indians</persName>, who had 
intruded and committed some depredations in the <placeName>Province</placeName>&#8212;On this
expedition which consisted of about <persName>Four hundred and fifty Men</persName>.
Fifty or sixty were <persName>French </persName>and <persName>Four Hundred Americans</persName> this 
circumstance convinced the <persName>Officers of the Spanish Government</persName>, of the
advantages arising from, the emigration of the <persName>Americans</persName>&#8212;The
<placeName>Pamphlets </placeName>Publish'd in <date n="xx-xx-1796">96</date> by the <persName>Commandants of <placeName>Upper Louisiana</placeName></persName>
became generally known in <date n="xx-xx-1800">1800 </date>in consequence the Emigration 
became as General and continued increasing, untill unexpectly checked
by the changes of <persName>Government </persName>in <date n="xx-xx-1804">1804</date>. It is not to be doubted but a
Continuation under the <persName>Spanish Government</persName> Four or Five Years
longer would have made the out <placeName>Settlements </placeName>sufficiently strong, to
protect and defend themselves, against the attacks of the <persName>Indians</persName>.</p>

<p>It was generally believed that all the <persName>Emigrants</persName>, who had made
arrangements to remove to <placeName>upper Louisiana</placeName> in all the Year <date n="xx-xx-1803">1803 </date>and
four under promise and permission, either written or unwritten from
the <persName>Spanish Government</persName>, and had arriv'd in the <placeName>Country </placeName>or were on
the way, would be sanctioned by the <persName>American Government</persName></p>

<p>In this state of things the <persName>American Government</persName> took possession of
<placeName>Louisiana</placeName>, No prohibitary Law was promulgated, to stop 
Emigration, untill <date n="03-xx-1804">March 1804</date>:&#8212;and this Law did not take place untill
<date n="08-xx-1804">October </date>following&#8212;From that period we may date the stoppage of<pb n="117"/>
the Emigration, and Settlement on <placeName>Public Lands</placeName>,&#8212;Before I proceed
to an explanation of the situation of the <persName>Inhabitants of this 
<placeName>Territory</placeName></persName>, In consequence of the present Laws of <persName>Congress</persName>, allow me to
give you a summary statement of the conduct of the <persName>Spanish 
Commandants</persName> of this part of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>&#8212;It is Notoriously known, that
for Years before the change of <persName>Government</persName>, the <persName>Commandants</persName> 
refus'd to give Concessions for Lands except on some particular 
Occasions, but at the same time, suffr'd the Emigration to continue and
gave verbal permissions to <persName>settlers</persName>, to establish themselves on any
Lands not in the possession of others,&#8212;But no sooner was it known,
that the <placeName>Province of Louisiana</placeName> was sold to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, than a
general and fraudulent Sale of Lands took place&#8212;A <placeName>Land Office</placeName> was
opened at <placeName>Cape Gererdeau</placeName>&#8212;The <persName>Agents of the Lieut. Govr</persName>. in every
part of the <placeName>upper country</placeName>, made use of every possible exertion, to
make the Sale of Lands Productive&#8212; Concessions for any quantity
of Land were daily granted bearing date in <date n="xx-xx-1799">1799</date> or further back if
the <persName>claiments </persName>demanded, the number of Acres Granted was govern'd
by the sum paid it is not necessary to say to what extent, this 
Speculation has been carried on&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>Agent of the <placeName>United States</placeName> for Land claims</persName>, will it is probable
make a report to the proper <placeName>Department</placeName>, on this subject&#8212; It is I
presume to correct this Speculation, that <persName>Congress </persName>has made the Law
appointing <persName>Commissioners</persName>, to examine the Land claims in this 
<placeName>Territory </placeName>and not as many suppose, to destroy the well founded claims
of the <persName>Citizens</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I have considered the <persName>Commissioners </persName>as a <persName>Court or board of 
examiners</persName>, to enquire into the nature of the claims of the <persName>Inhabitants</persName>,
and make a true and full report thereon, that our <persName>Government </persName>may
know the situation and extent of the claims, Such a report might
have given <persName>Congress </persName>an opportunity to make such other and further
Laws as are necessary to cover and serve the actual <persName>Settler</persName>, and
discard the <persName>Speculator</persName>&#8212; But from the high and in my opinion
improper interference of <persName>Govr. Wilkinson</persName> are in a measure defeated
That you may have a full knowledge of this part of our <persName>Govr</persName>. 
conduct, I inclose you his Proclamation and orders to the <persName>Surveyor Genl.
Ant° Soulard</persName> rais'd to that office by <persName>Govr. Wilkinson</persName>, The 
consequences produced by the Orders of <persName>Wilkinson </persName>respecting the 
surveying of <placeName>Lands</placeName>, were truly distressing, this step produced the greatest
consternation among the <persName>people </persName>The time far advanced for 
surveying Claims, and not a Plat or claim, would be receiv'd, by the 
<persName>Recorder Donaldson</persName>, unless first certify'd by <persName>Soulard</persName>, as being 
Survey'd under the Order of <persName>Wilkinson</persName>, not withstanding <persName>Deputies </persName>were
sent out to Survey the Claims of the <persName>People</persName>, not more than two<pb n="118"/>
thirds, of those claims were Survey'd in time and in consequence, not
Recorded agreeable to law&#8212;</p>

<p>The extravagant fees for Surveying rendered it impossible for
numbers of the Poor to have their claims Survey'd, admitting the
<persName>Deputies</persName>, could have survey'd them in time Perhaps no People
under any <persName>Government</persName>, were ever placed in a more difficult and
ruinous situation&#8212; On one hand the Law of <persName>Congress </persName>called for a
return, and Record of all claims, by a given day, under the penalty
of forever after being barred the right to bring them forward&#8212;On
the other <persName>Govr. Wilkinson</persName> by his absolute order declar'd that, unless,
all claims were survey'd agreeable to his mandate they should not be
receiv'd by the <persName>Recorder</persName>&#8212;To comply with both these demands was
as impossible as to serve God and Mammon;&#8212;because the number of
<persName>Deputies </persName>employed were not sufficient to do the work by the <date when="1804-03-01">first of
March</date>&#8212;and because it was not in the power of the People to raise
money to pay the <persName>Surveyors </persName>Demands,-&#8212;Twenty Thousand Dollars
is a sum the <persName>Poor People of <placeName>Upper Louisiana</placeName></persName> were not nor are able
to pay in Sixty or Eighty days&#8212;The <persName>settlers on the <placeName>River Arkansas</placeName>
and <placeName>St. Francis</placeName></persName> have suffer'd greatly&#8212; The distance from <placeName>St.
Louis</placeName>, being about Four Hundred Miles, and through a <placeName>Wilderness
Country</placeName>, had it not in their power, to make their returns by the <date when="1804-03-01">first
of March</date>-&#8212;The regulations of <persName>Wilkinson </persName>did not reach them untill a
few Weeks, before the time for Recording claims expir'd, and then
not a <persName>Surveyor </persName>untill some time in January&#8212;however, a number
sent forward their claims to be Recorded, but were refus'd for want
of <persName>Soulard</persName>s Certificate that the Surveys had been made agreeable,
to the Orders of <persName>Wilkinson</persName>, Therefore, all such Claims, which
comprehend one Third of all the claims in the <placeName>Territory</placeName>, are 
agreeable to the present Laws of <persName>Congress </persName>for ever lost.&#8212; The 
consequences resulting from such a State of things is readily told&#8212;It
drew down the imprecations of an enraged and injur'd People on
the <persName>Government</persName>, they contrasted their situation with that under the
<persName>Spanish Government</persName> it caused dissatisfaction and disaffection&#8212;It
was in vain to tell them the fault lay not with Government, but with
the <persName>Governor</persName>&#8212;the People felt themselves injur'd without the power
or prospect of gaining redress.</p>

<p>The objects of <persName>Wilkinson </persName>for thus Acting in open violation of the
Laws of <persName>Congress </persName>is yet to be told, if he has an excuse for his 
conduct, it behoves him to make it, for he has plung'd the <persName>people of
<placeName>Louisiana</placeName></persName> into a Labyrinth of difficulties which the interference of
<persName>Congress </persName>only can remedy&#8212;The Surveying system adopted by 
<persName>Wilkinson</persName>, was oppos'd by <persName>Judge Lucas</persName> but in vain, he was overruled
by <persName>Penrose </persName>and <persName>Donaldson </persName>thus you see the object of the <persName>Americans</persName>
Emigrating to this <placeName>Country</placeName>, became abortive&#8212;The promisses made<pb n="119"/>
by the <persName>Spanish Officers</persName> countermanded by the change of <persName>Government</persName>,
and the out <placeName>settlements </placeName>formed under an expectation of being filled
up and Strengthened defeated and the People left to the Mercy of
the <persName>American Government</persName>.</p>

<p>Under such circumstances the <persName>Commissioners </persName>began their duties,
and had they acted with the greatest prudence and judgment 
imaginable they could not have satisfy'd the <persName>People</persName>, because the Law 
excluded them from doing Justice, yet a temperate line of conduct
might have quiet'd, the minds of the people, untill the <persName>Government</persName>
could have made such alterations, as the situation of their case 
requir'd, and had <persName>Mr. Donaldson</persName>, the <persName>Recorder </persName>admited on record thier
claims presented, and strictly attended to the Law of <persName>Congress </persName>
instead of the Law of the <persName>Govr</persName>. the state of things would be pleasing,
even under all the restrictions of the Law to what they are at present</p>

<p>It now remains to point out how the affairs of this <placeName>Territory </placeName>may
be changed and placed in a situation to quiet the minds of the <persName>People</persName>
and do them Justice, and at the same time secure the <persName>Government</persName>
against Impositions.&#8212;To secure the <placeName>Frontiers</placeName>, against <persName>Spanish </persName>and
<persName>Indian </persName>depredations.&#8212;To prevent the extension of the <placeName>Settlements</placeName>
and lesson the necessity of regular <persName>Troops</persName>.&#8212;</p>

<p>You may, perhaps, think it presuming for any <persName>Citizen </persName>to, take on
himself to point out the measures <persName>Government </persName>ought to adopt to
effect so desirable an object&#8212;Yet I may have it in my power to 
mention some things worthy of communication.&#8212;</p>

<p>It is not for me to say wether the Purchase of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>, is or is
not an advantageous acquisition to the <placeName>United States</placeName>.&#8212;but I think
it my duty to point out in what manner, it can be best secur'd so as
to be the least expence to <persName>Government </persName>and do Justice to the <persName>People</persName>.</p>

<p>First, to content the <persName>People</persName>, give them a <persName>Governour </persName>unconnected
with the <persName>Military</persName>&#8212;Grant to the actual <persName>Resident</persName>, in the <placeName>Territory </placeName>up
to <date n="10-xx-1804">October 1804</date>, Lands equal in quantity to that usually granted by
the <persName>Spanish Government</persName>&#8212;-say not less than three nor more than
six hundred and forty acres, Confirm all <placeName>Spanish Grants</placeName>, not 
exceeding Six Hundred and forty acres, so that no man has confirm'd to
him but one <placeName>Grant</placeName>, provided always that the <placeName>Grant </placeName>is in favour of
an actual <persName>settler</persName>, and gra[n]ted at the time it bears date&#8212; Suffer
a division of Concession to be made where the object is for cultivation
and Building <placeName>Mills</placeName> provided the Concession or permission was
granted or given for that intent, but at the same time, not exceeding
six Hundred and forty Acres in all do this, and the difficulties
respecting <placeName>Land claims</placeName> will be remov'd and the People satisfy'd.&#8212;</p>

<p>To justify the claims of the <persName>Inhabitints of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName></persName>, up to <date n="10-xx-1804">October
1804</date> It may be observ'd, that the <persName>People </persName>emigrating to this Country
could have no knowledge of what was doing between <placeName>France </placeName>and<pb n="120"/>
<placeName>Spain</placeName>, nor between <placeName>France </placeName>and the <placeName>United States</placeName>, it was sufficient
for them to obtain liberty to settle from <persName>Spanish Officers</persName>, or in other
words, that they were suffer'd to settle on any Lands, within the
<placeName>Kings Domains</placeName> not in the occupancy of others&#8212; That the <persName>Spanish
Officers</persName> suffer'd the <persName>Americans</persName>, to emigrate untill the change of
<persName>Government </persName>took place cannot be denied, not only suffer'd, but 
contended they had a right to dispose of Land untill <persName>Gov'r Clabourn</persName>
took possession of <placeName>N Orleans</placeName>&#8212;Ought an uninformed People to 
suffer for settling on Lands promised to them by <persName>Spanish Officers</persName>, and
which their Printed Hand Bills assur'd them should be confirm'd
to them on condition, they become actual <persName>Setlers</persName>&#8212; It ought to be
remember'd, that whilst the <placeName>United States </placeName>were contracting with
<placeName>France </placeName>for <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>, the Emigration continued&#8212;no steps were taken
by the <persName>Spanish Officers</persName>, or <persName>Government </persName>to undeceive the <persName>People</persName>, and
that had the change never taken place, all the Actual <persName>Settlers </persName>would
have obtained Land for Cultivation</p>

<p>It ought also to be remember'd, that Hundreds, who Settl'd in the
<date n="Spring-1804">Spring of 1804</date>, had in the <date n="Fall-1802">Fall </date>and <date n="Summer-1803">Summer </date>of <date n="Summer-1802">1802</date> and <date n="Fall-1803">1803 </date>visited
this <placeName>Country </placeName>and return'd after their <persName>Families </persName>and some time was
necessary to dispose of Property and remove to the Country, and
although the change might have been heard of, their arrangements
were made and they could not Retract&#8212;Their <placeName>Houses </placeName>and <placeName>Lands </placeName>
dispos'd of thier little all a Float, and they were oblig'd to come 
forward and meet their fate be the Consequence ever so distressing&#8212;
Many of those <persName>settlers </persName>took possession of Land in the <date n="Spring-1804">Spring </date>and
<date n="Summer-1804">Summer of 1804</date> and after expending from Twenty to Thirty Dollars
for Surveying and Recording Fees, find themselves stripped of both
Land and Money</p>

<p>The Law of the <placeName>United States</placeName> cuts them off and presents to them
Misery and ruin&#8212;Murmurs and Complaints are the Consequence
Under such circumstances can the <persName>People of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName></persName> be well 
dispos'd towards the <placeName>United States</placeName>. Ask yourself wether, something is
not necessary to be done for them&#8212;wether their situation does not
call for some Act of Government to regain and secure thier 
affections :&#8212;This something is easily told&#8212; Give them a <persName>Govr </persName>who has
the interest of the <placeName>Territory </placeName>at heart Give Land to each <persName>resident</persName>
up to <date n="xx-xx-1804">1804 </date>Suffer the Country to settle, so as to strengthen the out
<placeName>Settlements </placeName>and the Cloud of Discontent will vanish, the <persName><placeName>United
States</placeName> Government</persName> will find <placeName>Louisiana </placeName>a valueable and advantageous
acquisition&#8212;</p>

<p>Secondly to secure this Country from <persName>Spanish </persName>and <persName>Indian </persName>
depredations to elucidate this point, I submit the following observations,
It is to be remember'd I have before stated that in <date n="xx-xx-1797">1797</date> the 
<placeName>outsettlements </placeName>began to form and continued to increase gradually untill<pb n="121"/>
<date n="xx-xx-1804">1804</date>, but in so short a time it cannot be suppos'd those <placeName>Settlements</placeName>
could become very strong&#8212;They extended about <placeName>Sixty Miles back
from the Mississippi Westward</placeName> and about <placeName>Forty or Fifty Miles above
the Missouri</placeName>, from the <placeName>upper Settlements on the Mississippi</placeName> down
to <placeName>N Madrid</placeName> the distance is about two Hundred and Fifty Miles,
from <placeName>N Madrid</placeName> to the <placeName>Arkansas </placeName>is about Three hundred Miles, and
is unsettled except on the <placeName>banks of the Mississippi</placeName>, <placeName>Arkansas </placeName>and <placeName>St.
Francis</placeName>. These <placeName>settlements </placeName>it is true are small, but small as they
are have a claim on <persName>Government </persName>for protection they were formed
under the <persName>Spanish Government</persName>, the <placeName>United States</placeName> found them 
Possessed of rights&#8212;and reason Justice and National Honour require
they should be secur'd and protected in those rights&#8212;It cannot now
be said, that the <placeName>out Settlements</placeName> are to be abandoned by 
<persName>Government</persName>&#8212;No the Protecting Arm of the <placeName>United States</placeName> must 
Encircle them how is this to be done,&#8212;To furnish <persName>Regular Troops</persName> to 
protect so extended a <placeName>Frontier</placeName>, together with the <placeName>low Country</placeName> will
require more <persName>Troops</persName>, than the <placeName>United States</placeName> have in Service&#8212;and
a sum of Money which would embarrass the <persName>Treasury</persName>&#8212;all these
difficulties, may in my opinion be easily remov'd and the <placeName>United
States</placeName> instead of expending money derive an advantage from the
systim to be now propos'd, and at the same time set bounds to a class
of men, who are never satisfy'd long in any place, and by their
frequent removals, to the Westard, will extend the <placeName>Frontiers </placeName>beyond
the controul of <persName>Government</persName>, which I am confident is for the Interest
of the <placeName>United States</placeName>, to check for the present&#8212;</p>

<p>Suffer a line of Demarcation to be drawn, Beginning as high
above the <placeName>Missouri </placeName>as will cover the <placeName>settlements </placeName>up to <date n="xx-xx-1804">1804</date>, extend
this line down the <placeName>Mississippi </placeName>to the <placeName>Arkansas </placeName>covering all those
<placeName>Settlements </placeName>between those two points which I have reason to believe
will not exceed Sixty miles in any place direct Westerly from the
<placeName>Mississippi</placeName>&#8212;Let this strip of Land be divided into Townships, 
Sections, half and quarter Sections, and sold or disposed of in such
manner as <persName>Congress </persName>shall point out reserving to the <placeName>United States</placeName>
such Land as are supposed to contain Lead and other Minerals, and
<placeName>Salt Springs</placeName>&#8212;These measures will in my opinion remove two great
difficulties it will strengthen the whole extent of our <placeName>Western 
Frontiers</placeName>, so that in two or three years, by a proper <persName>Militia </persName>
Establishment, the <persName>inhabitants </persName>will be able to protect themselves, it will set
bounds to the <persName>Wanderers</persName>, beyond which they will not attempt to
settle with an expectation from the <placeName>United States</placeName>&#8212;The <persName>settler </persName>Found
within the <placeName>Spanish limits</placeName> when the <persName>American Government</persName> took
possession of <placeName>Louisiana </placeName>will find himself secure in his situation the
objects for which he removd to <placeName>Louisiana </placeName>fully answer'd and every<pb n="122"/>
expectation filled up&#8212;<persName>Regular Troops</persName> except on the line of 
Demarcation will be unnecessary&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>Citizen</persName>, will then feel himself, bound to answer the call of
<persName>Government</persName>, to remove <persName>unauthorized Settlers</persName>, the <placeName>banks of the
Mississippi</placeName> secur'd from <persName>banditti</persName>, the <persName>Treasury of the <placeName>United States</placeName></persName>
replenish'd by the sale of <placeName>Lands</placeName>&#8212;the <placeName>Lead Mines</placeName>, the riches of
which are but imperfectly known will furnish an abundant supply
for the <placeName>United States</placeName> and yeald an increase, to the Public Chest,
which no common Calculation can reach&#8212;Such I am confident will
be the system founded on the principal I have pointed out&#8212;But
should the contrary [be] adopted, should the destroying System,
prevail and the government attempt to depopulate the <placeName>Western
banks of the Mississippi</placeName> as has been declar'd by <persName>Govr' Wilkinson</persName>,
was the object of the Executive, the <placeName>United States</placeName> will have cause
to regret, the moment they became possessd of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>, such a
project can never be effected but with immense expence and trouble
and after all the exertions of the <persName>Government </persName>would prove abortive&#8212;</p>

<p><placeName>Louisiana </placeName>under such a system would become a Nest of <persName>Robbers</persName>
and the <persName>outcasts </persName>from all <persName>Governments</persName>, would seek an Assylum in
this extensive <placeName>Wilderness</placeName>, and in a short time, the energy of 
Government, would be unequal to controul them, the Navigation of the
<placeName>Mississippi </placeName>would become more dangerous than to Traverse the
wilds of <placeName>Arabia</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>In addition to what has been observ'd respecting claims I ought
to have Noticed the situation of the <persName>Inhabitants of the <placeName>French
villages</placeName></persName>. It [is] a fact well known, that, these people have regarded
the Title to Land, of little consequence, and that the <persName>Spanish 
Government</persName>, suffer'd them to Cultivate such Lands as they thought
proper and that any piece of ground inclos'd by an <persName>inhabitant </persName>or
occupyed as a <placeName>Sugar camp</placeName>, has been consider'd as the legal right of
such <persName>Inhabitant</persName>, and when such piece of Ground or Improvement,
has been taken by Execution, the Validity of the <persName>Sheriff</persName>s sale has
always been considered as indisputable.</p>

<p>It is also proper to observe, that those <persName>Villagers </persName>commonly 
Cultivated Lands, a little distance from the <placeName>Village</placeName>, which Lands, are
not immediately attached to thier <placeName>Dwellings</placeName>, and therefore cannot
be considered as coming within the second Section of the Law of
<persName>Congress</persName>, I therefore think a Special Law of <persName>Congress</persName>, ought to be
made securing to the <persName>Villagers </persName>such Lands, as they have been in
the custom of Improving and also all <placeName>Town Lots</placeName>, whether they
have been built on or not so as they come under the Denomination
of <placeName>Town Lots</placeName>&#8212;</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
