<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0469">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Bryan to J. E. B. Austin, 01-15-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Bryan</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J. E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Hazel Run, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Colorado, TX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 463-464
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-01-15">01-15-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Settlers going to Texas. Selection of land.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Hazel Run</placeName> <date when="1822-01-15">January 15th 1822</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>I have not heard from you since you left <placeName>White River</placeName>. I have
no doubt that a letter may be at the <placeName>Office </placeName>for me. I presume ere
this you are nearly at the place of destination and I hope you have
enjoyed good health and all the party and I am flattering myself
with the antisipation of favourable News from you shortly after
your arrival at the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>, and I have no doubt that the 
<persName>emigrants </persName>are arriveing daily as it appears to be the General rage in
every quarter to Move to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and I have so favourable an 
oppertunity to write you, that I have concluded to fill the sheet if I say<pb n="464"/>
but little The <persName>bearer </persName><persName>Mr Bobert. C. Bruffy </persName>and his <persName>Brother </persName><persName>Majr
Hawkins</persName> and <persName>Doctr Hart</persName> are the party and a great number will
Move the insueing <date n="Fall-1822">Autumn </date>from the <placeName>Mines </placeName>and from this State
Generally may God Grant all favourable relative to the <placeName>Colony</placeName>,
and if nothing unfavourable occurs relative to the <persName>government </persName>it
will fill up imediately and will make a Market for Provissions, and
Merchandise. I trust you will arrive Safe, and that you can make
an advantageous Barter for Stock, and I will expect <persName>Stephen </persName>and
you to display Judgement in makeing a Selection of Land for me,
and I wish you to Hire two young men for me to make an 
Improvement and raise Some Corn and if you can procure Stock for
me they can take care of it; perhaps <persName>Bartholomew </persName>and <persName>Powell </persName>will
engage, I will bring on Some Provissions; and all I can of other
articles perhaps I will send on Provissions this <date n="Spring-1822">next Spring</date> I will
expect advices on this Subject from <persName>Stephen </persName>and you by every 
Opportunity I have no doubt Provisions will be very low in the <date n="Spring-1822">Spring</date>
at <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, nothing has happened of importance Since you left
us. We have a New County Called <placeName>St Francis</placeName>, and consequently
<persName>officers </persName>wanting and great anxiety etc.&#8212; The <persName>Legislature </persName>has made
a Property Law Property must sell for two thirds its value, or
the <persName>Creditor </persName>must wait two years and Six Months&#8212; No doubt before
you receive this you will See two <persName>Brothers </persName>of the Name of <persName>Howells</persName>
from Near <placeName>St Charles</placeName> I wrote by them to Brother <persName>Stephen </persName>and I
presume you will find them to be worthy men a few days Since <persName>Mr
Eaglebarger</persName> recd a letter from Cheak who Stated he was engaged
Surveying for <persName>Stephen </persName>and he Speaks Very Highly of the Country.
<persName>McCormack </persName>and <persName>McClain </persName>and a number more talks of moveing some
in the <date n="Spring-1822">Spring </date>others in the <date n="Fall-1822">fall</date>&#8212;please give me a full detale of every
important particular relative to the Country, Prospects etc.&#8212; You
will no doubt have many oppertunities to write I will Send by <persName>Mr
Bruffy</persName> the Certificate of your birth and Baptism&#8212; I have not as
yet recd any letters for you&#8212; If I do I will send them on, tell
<persName>Bartholomew </persName>and <persName>Powell </persName>I will expect to receive letters from
them and will answer them, I am in hopes <persName>Mr Henry Elliott</persName> will
have it in his Power to raise Some Cash there for me and Settle
it with me here <persName>Mother</persName>s health is much better than when you
left us, and the <persName>Family </persName>in good health and all relatives&#8212; God
Bless you   Our prayers is for your health and Prosperity</p>

<p><persName>J. Bryan.</persName></p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr J. E. B. Austin</persName> <placeName>Mouth of the Colorado Provence
of Texas</placeName>   Attention <persName>Mr. Bruffy</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
