<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Unknown, 08-01-1791</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-09">06-09-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Philadelphia, PA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 9-10
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Remarks</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1791-08-01">08-01-1791</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Remarks on casting shot.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>COMMON PLACE BOOK, began.&#8212; <placeName>PHILADELPHIA </placeName><date when="1791-08-01">AUGUST 1st- 1791</date></p>
<p><persName>WATTS</persName>'s  PATENT.     SHOT</p>

<p><persName>George the third by the Grace of God King of <placeName>Great Britain</placeName>
<placeName>France </placeName>and <placeName>Ireland </placeName>King Defender of the Faith</persName> etc, etc., etc.</p>

<p>Doth by these his Royal Letters Patent Grant unto <persName>Josiah Watts</persName>
of the City of <placeName>Bristol</placeName>&#8212;Manufactorer on Consideration of------&#8212;
sum in hand well and truely paid unto his <persName>Majesties Collectors of
the Revenues</persName> for Granting Patents to such ingenious <persName>Artists </persName>and
<persName>discoverers </persName>of arts by their Invention in such Improvements as
may now or hereafter be beneficial to these Realms for the special
encouragement of Arts Sciences and Commerce&#8212; for the space of
fourteen Years to hold to himself his <persName>Heirs </persName>and <persName>administrators</persName>
Solely . . . By these his <persName>Magesties</persName> Royal Letters patent in full
authority, his art of making Globe Shot; now patented to him
and his <persName>heirs </persName>only for the space of Fourteen Years as <persName>Watts</persName>'s patent
Shot.</p>

<p>Method of Making <persName>Watts</persName>'s Globe or Patent Shot Continued from
his own specification perused and examin'd by <persName>Henry Miller of
<placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></persName> on the <date when="1789-02-12">12th- Day of February 1789</date> in the <placeName>Petty Bagg
office Roles of the Chancery of England. Chancery Lane</placeName></p>

<p>Take any quantity of pure pig Lead; and Melt down in Kettle
first for the purpose as usual for Drop Shot<pb n="10"/></p>

<p>The quantity of aceripigmentum Viz Yellow Arsenic is one pound
to 80lb of Lead but this differs something from the Ductility of the
Mettal   the <placeName>Cornwall </placeName>Lead requires Less than the <placeName>Devonshire</placeName></p>

<p>The Height required in Casting is left very obscure, nothing
more being Mention'd than about 40 feet woud be required for small
size to upwards of 80 for the Largest Swan Shot.</p>

<p>Nor does said specimen explain anything Satisfactory respecting
the formation of Tower more than it must be constructed high
enough to perform the operation of Granulating the shot in its
decent by the opposition of air it receives in its fall.</p>

<p>REMARKS. by Experience I have found a Much better Mode
to introduce the arsnic and find the white much preferable to the
Yellow from it[s] purity in strength. And that a material 
difference of the Height is required in the Climate of <placeName>America </placeName>in the
Different Seasons of the Year.</p>

<p>DROP   SHOT   MANUFACTORY</p>

<p>After being prepared with a proper Building for your purpose
if with a communication of a stream of water so much the better.
Wherein must be a Capatious high Chimney, or more; large enough
to contain 1 or 2 Furnaces or Melting pots a reverberating Temper
furnace and Drying pans provide 2 Casting Tubs strongly Iron
whoopd provided with two Brass Cocks one to supply Cold water
and the other to Let of the Hot with a strainer near the Bottom.</p>

<p>shall add but little of the Construction of these utensils as they
are better understood by an artist than Described more than the
Kettles should not be less than 2 feet Diameter and not more than
1  foot Deep thick and Sound Made,   the Casting Tubs not less than
2  feet 4 inches Diameter and not More than 2 feet 2 inches above
Ground for the Ease of the Caster</p>

<p>The Temper Furnace remains a Secret to the Trade only and the
Drying pans may be Constructed of any size in proportion to the
works in the most convenient situation of the <placeName>factory</placeName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
