<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0955">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>R. R. Royall to Stephen F. Austin, 12-28-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>R. R. Royall</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Tuscumbia, Alabama</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 1004-1006
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-12-28">12-28-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning Spanish land grants which he has bought near Nacogdoches.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>U. S. State of Alabama</placeName></p>
<p><placeName>Town of Tuscumbia Franklin County</placeName></p>
<p><persName>Col. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p>Sir Haveing some claims of Land in your country I am though
a <persName>stranger </persName>restrained to solicit some Information Relative to the
necessary requisites of your Government on such Claims.   My two<pb n="1005"/>
Claims one to <persName>Gregora Mora</persName> Signed by <persName>Cortez </persName>with an Instrument
of Grant following signed by <persName>Jose Cayetano De Zepeda</persName> Situated
<placeName>five miles South of Nacogdoches</placeName> and extending to the Junction of
<placeName>Cany </placeName>or <placeName>Carez </placeName>with <placeName>Angelina </placeName>or <placeName>Orhillian River</placeName> warranted to me to
be 10 000 arpens Spanish. <persName>Gregora mora</persName> sold this to <persName>Monsieur
Reliquet</persName> whose <persName>widow </persName>without Issue married <persName>Capt Martin Despalier
a Spaniard</persName> who together with his <persName>wife </persName>sold it to me in <placeName>Alexandria
La.</placeName> the other signed by the same <persName>Zepeda Sandick [Sindico]</persName> and
Attorney at Law of the town of our <placeName>Lady of the Pilar of Nacogdoches
</placeName>and its vecinity this last is translated and reads that in the year <date n="xx-xx-1796">1796</date>
in Conformity to a preceeding decree that <persName>Don Joseph de La Vaga
</persName>and <persName>Pedro de Lara</persName>, from the place called <placeName>Patron-cito</placeName> about <placeName>18 leagues
from Nacogdoches</placeName> with a view to put <persName>Don Santiago Fin</persName> in possession
of aforesaid place <placeName>Patron </placeName>and after stating much ceremony puts said
<persName>Fin </persName>in possession of this <placeName>Royall grant of Land</placeName> States him to be in
possession sole master <persName>Owner </persName>and <persName>Proprieter </persName>of two leagues square
or in every direction of the wind. This I am told is near the <placeName>Sabine</placeName>
where the Road crosses it between <placeName>Natchitoches </placeName>and <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>
was given or sold by <persName>Fin </persName>to <persName>Daniel Kimball</persName> who sold to me in <date n="xx-xx-1819">1819</date>
Since which I have determined to reside in <placeName>Texas </placeName>as soon as the
Government of that country become setled and haveing learned that
it had attained a tolerable setled and desirable state I should have
visited my Lands and your <placeName>Settlement </placeName><date n="Fall-1824">this Fall</date> But my business
being such as to require my presence generally at Home I have sought
this method to relieve myself from uneasy feelings arising from
consious neglect of the claims. I wish to learn from you what the
Settlement of Emigration is in the country generally and 
particularly in the vecinity of <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>If you are informed But more
particularly anxious to know what the disposition of your 
<persName>government </persName>is towards Such claims and from such information as you can
afford I can Learn what necessity if any there is for a visit to the
country before the <date n="Fall-1825">fall of 1825</date> at which time I expect to settle myself
in <placeName>Texas </placeName>and probably will be best pleased with your <placeName>Neighborhood</placeName>
I beg to be excused for and should not have troubled a Gentleman in
public employ but Haveing no acquaintance to rely upon have
troubled you with this communication If no return of Favour ever
falls in my way must ask you to receive my sincere thanks You have
been spoken of to me by <persName>Docter Charles Douglass</persName> of our Town who
says he had some acquaintance with you in the<persName> City of Mexico</persName> and
who expects to accompany me to the country Being myself almost
totally Ignorant of the Country and its Government, Such Other
Information as you can afford such as Relates to Slavery Religion
etc and such common characteristicks as attend the country will be<pb n="1006"/>
Thankfully Received By your's with the Highest Considerations of
Respect</p>
<p><date when="1824-12-28">December 28th 1824</date></p>

<p><persName>R R Royall</persName>.</p>

<p>P S Haveing just benn favrd by my friend <persName>Douglas </persName>with a 
communication from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>which stated that the <placeName>seat of your State
government</placeName> was fixed beyond the <placeName>Rio Grande</placeName>. I would like to know
when it would be in Session and If my grants would require their
confirmation to secure them to me and as I possess the Art of 
Surveying would Like to be informed If the Bussiness is encouraged in
<placeName>Texas </placeName>and If so what paid for in Money or Land</p>

<p><persName>R. R. R.</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
