<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0920">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Dr. John Sibley to Stephen F. Austin, 11-21-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Dr. John Sibley</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Natchitoches, LA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 974-975
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-11-21">11-21-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Claim of late Dr. Robinson against Mexican Government, which he traded to William Alexander Danlin. European news.   Presidential election of 1824.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Natchitoches </placeName><date when="1824-11-21">Novr 21st 1824</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>A few minutes ago I accidentally meet with the <persName>bearer </persName><persName>Mr Alcorn</persName>
who is going to Leave here in an hour. I have but little time to
write you and in a hurry to Bundle up for you a few <placeName>News papers</placeName>.
I have some time ago received from <persName>Mrs Robinson</persName> the <persName>Widow of
the Late Doctor Robinson</persName> a power of Atty to pursue a Claim on the
<persName>Mexican Government</persName> for the Services of her <persName>Husband </persName>as <persName>Brigadier
General</persName> in the Service of that Government</p>

<p>When the <persName>Doctor </persName>left that Country his Account was settled and
the <persName>Government </persName>allowed him twenty thousand dollars, he became
acquainted with<persName> William Alexander Danlin</persName> who had been Sometime
in the Service of that Country. <persName>Mr Danlin</persName> informed the <persName>Doctor</persName>
that by the death of his <persName>Father </persName>property had been left to him in
<placeName>Mississippi </placeName>and <placeName>Indiana </placeName>in Lands and <persName>Negroes </persName>to the value of
$20,000. he gave <persName>Dr Robinson</persName> a power to receive that property in
the <placeName>United States</placeName> and the <persName>Doctor </persName>Authorized him to Receive his
Claim on the <persName>Mexican Govt</persName> by way of Exchange; but the <persName>Doctor</persName>
Could never find any property of <persName>Danlin</persName>'s here; <persName>Mrs. Robinson</persName> is
Anxious to know if <persName>Danlin </persName>Recd the <persName>Doctor</persName>s Claim and if not
to Notify the proper department of the fraud of <persName>Danlin </persName>and to
prevent if possible his receiving it.&#8212;<pb n="975"/></p>

<p>Now I have no doubt through some acquaintance you have in
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>you can by writing Ascertain for her what it is important
for her to know, you will do me a favour if you will as soon as you
can attend to this subject.&#8212;</p>

<p>I have nothing important to inform you of that the <placeName>News papers
</placeName>will not acquaint you. the death of the <persName>king of France</persName> will produce no
Change. The state of affairs in <placeName>Spain </placeName>is Horrid, and a most Bloddy
Revolution is looked for.&#8212; <persName>Count Artoi</persName> who will be <persName>Charles X</persName> the
<persName>Successor of Louis XVIII</persName> is Sixty seven and in Bad health his
successor will be <persName>Angoloeme</persName>.&#8212;</p>

<p>Who will be Our Next <persName>President </persName>no one knows and you can guess
as well as any one here&#8212;you will find the papers much taken up with
the visit of <persName>General Lafayette</persName>. History Certainly furnishes no 
parralell of such a Universal Burst of Gratefull expression by so many
Millions of People.&#8212;</p>

<p>I have lately seen a hand bill signed by <persName>Mr. Holtham a lawyer</persName> of
this place addressed to the <persName>people of <placeName>Taxas</placeName></persName> denouncing <persName>Mr John Cook
</persName>as a <persName>Swindler </persName>etc, I think it an act of justice to <persName>Mr Cook</persName> to inform
you that so far as I know those Charges are unfounded. <persName>Mr 
Nancanow</persName>(?) Introduced him here they came from <placeName>Washita </placeName>together,
and I have seen <persName>Genl Hughes</persName> and other gentlemen from <placeName>Washita </placeName>who
never intimated any thing to the prejudice of <persName>Mr Cook</persName>, when he left
here some Business of his were Unsettled particularly as <persName>Collector
of Taxes</persName>, his Bond was in my hands as <persName>president of the Town Police</persName>
and it was put in suit agt his securities in Compliance with a 
formality, but I do not believe he is much in arrears, the suit stands
Continued. <persName>Mr. Holtham</persName> and <persName>Mr. Cook</persName> had a dispute and some
Blows passed between them they parted on bad terms. I believe few
persons here think the worse of <persName>Mr Cook</persName> or the better of <persName>Mr. 
Holtham</persName> for this attempt to injure him in a strange country. I ever
Regarded <persName>Mr. Cook</persName> as a temperate, sober genteal man, well quallified
for Business, he had my Confidence and might have it again.&#8212;</p>

<p>I Am always happy to hear from you, of the Welfare and the 
prosperity of your <placeName>settlement</placeName>&#8212;I have lately been informed you have
had an important accession of Territory Added to your former Grant,
including the <placeName>Inlet and Bay of Galveston</placeName>&#8212;I Now think I shall at
some future time Move and settle somewhere in <placeName>Taxas</placeName>: but to get
from where I have lived so long is difficult and much time is required
to arrange ones affairs&#8212;It is some time since I have had a letter
from you the last was by your <persName>Brother</persName>. I have written you several
since and sent you some <placeName>News papers</placeName>.&#8212;Our Legislature is in session
since Monday last, but we have not heard from them</p>

<p><persName>John Sibley</persName>    [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
