<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0919">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William Johnson to Stephen F. Austin, 11-21-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William Johnson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Woodville,MS</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 973-974
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-11-21">11-21-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Emigration from Mississippi.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Woodville </placeName><date when="1824-11-21">November 21st 1824.</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>A few days since I recd by <persName>Mr Huff</persName> your letter of the <date when="1824-10-26">26th Ult</date>:&#8212;
which afforded me much satisfaction, to know the flattering 
prospects of a pure and permanent government in your delightful and
fertile country&#8212;And I can in truth say that I am not a little 
gratified to learn from <persName>Mr. Huff</persName> that he is well pleased with the country
and that you have been so liberal with him as to induce him and his
partner <persName>Mr. Servison</persName> to embark immediately on improvements which
will not only benefit them and their <persName>families</persName>, but will no doubt
greatly advance the public weal of the Colony&#8212;Those men are now
making preparations to carry into effect with promptness, and in
good faith, everything which <persName>Mr Huff</persName> agreed to do in their Articles
with you&#8212;And I feel satisfied that you will be pleased with the
performance on their part&#8212;They will be able to take with them
every facility necessary to complete the works in a reasonable time&#8212;
The present plan is to Charter a steam-Boat as the most safe and
easy means of conveying the whole out fit to <placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName>&#8212;
<persName>Colo Child</persName> left here a day or two since for <placeName>Natchez</placeName>, where he will
endeavor to make the arrangements for the steam-Boat&#8212;If this
arrangement succeeds, I shall no doubt be one of the party myself&#8212;
<persName>Mr Huff</persName> mentioned to me that you would on my going out and 
compliance with the terms of your government give me a <placeName>Grant </placeName>for two
Leagues of Land adjoining the <placeName>Mill Tract</placeName>, below, on the <placeName>Bernard</placeName>,
and that you would not otherwise dispose of it till you heard from
me&#8212;for your friendly disposition towards me in this business, you
have my grateful acknowledgements&#8212;And have to request that you<pb n="974"/>
will secure for me the two Leagues of Land above mentioned&#8212;<persName>Mr
Huff</persName> also mentioned that you spoke of letting me have a grant for
seven Leagues of Land to be located in the <placeName>wood-land</placeName> <placeName>between the
Brazos and Bernard</placeName>, on conditions, etc, etc,&#8212;I assure you Sir, I 
consider those offers flattering and worthy the attention of any man&#8212;
and shall endeavor to avail myself of them, and hope by my feeble
exertions to promote the prosperity of the <placeName>Colony</placeName>, in some degree to
deserve something&#8212;I say to you candidly, that when I settle my
family in your <placeName>Colony</placeName>, I shall be extremely solicitous to have as
neighbors, a few respectable acquaintances etc, from this vecinity&#8212;
who will be anxious to move with me&#8212;all of which I wish you to
bear in mind&#8212;And that I shall endeavour to take along <persName>friends of
Capital</persName>&#8212;who will take with them the means of advancing the 
importance of the Country&#8212;-<persName>Mr Huff</persName> requests me to say to you that he
will procure for you and take out with him, the Articles which he
promised you.&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Wm Johnson</persName>.</p>
<p><persName>Honbl. Stephen F. Austin</persName>&#8212;<placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>-&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
