<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0004">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Ruston to Moses Austin, 09-23-1794</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Thomas Ruston</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-09">06-09-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Mr Jos: Burr
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Moses Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Philadelphia, PA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 11-12
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1794-09-23">09-23-1794</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Virginia land warrants and other speculations.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Philadelphia </placeName><date when="1794-09-23">Sept: 23d: 1794</date>.</p>
<p>Sir</p>

<p>The <persName>bearer </persName><persName>Mr Jos: Burr</persName> is a gentleman, who has been in the
practice of attending surveys of land, for the purpose of making
observations on the soil, situation, climate, waters, rivers, timber,
mines, and such other things as may tend to give a compleat and
perfect knowledge of their nature and value. It is with this view
I have sent him on to view the lands we are taking up in the 
<placeName>neighbourhood of the mines</placeName>, and have committed to his care <placeName>Virginia</placeName>
Warrants for Two Hundred Thousand Acres of land in addition to
the Ten Thousand Acre Warrants, which I forwarded before, and
which you have recd-</p>

<p>In your letter of the <date when="1794-08-16">16th. of August</date> which I have recd. you 
mention two propositions with respect to the terms upon which you
wish the land to be taken up, one with regard to the first, the other
respecting the second Two Hundred Thousand Acres, and you say
that you had agreed to let the <persName>surveyor </persName>have 80,000 out of the first
<placeName>two Hundred Thousand Acres</placeName>, he paying the expences. do you mean
the <persName>surveyor</persName>s fees, <persName>chain carrier</persName>s, and other incidental expences.
With regard to your two propositions, I do not see the propriety of
your making any distinction betwixt them, the expense and trouble
attending the one will be as great as that of attending the other; and<pb n="12"/>
no more, besides, in all the <placeName>lands </placeName>I have taken up in <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>,
which have amounted to <placeName>many hundred Thousand Acres</placeName>, I have
never been asked by the <persName>discoverers </persName>for more than a third, some
times a fourth, sometimes a fifth, and it is always the business of the
<persName>discoverers </persName>(in which capacity you and <persName>Mr Gnes [Gains?]</persName> are to be
considered) to attend and to superintend the surveys. This third the
<persName>discoverers </persName>divide betwixt themselves in such manner as they can
agree, and as they think proper. In a former letter you hinted, that
you thought it would be more agreeable to the <persName>Surveyor </persName>to have a
compensation in money, to this I shall have no objection if we can
agree upon the sum, and I shall have no objection to do the same
thing with you if it is agreeable. I have accepted your draft for
five hundred Dollars towards paying for the <placeName>Kentucky </placeName>Warrants
as you desire. As soon as the <persName>Surveyor </persName>has made out the returns <persName>Mr.
Burr</persName> will proceed with them to <placeName>Richmond </placeName>in order to obtain the
Patents.</p>

<p>N. B. <persName>Mr Norwell</persName> has not brot the deed either from <placeName>Lynchburgh</placeName>
or from <placeName>Richmond</placeName>-</p>

<p><persName>Thos. Ruston</persName></p>

<p>Take care you do not buy more Warrants than you can find land
for.</p>

<p>Point out to <persName>Mr Burr </persName>those tracts in the <placeName>neighbourhood </placeName>that are to
be disposed of, in order that he may be able to give me some account
of them, and send me the lowest prices and the longest terms of 
payment which the owners will be willing to take&#8212;</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
