<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0594">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James E. B. Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 05-25-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James E. B. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Bexar, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 648-649
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-05-25">05-25-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning a business transaction of Gov. Trespalacios. Good crops. Commerce.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Bexar </placeName><date when="1823-05-25">May 25 1823</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Brother</persName>,</p>

<p>No one can imagine with what pleasure I received my dear
<persName>Brother</persName>s letters, from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and <placeName>Qeretaro </placeName>of the <date when="1823-04-15">15</date> and <date when="1823-04-23">23</date> of last
month; the very Idea of your having left <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and that I shall
have the satisfaction of giving you an embrace in course of a few
weeks, I can assure you alters very much the muscles of my face
and removes that "pesadumbre" that has attended me for the last
twelve months; You wish me to give you all the news; At present
I am void of information that would be interesting to you I had
communicated to you everything of note in letters sent to the care of
<persName>Andrews </persName>in <placeName>Satillo</placeName>, which I hope you will receive when you arrive
in that place&#8212;There remains some business to be transacted in the
city of <placeName>Monclova</placeName>, which if you can attend to will save some trouble.</p>

<p>In the year <date n="xx-xx-1822">1822</date> <persName>Dr Victor Blanco the Brother in law of Musquis</persName>
in Compy with <persName>Dn Franco Madero</persName> of the city of <placeName>Monclova </placeName>went to
<placeName>New Orleans</placeName> to purchase goods&#8212;<persName>Madero </persName>and <persName>Musquis </persName>returned in
the sloop Only Son owned by <persName>J. Hawkins</persName>, on their arrival in this
place, <persName>Madero </persName>not being able to raise the money to pay his part of
the freight (which amounted to 450 dollars) gave his note payable
in 60 days, with <persName>Trespalacios </persName>as security after the expiration of
some months, <persName>L. Hawkins</persName> to whom the note was given, called on
<persName>Trespalacios </persName>for the money he did not find it convenient to pay it
as <persName>Madero </persName>had not remitted him funds to do so the Business rested
so untill <persName>L. Hawkins</persName> left this, he put the note in the hands of an
<persName>agent </persName>and <persName>partner</persName>, a <persName>Mr Dimitt</persName>, for collection he immediately 
presented the note to <persName>Trespalacios</persName>, who refused to pay it and stated as
his reason that <persName>Madero </persName>had not sent him funds to do so with; and
that he was about to start for <placeName>Monclova </placeName>and would convince <persName>Sor.
Madero</persName> that he was not bound to pay it. <persName>Mr Dimitt</persName> accordingly 
forwarded on the note by <persName>Dn Alexandro Treviño</persName>, to <persName>Dn Victor Blanco</persName><pb n="649"/>
to collect the money. Now if you. could make it convenient to 
collect the money <persName>Dimitt </persName>wishes you to do so. the money is <persName>J. Hawkins</persName>.
If you do not attend to it he (<persName>Dimitt</persName>) will have to go himself to
<placeName>Monclova </placeName>the <persName>Doctor [James Hewitson]</persName> is in <placeName>Monclova </placeName>and can give
you some information on the subject the <persName>Dr </persName>is my most Intimate
<persName>friend </persName>I sent a note I held against an <persName>officer of the Dairango Troops</persName>
for $20 to the <persName>Doctor </persName>to see if he could meet with any method of
collecting the money. Intercede with him to sell it at most he can
get for it if there is no opportunity of collecting it.</p>

<p>The <persName>settlers </persName>are in the best of spirits their crops look beautiful
The season has been remarkable and they will raise more corn
than they will know what to do with</p>

<p><persName>Santiago    </persName>[Rubric]</p>

<p>P. S. Do not forget to bring me a Spanish saddle and <hi rend="italic">galapago</hi>,
and also a Spanish <hi rend="italic">Wide Brim, White, Wool, Hat,</hi> I understand they
are very cheap and it will be almost impossible to stand the <placeName>prairie</placeName>
without one&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
