<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0595">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James E. B. Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 05-25-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James E. B. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Bexar, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 649-650
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-05-25">05-25-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning a business transaction of Gov. Trespalacios. Good crops. Commerce.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Bexar </placeName><date when="1823-05-25">May 25th 1823</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Brother</persName>,</p>

<p>I have written you two letters this mail one directed to <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>
and the other to <placeName>Monterey</placeName>; the object of this is to inform you of
some business that if you can attend to will save some trouble to the
party concerned.</p>

<p><date n="Summer-1822">Last summer</date> <persName>Dn Victor Blanco</persName> of the <placeName>City of Monclova</placeName>, went on
to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> with his <persName>brother in law</persName> <persName>Dn Ramon Musquis</persName> of this
place (with whom you are acquainted) also <persName>Dn Franco. Madero of
<placeName>Monclova</placeName></persName>, after making a purchase of the Goods <persName>Musquis </persName>and 
<persName>Madero </persName>returned by water in the sloop only Son then owned by <persName>J. H.
Hawkins</persName>. After their arrival in [this] place <persName>Madero </persName>not being able
to raise money to discharge his part of the Freight (about 450 
dollars) gave his note with <persName>Dn Jose Felix Trespalacios</persName> as security 
payable in sixty days, after some months had expired <persName>L Hawkins</persName> the
<persName>Agent </persName>of his <persName>Brother </persName>and in whose favor the note was drawn, called
on <persName>Trespalacios </persName>for the money; he observed that <persName>Madero </persName>had not
sent on funds to discharge it, and he was not then in a capacity
to do so. The business rested so untill <persName>L. Hawkins</persName>'s departure;
Shortly after, <persName>Mr Philip Dimett an agent and partner</persName> presented the
note to <persName>Trespalacios </persName>a second time, he observed that <persName>Madero </persName>was
bound to pay the note, and that he had not sent on funds to do so.
he also stated that he was about to start for <placeName>Monclova </placeName>and would
see <persName>Madero </persName>and convince him that it was not equitable that he<pb n="649"/>
[Trespalacios] should pay it. <persName>Mr D.</persName> forwarded the note on by <persName>Dn
Alexdro Treviño</persName> to <persName>Dn Victor Blanco</persName> for collection, you may want
some money and if you could attend to the business <persName>Dimitt </persName>wishes
you to do so, the money is for <persName>J. H. Hawkins</persName>&#8212;<persName>Dimitt </persName>will direct <persName>Dn
Victor</persName> to deliver the money to you if it should be collected, also a
note for 30 dollars for Tin <persName>Hawkins</persName> sold <persName>Madero </persName>which is collected&#8212;
You had better see <persName>Trespalacios </persName>on the subject of the 450. The
<persName>Doctor </persName>is in <placeName>Montclova </placeName>and may give you some information on the
subject I sent a note (for $20 I held against an <persName>officer attached to
the Durango troops</persName>) to the <persName>Doctor </persName>to ascertain if it could be 
collected there being more communication between his town and 
<placeName>Durango </placeName>than between this the <persName>Doctor </persName>is my most intimate <persName>friend</persName>, try
and get him to purchase the note at a discount if there is no other
method of procuring money for it.</p>

<p>No news; the <persName>settlers </persName>are in high spirits at the thoughts of getting
lands soon, the season has been remarkably fine so far and if it 
continues (which it bids fair to do) they will all raise more corn than
they will know what to do with. No news from home since <persName>Bruffy</persName>
came out, you have a great number of letters, which I have read&#8212;
principally desiring to know something of the <placeName>P. of Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Santiago Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>Do not forget the Saddle Galápago and White Wool hat for the
Sun</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
