<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0685">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Baron de Bastrop, 02-03-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Baron de Bastrop
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 737-738
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-02-03">02-03-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asks legislature to authorize a recorder's office.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1824-02-03">Feb 3 1824</date></p>
<p>Dr. Sir,</p>

<p>The interest of the <placeName>colony </placeName>requires that there should be a recorders
office established in it for recording marks and brands of Hogs and
Cattle, and Tittle Deeds to lands, Bills of Sales and such other 
instruments of writing of importance that ought to be recorded, I
therefore wish that you would have the goodness to represent the
subject to the most Excellent Deputation and procure from them
a Decree authorising me to establish at this place a <placeName>recorders office</placeName>
for this <placeName>Colony </placeName>for the above purposes&#8212;It has become necessary
that this Colony should have a name to disignate it in Judicial 
proceedings as well as in authenticating instruments of writing of all<pb n="738"/>
kinds, at this time it has by common habbit taken the name of
<placeName>Austin's Colony</placeName> and if there should be no objection made by the
Deputation I should wish that the establishing the <placeName>Recorders office</placeName>
should be in the following form&#8212;</p>

<p>The most Excellent Deputation of the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName> taking
into consideration the inportance and necessity of establishing an
<placeName>office </placeName>in <placeName>Austins Colony</placeName> in this <placeName>Province </placeName>for the purpose of 
registering and recording the Marks and Brands of hogs and Cattle and
titles and sales of land or other property amongst the <persName>Inhabitants</persName>
of said Colony, have thought proper to decree and do hereby decree
that <persName>Stephen F. Austin Judge</persName> of said Colony is hereby fully 
authorized to establish in said <placeName>Colony </placeName>a <placeName>Recorders or Registers office</placeName> for
the purpose of recording and registering in Books to be kept for
that purpose all Marks and Brands of Hogs Horses cattle or other
stock and all titles for landed property and real estate and all sales
or other transactions between the <persName>inhabitants </persName>of said colony proper
to be recorded.</p>

<p>You know that in the <placeName>United States</placeName> there is a <placeName>recorders office</placeName> of
this kind in every <placeName>County </placeName>and the <persName>inhabitants </persName>here are therefore
accustomed to it and will not be satisfied unless one is properly 
established by the highest authority of the <placeName>Province </placeName>It is a subject
of great importance and is, so just and approachable a request that
I think it cannot be refused.</p>

<p>[Estevan F. Austin.]</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
