<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0525">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to James E. B. Austin, 07-08-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 530-531
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-07-08">07-08-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Learn Spanish. Cultivate the governor. Do not discuss politics. Be attentive to church. Business going slowly, but is hopeful. Impressions of Mexico City.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1822-07-08">July 8. 1822</date>.</p>
<p>Dr <persName>Brother</persName>,</p>

<p>I fear you have often gone to the <placeName>Post office</placeName> and returned 
dissatisfied with your <persName>Brother </persName>for not writing more frequently, in fact I
have had no very important news to communicate and the postage
of a letter every mail is a tax which our funds at present would feel,
for this reason I have not written as often as I otherwise should&#8212;I
hope by this time you begin to speak Spanish and also to write it,
remember that all your hopes of rising in this <placeName>country </placeName>depend on
lear[n]ing to speak and write the language correctly, without that,
you will do nothing&#8212;you have had a fine opportunity this <date n="Summer-1822">summer</date>
and ought to be able by the time I arrive to speak and write the 
language so as to make yourself well understood&#8212;this subject is so
<hi rend="italic">very important</hi> that I note it first before I say any thing about my
business&#8212;The Colonization law is still pending and as the <persName>Emperor</persName>s
Coronation is defered until the <date n="07-xx-1822">middle or last of this month</date> I 
expect nothing will be done for some time yet&#8212;I have only to wate
with patience and have no doubt that in the end all will be right&#8212;</p>

<p>I am uneasy about your situation as to money and have therefore
sent you a draft on <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> for $50 which you can probably
sell at <placeName>Bexar </placeName>for 10 to 20 prcent advance, you must be as frugal as
possible and not loose one moment, you should rise at day light
and be at your studies and continue at them all day, only taking 
exercise and amusement enough to keep you in health and to relax the
mind and above all things do not fall into the habit of sleeping a
siesta after dinner, you will not have such another opportunity of
lear[n]ing the language and if you neglect it you will repent it when
too late&#8212;attend to <hi rend="italic">writing </hi>it, and in order to learn the spelling as
well as to improve you in the language and in your <hi rend="italic">hand</hi>, write down
a <hi rend="italic">long </hi>lesson every day out of some book and as you write it look for
the words you do not understand in the Diccionary, and also attend
to the parts of speech their concordance and government etc and
thus you will learn to spell the words and in doing this you must
also try and improve your hand, you see how plain the <persName>Spaniards</persName>
generally write. If you could translate well and write a good hand
I could get a place for you in the <placeName><persName>Captain General</persName>s office</placeName> as 
translator worth at least $2000 a year, so that you see that your future rise
depends altogether on yourself, fortune is within your reach if you
will only exert yourself to take it&#8212;and all the exertion required is
<hi rend="italic">close study</hi> for 3 or 4 months&#8212;Try and be intimate with <persName>Governor
Trespalacios</persName> and if you can get into his office to copy and write for<pb n="531"/>
him. Speak to the <persName>Baron </persName>and <persName>Don Erasmo</persName> on the subject&#8212;I received
a letter from <persName>Dr Andrews</persName> stating that <persName>Milum [Milam]</persName> and <persName>Cristy</persName>
had made some extravagant threats about the <persName>Govr</persName>. you must act
cautiously and keep clear of those men if you find they intend 
anything against the <persName>Govr</persName>.&#8212;they are very imprudent men and I fear
will get themselves into difficulty&#8212;all you have to do is to study
hard, and say nothing about Politics and be attentive to church&#8212;I
have received two letters from you since my arrival here, in the
last you say you begin to "jabber Spanish" I am rejoiced to find
you are improving, it is of so much importance that I cannot too
earnestly press upon you the necessity of <hi rend="italic">close application</hi>,&#8212;I shall
probably not be in <placeName>Bexar </placeName>before the <date when="1822-09-01">1 of September</date>, but do not be
discouraged at my detention, all will be well, at any event a 
correct knowledge of the language will get you a situation for life if you
wish it, so that the application of this <date n="Summer-1822">summer </date>will lay the 
foundation of your fortune whether I succeed or not&#8212;</p>

<p>This <placeName>city </placeName>is truly a magnificent one, as regards the external 
appearance of the buildings, and altho I at first thought it not larger
than <placeName>New York</placeName>, I now think after a better examination of it that it
is much larger than any city in the<placeName> U. S.</placeName> and much more populous&#8212;
The population however is very much mixed and a great proportion
of them are most miserably poor and wretched, <persName>beggars </persName>are more
numerous than I ever saw in any place in my life&#8212;robberies and
assassinations are frequent in the Streets&#8212;the people are biggoted
and superstitious to an extreem, and indolence appears to be the gen
aperal order of the day&#8212;in fact the City Magnificient as it is in 
pearance is at least one century behind many other places in point
of intelligence and improvement "in the arts" and the nation 
generally is in the same situation . . . [Eight lines are here torn away.]</p>

<p>Should anything of consequence happen write to me directed to
the care of <persName>Dr. R. Andrews</persName> <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>and I will get the letter as I
pass&#8212;Remember me very particularly to the <persName>Baron </persName>and speak to him
about the surveying for <persName>H. Elliott</persName> write me to <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>how many
<persName>families </persName>have moved in since I left there etc&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
