<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0906">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Gaines to Stephen F. Austin, 11-10-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Gaines</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Sabine, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 937-940
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-11-10">11-10-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Complex barter. Gaines' claims for land as a member of the Gutierrez expedition. Complaints made against Austin by his colonists.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Sabine </placeName><date when="1824-11-10">Novr. 10th 1824</date></p>
<p><persName>Col Stephen F Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir    Since I give you an account of the Case of <persName>Roberson
Hall</persName> and <persName>Col Coles</persName> I am Told you and the <persName>Political Chief</persName> had de-<pb n="938"/>
cided I Could not hold land At the <placeName>Brassos</placeName>, this I cant say gives me
much uneasiness, Although I have at all times contemplated on
Being a <persName>Citizen of the <placeName>Brazos</placeName></persName> as such I have never strained on a man
who owed me when Starting to that place not Recollecting agreeable
to the <persName>Indian </persName>Rule It might ultimately be the Cause of Depriving
me of Citizenship, as that might stimulate villians who owed me to
Circulate falsehood, by which If Possible Deprive me from being
Entitled to Justice</p>

<p>I am also informed <persName>Holloway </persName>has sworn before <persName>Col Coles</persName> that he
was present when <persName>Roberson </persName>and myself setled, and that <persName>Roberson</persName>
Settled <persName>Hall</persName>s account also, when It is well known by <persName>Hall </persName>that a
Great part of His account Originated after <persName>Roberson </persName>and my self
Setled, True it is <persName>Roberson </persName>proposed in the presence of <persName>Holloway </persName>to
let me have a first Rate young American horse in Liew of the mule
he owed me on Condition I would let him have a Spanish horse to
Take him to the <placeName>Brazos</placeName>, by which he stated I must throw in <placeName>Hall</placeName>s
account which was then small I answered him to Bring the horse and
If I Liked him I would do so, But when he Brought the horse he
Came in Company with <persName>Mr. John Jones</persName> the horse had been snake
bit and was very Poor, I then Positively Refused to give any thing
but the Spanish horse and his account which was $56 which I 
Considered that much Lost this was in the presence of <persName>John Jones</persName> and
several others <persName>Mr. Jones</persName> also helpd- him Take away the Powder and
Lead and heard him Boast all the way to the <placeName>Ayish Bayou</placeName> that I had
Credited him when on Starting away with $14-25, the said <persName>Mr. John
Jones</persName> is at his <persName>Brother </persName><persName>Henry Jones</persName>'s on the <placeName>Brazos</placeName></p>

<p>As I cant have Lands on the <placeName>Brazos </placeName>the $108-25c which I hold
your Receipt for If you Can Settle with <persName>Wm Prater</persName> on his Land I
should be glad</p>

<p>and the horse <persName>Col Coles</persName> Sold of mine, and <persName>Alsberry</persName>'s note of $20
If you can Settle with <persName>Holland </persName>the Amt of three heiffers with Calf
which I owe him for a horse I should also be very glad, they were to
be Delivered here, but he has not calld. for them and are worth here at
this time $10. Each <persName>Holland </persName>Holds <persName>Col Coles</persName> Receipt, for <persName>Parker</persName>s
note for a mule and an account of $12-50 and <persName>Alsberry</persName>'s note of $20
for Collection which If you settle with him in the way of his Land
for the heiffers Take up the Receipt</p>

<p>I shall Compleat the Road Between now and Christmas from here
to the <persName>Alabama Indians</persName> and Establish Boats on the <placeName>Nachez </placeName>and
<placeName>Angelline </placeName>which Runs a Southwest Direction from this place 
supposing It to bear a good Course for <placeName>St. Philip De Austin</placeName>, which will
shorten the Road upwards of one hundred miles to that place when
I Compleat that I shall Start to <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>in march to se If my <persName>wife</persName>s
being Entitled to Lands here will Deprive me of holding Lands<pb n="939"/>
Elsewhere when I hold three <placeName>Grants </placeName>bearing Date in <date n="xx-xx-1813">1813</date>, to be
-Laid at that time on any unappropriated Lands in Texas and spent
at that Time one years service and $1500 in Silver on the 
Independence of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName>, and I am firm in the Belief that when
Old <persName>Traitors </persName>and <persName>Tories </persName>is Turnd out of Office Justice will be Done
to that Expedition; this I look for on the Establishment of the <persName>State
Government</persName>, when Rough places will be made Smooth and Crooked
places made straight and the naked Truth in all Cases, Come to
Light</p>

<p><persName>Judge Murry Bullard</persName> and All the Enlightened part of <persName>Don 
Bernardos Army</persName> are ingaged In persuing Documents to be Laid before
the <persName>Government </persName>in <date n="Spring-1825">next Spring</date> and from what they have already
Recd from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>they [are] Confident of Success It apears the
<persName>Mexican Government</persName> has acknowledged that Espedition and the
Debts thereof, by which the <placeName>Province of Texeas</placeName> Stands Pledged, for
466 Square Leagues of Land of first Choice Besides to Secure the
paymt of the Expences of the Expedition which was very great</p>

<p>I Expect you Dont Beleive in this Business But Rely on It 
Business will Take, a Great Change in the Course of next Year, when
Likely the first will be Last and the Last first, the Great Small and
the Small Great Such is the nature of things in the Establishment
of new Governments, and such it apears will have to be the Case
before Justice Can be Done in <placeName>Texes</placeName></p>

<p>Although you have more Education than myself yet you must
acknowledge I am older than you as such may I venter to give you
a peace of advice, that is, to wind up your <placeName>Colony </placeName>Business as soon
as you can, you certainly Can by this Time form an Opinion of a
Majority of your people now and well know by what Tye you
Govern them, whenever that Tye is Removed by accident or 
otherwise what Treatment do you suppose you will Receive from them,
me at this distance Can Tell better than you It will be Curses and
Abuse, this you may Rely on, as they accuse you of Every thing
bad and threaten Continually Revenge they say they bore the heat
and Burthen of the Day, and you Slight them By Reserving to 
yourself all the good Land they say you are never governd. Two days
by the same Rule nor Law you give some young men 1/4 League
of Land and others one and more Leagues Some men of wealth
and Respectability you wont give but one League Others of Less
wealth get Two three or four Leagues, now when they have 
obtained their Titles, and the Teror of being Drove out of the Country
is Removed and they have whisky (?) plenty then Look for the 
Revenge so Long threatened<pb n="940"/></p>

<p>For these Reasons I advise you to Close your Business of the
<placeName>Colony </placeName>you may accuse me, of Design in this as you have been
Taught, to believe me your <persName>Enemy</persName>, so far I can say I have never
failed to do Everything in my Power for your good and that of the
<placeName>Coliny </placeName>all intirely from pure motives My advise is also from pure
motives one favor I ask is Lay it up and se If my Predictions Dont
Come to pass, I may be Mistaken but such is my Belief.</p>

<p>I Dont give this as Ever Expecting to se you again and I am sure
it is not given to Insult nor injure your feelings, I always had 
Contemplated on setling at the <placeName>Brazos </placeName>until I heard very Lately by 
<persName>McNeel </persName>I Could not, I beg the favor that you will write me an Answer
and</p>

<p>Remain Respectfully Yours</p>

<p><persName>Jas Gaines</persName>    [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
