<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0092">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to General Wilkinson, 07-22-1805</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-24">06-24-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        General Wilkinson
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Burton Mine, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">St Louis, MO</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 97-98
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1805-07-22">07-22-1805</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-24" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Efforts of John Smith to cause the removal of Austin from office. Austin's aims.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mine A Burton</placeName> <date when="1805-07-22">July 22th. 1805</date></p>
<p>To His <persName>Excellency James Wilkinson</persName></p>

<p>Haveing this day recv'd a letter from <persName>John Smith of <placeName>St Genveive</placeName></persName>
Stateing that he is proseeuting measures to obtain Certificates in
Order to lay before your Excellency to effect my removal from Office, 
I have taken the liberty to address your Excellency on the subject,
few men in public Stations escape the milignant tongues of the 
restless <persName>members of society</persName>. I therefore Aught not to be surpris'd that
at this moment of party madness, I am marked Out As a <persName>Victim </persName>to
disappointed ambition. It is well known that I never had a wish to
be notic'd in the appointments of <persName>Govr. Harrison</persName>. No man is more
fully convinced of the Difficulties of holding an Office in a Country
Where the people are so little accustomed to the <persName>American </persName>form of
<persName>Government </persName>then myself It is next to impossible to bring men into
measures they cannot Judge of. Ignorant of all the principles of our
Government they View things with an evil eye.   from this knowledge<pb n="98"/>
of the disposition of a part of the people. It was with no small
reluctance I entered on the Duties of my Office being persuaded
Sattisfaction could not be given, The insufficiency of my own 
Abilities together with dispositions manifested in some of the <persName>members of
the Court</persName> Known to be Unfriendly towards our government rendered
the discharge of my Duties still more Difficult and disagreeable.</p>

<p>That I may have commited Errors in Judgment is possible but I
am Conscience of no offence Unless it be an Offence to disagree in 
Opinion with my Opponents. I have only to ask of your Excellency
that I may have an Oppertunety of seeing a Copy of the Charges
that may be exhibited by <persName>John Smith</persName> and others that I may make
my refutation. The Justice I owe myself <persName>family </persName>and my <persName>friends</persName>
require that I Should hold my Office untill a termination of this
business. After which your Excellency has made such a decree
as in your Judgment may seem proper. I shall leave myself at your
Excellency's disposal.</p>

<p>Nothing but the malicious prosecution Commenced against me
could create a wish to retain the Office I have the Honor now to hold.</p>

<p>Be my fate what It may be in the termenation of this Undertakeing,
I have an internal Sattisfaction the Calumniators of a World 
cannot take from me Warmly inclin'd towards my <placeName>Mother Country</placeName> and
Government, Tenacious of her Honor and Dignity I may have View'd
the Conduct of my Opponents with to scrupulous an Eye</p>

<p>I have Ever wish'd a harmony and union of Opinion might take
place between the <persName>French </persName>and <persName>Americans </persName>and with confidance do I
Declair that Its not my fault there exists a Difference</p>

<p>With the fullest con[fi]dence of your Excellency disposition to do
justice to all parties</p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin.</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>To His <persName>Excellency James Wilkinson <placeName>St. Louis</placeName></persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
