<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0075">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Antoine Soulard, 08-04-1803</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-24">06-24-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Antoine Soulard
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Burton Mine, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 85-87
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1803-08-04">08-04-1803</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-24" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning misrepresentations against Austin by an unknown person. Austin's opinion of Thomas Madden.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mine Au Burton</placeName> <date when="1803-08-04">Augt. 4th 1803</date></p>
<p>Sr</p>

<p>I Rec'd by the Hands of A <persName>Mr. Mason</persName>, an, <hi rend="italic">Anonymous </hi>letter the
Contents of Which gave me to understand from Whence, It, came.<pb n="86"/>
In that paper I am told that <persName>Mr. Bolvan</persName> [?] is Charged with some
particulars you have rece'd <hi rend="italic">via</hi>, your <persName>friends</persName>, Which he will 
Communicate to me. Having recd his Communications, I make you my
Answer&#8212;</p>

<p>As to the Information you have Rec'd from your <persName>friend </persName>If he
says that he has hear'd from me a word that Can in any Manner
terminate Either to your Damage or that of your <persName>friend </persName>he says what
is <hi rend="italic">false</hi>, and If you will favour me with his name I will immediately
Demand an Explenation the transactions that have taken place 
between you and myself have rested with me and those-<hi rend="italic">Intristed </hi>and I
cannot believe either of them have said any thing to your <hi rend="italic">Dishonour</hi>,
as to my Nameing, the <persName>Govr</persName>. in any manner in this business I also
pointedly Deny haveing done so.</p>

<p>When <persName>Doct. Watkins</persName> mentioned this subject to me I then told him
the difficulties that might Arise unless some man Other then <hi rend="italic">Maddin</hi>
Survey'd the land, he thought with me and said he would write you
on the subject, on my Arrivel, At <placeName><hi rend="italic">St. Louis </hi></placeName>finding the business
widely different from what I expected I immediately gave up all
Idea of a Speculation with my friend <persName>Watkins</persName>, and what-business
I Executed with you was for my <persName>friends </persName>and Such Men As I Know
will be of advantage to the <placeName>Country </placeName>Its the first time in my life
that A letter came to Me with out Date or Name, it bespeeks your
Opinion of me and I shall take such Steps as my injur'd Honour 
demands, by first returning not Onely the last but all the papers that
have come into my Hands from you <persName>relative </persName>to this Matter Except
the petitions and them I shall retain untill I have an Opportunety of
Stateing your Communecations to those Intristed, and Since its your
wish be assured I shall do all in my power to obtain leave to return
each and Every petition to you again, I wish Nothing to remain in
my hands that can put it in my power or-that of my friends to do
you Injustice and whin I am debarrass'd of all those things I hope Sr
you will do me the Justice to grant me an Intervew with your 
<persName>informer</persName>&#8212;When I shall Demand from him such sattisfaction as the
nature of the business-Requires                       </p>

<p>You are to remember Sr. that how Ever improperly I may think
myself treated in this Affair Yet Nothing will go from me that shall
give you grounds to call my Honour in question.</p>

<p>the Manner in which you say the Surveys must be made at Belie
Veiw will render them useless to the <hi rend="italic">Intristed </hi>the situation of the
place render it impossible for the lines of each Survey to Close. You
also Demand my note with the Intristed for the fees of Office and that
payable in Spanish Dollars unless paid at the Day and <hi rend="italic">Hour </hi>they
become <hi rend="italic">Due</hi> <persName>Tom Madden</persName> has Never Demanded Security from
Others and Why Demand it at this time. I am bold to say each and
Every man are as Equal to pay there Debts as <hi rend="italic"><persName>Madden   </persName></hi>You cannot<pb n="87"/>
Expect me to put myself in the power of a man who has proven by
his Conduct that No thing but an Oppertunety is Wanting to ruin
my Reputation.</p>

<p>I have told you before and I now tell you that <hi rend="italic"><persName>Madden </persName></hi>has lost
you more money then he has made you and his friendship may at this
time Cost you 700 Dollars. Under such circumstances Can you 
Suppose me so pusillanimous an animal as to Submitt myself to his will
<hi rend="italic">No Sr.</hi> In this Business I feel myself Unjustly injur'd and Insult'd.
but I have given you my word that nothing shall go from me 
prejucicial either to your Honour or your Intrest I shall therefore untill
I have your leave deposit in my Brest this whole <hi rend="italic">Affair </hi>and at a
proper time Demand sattisfaction of those who have so Unjustly
Represented my Conduct towards you</p>

<p>Inclosed are all the papers that relate to this buseness&#8212;</p>

<p>[M. Austin.]</p>

<p>[Endorsed:] Letter   <persName>Anto Soulard </persName>  Copy <date when="1803-08-04">Augt 4th 1803</date></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
