<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0597">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Felipe de la Garza, 05-27-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Felipe de la Garza
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monterrey, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 651-653
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-05-27">05-27-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asking definition of his authority to administer justice, make war on hostile Indians, and issue clearances to vessels; and that his rank in militia be determined and a port legalized.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>The <persName>Supreme Government</persName> having authorized me to effect the 
settlement of a <placeName>colony</placeName>, which I proposed to establish in the <placeName>Province of
Texas</placeName>, under the regulations which have been prescribed to me,
and communicated to your <persName>Lordship</persName>, through his Excellency, the
<persName>Secretary of State and Home Affairs</persName>; some doubts arise in my mind<pb n="652"/>
as to the best method of preserving order in the settlement. My 
difficulties are upon the following points:</p>

<p>1st Whether the authority given me to administer justice while
the <persName>government of the <placeName>settlement</placeName></persName> is organizing, extends so far as to
empower me to punish Capital Offences committed within its limits;
such as Murder, Piracy on the coast, Theft, aiding the hostile 
<persName>Indians </persName>to wage war against us, etc., or whether, the said authority is
merely to arrest the <persName>offenders</persName>, and send them to <placeName>Bexar</placeName>. If the latter,
tell me upon what fund I should draw to defray the expenses
incurred by their transportation, and if the former, what rules are
to be observed, in order to conform with the laws of the country.</p>

<p>2nd Whether I can or cannot make war against the hostile <persName>Indians</persName>,
and to what extent.</p>

<p>3rd What rank I am entitled to in the <persName>National Militia</persName>, and what
are the rules and regulations under which I have to organize the
same. The <persName>Government </persName>authorizes me to organize the <persName>colonists </persName>into
a body of this kind, but did not define either of these points, and
both of them are very essential. The <persName>Secretary of State</persName> informed
me verbally that this <persName>Government </persName>would regulate this matter. The
force of the Colony should consist at least of one <persName>Battallion</persName>: Its
extent and isolated situation exposed not only to the attacks of the
<persName>Indians</persName>, but also to the aggressions of evil disposed persons requires
a prompt and effective organization of the only arm of defence which
has to sustain it; all of these considerations induce me to ask that
some system may be established for my government, and also my
rank, which should be sufficient to command the <persName>Captains in the
Corps</persName>.</p>

<p>4th Inasmuch as, at the present time and until the <placeName>colony </placeName>shall be
well established, there may be an absolute necessity of bringing from
<placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, by sea, Provisions, utensils, goods and household 
furniture for the use of the <persName>Colonists</persName>, it appears to me indispensable
that this Government should make a <placeName>port of Entry</placeName> provisionally
of one of the <placeName>Harbours </placeName>on that <placeName>coast </placeName>authorizing me at the same
time to furnish such vessels so trading to the <placeName>Colony </placeName>with a clearance,
for without this requisite these vessels might be considered at <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName> as engaged in a clandestine and illegal trade, and 
consequently deprive the <persName>colonists </persName>of these resources so necessary to their
support and prosperity. For the want of topographical information,
I cannot now designate the place on the <placeName>coast </placeName>best adapted to this
purpose, but this I may be enabled to do after conferring with the
<persName>Commissioner </persName>who has to be appointed for the other purposes treated
of in my Commission. I have no private wish to gratify, my only
object in propounding these questions is to promote the best interests
and the prosperity of the <placeName>Colony </placeName>in particular, which ought to coin-<pb n="653"/>
cide with that of the whole <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName> and the welfare of
the <placeName>nation</placeName>. The will of the <persName>Government </persName>in this as in all other cases
shall be my own, and for this reason I have considered it my duty
to consult with your <persName>Lordship </persName>on the subject above referred to,
soliciting your decision in the matter, that I may punctually execute
your orders, which I feel assured will be in consonance with the
accustomed beneficent intentions of the <persName>Government</persName>. God protect
your <persName>Lordship </persName>many years.</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p><placeName>Monterey</placeName>, <date when="1823-05-27">May 27th 1823</date>.</p>

<p>[To Felipe de la Garza, <hi rend="italic">Comandamte General</hi> of the Eastern 
Interior Provinces.]</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
