<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0086">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Stephen Austin, 12-16-1804</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-24">06-24-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">St Geneieve, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Colchester, CT</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 93-95
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1804-12-16">12-16-1804</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-24" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Advice as to education, associates, etc.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>St Geneive</placeName> <date when="1804-12-16">Decr. 16th., 1804</date></p>
<p>My Dear Boy</p>

<p>Your letter Dated <date when="1804-09-26">26th of Septr</date>. came to hand in Due time and be
assurd It gave inexpressable pleasure to your Dear <persName>Mother </persName>and <persName>Sister</persName>
as well as to all your <persName>friends</persName>. Your troubles on your Journey will
learn you a little of what you are to expect to meet with in life. I
am sorry for the situation of <persName>Mr Phelps</persName> and hope he may yet Recover
his health and property&#8212; I am greatly pleased that you are placed
under the care of so good a friend as <persName>Mrs Penniman</persName> I am confident
she will take as good care of you as myself. I hope and pray you
will improve Every moment of time to the utmost advantage and that
I shall have the sattisf action of seeing that my expectations are not
Disappointed, remember my Dear Son that the present is the 
moment to lay the foundation for your future greatness in life that
much money must be expended before your Education is finished and<pb n="94"/>
that time lost can never be recalled, therefore be studious and 
attentive to obtain full information of all matters given to you to learn&#8212;
I have forwarded by post a letter to <persName>Mr. Penneman</persName> and before I
became acquainted at what place you was to be placed I forwarded
to <persName>Mr Timothy Phelps</persName> 50$ Dollars for your use I shall shortly 
forward you 50$ more to the Care of <persName>Mr Penniman</persName> who will pay it away
as you may want&#8212; I have given Orders that you be furnished with
Clothing suited to the Situation you are in and as to Expense money
what <persName>Mr and Mm Penniman</persName> may think proper you shall have I do
not expect you will expend money unwisely Yet I do not wish you
to render yourself Disagreeable to your young <persName>friends </persName>to avoid 
expending a few Dollars when it appears necessary for you to forme
company pay readely your part of all expenses that may arise but
Never lett yourself be imposed on by an improper Demand and If
you finde a Disposition in any of your young <persName>friends </persName>to do such an
Act, I charge you, have nothing more to Do with them, Keep not
there Company and promptly tell them the Cause, that is, that you
will never keep Companey with a Boy disposed to impose on you, nor
allow yourself to make an improper Demand on your <persName>friends </persName>to
save a Dollar these are things many suppose of Small moment, but
I do not. its small things that stamp the disposition and temper
of a man and many times, Boys lessen there greatness in life by
small things which at the moment they think of little or no 
Consequence, you ask me to point out to you the improper things in your
letter If any. I am pleased with your letter Generally but some
things you have Omitted you did not tell me how you was recd by
your <persName>friends in <placeName>New Haven</placeName></persName> that is by the <persName>family of Elijah Austin</persName>,
by <persName>Mrs. Archd Austin</persName>, etc. you said nothing about your <persName>uncle Elliot</persName>s
<persName>family </persName>how you was receivd by them you said nothing how you liked
the <placeName>Country </placeName>and the manners of the people whether things appear
agreeable to you or not, of these things you must speek in your Next
and remember I charged you to write Every month and state your
situation [your advancement in] learning, you made three Black
[marks at the] close of your letter and put your name [on the left]
hand side of the paper, this is wrong, always [put] your name as
near the right side of the paper as you can with convenience, I have
under gon a Distressing Spel of Sickness since you left us&#8212; from
<date n="09-xx-1804">Sept</date>, until a few Days past I have been confined to the <placeName>House </placeName>and
for six weeks it remained Doubtfull whether I should recover or not,
I am now greatly mended but not fully recoverd and I hope to God I
shall be spared until I see you arrive at an age to give protection to
your Dear <persName>Mother </persName>and <persName>Sister </persName>and little <persName>Brother Elijah Brown</persName>, 
remember that to you they will look for protection should it so happen<pb n="95"/>
that my life should be shortened keep in minde that this may 
happen. Your Dear <persName>Mother </persName>[and] <persName>Sister Emily</persName> send you their Blessing
as also <persName>Mrs. James Austin</persName> and <persName>family </persName>I have heard that<persName> Doct. Elliot
</persName>is <placeName>on the Ohio </placeName>and I Daly Expect him and <persName>family </persName>You will make
my best respects to <persName>Mr and Mrs. Penniman</persName> and may the Blessing of
your God be always with you</p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin</persName>.    [Rubric]</p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr. Stephen Fuller Austin</persName> <placeName>Colchester, Connecticut</placeName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
