<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0355">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to James Bryan, 04-30-1820</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-09">07-09-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James Bryan
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Arkansas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Arkansas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 358-359
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1820-04-30">04-30-1820</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Enmity of Russell. Family fortunes.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Post or Arkansas</placeName> <date when="1820-04-20">April 30 1820</date></p>
<p>Dr <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>I am very comfortably accommodated in <persName>Judge Scott</persName>s family who
has had the kindness to board me as long as I wish to remain,&#8212; I
feel great anxiety on your account You make such sanguine 
expectations and calculations that I am fearfull you will become too
much intangied ever to get out&#8212; there is much uncertainty as to
the <placeName>seat of Government</placeName>'s going to the <placeName>Little Rock</placeName> and you must take
care and not spend too much money there. I find that <persName>Wheeler </persName>is
generally unpopular and I believe the general interest of all 
concerned would be promoted by his removal   I have no confidence in<pb n="359"/>
<persName>Ohara</persName>, lie may be an honest man but I confess my present 
impressions are against him, and I have to request you, as you value your
own safety, to have nothing to do with his <persName>Bank </persName>or his paper, and
above all things do not give it currency, or take it at all, that <persName>Bank</persName>
will blow up before long, and then you will be blamed and injured
for giving credit to the notes <persName>Wheeler </persName>I believe has done all he
could for the best but he is a bad <persName>manager</persName>, he blabs and splutters
too much&#8212; you aught to retain the whole of your half of the
original location, if you do so I can make a sale of a part of it in
a way that will secure the <placeName>seat of Government</placeName> if any thing will do
it&#8212;¦ I have no apprehensions at all as to the ultimate decision of
the dispute with <persName>Russell </persName>but it will have an unfortunate effect at
this critical time, and indeed I should not be surprised if the <placeName>seat of
Government</placeName> was to be fixed at <placeName>Chrystal Hill</placeName> or <placeName>Cadron</placeName>, <persName>Russell </persName>is
the most unaccountable man I ever saw. Money is his idol, and yet
he is distroying his own interest and throwing away thousands to
gratify a little spleen and malice. My opinion of mankind has,
unfortunately perhaps, been as bad as it could be for some years,
but the longer I live the worse it grows. Were it not for this man
<persName>Russell </persName>our unfortunate <persName>family </persName>might yet be enabled to secure a
small, but decent competence for if his opposition was removed I
believe there would be no difficulty in getting the seat of government
removed to the <placeName>L. Rock</placeName>, which might be the means of saving a
worthy and respectably family from total ruin and want whereas
be gains nothing by his opposition, but the pleasure of gratifying
his enmity and passions which I once thought were rarely to be met
with in the human brest, but I have now learnt to be surprised at
nothing I see in man, unless it is when I find him honest&#8212; I shall
remain here this <date n="Summer-1820">summer</date>, and after that it is uncertain where I shall
go if my <persName>Father </persName>saves enough to support him and you get through
your difficulties so as to support <persName>Emily </persName>in the stile she aught
to live, I shall be satisfied, as for myself I believe I am nearly
indifferent what becomes of me, or whether I live or die,, unless I
am to be of use to my <persName>Family </persName>by living, and then I should be as
anxious to live as any one.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr James Bryan</persName> <placeName>Little Rock</placeName> care of <persName>E. A. Elliott
</persName><placeName>Arkansaw Territory</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
