<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0772">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Anthony R. Clarke to Stephen F. Austin, 06-12-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Anthony R. Clarke</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Atoack, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 828-829
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-06-12">06-12-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Position of the unauthorized settlements in east Texas. Attitude of the settlers toward Austin. Character of Gaines.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Atoack </placeName><date when="1824-06-12">12th June 1824</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>your favour of the <date when="1824-05-12">25 ultmo</date> was duly received. I am very sorry
for the arangments which has taken place that will prove a private
injury to you, but I flatter myself that it may yet turn out better<pb n="829"/>
than you first antisipated, You state that you intend to close all
the affairs of the <placeName>settlement </placeName>by the month of <date n="10-xx-1824">October</date>, I sincerely
hope you have no intention of leaving the <placeName>settlement</placeName>, such a step
would be (I think) ruinous to the <placeName>Colony</placeName>-&#8212;I am clearly of oppinion
from my own knowledg that their never was a man more 
universally beloved and respected by all the <persName>setlers </persName>than yourself, it would
be like leaving so many Orphan Children without protection.&#8212;In
my last letter to you by <persName>Mr. Cummings</persName> I wrote my real oppinion
to you of <persName>Capt Gains</persName>'s carractor. I reflected on my self after I
sent it for fear you might think I was endeavouring to traduce the
Man. The last dispute I had with him I told him the business
between him and myself was like an old sore healing up I did not
wish to tear it open afresh, since then he stops at my <placeName>house </placeName>eats
and drinks I do the same at his <placeName>house</placeName>, so far we are <persName>friends </persName>but I
still think it my duty to prevent him from deceiving others as he
has me, on his return from <placeName>St Antonio</placeName> he spoke very ill against
the <persName>Political Chief</persName> and <persName>counsel </persName>stating that he was fifteen days 
disputing with them in supporting the <persName>American settlers</persName> in this 
<placeName>District</placeName>, but gave no correct information respecting the intentions of
Government about this <placeName>district</placeName>, Since that time a <persName>Spaniard </persName>has
passed through here from <placeName>St Antonio</placeName> and who is said to be a good
Man&#8212;his name is sounded, <persName>Hose Ankle [José Angel]</persName> he informed me
that <persName>Gains </persName>while at <placeName>St Antonio</placeName> spoke very bad of all the <persName>Americans</persName>
in this <placeName>settlement</placeName>. I since lern that he gave <persName>Col Bean</persName> the same 
account but spoke more fully to him as he speaks Spanish well, since
that time some <persName>setlers </persName>from the <placeName>Brassos </placeName>has passed here and inform
the <persName>Inhabitants </persName>that <persName>Don Jose Anto Saucedo</persName> while at the <placeName>Brassos</placeName>
gave you the same information and go so far as to relate your
answer&#8212;</p>

<p>I wish you to write me and inform if this is true the people here all
believe it. if true, I feel confident that you would be among the last
men that would attempt to screen a man that was capible of such
disception.</p>

<p>We are here quite ignorant of the late regulations of Government
respecting this <placeName>District </placeName>the papers that have come on have been 
translated by <persName>Col Bean</persName> but so badly that we can make but little sence of
it, there is many reports we do not know what to believe I will take
it as a great favour if you will give me such information as you
may possess on this subject, that I may know what to depend on
I think that <persName>Saucedo </persName>must have conversed with you on this subject
such part as you wish to be considered as confidential you will please
to name&#8212;by complying with this request you will add to the many
obligations that I have the pleasure to acknowledge&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Anthy E. Clarke</persName></p>

<p><persName>Col S F Austin</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
