<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0030">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Kendall and Bates, 12-xx-1797</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-21">06-21-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Kendall 
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Bates
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 38-39
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1797-12">12-xx-1797</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Instructions for building furnaces and sawmill, and purchasing waste ore from old workings.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[Dec. &#8212;, 1797.]</p>

<p>Above I have given you as good an idea as I can of the Situation
of the <placeName>Lead Mines</placeName> and marked out the place I wish the furnce to
stand as I was not at the place long I may have made some mistake
in laying it Down however I wish to have the furnac Hous at the
<placeName>lower end of the Village</placeName> that is <placeName>Down the Creek at the point of the
Road that goes to the Mines</placeName>. You will have the Hous of the 
following Dimentions say 38 by 30 feet and 12 feet in higth. a good
strong frame a <placeName>Saw mill</placeName> and [undecipherable] or any other Kinds of
<placeName>Mill </placeName>you think will be best So send <placeName>Down the Creek</placeName> untill you finde a
good place, the stone and Timber as also the lime for Building the
Brick and Stone work <persName>John Storts</persName> <persName>Drury Green</persName> <persName>Mathew Mull</persName> ins
<persName>Timothy Mullins</persName> and <persName>Montgomery </persName>must be sent out to the <placeName>Mines </placeName>as
soon as possible <persName>Shouse </persName>may stay in <placeName>Kaskaskia </placeName>and help <persName>Nail </persName>git the
<placeName>Distillery </placeName>ready&#8212;I wish a shaft Immediately Sunk and you will finde
the ground such as will require to be Timberd I expect however
this you will best Know when you see the place either you or <persName>Mr
Bates</persName> will be obliged to go out to the <placeName>Mines </placeName>untill <persName>Mr. Shouse</persName> has
finished the <placeName>Distillery</placeName>, I have given <persName>Elias Bates</persName> Orders respecting
the <placeName>factory </placeName>but as <persName>Elias Bates</persName> will have to be much of his time at the
<placeName>Mines </placeName>I do not expect much Can be Don as to the <placeName>factory </placeName>untill I
arrive unless a <placeName>Hous </placeName>can be had already Built which I suppose may<pb n="39"/>
be Don in that case It may be easily put in Order by <persName>Elias </persName>and
<persName>Montgomery </persName><persName>Elias </persName>will fix his <persName>family </persName>at <placeName>St Genevieve</placeName> as soon as
he can with whom <persName>Shouse </persName>will board when he is from the <placeName>Mines </placeName>If
<persName>Montgomery </persName>wants all the <persName>Hands </persName>with him you may lett the 
sinking the Shaft a lone untill I arrive you will finde a great quantity
of Ore at the places where others have melt Down Ore in log fires
this Ore you are to Demand of the <persName>Commandant </persName>to Know if I am not
to have all I finde on the ground and If you finde anything said
about the Ore that is about the Old works being taken away make a
purchase of it all as it Stands also Make a Purchase of all the refuse
Ore at the <placeName>Mines of De Le Mott</placeName> make your Contract so that I may
have the liberty to work up all the Ore I finde in and about the <placeName>Mines
of De Le Mott</placeName> above ground for unless I have this Liberty It will
not be worth while to Build a furnace at the <placeName>Mines of De Le Mott
</placeName>give all the <persName>Hands </persName>absolute Orders not to say a word as to the Value
of the Ore about the Old Workings for If they say much about the
Value of the Ore It may make trouble for me in all things you and <persName>E
Bates</persName> will both do for the best and take advice of each Other Call
on <persName>Mr Jones</persName> for advice and pay Great respect to <persName>Mr Valle</persName> and
<persName>Lesses [De Lassus's]</persName> advice&#8212;You will make a purchace of all the
Lead Ore you Can both at the <placeName>Mines of Breton</placeName> and the <placeName>Mine of De
Le Mott</placeName> If you can git it for 12 1/2 pr Hundred for good Clean Ore
the goods you will manage to the Best advantage in your Power for
the Best Interest of us all&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>To <persName>Messr Judather Kendal</persName> and <persName>Elias Bates</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>[Endorsed:] Memorandum of instructions for <persName>Mess. Kendal</persName> and
<persName>Bates </persName>respecting the <persName>Illinoies</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
