<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0790">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas M. Duke to Stephen F. Austin, 06-xx-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Thomas M. Duke</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Waco Village, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 842-843
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-06">06-xx-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Waco and " Towaash " Indians.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Wacoe Village</placeName> <date n="06-xx-1824">June &#8212; 1824</date></p>
<p><persName>Coln. Stephen F Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir this will be handed you by <persName>Mr. Beard</persName> who is going down
as an <persName>express </persName>we arrived here a few days ago and met with five of
their <persName>Nation </persName>in the <placeName>Village </placeName>they appeared very friendly towards us
the rest being out on <persName>War parties</persName> against the <persName>Osages </persName>and a buffaloe
hunting yesterday Say ten or fifteen <persName>families </persName>came in and we had
a talk with them they denied positively the murder of <persName>Tumlinson </persName>and
likewise the stealing of any horses from the <persName>Americans </persName>or any knowl-<pb n="843"/>
edge of those that had committed those outrages and from their 
conduct appear to be friendly disposed towards us we have seen one
Sorrel mare mule marked with the brand that you requested us to
enquire after but have not as yet made no demand for it being in
hopes that we may see some more that have been stolen&#8212; A fiew
Minutes ago two <persName>Wacos </persName>came in and inform us that the <persName>Towaash
Indians</persName> had started with a party that half were to go against the
<persName>Spaniards </persName>and the others against the <persName>Americans</persName>, they told us in
the council that the <persName>Towaash Indians</persName> were enemies of ours and wished
them to go to war against us but that they would not concent to it the
<persName>Towaashs</persName> live some where towards the <placeName>head of this river</placeName> about Six
days travel from here&#8212;We have consulted amongst ourselves and
think that if you approve of it that now would be a fit time for us to
make a campaign against them as we have a faithful <persName>Chicasaw Indian</persName>
with us who could pilot us to the <placeName>Towaash town</placeName> and now is the time
to strike a decisive blow as we can keep it secret from the <persName>Wacoes </persName>and
will be certain to find a part of them in their <placeName>towns </placeName>when we may
destroy their corn etc We have acted pretty independently since
we have been here and I am certain that a campaign would make
[them] take care how they tamper with the <persName>Americans </persName>we shall wait
here fifteen&#8212;or twenty days for men&#8212;to come on and in case we
start before you come on we have preconcerted signals and marks
with <persName>Beard </persName>who will know them this <persName>town </persName>is situated on the <placeName>West
Bank of the River</placeName> about<placeName> half a mile from the River</placeName> they have a
spring almost as cold as Ice itself all we want is some Brandy and
Sugar to have Ice Toddy they have about four hundred acres planted
in corn beans pumpkins and melons and that tended in good order
their <placeName>Village </placeName>consists of about Sixty houses built in pretty good
order I think they cannot raise more than One Hundred <persName>Warriors</persName>,
one of the <placeName><persName>Tawackanaw </persName>towns</placeName> is about three miles below this on the
opposite side of them consisting of seven houses their principal town
is some distance from this on the <placeName>Waters of the Trinity</placeName> for any 
particulars enquire of <persName>Mr Beard</persName></p>

<p><persName>Thos M Duke</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
