<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0628">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Robert Andrews to Stephen F. Austin, 09-05-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Robert Andrews</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Parras, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Bexar, TX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 693-694
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-09-05">09-05-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Plans for business in Texas. The Viesca family at Parras.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Parras</placeName>, <date when="1823-09-05">Sept 5th 1823</date>.</p>
<p>Dear <persName>Austin</persName></p>

<p>I had the satisfaction to receive your letters of the <date when="1823-07-09">9th</date> and <date when="1823-07-24">24 July</date>
dated in <placeName>Bexar</placeName>, but you speak of one from <placeName>Monterrey </placeName>by private
conveyance which I never recd, that of the <date when="1823-07-09">9th</date> I answered by last mail
supposing that you have an arangement made to convey letters
from <placeName>Bexar </placeName>to the <placeName>Collorado</placeName>.<pb n="694"/></p>

<p>I am extreemly <hi rend="italic">happy </hi>to hear that the all essential article <hi rend="italic">corn</hi>
is likely to be plenty among you, and particularly that Ally has a
good share for I feel in my heart for those <persName>adventurors</persName>, who must
necessarily have suffered much</p>

<p>I am sorry to find myself so situated that I cannot accompany you
in the woods, but such are the circumstances that it is not in my
power, it is true that my whole heart and soul is in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, that I
look forward with delight to the time when I shall be planted
amongst a number of confidential <persName>friends </persName>on the <placeName>orilla of the 
Colorado</placeName>, but I am of opinion that the shortest method to obtain this,
and to place me in the situation to be useful and comfortable, is to
persue my present object which may produce something with which
to begin I would willingly accept the offer you make but that
I would have to spend money continually without receiving any
for some time, and the life of a <persName>surveyor </persName>is so hard, that he ought
always to have a certainty in view&#8212;My present object is a trip to
<placeName>Orleans </placeName>altho I take only money for my expenses, jet I hope to
do something for this reason I am desirous that you should write
a few lines to <persName>Mr J. H. Hawkins</persName> conserning me. I shall probabilly
have leave here the <date when="1823-10-01">first of October </date>and be in <placeName>Orleans </placeName>some time
in <date n="11-xx-1823">November</date>, if I succeed I shall return immediately, if not I know
not what I shall do, my subsequent movements will always depend
on circumstances In this place I am the intimate <persName>friend </persName>and daily
companion of the family named <persName>Viesca </persName>one of whom you seen perhaps
with <persName>Dr Ramos</persName> in <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>, this family is rich, large, respectable,
learned, sensible, and honorable, they believe not in this d&#8212;d foolish
religion and possess two very fine libraries of miscellaneous and
scientific Books, two of the <persName>sons </persName>talk of going with me, but it is
uncertain yet-&#8212;more than all, I believe I could marry a little <persName>niece</persName>
about 14 years of age, but she is not well educated and her part will
not be more than 10000&#8212;the whole connection is free from <persName>Indian</persName>
blood&#8212;at all points I shall be happy to hear from you, and assure
you that nothing can give me more pleasure than the flattering
prospects of a friend whom to me is so dear. I flatter myself that
Providence will reward your indefatigable perseverance and 
industry tho we know well that these works of providence depend at
present on this confused and instable <persName>govt</persName>-&#8212;<placeName>Zacatecas </placeName>has declared
herself as independent as <placeName>Great Britton</placeName>, but it is understood that
<persName>Negrete </persName>will use the weighty argument of lead and powder to prove
to them that they are <hi rend="italic">rong</hi>.</p>

<p><persName>Andrews</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Al Caronel Sr Dn Estevan Austin Bexar</persName> ó el <placeName>Rio
Colorado Texas</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
