<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0260">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to John S Brickley, 02-22-1815</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-02">07-02-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        John S Brickley
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Burton Mine, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 247-250
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Memo</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1815-02-22">02-22-1815</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-02" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Memorandum concerning provisions for negroes. Furnace regulations.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mine a Burton</placeName> <date when="1815-02-22">Feby the 22nd 1815</date></p>
<p>Copy of a memorandum of <persName>Mr Austin</persName></p>

<p><persName>Mr John S. Brickey</persName></p>

<p>I give you the following Memorandum by which you will fully
understand, what wish you to take under your Charge; and to
which your attention will be Directed.</p>

<p>1st You will make a mess Book in which you will enter this 
memorandum as a standing order and in which you will enter the names
of each <persName>Negroe</persName>, in the <placeName>Mess</placeName>.   The <placeName>Messes </placeName>you will number.   You will<pb n="248"/>
see that provisions are delivered to each <placeName>mess </placeName>both of meat, and meal,
you will see that meal is procured&#8212;</p>

<p>2 The regular allowance to each <persName>hand </persName>is 3/4 of a pound of meat
pr Day and at the rate of a peck of sifted <persName>Indian </persName>meal pr week. Or
half meal, and half Hominy, potatoes and beans will be given in lieu
of hominy-</p>

<p>3rd You will take charge of the Keys of the <placeName>Meat, and Corn
House</placeName>, also, the <placeName>waggon Yard</placeName>, and see that the corn is properly
divided out, also see that the work oxen, and milk cows are properly
attended to and salted, and that all strange horses, and Cattle are
kept from the <placeName>wagon and stable yards</placeName>, and they secured.</p>

<p>4th You will examine each morning and see, that all the <persName>hands </persName>not
engaged at the <placeName>mine hill</placeName>, are at work by sun rise and that they do
their duty; and <hi rend="italic">never </hi>suffer your <hi rend="italic">orders </hi>to be <hi rend="italic">neglected</hi>, or set
<hi rend="italic">aside</hi>.</p>

<p>5th You will see that <persName>the Cook in the <placeName>negroe Kitchen</placeName></persName> keeps it in
proper order, and has her meals in due time, that Homony is made
ready, and duly provided</p>

<p>6th It has been always my rule to have as much homony made ready
the evening as may be wanted the next day&#8212;Each in turn to pound
a mortar of Homony. This must be the rule and the Homony 
delivered each morning.</p>

<p>7th You will each night before you go to rest examine and see that
all strange <persName>negroes </persName>are ordered away, and the yards closed, and the
<placeName>Cooks Kitchen</placeName> lock'd. The key may be lodged with <persName>Old Jack</persName> who
will be accountable for the same</p>

<p>Furnace Regulations</p>

<p>8th When the Furnace is out of Blast you will see that the Lead
is removed, and the <placeName>house </placeName>cleaned out, and made fast, both Doors
and windows, and all the Tools collected and placed in a corner of
the Furnace. Its the duty of the <persName>hands </persName>not in the Last Charge to
clean up and secure the furnace</p>

<p>9th When the Furnace is in Blast you will see that no strange
<persName>negroes </persName>are suffered to lounge about, but order them away, and make
them off. The proper time to Smelt a charge is 18 hours and 20
hours the longest time and for each 2000 pounds of mineral ought
to produce 30 to 31 &amp; 32 bars of Lead of 42lb. each. You will observe
that proper wood is of the first consequences to Smelt well. You will
therefore cause the back door <persName>hand </persName>to bring in his wood, that is to
furnish his Charge, and place it over the furnace, and at the furnace<pb n="249"/>
ash hole to be made as dry as possible, and this ought to [be] done
as soon as the Charge goes into the furnace, and so remain untill
the Charge is nearly finished when it may be used. You will also
understand that dry wood is necessary for smelting Lead Ore,
<persName>Negroes </persName>and <persName>Whites </persName>aught to be prevented, Visiting the furnace nor
suffered to remain about the furnace, they draw off the attention of
the hands, the furnace tools should be always kept in order and the
<persName>master </persName>of each charge should and must be made accountable for any
damage done the furnace and Tools to him you will give any orders
you may receive respecting the furnace&#8212;</p>

<p>10th You will see that mineral is cleaned and Buckd down to
charge the furnace in due time, and also that both the <placeName>furnace and
mineral house</placeName> are kept clean and nothing wasted, the Charge for the
furnace will be 2000Ib mineral and aught to be weighed up in time
not to detain the work.</p>

<p>11th You will see that all the Tools, such as axes, hoes, plows, and
every kind of Tools is taken good care of, and each person that uses
them must account for them, and you will remember, that not a Tool
can be lent out to any man, on any account whatever. The waggon
and carts must be considered under your care, and each <persName>waggoner</persName>
must be accountable for every thing belonging to his waggon. Every
thing that may be wanting to keep the waggons in order, and horses
also, you will consider under your charge.</p>

<p>12th. If any are sick you will let me know, and you will at all times
take the utmost care that they be provided for, and treated with
Humanity.</p>

<p>13th. You will suffer no Drinking or fighting among the <persName>negroes</persName>
without letting me know of it, if you can not stop it yourself, report
it to me.</p>

<p>14th. You will report to me should it be necessary in time that I
may provide such things as may be needed to carry the above 
regulations into Execution, which I request may be most strictly executed
to the utmost of your power,</p>
<p>I am respt Yrs-</p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin</persName><pb n="250"/></p>

<p>Memorandum of the <persName>Negroes </persName>Names and Messes</p>

<p><placeName><persName>Ellick</persName>s House</placeName>
<persName>Manuel </persName>	1
<persName>May  </persName>		1
<persName>Rose</persName>		1
<persName>Jone</persName>		1
<persName>Arnold</persName>	1
<persName>Siller</persName>	1
2 <persName>Children</persName>	2
		__
<persName>Wilson</persName>	8
	5 pounds meat
	1 peck meal</p>

<p><placeName><persName>Bill C. </persName>House</placeName>
<persName>Juba</persName>		1
<persName>Charls</persName>	1
<persName>Hannah</persName>	1
<persName>Hannah</persName>	1
<persName>Sue</persName>		1
<persName>Amey</persName>		1
<persName>Melina</persName>	1
<persName>Children</persName>	4
		__	
		8</p>

<p><placeName><persName>Nance</persName>'s Kitchen</placeName>
<persName>Jacob</persName>		1
<persName>Charles</persName>	1
<persName>Quash</persName>		1
<persName>Osmond</persName>	1
<persName>Allen</persName>		1
<persName>Sam</persName>		1
<persName>Tom</persName>		1
<persName>Bill Cannon</persName>	1
<persName>Richmond</persName>	1
<persName>Little Bill</persName>	1
<persName>Nance</persName>		1
<persName>Elleck</persName>	1
		___	
		13</p>

<p>10  pound Meat&#8212;
11  pecks meal&#8212;</p>

<p>6 pounds meat
1 peek meal
<persName>Jesse </persName>1 peck pr. week
<persName>Ralph </persName>one peck pr. week</p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin</persName>
<persName>Mrs. Austin</persName>
<persName>S. Austin</persName>
<persName>S. Hynes</persName>
<persName>R. Bruffee</persName>
<persName>Mrs. Bruffee</persName>
<persName>Henry </persName>and <persName>John</persName>
<persName>J S. Brickey</persName>
<persName>H Luty</persName>	
<persName>H Luty </persName>  	10
	12lb pounds meat	
	1 Bushell meal</p>

<p><persName>Lucy</persName>
<persName>Aggy</persName>
<persName>Jack</persName>
<persName>Poll</persName>
________	5
		___
		15
		3
		___
	4)	45	
		___
		11 1/4 pounds pork

Half Bushell meal pr. Day</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
