<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0738">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to James E. B. Austin, 05-04-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 787-790
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-05-04">05-04-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Instructions for moving mother and sister to Texas. Transportation. Commerce. Condition of the colony.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[May 4,1824.]</p>

<p>Memorandum for my brother <persName>J. E. B. Austin</persName></p>

<p>You will go on to <placeName>Nackitosh </placeName>and on your arrival there determine
wheither to continue on by land through <placeName>Arkansas </placeName>or to go up the
<placeName>Mississippi </placeName>by water&#8212;if the weather appears favourable and the<pb n="788"/>
waters are down I had much rather you should go by<placeName> Little Rock</placeName>,
Call on <persName>McNeil </persName>beyond <placeName>Nacogodoches </placeName>and deliver my letter to him&#8212;-
also on <persName>McGuffin </persName>and on <persName>Dr Sibly</persName> and <persName>Mr Cable</persName> in <placeName>N[atchitoches]</placeName> you
must send me from <placeName>Nackitoches </placeName>or <placeName>Alexandria </placeName>if you go by there, two
Reams of good writing paper if you can get an opportunity and if
you cannot send so much send as much as you can I want it for
the deeds also one large blank book&#8212;2 yards of Red buntin or flannel
2 of Green and 2 of white for a flag some narrow Red, white and
green ribbon for cockades&#8212;also some barks and Salts-&#8212;these are all
the articles I want from there&#8212;and perhaps <persName>House </persName>can bring them
<hi rend="italic">&#8212;also a good Mosquetoe bar </hi>&#8212;</p>

<p>If y[ou do] not go on by land proceed as far as <placeName>Alexandria </placeName>and
if the road is passable, as far as <placeName>Natchez </placeName>and sell the horse and
mule as well as possible and be very particular not to spend <hi rend="italic">one</hi>
cent more than you are obliged to do&#8212;enquire for the Dolphin or
some boat bound to <placeName>St. Louis</placeName> but try and get in a good one&#8212;</p>

<p>You will encourage all good moral and industrious men of <persName>families</persName>
to move here who have some property to begin with&#8212;those who
are not of that character you need say nothing to&#8212;<persName>Single men</persName> 
cannot get any Land [from] me for as many of them are already [in
the colony?] as can be, but wages here are high and they may do
well in that way and buy land from others&#8212;some may want you
to give them letters to me, but you must be <hi rend="italic">very </hi>cautious to know
who and what they are before you give a letter to them and let it
be generally known that those who come without good 
recommendations cannot get land nor be allowed to remain here and let the
<persName>Methodists </persName>know the truth relative to Religion&#8212;also let it be known
that a part must be paid down in cash or cattle&#8212;but do not make
any display or noise, treat all who make enquiries politely [answer]
them as well as you can, and put nothing in the <placeName>news papers</placeName>--
If you go by <placeName>Little Rock</placeName> be very particular to get possession of my
trunk that was left at <placeName><persName>Vaughn</persName>s </placeName>on the <placeName>little Missouri</placeName> <persName>Stevenson </persName>had
the care of it, and send the things to <persName>Nathaniel Cox</persName> in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
-&#8212;at <placeName>Little Rock</placeName> collect all the property left there by me or my
<persName>father </persName>or <persName>Bryan </persName>and send it to <persName>Cox </persName>in <placeName>Orleans</placeName>&#8212; enquire of <persName>Ashley</persName>
relative to the <placeName>little Rock property</placeName> and insist on his giving a deed
to <persName>Mrs Bryan</persName> of her part of that property which was deeded by
<persName>Bryan </persName>to <persName>H. Elliott</persName>&#8212;tell him that <persName>Elliott </persName>told me he had never received 
any compensation for it and only took the Deed to befriend
<persName>Bryan</persName>&#8212;and if <persName>Ashley </persName>will not do what is right employ <persName>Crittenden</persName>
to commence suit and let the people know how <persName>Ashley </persName>has acted
in the business, but be particular not to say anything about it untill
you see <persName>Ashley </persName>and know That he will do&#8212;If you do not go by
<placeName>Little Rock</placeName>, Soon after your arrival in <placeName>Herculanium </placeName>go to <placeName>St Louis</placeName><pb n="789"/>
and see <persName>Mr. W. C. Carr</persName> relative to the <placeName>Little Rock</placeName> business and
explain it to him and <persName>Mrs Elliott</persName>&#8212;and then go to <placeName>Little Rock</placeName>&#8212;
also enquire what <persName>H. Elliott</persName> did with <persName>Sylvanus Castleman</persName>'s Lot
of land in the <placeName>big field</placeName> and take that business out of their hands
and rent the lot&#8212;</p>

<p>Ask <persName>Mrs H. Elliott</persName> wheither she wishes me to secure her any land
in this country and [assure her of] my desire to serve her&#8212;that is if
justice is done to <persName>Emily</persName>-</p>

<p>Be very particular to collect all the little property that <persName>Emily </persName>has
and provide well for them on the journey, bring all their beds and
bedding and pot kettle and crockery ware &amp;c that are of light 
carrage, and bring all kinds of Garden seeds and roots, particularly
nectarines Peach, Pairs Grapes &amp;c &amp;c&#8212;Currants&#8212;Gooseberry&#8212;
<hi rend="italic">Rose Roots</hi> of the ... etc [Perhaps arrangemen]ts can be made by
you and <persName>Varner </persName>to come by Sea write me immediately, and if I make
any arrangements here I will write to <placeName>Natchez </placeName>and to the <placeName>mouth of
Red River</placeName> to be left with <persName>Warren Hall</persName>. I am most in favor of your
coming by land&#8212;bring a light dearborn waggon and gears which
ever way you come&#8212;bring the <persName>family of negros</persName> that <persName>Emily </persName>has at
all hazards and I will settle with <persName>Bryan </persName>for them&#8212;if you can get
<persName>Lucy </persName>and <persName>Babtiste </persName>and <persName>Poll </persName>without paying too much money do so
and not without</p>

<p>You must bring a good sett of <persName>blacksmith</persName> tools&#8212;Some homade
cloth for me for summer and winter clothing. I wish all the family
to wear nothing else&#8212;</p>

<p>Try and move <persName>Aunt Austin</persName> and help her all you can have a good
tent provided for the road and bring as much furniture as you think
a light waggon could haul from <placeName>Nachitoches</placeName>&#8212;all these things you
must arrange the best way you can&#8212;bring 1000. of lead which send
to<persName> N. Cox</persName> of <placeName>Orleans </placeName>and some shot&#8212;and all the heavy articles send
to 1$- <persName>Cox </persName>but pay the fright and write to <persName>Cox </persName>to ship them to me at
the <placeName>mouth of this River</placeName> as soon as he can&#8212;try and make an 
arrangement with <persName>Honey </persName>to [ freight ] down the <persName>family </persName>and things and wait
[for payment] or I will save him [some lan]d here of 600&#8212;or a
1000 acres&#8212;[Bring] sugar and Coffee and Rice etc for the
[journey?] a keg of allspice to season pumpkins and . . . [also?]
bring 2 sets of plain shovels and tongues [some?] garden spades
and 2 mining picks to dig [ out ? ] the mill race&#8212;andirons&#8212;mosquitoe
bars tell <persName>Roberts </persName>and <persName>Bruffy </persName>&amp;c that I have done all I could for
them and will send money to them as soon as I can&#8212;if they come
here I can pay them in land that will be a fortune to them&#8212; try and
get <persName>Saml. Perry</persName> to come on with the <persName>family </persName>and look at the country-
remember me to all my old <persName>acquaintances </persName>at the <placeName>mines </placeName>&amp;c&#8212; have a
handsome flag made with an Eagle painted on it&#8212;<persName>Mother </persName>and <persName>Sister</persName><pb n="790"/>
can make it bring some shoes for us all&#8212;lot <persName>Sister </persName>make me some
Cokades for the <persName>militia officers</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I will send in the waggon so as to be at <placeName><persName>McGuffin</persName>s </placeName>by the <date when="1824-10-15">15</date> or
<date when="1824-10-20">20 day of October</date> and let them wait there untill they hear from
you, so that when you arrive at <placeName>Alexandria </placeName>or <placeName>Nachetosh </placeName>you must
send up to <placeName><persName>McGuffin</persName>s</placeName> for the Waggon and Horses&#8212;I will also send
in a few Horses or mules to sell to buy a few Cows to drive along
to give milk on the road be cautious about making any contracts
with any one for lands or <placeName>settlements </placeName>here, for by the time you
return the 300 <persName>families </persName>may all be filled up and then I should have
difficulty with them, but if you can get 500 or 1000 dollars in <hi rend="italic">Cash</hi>
to help towards buying a vessel . . . land If <persName>S. Perry </persName>comes he
. . . vessell of 40 or 50 tons------</p>

<p>Encourage all good men of families [to come] if they do not get
land from me they can [buy from others] Let <persName>old Jack</persName> do as he
pleases about coming . . . he should come for I will take good care
[of him as long] as he [live]s</p>

<p><persName>S. [F. Austin]</persName></p>

<p>write [me eve]ry opportunity&#8212;&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
