<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0082">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Antoine Soulard, 01-20-1804</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-24">06-24-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Antoine Soulard
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Burton Mine, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">St Louis, MO</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 91-92
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1804-01-20">01-20-1804</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-24" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning the arbitrary transactions of Thomas Madden, surveyor.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Mine A. Burton</placeName> <date when="1804-01-20">Jany. 20th. 1804</date>.</p>

<p>a few Days past <persName>Mr. Maxwell</persName> mentioned to me that he held a note of
mine and at the same time handed me your letter. <persName>Mr Maxwell</persName> 
observed that the intrested had liberty to either make payment or 
return the Concessions to me the concequences are the same I have not
a Dollar at Stake but as I had recd orders from some of the Intrested
not to make payment I requested from <persName>Mr Maxwell</persName> time to learne
the Determenation of the Gentlm after which I would Either make the
payment or Return the Concessions. I receiv'd from all the <persName>Gentlm</persName>-
for answer that the Concessions Should be returned for reasons-
following first that <persName>Mr Madden</persName> has made a Survey for an <persName>Indian boy</persName>
of <persName>Pratt</persName>s of a <placeName>peice of Land</placeName> he was informed two weeks before was
intended for <persName>Mr Shaw</persName> and <persName>Mr Treat</persName> also after being made acquaint'd
Where <persName>Mr Stuart</persName> wish his Survey made he Survey [ed] a Concession
for some of his <persName>family </persName>or <persName>friends </persName>a preference being given to an
<persName>Indian Boy of Pratts</persName> After Messr <persName>Shaw </persName>and <persName>Treat </persName>had paid one
Hundred and Twenty Dollars to some of the settlers of the <placeName>Mine of
burton</placeName> who have made some improvement on the land they intended
to take and which <persName>Madden </persName>surveyed by the <persName>Indian </persName>not 
withstanding being for <persName>old Mr Duelle</persName> thus treated by a man you promis'd
Should execute your orders with out deviation has induced them to
suppose that this Conduct of <persName>Madden</persName>s meet your Approbation under
such impressions you are not to be surprised that they have Declaired
there dissattisfaction in the highest terms, what confidence is to be
given to <persName>Madden </persName>who the moment he had information Where the
<persName>Gentlm</persName>. in question wish'd there [concessions] Survey'd, immediately
made Surveys for Others on the same lands this with Other 
Considerations which I can communicate to you when an opportunity offers
has Determened them all to Return the Concessions As to myself I
have but One Observation to make and that is that I cannot 
sufficiently express my dissattisfaction with my Self, that I have had a
part in this business by which I have not onely recd from you a
Charge of Conduct of which I always shall Declair myself 
Blameless and have been Shamefully abus'd by your freind <persName>madden </persName>I have
given Great dissattisfaction to the Gentlm for whome I acted, all of
which has been brought about by a man altho your friend is 
uneversally Detested by the <persName>American People on the <placeName>West Bank of the 
Mississippia</placeName></persName> notwithstanding I beleave your intentions have been always
to give Sattisfaction to Evry man yet your unbound'd confidance
in <persName>Madden </persName>and his friends has induced you to look on me as a man<pb n="92"/>
unworthy of belief&#8212;and Capable of many improper thing haveing
as you was pleased to express yourself to a friend of yours Clouds
before my eyes which you have not been able to remove</p>

<p><persName>M Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Endorsed:] Copy letter <persName>Mr. A. Soulard</persName>.   <placeName>St. Louis</placeName> <date when="1804-01-20">Jany. 20 1804</date></p>

-         

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
