<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0060">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Irwin to James Austin, 07-01-1801</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Irwin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-23">06-23-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Statesville, NC</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 75-76
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1801-07-01">07-01-1801</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Inquires price of lead. Barter. Way bills.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Statesville North Carolina</placeName> <date when="1801-07-01">1st. July 1801</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr. James Austin</persName></p>

<p>Sir, by information I hear you are <persName>proprietor </persName>and<persName> manager of
the <placeName>Lead Mine</placeName></persName> on <placeName>New river</placeName>, as I want a ton of Lead and Shot let
me know what the price is in Cash, as that is what I will pay in.
as you doubtless keep a number of hands at work please to let me
know if you Stand in need of any tow Cloth or homespun linen,
and the prices&#8212;as I have a quantity on hand I would gladly dispose
of it or if you Stand in need of any other kind of Country produce
State the price and if it Suits I can as easily send the wagon Loaded
as empty</p>

<p>[James Irwin]</p>

<p>direct to <persName>James Irwin</persName>, <placeName>Statesville Iredell County North 
Carolina</placeName></p>

<p>[Endorsed:] <persName>S. Austin</persName>s Letters</p>

<p>Way Bills</p>

<p>Shipped in good Order and well conditioned, by <persName>John F
Merieult</persName> in and upon the good schooner called the Nancy
whereof is <persName>Master </persName>for this present Voyage <persName>John Smith</persName>
now riding at anchor in the Harbor of <placeName>New-orleans</placeName>, and<pb n="76"/>
bound for <placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>five H'h'ds muscovado sugar for
the proper account and Risk of <persName>Mr. Thomas Hanchly</persName>
<persName>mercht </persName>and <persName>citizen of the <placeName>united States of america</placeName></persName> 
resident at the afore Said place being marked and 
numbered as in the Margin, and are to be delivered in the like
good Order and well conditioned, at the aforesaid <placeName>port
of Philadelphia</placeName> (the Danger of the Seas only excepted)
unto <persName>Mr. Thomas Hanchly</persName> or to his <persName>Assigns</persName>, he or they
paying Freight for the said fifteen Dollars per H'h'ds 5
prct Primage In Witness Whereof, the <persName>Master </persName>or <persName>Purser </persName>of the said
schooner hath affirmed to four Bills of Lading, all of this
Tenor and Date; the one of which four bills being 
accomplished, the other to stand void. Dated in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> the <date when="1801-07-02">2d Day of 
July 1801</date></p>

<p><persName>John Smith</persName></p>

<p>SHIPPED in good Order and well conditioned, by <persName>John
F. Merieult</persName> in and upon the good Schooner called the
Nancy whereof is <persName>Master </persName>for this present Voyage <persName>John
Smith </persName>now riding at anchor in the <placeName>Harbor of New 
Orleans</placeName> and bound for <placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>thirteen H'h'ds 
Muscovado Sugar for the proper account and risk of <persName>Mr.
George Fisher</persName> of<placeName> Kaskaskea</placeName> <placeName>Western territory</placeName> and 
<persName>Citizen of the <placeName>United States of America</placeName></persName> Consign'd to <persName>Mr.
James Miller merch.</persName> of the above place being marked
and numbered as in the Margin, and are to be delivered
in the like good Order and well conditioned, at the 
aforesaid port of <placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>(the Danger of the Seas only
excepted) unto <persName>Mr. James Miller</persName> or to his <persName>Assigns</persName>, he or
they paying Freight for the said fifteen Dollars per
H'h'ds 5 pr ct Primage IN WITNESS WHEREOF,
the <persName>Master </persName>or <persName>Purser </persName>of the said Schooner hath affirmed
to four Bills of Lading, all of this Tenor and Date: the
one of which four Bills being accomplished, the other
to stand void. Dated in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> the <date when="1801-07-24">24 Day of
July 1801</date></p>

<p><persName>John Smith</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
