<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0727">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Mrs. Joseph H. Hawkins, 04-20-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mrs. Joseph H. Hawkins
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 773-775
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-04-20">04-20-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Condolence on death of her husband. Austin's philosophy. Condition of the colony.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Brazos River Province of Texas</placeName> <date when="1824-04-20">April 20. 1824</date></p>

<p>Dr. <persName>Madam</persName>,</p>

<p>I scarcely know in what language to express how much I 
sympathise with you for the great loss you have sustained in the death of
your kind and affectionate <persName>husband</persName>&#8212;I have so long esteemed Mr
<persName>Hawkins </persName>as a <persName>brother</persName>, as a bosom <persName>friend </persName>that indeed I feel too much
in need of consolation myself for his loss to be able to offer it to
others. I had anticipated many years of tranquil happiness in his
and your Society and that of my <persName>family </persName>in this <placeName>Country</placeName>, the past
fatigues and exposures I have endured would then have been 
forgotten or only afforded subject for amusement, but fleeting and
illusory are all human calculations&#8212;he is gone, and we must console
ourselves with the hope that he has passed from a world of trouble
and care to one of peace and happiness&#8212; The friendship I had
for <persName>Mr Hawkins</persName> was of a nature that cannot be easily or soon 
forgotten, while living I viewed him as a <persName>brother</persName>, and as such lament
him</p>

<p>I have written to <persName>Mr Nathaniel Cox</persName> relative to <persName>Mr. H.</persName> affairs
in this <placeName>country </placeName>presuming from the known intimacy and friendship
between them that he would probably have the settlement of the
Estate, but have never recd any answer&#8212;I believe it was <persName>Mr. H</persName>'s
intention to move to this country, but presume that at this time you
will not think of such a thing&#8212;indeed I could not advise it;  the<pb n="774"/>
country is yet new and wild, we have no luxuries, few comforts, tho
abundance of the common necessaries of life&#8212; I have however 
dispatched my <persName>brother </persName>to <placeName>Missouri </placeName>to move on my <persName>mother </persName>and <persName>Sister</persName>
and <persName>Aunt</persName>, (the <persName>sister of my mother</persName>) all widows; and should your
situation not be agreeable and [should you] think that a removal
here would better it, the same accomodations shall be made for
your <persName>family </persName>that are for mine.</p>

<p>If <persName>Mr H.</persName> did not dispose of the interest he held with me here
I think it will be a handsome fortune for his <persName>family </persName>at no very 
distant period and I assure you that my desire is that <hi rend="italic">they </hi>and they
alone should reap the benefit of it. I shall not willingly consent to
see any advantages resulting from my labors appropriated to the
discharge of his old debts when it could be much better applied in
supporting his <persName>widow </persName>and <persName>children</persName>-&#8212;I therefore request that you
would write to me with frankness as to a sincere <persName>friend </persName>and inform
me of your situation and future wishes, and how I can serve you.</p>

<p>I expect that my <persName>mother </persName>and <persName>sister </persName>and several other <persName>families </persName>will
leave <placeName>Herculanium in Missouri</placeName> for this <placeName>Country </placeName>some time in 
<date n="10-xx-1824">October next&#8212;</date>might we not form a little circle a kind of isolated world
of our own amidst these wilds and hope that happiness would 
become our presiding goddess? I have thought it practicable&#8212;
perhaps it was a romantic dream&#8212;perhaps the symplicity of a rural life
would be dull monotony, its peaceful quiet scenes be lost in vain
regrets for past enjoyments in the gay and bustling world, and the
proud independence of a farmer be viewed as degrading servitude.
The mind of man is of too unstable a texture to found even a theory
of happiness upon. When oppressed with cares, harrassed by 
unfeeling <persName>creditors</persName>, agonized by the ingratitude of <persName>friends </persName>and driven
to madness by the prospect of a starving <persName>family</persName>, a desert would be
a paradise to him if it only afforded sustenance; but when the 
effervescence of the mind had subsided this desert would be as loathsome
as a dungeon&#8212;perhaps however if he found a small circle of 
honorable minded men who had like himself passed through the school of
adversity and learned fortitude to meet the privations of their 
situation, philosophy to find contentment in a plain and comfortable
competancy without the glitter of wealth, and charity to do unto
their <persName>neighbors </persName>as they would be done by&#8212;and if female society like
a celestial halo could also shed its mild effulgence around them&#8212;
perhaps, in such an event he might find happiness&#8212;and perhaps the
evil passions of the human heart would soon prove the fallacy of
all such dreams&#8212;For my own part I feel disposed to try the 
experiment and shall endeavor to collect my scattered family to one
point&#8212;The Earth from which we sprung will yield us food and
raiment, and the privations of our situation I think can be better<pb n="775"/>
borne than the unfeeling indifference and contemptuous mockery
which the unfortunate generally receive from the fashionable world
and which (for fashions sake) is called friendship&#8212;</p>

<p>The affairs of this <placeName>colony </placeName>are prosperous and highly flattering&#8212;
last year we were threatened with starvation, this year we have a
superabundance of corn, so much so that it can be purchased for 37 1/2
cents pr bushel&#8212;All goes on well&#8212;The <persName>Government of the <placeName>Mexican
nation</placeName></persName> has settled down on the Federal Republican System and our
prospects are bright from every quarter&#8212;I think that my labors in
these wild deserts will result advantageously to many of my fellow
beings and that you and family will in the end be greatly benefited
by them&#8212;at least such is the earnest wish of your sincere friend</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
