<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0559">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Robert Andrews to James E. B. Austin, 01-25-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Robert Andrews</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Saltillo, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Bexar, TX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 574-575
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-01-25">01-25-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Mexican political news. Commercial projects. Mexican character.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><persName>Saltillo </persName><date when="1823-01-25">Jany 25th /23</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>James</persName></p>

<p>I this minut recd. yours of the <date when="1823-01-05">5th Inst</date>, and am happy to hear
that you are not "sin consuelo".&#8212;I live at present on hope altogether,
there being no call for a <persName>Physician</persName>; upon the aggregate of good
and bad times, I bearly live decently. I should certainly have left
this place before this, had it not been that I have continually 
expected the arrival of your <persName>Brother </persName>since the <date when="1823-01-20">20th of this month</date>,
according to his letter of the <date when="1823-01-01">1st Inst</date>, saying that he would certainly
leave <placeName>Mexico </placeName>on the <date when="1823-01-06">6th</date>&#8212;I this morning recd another from him dtd,
the <date when="1823-01-15">15th</date> in which he says "I will leave here in company with the
<persName>Capt. Genl. Bustamanta</persName> who calculates to start in 8 days for <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>,
but if he should not go I will set out in that time "&#8212;The collonization
Law passed and was published on the <date when="1823-01-04">4 Inst</date>, which no doubt you will
see before you see this&#8212;he says in his letter that the <persName>Junta </persName>is now
debating the articles of a constitution which is compleatly 
demonstrative of all the Ignorance Inability and Stupidity of the <placeName>Nation</placeName>,
and will probabilly do more harm than good to the Emperial cause,
that the House is much divided, that there has been much pithy
speaking on the subject, and a prospect of many of the <persName>members</persName>
holding an honorable pole for the <hi rend="italic">Carcel</hi>, he also says " The 
Cannon and Bells this moment announce the acknowledgement of the
independence of the <placeName>Empire of Mexico</placeName> by <placeName>Peru </placeName>and <placeName>Chili</placeName>"&#8212;I
suppose you have heard by this time of the malcontents of <placeName>Vira Cruz</placeName>,
it is said by some that they are depreciating, and by others that
they increase every day, that the influence of the two <persName>Genls</persName>. who
left <placeName>Mexico </placeName>the other day for the other party, is so great, among the
<persName>troops </persName>that it will have a great affect, it is also whispered that the
<persName>Emperial Troops</persName> attacked <placeName>Vira Cruz</placeName>, and were defeated with 
considerable losses&#8212;the act instituting paper money on so very weak
a plan is much dispised by the people big fools as they are, this
will also have its weight, and the Constitution coming out together<pb n="575"/>
with the natural inclination of the major part of the people, I think
in a fiew months will close the scene&#8212;I live on hope with closed lips,
which is one of the requisites of this free nation, the other day our
<persName>Genl</persName>, made known in town that he had it in his power to put to
death in 3 days, any person who spoke against the present Govt, or
religion&#8212;I am happy to hear of the health of my relations, and
am sorry to say that I expect it will be out of my power to see
them in a short time if ever, for I design going to <placeName>Altamira </placeName>in the
course of the <date n="Winter-1822">winter </date>to imbark for my health which is still threatened
by the complaint in my breast&#8212;the trip I had intended to the
<placeName>U. S.</placeName> with Mules is altogether uncertain and what I do or wether I
go is also uncertain, I think I love chastity too well to mary in
this country, yet I know not what effect a pritty <persName>girl </persName>with 2 or
300,000 in my power might have, but there are none of this clase in
<placeName>Saltillo</placeName>&#8212;My best Respects to all countrymen and friends&#8212;hoping
to see you and them once more I tender you my most sincere wishes,
I remain</p>

<p>Your Friend</p>

<p>[Robert Andrews.]</p>
<p>If the Alleys should return to <placeName>Bexar </placeName>be so good as to give them
this letter.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] A <persName>Snr Dn Santiago Austin</persName> <placeName>Bexar Texas</placeName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
