<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0695">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James W. Jones to Unknown, 02-26-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James W. Jones</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Fort Settlement, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 747-748
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Deposition</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-02-26">02-26-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Economic conditions.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Fort Settlement</placeName> <date when="1824-02-26">26th Feb 1824</date></p>

<p>I certify that early in the month of <date n="07-xx-1822">July 1822</date> my <persName>Brother </persName>and
myself found <persName>Mrs Jane Long </persName>low down on the <placeName>river St Hyacinth</placeName>
in a <placeName>Palmeter camp</placeName> exposd to the rains and sun and nothing to 
support herself and <persName>family </persName>on except a small quantity of milk which
she got of a <persName>family </persName>that livd near We took pity on her and proposd
to build her a <placeName>cabin </placeName>near where we were and that we would hunt
and support her in the best manner we could until her <persName>relations</persName>
would send for her; to which proposition she agreed we hired
<persName>hands </persName>and movd her and furnishd her with corn meal, pork and
salt and at all times found her in plenty of venison until late in
<date n="08-xx-1822">August </date>when she proposd going to <placeName>St Antonia</placeName> saying that the
<persName>Govournor </persName>had given her encouragement to go on there and he
would do every thing in his power for her she proposd that we
should go with her She promisd to satisfy us to our full 
satisfaction when she arrivd in <placeName>St Antonia</placeName> we furnishd her horses to pack
her Bagage and for part of her <persName>family </persName>to ride And meal and meat
for the Journey we walk'd ourselves for to accomadate her and
<persName>family </persName>through the heat and dust and at some places twenty miles
without water with the calculation of being reasonably compensated
We arrivd at <placeName>St Antonia</placeName> after we had been there for or five days
we proposd to return she then informed us that it was utterly out
of her power to compensate us as she had promisd at the time she<pb n="748"/>
had started that she had been there so short a time and had had
but little conversation with <persName>Govournor </persName>and dislikd asking him for any
thing to pay us With but that we should be amply satisfd in a short
time, she then let my <persName>brother </persName>have her rifle If we left the <placeName>Province</placeName>
the gun was to be left at <placeName><persName>Mr Banian</persName>'s</placeName> If we remaind he was to keep
the gun until she calld for it. She gave up the horse for us to use
until we were settled With at the same time requestd that we would
not part with him as she wanted him for her <persName>Daughter </persName>she was
to have Borne our expences she let us have five Dollars only to
bur Provision when we set out</p>

<p><persName>James W. Jones</persName>&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
