<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0232">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John Bowman to Stephen F Austin, 08-05-1813</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John Bowman</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-30">06-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Fayette County, KY</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Burton Mine, MO</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 226-228
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1813-08-05">08-05-1813</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">War politics in Kentucky.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Fayette County Ky</placeName>, <date when="1813-08-05">August 5th 1813</date></p>

<p>My old Friend,</p>

<p>I once again have taken up my pen to address you; to inform you
that I have not quite forgotten you, and to make my apology for
not writing long since&#8212;The Reason is that I have never heard where
you were, since I had the pleasure of receiving your letter dated in
<date n="07-xx-1812">July, 1812</date>, written from some place in <placeName>Louisiana </placeName>but I could not tell<pb n="227"/>
precisely where; until I fortunately met our friend <persName>William Bates</persName> in
<placeName>Lexington </placeName>ten or twelve days ago, who for the first time informed
me that you had returned to the <placeName>mines</placeName>; I had always previous to this
information been impressed with a belief that you had gone on to
the <placeName>Eastward </placeName>as you wrote me&#8212;and of course I knew not where a
letter would have found you&#8212;This my dear <persName>friend </persName>is the reason you
have not often heard from me; and not (as you may have supposed)
that our former intimacy and friendship are forgotten by me&#8212;no
<persName>Stephen </persName>true friendship with me is of a more lasting duration, and
cannot thus easily be forgotten, though we have been for a long
time separated by the distance of some hundred Miles, and scarcely
heard of each other; and though it may be that fate has decreed that
we shall never again see each other, yet still you my friend shall
live bright in my recollection, neither time nor distance shall ever
efface from my mind the thoughts of that friend, with whom I have
spent so many agreeable hours, whose kind attention to me while in
a strange country has been unequaled; think not that these are the
effusions of a mind that is disposed to flatter, far be it from me to
sport with your feelings by attempting to flatter you; a grateful
recollection of past occurrences has drawn from me this candid 
declaration of the high esteem in which I hold you</p>

<p>I might here have closed my letter which was commenced 
principally with a view of renewing that friendly correspondence which
heretofore existed between us but before I conclude I will give you
the politicks of the day about <placeName>Lexington</placeName>&#8212;We are divided into to
<persName>parties</persName>, the <persName>Federal </persName>and <persName>Republican </persName>or in other words the <persName>peace
party</persName> and the <persName>war Party</persName>&#8212;ever since the declaration of war (and I
believe long before) the <persName>Federal party</persName> have violently opposed the
measures of the <persName>Government</persName>, with what view I am at a loss to know,
unless they expect by their great opposition to render the present
administration unpopular at a time when our <persName>armies </persName>have met with
so many defeats <placeName>to the north</placeName>; there by expecting to put our <persName>leading
Characters</persName> out of office, that they may come into power themselves,
and in order to effect this object I believe there are some characters
base enough to sacrafice our Republican institutions an[d] upon the
ruins thereof erect a government, the Spirit and genius of which I
think would be more congenial to a foreign Clime&#8212;I would not
wish to be understood as believing that there are many in this quarter
who would go thus far, but there are a number (whose motives I
cant help thinking are pure and innocent) who have united 
themselves to that party, the principal <persName>Leaders </persName>of which would go to
any lengths in order to put down the <persName>Republicans</persName>&#8212;our Election
which closed yesterday will go to shew the strength of the <persName>two parties
in <placeName>Fayette</placeName></persName>. <persName>John <hi rend="italic">Pope</persName> who had disgraced himself by his opposition
to the war,</hi> came forward as a candidate to represent the people of<pb n="228"/>
<placeName>Fayette </placeName>in the next Legislature; he met the fate he deserved, that is
the people chose to let him stay at home. <persName>Genl. R. S. Russell</persName> between
whom, and <persName>Pope</persName>, the contest lay had 1208 [or 1268] and <persName>Pope </persName>434
thus you see the strength of the two parties here&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>Executive of <placeName>Kentucky</placeName></persName> has been called on by <persName>Genl Harrison
</persName>for as many men as he can furnish, who are to rendevous at 
<placeName>newport </placeName>the last of this month&#8212;there will be <persName>volunteers </persName>a plenty, and
<persName>Shelby </persName>takes the command of them&#8212;I shall go myself&#8212;Adieu my
friend for a while&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>John Bowman </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Mr Stephen F Austin</persName></p>

<p>P. S. My Warmest respects to your <persName>Mother </persName>and <persName>sister </persName>and all
enquiring <persName>Friends</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>J. B</persName>.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Stephen F. Austin Esqr</persName> <placeName>Mine A Burton Territory
Missouri</placeName>  Politeness of <persName>Mr Wm Bates.</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
