<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0577">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Robert Andrews to Stephen F. Austin, 04-19-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Robert Andrews</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Parras, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 630-631
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-04-19">04-19-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Wants surveying in the colony. Introducing Ramos Arispe.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Parras </placeName><date when="1823-04-19">Apl 19th 1823</date></p>
<p>Dear friend <persName>Stephen</persName></p>

<p>It is now some time since I recd a letter from you, it is six weeks
since I left <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>, but having no information of your having passed
there, I presume you are in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>yet to which place I direct this
letter, believing that you understand your business, and knowing
the confused state of public affairs I have no idea you will leave
there soon - I will say but little untill I receive your answer - I am
in good health but doing a very slender business, I intend to go to
<placeName>Durango </placeName>in a month or two if nothing particular takes place, but
shall be here long enough to receive your ansr I am a candidate
of the office of <persName>surveyor </persName>in the <placeName>province of Texas</placeName>, if a removal should
take place which might be the case the reasons I advance in my
letter to the <persName>Revd Doctr Dn Miguel Ramos de Arispe</persName> who is my
<persName>friend </persName>are the following&#8212;all the necessities of running the surveys
according to the true meridian which must be ascertained by the
surveyor in sd <placeName>province </placeName>- of calculating the contents by Lat. and
depart. the only true method, likewise the ability of the <persName>surveyor </persName>to
do all this, keep his records in Spanish, speak English and attend
personally to the work, all of which are very assencial to the peace
and quietude of the <persName>inhabitants </persName>and consequently to government,
to do all this, to the satisfaction of <persName>Govt </persName>and the <persName>people</persName>, I pledge
my [self], your friendship in this can be of much service - seeing
that my profession can do but little for me in the country I have
thought sometimes of establishing myself on a <placeName>farm </placeName>near <placeName>the falls
on the Collorado</placeName> with about 20 of those labouring <persName>Indians </persName>but I am
in much hesitation what to do, I wish to hear from you very much
concerning your ideas prospects etc. If the <persName>Doct. Hamos</persName> should be
in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>I wish very much you would seek an acquaintance with
him, the first introduction to which may be a visit on my part with
my best wishes for his health etc. which I believe is the mode of the<pb n="631"/>
country - you will be pleased with him no doubt and my particular
<persName>friend </persName><persName>Ximenes del Rio</persName> who must never be forgotten if he should be
with the <persName>Doct</persName>. or in the <placeName>House of <persName>Mrs. Odonohu</persName></placeName> where he hitherto
lived for he is an excellent youth</p>

<p><persName>Andrews    </persName>[Rubric]</p>
<p>[Addressed:] A <persName>Sr. Dn Estefan F Austin</persName> <placeName>Mexico</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
