<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0499">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Bryan to Stephen F. Austin, 04-15-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Bryan</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Hazel Run, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 495-496
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-04-15">04-15-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Prospects flattering. Company of a hundred in Kentucky sending agents to Texas to inspect. Reports from East. Sends goods to trade.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Hazel Run</placeName> <date when="1822-04-15">April 15th 1822</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Brother Stephen</persName></p>

<p>I intend you shall not have cause To complain I do not write, if
I have but little News of importance; we have not recd a letter from
you or <persName>Brown </persName>since you both left <placeName>Nachacdosh </placeName>and I can assure you
we are very anxious to hear from you both we do expect <persName>Mr Henry
Elliott</persName> <placeName>home </placeName>in all <date n="04-xx-1822">this Month</date> and will expect letters by him, as also
a detailed account of the <placeName>Colony </placeName>Prospects etc&#8212; The prospects
are yet very flattering as it respects <persName>emigrants </persName>to the <placeName>Colony </placeName>from
all the States I have no doubt but that the <placeName>Colony </placeName>will be filled up
in twelve Months should those that have gone to explore report 
favourable on their return&#8212; a <persName>company in <placeName>Kentucky</placeName></persName> have agreed to
send on four men to explore and if they are pleased to select Lands
for said <persName>Company </persName>say one hundred <persName>Families</persName>, and I have latety
heard from the <placeName>Eastern States</placeName>, and am informed a number of
<persName>families </persName>will move to the <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212; If you have formed a good 
Constitution and the <persName>Government </persName>is settled I am clearly of the Opinion
that no <placeName>Section of Territory</placeName> has ever settled so rapidly as the <placeName>Texas
Colony</placeName>, or the <placeName>Austin Colony</placeName>&#8212; and I flatter myself that we shall
once more be independent that is as it respects debt&#8212; I hope you
have got the <placeName>Grant </placeName>fully confirmed&#8212; and I have heretofore in a letter
requested the particular favour of having the best <placeName>Mill Seat</placeName> Selected
for me and three miles square of Land and I will have it improved
as soon as Possible, I have also before mentioned <persName>Majr Calloway</persName>
stated that there was a fine Grove of pine on the <placeName>Colorado River</placeName>,
it being some distance from Town is not an objection if on or near
the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>, I expect <persName>Samuel M. Parmer</persName>, and <persName>Old Mr Winds</persName> and
his <persName>son Wm</persName> will start with some more men I have engaged on the
<date when="1822-05-01">first of May</date>&#8212; I shall make the necessary arrangements with them
and will write you by them and let you know what they are&#8212; the<pb n="496"/>
<persName>Bearers </persName>are <persName>Thos V. Alley</persName> and his two <persName>Brothers </persName>all intend if they
are pleased to remain in the <placeName>Colony</placeName>. I have given them a permit
and also have told them you will give them indulgence should they
need it for the payment of their Lands,, you no doubt can find there
imploy of some kind to pay for their Land etc&#8212; I send a few 
Barrels Flour and some other articles by <persName>Thos V. Alley</persName> to you, which
you will take an account of and I will probably send some more
shortly&#8212; last years wheat is so bad it will not make much flour fit to
eat, on the return of <persName>Mr H. Elliott</persName> should his report appear to 
require it, I may conclude to go on Immediately myself, and if so will
bring some Whiskey, Flour, Lead and Pow[d]er etc&#8212; I will expect
you to have a Building under way for my <persName>family</persName>&#8212; I am in hopes
to get business Closed in this quarter shortly, a number are waiting
the return of <persName>Elliott Murphey</persName>s and <persName>Bruffy</persName>s reports relative to the
<placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212; hope this letter will meet you and <persName>Brother James</persName>, and all
acquaintances in good health&#8212; we are all tolerable well, bad colds
are prevalent no News here worthy of your attention</p>

<p><persName>James Bryan</persName></p>

<p>Our affection to <persName>Brother James</persName>   We will expect him to write</p>

<p>P. S. We wish to start in <date n="10-xx-1822">Octr </date>for <placeName>Texas</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
