<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0014">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John D. Blanchard to Moses Austin, 05-17-1795</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John D. Blanchard</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-11">06-11-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Moses Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Philadelphia, PA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 22-23
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1795-05-17">05-17-1795</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Financial depression. Relations with Ruston. Stephen Austin's operations in England.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Philadelphia </placeName><date when="1795-05-17">May 17th. 1795</date></p>

<p><persName>Mr. Moses Austin</persName>.</p>

<p>Dr Sir Your favor of the <date when="1794-04-25">25th April </date>I have just receiv'd, am
happy you found the <persName>family </persName>well and all going right, it gives me
pleasure also to hear that the surveys will soon be return'd. will
thank you to hasten them as fast as possible, <persName>Mr. L</persName> and myself wish
also to hear of your first locations for which we are ready to answer
your drafts for more warrents, but tho land cannot be said to have
fell in price here yet I believe there has not been a sale made since
your departure, nor do I hear half the talk about them there was
while you was here and from enquiring I find they are very flatt-and
down tho' attribute it to the continued scarcity of money which 
prevents speculations in them <persName>Dr. Euston</persName> has frequently been with me
to write you concerning the <placeName>20000 Acres</placeName> of Land you are to take the
patents in his Name for and for which he says I have garanteed.
Have you put that business in train for him. He still remains a 
barrier in the way of any negotiation by Notes either for your <persName>House</persName>
or my <persName>Firm </persName>and I am laying on his paper as indorser to the amount
of 12,000 Dolls, protested in the different <placeName>Banks </placeName>which has stopped
all my paper and all the remainder of the paper of <persName>Stephen Austin
and Co</persName>&#8212;and when he will be able and willing to relieve me I know
not. I can do no business for that <hi rend="italic">Rascall</hi>. You must write me by
the return of Post at what deduction I must take the goods from
<persName>Lauman and West</persName> on my own a/c as I wish to appropriate it 
immeadiately; the goods sent to <persName>Shannen's Auction Store</persName> Neated the
sum of £297.7.8 and the Amount sent to him was £453.19.4 
difference £156.118 you see more than a third part is lost&#8212;you must
know it is but right that some certain price should be affix'd and what
rate I must take the goods on my own account, I want no advantage,
but I am dunn'd very much and stand much in need of relief, Pray
fix this matter for as to taking the goods by the package at £150 pr
br. [?] advance price from the Sterling cost it will not do and he will
not give them less&#8212;Inclosed you have a letter from your <persName>Brother</persName>
you find I am to receive 960 £ Sterling in musical instruments I
could wish I knew what to do with them when they arrive, he has
sold 35,000 Acre of Land at 3/ Sterling, pr Acre, no doubt he writes
you on the subject he has not yet sold the <placeName>mines </placeName>nor does he seem
like to yet, but seems in good spirits and is determined, to do 
something great before he quits <persName>Mm Austin's family</persName> are well&#8212; I had
a bill drawn on me by <persName>Thomas Norwall of <placeName>Richmond</placeName></persName> which it was out
of my power to pay and I thought he was not to draw bills on me<pb n="23"/>
therefore suppose it has been return'd I would have paid it 
nevertheless had I had money but it was otherwise&#8212;let me hear from
you soon and believe me Yours sincerely</p>

<p><persName>JNO D BLANCHARD</persName></p>

<p>Remember <persName>Miller</persName>s things to be for my account and dont forget the
Hams&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
