<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0945">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Mrs. James F. Perry, 12-17-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mrs. James F. Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 991-992
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-12-17">12-17-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Good immigration from Mississippi. "Some with a number of negroes." Hopes to gain religious toleration. Pioneer conditions.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1824-12-17">Decr 17. 1824</date></p>
<p>Dr <persName>Sister</persName>,</p>

<p>Report has just reached here that <persName>Brother </persName>is not coming out this
<date n="Winter-1824">winter</date>&#8212;but do not know wheither it is true or not. tho have supposed
it might be and that you and <persName>Mr Perry</persName> may possibly visit the Country
<date n="Sumemer-1825">next Summer</date></p>

<p>It is not my wish that <persName>Mr Perry</persName> Should make any arrangements
whatever to move here untill he has first seen the <placeName>Country</placeName>&#8212;he
positively must not move on my recommendation nor that of
<persName>Brother</persName>'s&#8212;perhaps he may not like it, but if he moves without first
coming to see, it will be too late to remedy it&#8212;he is now in a good
business and you have good Society, here business will be good after
a while, but not much can be done immediately, and our Society like
all new countries is small, you must not therefore think of moving
here untill he first comes to see&#8212;Things are going on very well and
many <persName>emigrants </persName>are coming in from <placeName>Mississippi</placeName>. Some with a 
number of <persName>negros</persName>, and I have every confidence that the <placeName>Colony </placeName>will
flourish rapidly <persName>Mr Perry</persName> must attend to the <placeName>Little Rock</placeName> business,
or if <persName>Brother </persName>stays through the <date n="Winter-1824">winter </date>he can do it&#8212;<persName>Mrs Elliott</persName>
writes me that she is ready to state that <persName>Mr Elliot</persName> told her the 
property was put into his hands confidentially to save it&#8212;I cannot attend
to it for I do not expect to be in that country for many years to come,
as regards the <placeName>mine a Burton</placeName> Estate I am willing to give any 
authority to commence Suit and if any thing can be recovered I shall 
cheerfully give up my share of it to your <persName>children </persName>for I never will live there
if the whole was given to me&#8212;I want to free my self from debt and
then to sit quietly down on a farm in this Country for the balance of
my life and hope to see <persName>Brother </persName>married and settled on one side of me,
and if it could be <persName>Mr Perry</persName> and you on the other but all my plans
have been broken in upon and I make no more calculations except
to spend my life here; wheither rich or poor, here (that is in this
colony) I expect to remain permanently&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>Methodists </persName>have raised the cry against me, this is what I
wished for if they are kept out, or would remain quiet if here for<pb n="992"/>
a Short time we shall succeed in getting a free toleration for all
Religions, but a few fanatic and imprudent preachers at this time
would ruin us&#8212;we must show the <persName>Govt </persName>that we are ready to 
submit to their laws and willing to do so, after that we can with more
certainty of success hope to have our previleges extended</p>

<p>Adieu my Dear <persName>sister</persName>&#8212;my lot is cast in the <placeName>wilderness </placeName>but I am
content, trouble and fatigue have become so very familiar to me
that they begin to appear like bosom friends. I hope and pray 
however that for the future <hi rend="italic">you </hi>will not be tormented by <hi rend="italic">Such friends</hi></p>

<p>Remember me to your <persName>husband </persName>and the <persName>Mr. Perries</persName> and their
<persName>families </persName>and tell my New <persName>Brother in law</persName> that he must write me,
let him inform me what his prospects are there, and I can the
better judge wheither a removal would benefit or injure him and
know better how to advise him</p>

<p>If <persName>Brother Brown</persName> is with you <hi rend="italic">Make </hi>him study Spanish every
day and tell him to be industrious in doing what he can to see
what is the state of the wreck of our property&#8212;I have disposed
of the land I intend[ed] for <persName>aunt Austin's family</persName> as there 
appears no prospect that any of them will come on&#8212;I am still very
poor and live poor&#8212;corn coffee&#8212;corn bread&#8212;milk and Butter and
a Bachelors household, which is confusion, dirt, and torment, are
small items of my living&#8212;your marriage will force either Brother
or me to marry for I must have somebody to keep house. So that
you have made a lucky escape for my house is a thoroughfare for
the whole country&#8212;</p>

<p>I sent in two wagons to meet you at <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, they are on
the way back as I hear from report, empty of course&#8212;it has cost
me a good deal&#8212;What has become of faithful old <persName>Jack</persName>? you
must take care of him in his old age for what he has been&#8212;I am
much more contented and happy since you are married than I was
before the thoughts of your destitute situation sometimes almost
ran me mad, <hi rend="italic">that </hi>trouble is now gone and I have one less than I
had&#8212;I am fast loosing the desire I once had to make a fortune,
which encourages me to hope that I am yet to enjoy much happiness,
for a gready man can never be happy, the loss of a cent makes him
miserable.</p>

<p>forever your always aft.</p>

<p><persName>Stephen</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
