<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0632">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Robert Andrews to Stephen F. Austin, 10-04-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Robert Andrews</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Parras, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 696-697
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-10-04">10-04-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Applying for grant of land on Red River; also for office of surveyor general for Texas. Asks Austin for testimonial to be placed before Congress.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1823-10-04">Oct. 4th 1823</date>   <placeName>Parras</placeName></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Austin</persName></p>

<p>I wrote you by last mail but as you are in the <placeName>settlements </placeName>on 
business of such a nature it is uncertain if you will receive my letter,
for which reason I write you again in order to be more sure of
the receipt.<pb n="697"/></p>

<p>I thot to have been on my way before now for <placeName>Orleans</placeName>, but am
detained by a <persName>Mr. Leporte</persName> who I expect to accompany me, I think
however I shall set out in less than a week from this place, by the
way of <placeName>altamira</placeName>, and as I do not take with me money enough to
purchase medicines and may not fall in with accquaintances from
<placeName>St. Louis</placeName> or <placeName>Missouri</placeName>, I wish you to do me the favor to inform
<placeName>Mr J. H. Hawkins</placeName> of my character to whom I may recur if 
necessary in my dealings-&#8212;I will here communicate you a design as I
always have communicated to you as my most faithful friend in
whose opinion I have the utmost confidence, I am about to make a
formal representation or application to the <persName>Govt</persName>. thro the medium
and friendship of <persName>Doctr. Ramos</persName> who is now a <persName>member of Congress</persName>,
for all the <placeName>Red River country</placeName> including <placeName>Pecon point</placeName> as I presume
it is not yet occupied, also a letter of the right of citizenship and
the appointment of <persName>Surver [Surveyor]</persName> for all <placeName>Texas </placeName>or the 4
<placeName>provinces</placeName> if you please, this however, will never interfere with
your right to survey all your tract, but rather stimulate me to <placeName>Texas</placeName>
sooner when I will take a pleasure in being serviceable to you in
this business&#8212;consulting with a <persName>lawyer</persName>, he tells me it cannot be
convenient to obtain the imploy without a certain document or 
cirtificate of my abilities from a person who may know me to be presented
in the <persName>congress</persName>, which I can alone ask of you as the only one known
in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>who knows my qualifications this I wish you to have the
goodness to remit by the first opportunity to <placeName>Mexico </placeName><persName>Doctr. Ramos</persName>
who will have the care of my business, perhaps it ought to be in
sealed paper, but notwithstanding send it on any. The post is
seting out I cannot say more I live in great hope to see you before
another years Rolls round.</p>

<p>I wish you all success in the world and remain your ever sincire
friend</p>

<p><persName>Andrews    </persName>[Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] Al <persName>Coronel Estevan Austin</persName> en la <placeName>provincia de Texas
Rio Colorado</placeName>.</p>

<p>[On cover:] Tendrá la bondad el <persName>administrador ó </persName>algún otro <persName>amigo</persName>
de mandar esta carta por mano al dueño si este en el <placeName>Rio Colorado</placeName></p>

<p><persName>Roberto Andrews</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
