<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0897">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Gaines to Stephen F. Austin, 11-01-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Gaines</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Sabine, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 932-933
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-11-01">11-01-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Complicated trading.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Sabine </placeName><date when="1824-11-01">Novr 1st 1824</date></p>
<p><persName>Col Stephen F Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir I Regret not being able to move out this <date n="Fall-1824">fall </date>on account
of the unsetled situation of my affairs;</p>

<p>I Beg leave to call your attention to some business of mine in your
<placeName>Colony </placeName>which has transpired since I Left there the Inclosed 
Documents will show the true State of the Case (that is its origin) that
is in my absence in <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821 </date>a man that was doing business for me
Credited <persName>Andrew Roberson</persName> for Groceries Ferriages etc to the amount
of $56, which he was to discharge in a mule, when I Returnd well
knowing <persName>Roberson</persName>s way of swindling and shirking out of paying
his Debts, agreed to swap horses with him to get the Debt, and give
him the Debt to boot which is $56&#8212;agreeable to an Entry made on
the <date when="1824-10-10">10th of October 1821</date> which Book I send you for your information
after we had setled he Told me he was about to start to the <placeName>Brazos</placeName>
and had no amunition to kill meat for his <persName>family </persName>and had no means
of geting any Except I would Credit him I answered I waz Friendly
to that business and would spare him all I had which makes the 
account of $14-25 I se him at <placeName><persName>Inglishe</persName>s</placeName> in the <placeName>Pallo Gouch [Palo
Gaucho]</placeName> <date n="Fall-1824">Last fall </date>he then promised to pay me when I came to the
<placeName>Brazos </placeName>when I went to the <placeName>Brazos </placeName>I Could not find him at home
but met him in Company with <persName>Capt Jones</persName> and others he Told me
<persName>Jackey Hall</persName> was waiting at home to settle with me I Considered
that sufficient and I made no application to him when I went to se
<persName>Mr Hall</persName> To get through with what I thought a bad Business I bought
an old horse of <persName>Hall </persName>and presented <persName>Roberson</persName>s account of $14-25,
which he stated he Recollected, and Took it, in part pay</p>

<p>I will now give you a True Statement of <persName>Col Cole</persName>s Proceedings
with me and on that Case, as I went to <placeName>St. antonio</placeName> I left an 
account on <persName>John Mitchell</persName> of $12 50 for Collection he Collected a
good horse and Lent him to <persName>Mr. Whiteside</persName> when I Returned
he was missing and I Could not get him but he promised to Send
him by the first safe hand I then Left with him for Collection
a note on <persName>Joshua Parker</persName> for a mule and an account on the same
for $125    also a note on <persName>G Alsberry</persName> for $20    Sometime after that<pb n="933"/>
he wrote me that <persName>Roberson </persName>had Denied the account and that Hall
Talkd of attaching But that he had not seen him I conceived
It so unfounded that it would End in Idle Talk</p>

<p>But on the <date when="1824-09-07">7th of September</date> he wrote me that <persName>Hall </persName>had attached
and he had given up <persName>Parker</persName>s note for a mule and his account
for $12-50 to pay the Debt of $14-25,</p>

<p>Now what apears Curious to me <persName>Col Cole</persName> had sold my horse
he Collected of <persName>Mitchell </persName>to <persName>Car </persName>to pay his Own Debt of $25&#8212; If
he Considered <persName>Hall</persName>s Claim good against me for $14-50 why Did he
not pay It out of my money without a Sacrafise or why Did
he not Collect It of <persName>Parker </persName>or <persName>Alsberry</persName>, all of which Claims had
been put in his hands for Collection Long before <persName>Hall</persName>'s against
me, had <persName>Hall</persName>s Claim been a just one I Should Consider It a 
Daring outrage Comited on me, an attachment against an <persName>Inhabitant</persName>
of the <placeName>Province </placeName>and Residing in the Same Place During the Time
of all the Contracts and proceedings, and the <persName>Officer </persName>to hold my
money and supply $52-50 to be Sacrifised for $14-25, and that
apeared of the Basest nature, and may justly be Considered I
am Swindled (If I was to Let It Remain so) out of $66-75 for
Befriending a <persName>villain </persName>with Powder and Lead to Save the Lives
of his <persName>family </persName>to the <placeName>Brazoz</placeName></p>

<p>Your Honer will please Examin the whole Documents and 
Inform me If any Redress may be Expected   I am sir</p>

<p><placeName>Jas Gaines </placeName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Re-Addressed by Austin:] <persName>John P. Coles Esquire</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
