<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0032">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen Austin to James Austin, 09-12-1798</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-21">06-21-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Haven, CT</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 41-43
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1798-09-12">09-12-1798</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Yellow fever epidemic. Purchase of horses, etc.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>New Haven</placeName> <date when="1798-09-12">12th Sept. 1798</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir:</p>

<p>I wrote <persName>Charles </persName>from this Place the Post before the Last 
informing of our arival here with <persName>Mrs Austin</persName> <persName>Nancy </persName>and <persName>Juliana </persName>being
obligd to fly from <placeName>Philada </placeName>again from the fever which now rages in
that Most unfortunate <placeName>City </placeName>with greater violence than it Ever has
done before the City is almost wholly Deserted <persName>40 Thousand of
the Inhabitants</persName> are soposd to have Left it and the Remainder 
Incampd around the City in Tents and Sheads Built to Keep them
from the Weather Although such Number have Left the <placeName>City </placeName>yet
the Daly Cases admitted at the <placeName>City Hospital</placeName> are 90 to 100 and the<pb n="42"/>
Deaths average About 50 a day but what adds to this Misfortune is
that the Fever Rages also at <placeName>New York</placeName> and Near half the people
have also Left that <placeName>City</placeName>&#8212;and at <placeName>New London</placeName> also it is yet worse
the People have all Fled from that Place before which the Deaths
were Greater than in <placeName>Philad </placeName>so that it appears as though this 
<placeName>Country </placeName>is to be ravaged by this Devouring Pestilence&#8212;Two of the <persName>Banks</persName>
have Left <placeName>Philada </placeName>a[nd] gone to<placeName> German Town</placeName> and all the Publick
offices are gone to <placeName>Trenton </placeName>the <persName>Bank of <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName></persName> was Robd
Just before they Left Town of 150 Thousand Dollars in Bank
Notes&#8212; 1000 Dollars is offerd as a Reward to Detect the <persName>Villiens</persName>&#8212;
Indeed Nothing Can equal the Genl. Distress of that <placeName>City </placeName>as to
the <placeName>News Papers</placeName> <persName>Charles </persName>Says you have had None Since I Left you
I sopose the <persName>Printer </persName>is Dead or Fleed I know his Brother <persName>Sam
Smith</persName> is Dead with the Fever three others of the <persName>Printers </persName>are
Stopd they stayd untill the Fever Overtook them&#8212;this unfortunate
Sickness will Prevent my shiping the articles I intended untill I can
Return which I fear will not be untill the <date when="1798-10-31">Last of October</date> when it
will be so Late that I think to Purchase a Waggon and Horses and
Load it with goods and send it on by Land to you I Can Purchase
Good Stout Horses at <placeName>Philad </placeName>when I return Very Low at 50 Dolls a
Head and as good a Horse as <persName>Charles </persName>was at 50 Dollar also and
unless you Can Purchase <persName>Mr Sanders</persName> Waggon and Horses Nearly
at this rate it will not do to Promise Cash Nor Lead which is as
good as Cash&#8212; I should Sopose you may at this Season Imploy
the Waggon about you on Such Terms as to anser as well as to
Send our oan Waggon as to this do the best you Can&#8212; I have
ordered 28 Sacks of a Salt from <persName>Mr Pollard of <placeName>Norfolk </placeName></persName>to be Sent
to <persName>Mr Saml Paine</persName> to be forwarded to <placeName>Lynch bourgh</placeName>&#8212;which is for
you to Put up your Beef and Poark which take good Care to have
well salted&#8212;and get all you Can&#8212;I am Sorry <persName>Charles </persName>has been so
unfortunate as to Loose his horse but this I expected when he told
me he rode him so hard that extreem hot weather I wonder he had
not killd himself and all this for Nothing sopose he had not have
Seen <persName>Thomson</persName>&#8212;No Consequences Sufficient for Such Imprudence
to him Self&#8212;I have here Inclosd you 100 Dollars to help you along&#8212;
and if you find it Necessary you may Draw on Me at 30 Days for
what you may want if this Cant be Done inform me wheather I shall
forward you more money or not&#8212;as in Paying Part Cash and Goods
should Sopose you may Imploy Waggon and I want all the Shot
Rushd on to <placeName>Linchbourgh </placeName>Possible that it may be ready at <placeName>Richmond</placeName>
to Ship before the <placeName>River </placeName>Closes&#8212;and write <persName>Mr Paine</persName> to Keep it not
Sell it as it will bring 250 Dollar pr Ton this <date n="WInter-1798">Winter </date>at <placeName>Philad</placeName>&#8212; all
our <persName>family </persName>Join in Love to <persName>Charles </persName>Self and <persName>Peggy </persName>with yours 
affectionately</p>

<p><persName>S Austin</persName><pb n="43"/></p>

<p>I hope you will have all the <placeName>Fields </placeName>Sowd with Eye as I Proposd and
as to the Clover Seed I shall forward that but if you had it it must
[not] be Sowed untill <date n="04-xx-1799">April Next</date> this I find is the best time when it
must be Bold in which will not hurt the Eye&#8212;</p>

<p>[Addressed:]    <persName>Mr James Austin Post Master</persName> <placeName>Austin Ville Wythe
County Virginia.</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
