<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0345">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Citizens of Jefferson County, 01-10-1820</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-08">07-08-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Citizens of Jefferson County
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Jefferson County</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 352-353
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1820-01-10">01-10-1820</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning attack on his house by the sheriff, George Hammond.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>To the <persName>Citizens of the <placeName>County of Jefferson</placeName></persName></p>

<p>Gentlemen</p>

<p>When the civil rights of a Citizen are invaded, when the sanctuary
of his Dwelling is beset by a <persName>Posse </persName>under the command of a man
clothed with the ensigns of authority. It is taken for granted that
the man has been guilty of some Criminal Offense against the laws
of his Country. Considering myself bound by the strongest ties of
Justice to myself, my <persName>family </persName>and society&#8212;I take the liberty to address
you this letter in Explanation of the assault made on my house this
day by <persName>Geo. Hammond&#8212;Sheriff of your County</persName>, It is not my 
intention to go into a full exposition of this mans conduct but confine
myself to the transactions of this day.</p>

<p>About two O Clock P. M. <persName>Geo Hammond</persName> with a <persName>posse of men</persName>
came to the frunt door of my <placeName>house </placeName>in this place and demanded to
enter the House, his business being asked he said he had a suit
against me wherein <persName>James Rankins</persName>, <persName>John Giger</persName> and <persName>John Findly</persName>
were <persName>Pltf </persName>and myself <persName>Deft </persName>for my donation subscribed to aid in
building your <placeName>courthouse</placeName>. I was given the alternative either to
acknowledge he had legally Served said writ on me some time 
between the <date when="1819-11-15">15</date> and <date when="1819-11-30">last of Nov.</date> and I was also required to agree that
I made this acknowledgment fully and with out restraint, on my
refusal he swore he would force his way into my house by Brakeing
Down my door with an ax which he had then uplifted ready to
execute his denounciation</p>

<p>I resisted his threats until the last extremity when by the 
solicitations of some of the persons present I consented to accept of the
lesser evil to avoid the greater and to agree to any terms or do 
anything he might dictate to me to say, knowing that the loss of life
would be the consequence. If my door was forced, the laws of our
<placeName>Country </placeName>has marked out the duty of her <persName>officers </persName>and at the same time
secured to every Citizen his civil and religious liberties and for a<pb n="353"/>
violation of those rights I hold the <persName>sheriff </persName>and his Securities 
accountable. When our rights are invaded it is of no Consequence to
the Citizen or subject whether it comes by the hand of an Emperor
King or Demon in office under a Republic, they are alike 
distructive of all security to person and property. I do now most solemnly
declair that the acknowledgements I made to <persName>George Hammond </persName>
During the time my house was beset by himself and <persName>posse </persName>were extorted
from me to avoid a violation of my House and for the safety of my
<persName>wife </persName>and <persName>family </persName>and to prevent consequences which would have been
Dreadful in the extreme.</p>

<p>I do also most solemnly declare that the writ which he says he 
executed between the <date when="1819-11-15">15th </date>and <date when="1819-11-30">last of November</date> was never served on me
as stated.</p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p><date when="1820-01-10">Jany-10th, 1820</date></p>

<p>Dear <persName>Emily</persName>&#8212;Copy this and hand a Copy to <persName>Dr Andrews</persName> and lett
any person see it that you think proper I hope <persName>Mr Bryan</persName> will come
and see me as soon as he arrives   Affectionately Your <persName>father</persName></p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mrs James-Bryan</persName> <placeName>Hazel Run</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
