<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0370">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Maria Austin, 01-20-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Maria Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, LA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 373-374
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-01-20">01-20-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Hardships of the family. Business depression in New Orleans. Friendship of Joseph H. Hawkins.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[New Orleans, January 20, 1821.]</p>

<p><persName>Elias Bates</persName> arrived here this day in a Steam Boat from 
<placeName>Alexandria </placeName>; he went as far as the <placeName>Sabine </placeName>and heard that <persName>Father </persName>had arrived
at <placeName>St Antonio </placeName>and was to be back at <placeName>Natchitoches </placeName>by the <date when="1820-02-15">15th of
February</date>; he was well. I know nothing as to my <persName>father</persName>'s objects or
prospects. <persName>Elias </persName>will remain in the country until my <persName>father </persName>returns.
As to <persName>Bryan </persName>and <persName>Sister </persName>my heart bleeds for their troubles&#8212;if I
can be of any servise to you or them let me know it, and I will go
home; I will do anything that is right. My reputation is <hi rend="italic">all </hi>I have
on earth, if <hi rend="italic">that </hi>is destroyed I can be of no use to you or any one
else, and there will no longer [be] a necessity of my remaining either
in this <placeName>Country </placeName>or any other.</p>

<p>I came here with a hope of getting employ; I offered to hire myself
out as <persName>clerk</persName>, as an <persName>overseer</persName>, or anything else, but business is too dull
here to get into business. There are hundreds of young men who are
glad to work for their board. I met with <persName>Kenner</persName>; he <hi rend="italic">said </hi>he would
befriend me, but I have not seen him since. In this state of things it
was my good fortune to get acquainted with <persName>Joseph H. Hawkins Esqr</persName>.
(formerly of <placeName>Lexington Kentucky</placeName>) who gave me employ in an <placeName>office</placeName>.
He is a man who in every respect is an honor, and an ornament to the
human race. He has kindly advanced me money enough to purchase
a few groceries for you and <persName>sister</persName>, which I have shipped on board
the Velocipede <persName>Capt. Beckwith</persName>; enclosed is a Bill of lading; and I
will send $10 in a letter by the boat toward paying the freight; this
is all I can do now&#8212;when I earn some more I will send another
supply and will try to keep you and <persName>Bryan's family</persName> supplied with
sugar and Coffee at least.<pb n="374"/></p>

<p><persName>Mr. Hawkins</persName> is a <persName>lawyer </persName>of the [highest] standing in this place-
he is not rich&#8212;but he has a most generous heart&#8212;he has made me
this offer&#8212;if I will remain with him he will board me, permit me the
use of his books, and money for clothes, give me all the instruction in
his power until I am well fitted to commence the practice of law
in this <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;for my board and the use of his books he will charge
<hi rend="italic">nothing</hi>, and for the money he advances he will wait until I make
enough by my profession to repay him; an offer so generous and
from a man who two months ago was a stranger to me, has almost
made me change my opinion of the human race. There are however
two obstacles in the way; one is that I shall earn nothing to help you
with, for at least 18 months; another is that perhaps those I owe in
<placeName>Missouri </placeName>may prosecute here; it will do them no good I have
nothing&#8212;all the property I had in <placeName>Arkansas</placeName>, I gave to <persName>Father</persName>. If I
am left alone a few years I may get up and pay all off; it will take
me 18 months to become acquainted with civil law which is in force
in this country and learn the French language-&#8212;that once done I
then shall have the means of fortune within my reach. I am 
determined to accept of <persName>Hawkins </persName>offer.</p>

<p>I have been engaged in aiding to edit a <placeName>newspaper</placeName>, the <placeName>"Louisiana
Advertiser "</placeName> I have sent some numbers to <persName>Post Master <placeName>Herculaneum</placeName>
</persName>which you now doubt can get</p>

<p>Your <persName>Son</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
