<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0443">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James C. Shields to Stephen F. Austin, 12-09-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James C. Shields</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Lexington, KY</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">New Orleans, LA</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 443-444
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-12-09">12-09-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Hard times. Terms of settlement in Texas.   His mechanical ability.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Lexington </placeName><date when="1821-12-09">December 9th 1821</date></p>

<p><persName>Mr Stephen F Austin</persName> Dear sir after my compliments to you I take
the liberty of writing you a few lines to git you to give me a corect
statement of the <placeName>texes </placeName>or that part of the Country that you have
large posesions in the peeple in this part of the country have various
oppinions respecting the inducement that is held out to <persName>mecanicks</persName>
that would migrate to <placeName>that part of the Country</placeName> some say there is no
compultion on your giving them any thing only what they will pay
for your letter in the paper says there will be <placeName>grants of land </placeName>
appropriated to <persName>farmers </persName>and <persName>mecanicks </persName>it does not mention that it would
be at your option whether you give any thing or not I know of
<persName>mecanicks </persName>that would go if i was to go but as the paper states the[y]
would not be there in time to make a crop <date n="Summer-1821">next summer</date> then they
might be cut short of any thing  this place is very dull no incourage-<pb n="444"/>
ment for <persName>mecanicks </persName>I have been for a long time dissatisfide with
the place I have often been sorry that I dident take your <persName>father</persName>s
advice and go back to <placeName>herculanenm </placeName>he frequently wrote for me to
come back but I was ingaged in making machinery and could not
come at the time&#8212;as you are going to reside permanently in that
part of the Country I would like very much to move there and spend
the balance of my days you will please to write me imediately on
the receipt of this give me the perticulars of the country write
me what acknowledgment you will make me and my <persName>family </persName>to come
on as soon as i can my <persName>family </persName>is small there is none but my <persName>wife </persName>and
myself I have frequently been gocking her about going she says
she wont go but she knows better if i say go the worst of all is i am
in low circumstances to take a journy of that length if my business
was setled so that I could come on I would need some little assistance
to inable me to git on as to my caracture you are aquainted with me
since I returned to <placeName>lexington </placeName>this eight years I am well known by
the first caractures in the place&#8212;us respects being usefull to the
settlement as a <persName>mecanick </persName>I can make any of the farming utentials
and a house to live in and furniture I have worked a grate deal in
the <placeName>steem and watter mills</placeName> in this place I have made stove paternes
for the furnace and all the mouls for the <placeName>paper factory</placeName> machinery of
all kinds&#8212;you will please to write me imediately on the receipt of
this say what incouragement you think i would meet with or what
you think you would be willing to do for me    nothing more at
Present                                                                   <p><persName>James 0. Shields</persName></p></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr Stephen F. Austin</persName> <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></p>
<p>if <persName>austin </persName>is not there the <persName>post master</persName> will forward this to him at the
<placeName>texis</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
