<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0147">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Frederick Bates, xx-27-1808</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-28">06-28-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Frederick Bates
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Burton Mine, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 151-152
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1808">xx-27-1808</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-28" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asking justice for Mathews and Hart. Confidence in the Government of the United States. Opposing appointment of John Smith T to the bench.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            



<p><placeName>Mine a Burton</placeName><date n="xx-27-1808"> 27th 1808.</date></p>
<p><persName>Frederick Bates Esq</persName>.</p>
<p>D Sr</p>

<p><persName>Colo. Mathews</persName> having determined to visit <placeName>Saint Louis</placeName>, 
affords an opportunity for me to tender my congratulations on the safe
arrival of <persName>Gov. Lewis</persName> in this <placeName>territory</placeName>, believing as I do that his 
arrival will be to you no small gratification, in as much, as you will be
releaved from much of the responsibility heretofore attached to your
office. <persName>Colo Mathews</persName> deeply feels the outrages lately committed on
his property and the insults offered his person, and depends much
on you to see him remunerated for his losses. I have expressed to
Messrs. <persName>Mathews</persName> and <persName>Hart </persName>my belief that they would find in you
a firm advocate, and that <persName>Gov. Lewis</persName> would doubtless take prompt
and efficient measure to attain them redress, I cannnot but express
my hope that our <persName>Gov.</persName> will deliberately investigate the wrongs they
have suffered from the <persName>agents of Smith and Brown</persName>, and cause
restitution to be made them, suffer me also to add that no act of
violence within my knowledge equals the one committed on those<pb n="152"/>
gentlemen, as well as on the authority of the <placeName>U. States</placeName>, such outrages
unnoticed has created the most sovereign contempt for the constituted
authorities, and imbolden the perpetrators of repine and discord to
continue these outrages. I trust I shall be excused for expressing
my solicitude on this occasion as Messrs. <persName>Mathews</persName> and <persName>Hart </persName>leased
lands of the <placeName>U States</placeName> by my advice, and in consequence I consider
myself in some measure instrumental in placing them in the situation
in which they now stand, I have always expressd my confidence in
the Justice of the <persName>General Government</persName>, also my firm belief that <persName>Gov.
Lewis</persName> and yourself would shield them from the daring attempts of
<persName>Smith </persName>and <persName>Brown</persName>, nor can I yet believe I shall find myself 
disappointed in my expectations of the just intentions of the <persName>Executive of
this <placeName>Territory</placeName></persName>, you are fully apprized of my determination 
(heretofore made known to you) not to interpose in any wise as to 
appointments that might be contemplated for this district, either civil
or military, yet such is, my extreme concern on seeing the bold 
attempts to again introduce <persName>John Smith T.</persName> into office that I cannot
remain silent, it appears to be a principle adopted by the <persName>General
Government </persName>that all persons who have in any manner associated
with <persName>Aaron Burr</persName>, ought to be divested of all authority, nor trusted
with confidential offices under the Government, that <persName>John Smith T.</persName>
did actually enter into the views of <persName>Burr</persName>, (in my opinion) may be
established by concurring testimony sufficiently strong to convince
every man in this district friendly disposed towards the <placeName>U. States</placeName> of
the impropriety of his holding an office under the Government, the
advocates of <persName>Smith </persName>have a double object in view, by reinstating him
in office, they expect by so doing to fix a stigma on the <persName>Secretary of
the <placeName>Territory</placeName></persName>, and prove to the World that his removal from office
arose from personal motives and not from any improper acts of his,
they also expect to regain a complete ascendency over this District,
and create a breach between the <persName>Gov</persName>. and <persName>Secretary </persName>which, is said
and impressed on the minds of the people has already taken place,
and that <persName>Gov. Lewis</persName> has expressed his dissatisfaction of the 
<persName>secretary</persName>'s conduct&#8212;thus you see the engines of discord are in motion
to influence the people against every man that has dared to act in
contradiction to the will of the <persName>Ex Secretary</persName> and his friend <persName>Smith</persName>.
I cannot but feel deeply impressed with the importance of the present
question, whether <persName>John Smith T.</persName> shall be reinstated or not, a 
question of no small consequence in my estimation, my confidence in the
correct views of <persName>Gov. Lewis</persName> are such that until I am convinced by
seeing <persName>Smith </persName>clothed with the ensigns of his office, I will not believe
him reinstated in the-confidence of the <persName>Governor</persName>, altho proclaimed by
a thousand tongues.</p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
