<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0286">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Joshua Pilcher, 05-13-1817</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-02">07-02-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Joshua Pilcher
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">St Louis, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">St Louis, MO</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 306-316
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Report on Quarrel</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1817-05-13">05-13-1817</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-02" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Quarrel between Stephen F. Austin and Joshua Pilcher&#8212;Biographical: (1) Pilcher to Austin, May 13-14, 1817. (2) Austin to Pilcher, May 14, 1817. (3) Masonic committee to Austin, May 16, 1817. (4) Resolution of Masonic lodge, May 31, 1817. (5) Austin challenges Pilcher to a duel, June 1, 1817. (6) Austin's statement of the history of the misunderstanding. (7) Report of committee of arbitration, ruling that Pilcher should apologize, June 7, 1817. (8) Pileher's apology, June 7, 1817.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p>1.  <persName>PILCHER </persName>TO <persName>AUSTIN</persName></p>

<p><placeName>St Louis</placeName> <date when="1817-05-13">13 May 1817</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr. Stephen F Austin</persName></p>

<p>Sir This evening you called on me and remarked that you thought
you had perceived a coolness in my conduct towards You during
Your present visit to <placeName>St Louis</placeName>; at the same time observing that if
your impression was correct, You ware intirely unable to account
for it. I informed you that I was not disposed to enter into verbal
explanations of my conduct; but as you have taken the liberty of
introducing the subject I consider it my right to and perhaps my
duty to renew it, which I will do in a manner not to bee forgotten,
though it should leave you as much in the dark with respect to the
cause as you professed to bee this evening. You sem'd to think it
your duty to make those inqueries in consequence of *******
[sic] a dutiful young man indeed! it is a pity you had not have
reflected on these duties at an earlier period, among other 
conjectures too insignificant to mention, you concluded by observing that
you ware bound to infer that my conduct grew out of a suspicious
disposition but could not imagine of what I suspected you&#8212; Strange
indeede, that you should suppose I suspected you of something and
you not able to say what.&#8212; I immagine I understood you, but you
being either afraid to insinuate the meaning or ashamed to expose
your own vanity could not tell, but be ashur'd Sir you ware 
mistaken. I never permit suspicions to govern me in my conduct I
am always governed by existing facts,&#8212;so this conclusion is false
but being the production of your own fertile immagination will no
doubt be receiv'd and given as matter of fact as other conjetures
have been with which your brain seems always pregnat&#8212;</p>

<p>Had you have possessd comn sagacity you might have made this
wonderful discovery some months ago but finding that you either
would not or could not understand, and finding the necessaty of such
a couse still increasing and that nothing but down right contempt
would make You understand, I was redusd to the necessaty of 
adopting a course of conduct even in my own room which I should never
do unless it was under the like imperious circumstances</p>

<p><date when="1817-05-14">May 14th</date></p>

<p>To enter into such an explanation as you would require would
not only bee attended with difficulty but necessarily involve 
unpleasant circumstances and the names of individuals for whom I
entertain too high an opinion and for whose feeling I have too much it<pb n="307"/>
respect ever to permit them to escape either my lips or pen on an
occasion like this, by way of explanation however I would 
remark that there are two classes of men in the world who in my
opinion are equally contemptable.&#8212; The deceitful treacherous 
fauning sycophant who by ambiguous insinuations will, under the sacred
name of friendship wound the feelings of others choseing such time
piase and circumstance as to piase it out of the power of the person
injured to treat such conduct as it merits; and the officious news
gatherer who goes about collecting trash and construes the idle and
loose remarks of others into mighty things and gives his own foolish
conjectures as facts those two characters combined become still more
odious and I never can reconcile to my feelings to recognise them
as friends</p>

<p><persName>Joshua Pilcher</persName></p>

<p>I have taken the liberty of delivering this in person</p>

<p><persName>AUSTIN </persName>TO <persName>PILCHER</persName></p>

<p><placeName>St Louis</placeName> <date when="1817-05-14">May 14 1817</date>&#8212;</p>
<p>Sir</p>

<p>Dureing my present visit to this place I observed a coolness in you
towards me and being fully under the conviction that I had 
intentionally done nothing either directly or indirectly to injure you or
wound your feelings, I noticed this singular Change in your 
deportment with real astonishment expecting however that you would
persue that course toward me which a Man of honor and of Sperit
never hesitates about adopting when he finds or conceives himself
injured by another, I waited patiently untill <date when="1817-05-13">last evening</date>, expecting
to be call'd on to answer for those injuries your deportment told me
you conceived I had done you, I waited in vain&#8212;you remained
Silent&#8212;and intending to leave Town this day I called on you Myself
for an explination of your conduct, not doubting, but that I should
have recd one, and not doubting but that, that full explination would
have enabled me to convince you that I did not merit the treatment I
had received and that the cause of your singular deportment might
be very readily traced to the false representations of some
meddling busybody; or to the misconception of some innocent
and inadvertant act or expression of mine, which was never
intended to wound the feelings or injure the reputation or
views of any person liveing, much less <hi rend="italic">one </hi>who I <hi rend="italic">once </hi>considered
a man of principle and consistancy and who I <hi rend="italic">once </hi>esteemed
as a <persName>friend</persName>. I consider it one of the first duties of a Gentleman
to render reparation where it is due and there are *<hi rend="italic"> certain
other   duties</hi>   [Austin   inserts   the   marginal   note   "Masonic"]<pb n="308"/>
which sometimes exist between men and which to me I hope will
always be <hi rend="italic">Sacred </hi>however lightly and contemptuously they May be
<hi rend="italic">treated </hi>by others, and in order to do <hi rend="italic">my </hi>utmost in the discharge of
these duties I was induced to call on you to State to me <hi rend="italic">when </hi>and
how, I had injured you, that I might make reparation if bound as
a man of honor to do so, or that an explination of your conduct-
might the better enable me to regulate my future deportment 
toward you, I applied to you Sir with <hi rend="italic">these </hi>motives, <hi rend="italic">with these views,
</hi>and in the true Sperit of conciliation, and what was my answer?
that you had no verbal explanation to make which at that time I took
for a total denyal to make any explination at all. The first 
impression which this declaration made upon my mind was <hi rend="italic">Surprise</hi>
that you Should treat me with coolness bordering on contempt.
And when called on be either <hi rend="italic">afraid </hi>or unable to assign the cause,
was certainly a matter of astonishment, this impression of surprise
however was soon displaced by <hi rend="italic">another </hi>which must naturally have
arisen in the breast of every Man of Correct principle under similar
circumstances, the impression I allude to is <hi rend="italic">Contempt</hi>, the answer
that you had no verbal explination to make at once convinced me
that you either had no just and substantial cause for your conduct,
and was therefore ashamed to assign the rediculous trifles which
your suspicious imagination had Magnified into injuries&#8212;or that
your cowardly soul shrunk from taxing a Man to his face with acts
which you knew he never performed, with intentions which you
knew he never possessed&#8212;it was with regret I turned with scorn
from a Man who I once esteemed, and who but a few moments before
I conceived to be consistent and honorable, as I left you, you told me
I should hear from you again before I left Town. I received this
intelligence with real pleasure hopeing that in a written 
communication, I should receive a full and complete development of the
affair, not doubting as I before observed but that an amicable 
understanding must have accrued therefrom&#8212;therefore when you handed
me your letter <date when="1817-05-14">this Morning</date>, viewing it as a harbinger of peace, I
received it with joy, the impression of contempt which your first
answer had forced upon my mind was Momentarily Suspended and
I now hoped to find you that candid man of honor I had 
heretofore believed you to be, but however My pleasing anticipations, my
hopes and my wishes disappointed and disapated, and with what 
renewed force did the Suspended Impression of contempt fall upon
my Mind, on pexuseing your letter, have you given Me the 
explination I asked for ? have you given me the least clue which will lead
to Solution of the Mistery and to a discovery of the injuries I have
done you? No sir, you have said nothing pointed, all is 
ambiguous, inconsistent, and unintelligable, and I am now compeled to<pb n="309"/>
remain under the conviction that the injuries I have done you Knew
no other existence than in your own fever'd and distempered brain,
and that either wanting sufficient common sence to discriminate 
between a fiction and a reality, or possessing one of those Mean 
dispositions which Suspecting every thing that is and thousand of
things that are <hi rend="italic">not </hi>gives importance and magnitude to every 
frivolous and unmeaning act or expression and converts them into an
injury or an insult. You have fixed your jealous Suspicions on
Some inadvertant Expression Some unmeaning act of Mine which
you have revolved in your disordered brain untill it has swelled to
the immense magnitude of a <hi rend="italic">deadly injury</hi> a vital stab in your 
reputation, your prospects or whatever rediculous bubble your 
imagination may have been blowing up. Your letter is too pitifully 
prevaricating to merit an answer in detail, I will however give it one
in part. You say it is a pity I had not reflected on those duties at
an earlier period, this observation merits no answer, and certainly
can have no application to me untill I am Shewn that I have
neglected or violated them and I defy <hi rend="italic">you </hi>before the eternal God to
State an instance where I have violated them with you, you say I
was " either afraid to insinuate my meaning, or ashamed to own my
vanity " let me caution you Sir to beware of cherishing the idea that
<hi rend="italic">fear </hi>ever has, or ever will deter me from utering my sentiments
freely and openly <hi rend="italic">to you</hi> and to the world&#8212;and it may be discovered
that I have spirit enough to resent contemptable and unwarranted
insinuations, and to chastise impertinance as it Merits&#8212;As to what
you say about vanity I see no application it can have to the subject
at all and Suppose you must have put it in to fill up the sentence
or because your imagination not being as fruitful as usual&#8212;could
furnish you with nothing else You say that you are not governed
by <hi rend="italic">Suspicions </hi>that you are governed by <hi rend="italic">facts </hi>I have demanded of
you Sir what are <hi rend="italic">those facts</hi> and received an evaseive, equivocating
answer which a Gentleman would feel himself <hi rend="italic">disgraced </hi>in giveing,
but you repeat that you are governed by facts and I again reiterate
the demand <hi rend="italic">What are those facts?</hi> You Say that " I might have
discovered your coolness Some Months ago if I had possessd common
understanding ["] I am now Sencible that I did perceive a 
coolness in your address to me when I was at Herculanium and felt a
little piqued at it but being equally conscious at that time as I now
am, that I had intentionally done nothing to offend you I took no
further notice of it and soon totally forgot it&#8212; Under date of <date when="1817-05-14">May
14th</date> you Say that "you cannot enter into the explination you 
require without mentioning the names of those you respect etc. ["] I
know not who you allude to, but as you have left me entirely to 
conjecture I have been induced by a great variety of circumstances to<pb n="310"/>
Suspect who you mean and here I will remark that if I am correct
in my conjecture and if you intend to insinuate that I have ever
directly or indirectly or in any manner whatever intentionally
treated these persons with the least disrespect or impropriety. You
insinuate what is false, you have discribed two characters in the last
clause of your letter which you Say you can not recognise <hi rend="italic">as friends</hi>
and which I suppose I am to conclude you apply to me, but which
I think do not at all Suit me I do not merit Such a <hi rend="italic">portrait </hi>and
you seem indirectly to insinuate that I " have willfully tried to hurt
your feelings chooseing such time, place, and circumstances as put
it out of your power to treat Such conduct as it merits "&#8212;</p>

<p>Sir I can think of <hi rend="italic">no time, no place, no circumstances,</hi> when a 
person could wantonly and openly wound my feelings without having
it [in] my power either <hi rend="italic">instania </hi>or in a very Short time afterwards
to resent Such treatment as it merits, but you poor pitiful good
natured creature, <hi rend="italic">you </hi>could have your feelings wounded, and Suffer
the Sacred name of friendship to be basely prostituted as a cover from
behind which you could be assailed in the Most vulnerable part, <hi rend="italic">you</hi>
could suffer <hi rend="italic">all </hi>this to be done by me as you insinuate and find no time,
no place to punish it no way to resent it but by Sullenness for I know
not what more deserving name to give it. Since when called on to
State what ails you, like a Sullen child you answer not but continue
to <hi rend="italic">pout </hi>and doubtless the Same remedy applied to Sullen children
would be of equal service to you, the other character you have drawn
is that of a <hi rend="italic">tattler </hi>a <hi rend="italic">talebearer </hi>and if you intend to apply this [to] me,
every person who knows me, all who have known me from infancy
will at once give the lie to Such a charge. I will now Sir Most 
pointedly, observe, that if you intend to insinuate (for your letter is such
a type of ambiguity and inconsistancy that I [hardly] know what
you intend) if however you intend to insinuate that I have under the
cover of Friendship Secretly or in any other way intentionally 
injured you I pronounce Such an insinuation <hi rend="italic">false </hi>and the person who
makes it a <hi rend="italic">Liar</hi>, and further if you intend to insinuate that I have been
or am a tattler a talebearer Magnifying trifles into Mighty things
with an evil intent, giveing my own foolish conjectures as facts and
attempting to injure others by dark and ambiguous insinuations I also
pronounce <hi rend="italic">Such </hi>an insinuation <hi rend="italic">false </hi>and the person who makes it a
<hi rend="italic">liar</hi>.</p>

<p>I shall now close this communication, probably the last one which
will ever pass between us, by reiterating the assertion which I 
repeated to you verbally that I am unconscious of ever haveing at any
time, in any place or under any circumstances injured you or wounded
your feelings or even harboured the Most distant the least Shadow of
an intention to do so in my life, Actuated by a Sence of my duty to-<pb n="311"/>
ward you as a <persName>Mason</persName>, as one who once esteemed you, as a Man of
honor who was ready to make reparation where it was due I called on
you for an explination of your conduct, your answer has erased every
vestage of the esteem the respect I once felt for you and left me with
no other impression towards you but contemft, a contempt which
can only be removed by an elucidation of the Misteries which now
envelope you and an explination of the absurdities and inconsistencies
of your conduct, at the same time repeating what I have here [to] fore
said that when I am made sencible thai I have injured you, I shall
always be ready to give any explination or satisfaction a Gentleman
ought to give&#8212;</p>

<p>I want no more communications from you unless they explain your
conduct</p>

<p><persName>J. Pilcher</persName>                                                        <persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>3.  <persName>MASONIC COMMITTEE</persName> TO  <persName>AUSTIN</persName></p>

<p><placeName>Saint Loues</placeName> May 16th 1817</p>
<p>Having perus'd  the  communications  between Mr Pilcher  and
Mr Austin, We <hi rend="italic">must request</hi> that those Gentlemen will suspend all
further proceedings for, at least, four or five days&#8212;
They will please say whether this request will be complied with&#8212;
With esteem</p>

<p>T Douglass</p>
<p>Jerh Connor</p>
<p>Stephen Rector</p>
<p>[Addressed:] Mr Stephen F Austin Present</p>

<p>4. RESOLUTION OF MASONIC LODGE</p>

<p>Resolved, Mem. [sic] Con, That as the efforts of a <persName>volunteer 
committee of this Lodge</persName>, as also of a <persName>Committee </persName>appointed at a special 
meeting called for the express purpose have proved ineffectual towards
settling the unfortunate misunderstanding between Brothers <persName>Pilcher</persName>
and <persName>Austin</persName>, that the <persName>Worshipfull Master</persName> be authorised to appoint a
<persName>Committee of three Masters Masons</persName> to watch the Hostile movements
of said <persName>Brothers </persName>against each other. And in case they will not
agree to submit said misunderstanding to this <placeName>Lodge </placeName>the Committee
so named be authoris'd and commanded to call the <persName>officers of Justice
</persName>to their aid to arrest an act which this <placeName>Lodge </placeName>fears they 
contemplate, equally abhorrent to Religious Masony and Law&#8212;<placeName>Missouri
Lodge</placeName> <placeName>St Louis</placeName> <date when="1817-05-31">May 31. 1817</date></p>

<p>by order of the <placeName>lodge</placeName></p>

<p><persName>J. G. Brady W M P. T </persName>   [Rubric]<pb n="312"/></p>

<p>5.  CHALLENGE TO  A DUEL</p>

<p><placeName>St. Louis</placeName> <date when="1817-06-01">June 1th 1817</date></p>
<p>Sir,</p>

<p>You have wantonly and without provocation insulted me, and
injured my person, I demand of you that Satisfaction which is due
to the outraged honor of a Gentleman</p>

<p>My friend<persName> Doctor Farrar </persName>will point out to you the mode and
manner by which you are to make reparation</p>
<p>Yours</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>
<p><persName>Mr. Joshua Pilcher</persName></p>

<p>6.<persName> Austin</persName>'s statement of the cause of the dispute</p>

<p>[June 1, 1817?]</p>

<p>for Some time past I observed a coolness in <persName>Mr. Pilche</persName>[r]s 
deportment toward me, which I noticed with the utmost astonishment being
perfectly unconscious of ever having, even in thought, injured him
in my life. I waited untill the <date when="1817-05-13">13th May</date> for him to call on me for
a redress of these greivences he thought I had done him, but finding
that he would say nothing but continued his coolness I thought it
my duty to call on him for a candid declaration of the causes of his
conduct. I deemed my duty to do so in consequence of our being
<hi rend="italic"><persName>Masons </persName></hi>amongst whom the utmost candour and frankness aught
always to exist, another reason which induced me to call on him was
that I feared if an open rupture took place between us, it might be 
attributed by the world to a young <persName>Lady </persName>whose feelings of course
would have been mortified thereby I therefore called on him for an
explination of his conduct his Letter to me and my reply contain
the Substance of what passed verbally between us. He gave me no
Satisfaction as to the cause, either verbally or in his letter he gave
me his Letter on the morning of the <date when="1817-05-14">14th May </date>and he recd mine in
<date when="1817-05-14">evening of the Same day</date> the <date when="1817-05-15">next morning</date> as I was walking down
Street with <persName>Mr. Wash</persName>, <persName>Pilcher </persName>came up behind me and without 
giving the least notice or warning of his intention Struck me before I
saw him and injured my eye so that I was deprived of the use of it
for more than ten days&#8212;I wished to demand satisfaction of him
<hi rend="italic">immediately</hi>, but my <persName>Friends </persName>would not permit me to do so untill my
eye was recovered, and on the <date when="1817-05-16">16th</date> <persName>Mr J Connor</persName> call'd on me and
requested that I would submit the subject of dispute to <persName>T. Douglass</persName>,
<persName>S Rector</persName> and himself&#8212;I freely submitted every thing I knew of the
business&#8212;and gave them the Letters which had passed on the <date when="1817-05-17">17th-</date>
I recd. a note from the above gentlemen requesting me to suspend all
further proceedings for 5 days&#8212;I answered that my eye was in such<pb n="313"/>
a state that I should be compelled to suspend proceeding untill my
recovery&#8212;from Those <persName>Gentlemen </persName>I have never heard more on the
subject and know not what they [have] done or attempted to do&#8212;
on my arrival in <placeName>St Louis</placeName> on the <date when="1817-05-30">30th May</date> I was called on by <persName>Mr
Kennerly</persName> and <persName>Hanly </persName>a <persName>Committee </persName>appointed by the <placeName>Lodge </placeName>to 
investigate the cause of the differance. I gave them at once all the 
information on the subject in my power and they professed to be much 
gratified at the promptness with which I complied with the request of
the <placeName>Lodge </placeName>made through them, they then informed me that they
would call on <persName>Pilcher </persName>for an explanation of the causes of his conduct-
they did so and he refused to give them, on the <date when="1817-05-31">31 May</date> in the 
morning I sent <persName>Pilcher </persName>a note by <persName>Doctor farrar</persName>, and soon after recd. an
order from the <placeName>Lodge </placeName>to attend at the <placeName>Lodge </placeName>room at 3 o clk of <date when="1817-05-31">that
day</date> I accordingly obeyed the order and attended. I was called on
to state what I knew of the cause of&#8212;dispute, and answered that I
knew not the cause of <persName>Pilcher</persName>'s conduct and assured the <placeName>lodge </placeName>that
I was unconscious of ever haveing done or said anything in my life
to wound feelings of <persName>Mr. Pilcher</persName> <persName>Mr. Douglass</persName> then rose as the
<persName>representative </persName>of his friend <persName>Pilcher </persName>who refused to attend and stated
that the ground work of his offence was this&#8212;that <persName>Pilcher </persName>had 
communicated to me in <persName>Masonic </persName>confidence the particulars of an affair he
had in <placeName>Tennessee </placeName>with a <persName>girl</persName>, and that one evening in a large 
company <persName>Pilcher </persName>and myself were joking each other and I asked him if
he had lost his heart, he answered no he had it safe and I then
answerd <hi rend="italic">yes </hi>I presume it is secure as it has gone through the <hi rend="italic">wars</hi>
in <placeName>Nashville</placeName>&#8212;this he said was the first cause of offence the cause he
said was of a nature which he could not mention without introducing
names which delicacy forbid thereby alluding as I conceive to
<persName>females</persName>&#8212;<persName>John W. Honey</persName> informed me that the first cause of offence
was this, that <persName>Pilcher </persName>presented <persName>Miss F_________</persName> with a Ticket for the
play and walked with her to the <placeName>Theatre</placeName>, when the play broke up
he says, that I took hold of <persName>Miss F_____</persName>'s arm and walked <placeName>home </placeName>with
her and he conceived it to be <hi rend="italic">his right</hi> to walk <placeName>home </placeName>with [her] since
he had walked there with her. <persName>Honey </persName>says that he knows this was
the <hi rend="italic">first cause</hi> of offence</p>

<p><persName>Pilcher </persName>has absolved me from all restrictions as to what he 
communicated in confidence I shall therefore state what it was he 
informed me that he had been engaged to a <persName>Girl in <placeName>Nashville</placeName></persName> but did
not return at the time appointed and therefore the match was
broken off&#8212;he did not state the name of the <persName>Girl </persName>or any other 
particulars and I had heard the same thing before in substance from
various sources before he told it to me, but after he told me [the]
circumstances I never communicated to any living soul in the
world and I defy him to prove that I ever did&#8212;I must infer that<pb n="314"/>
he has recd. his intelligence from <persName>FEMALES</persName>, the only <persName>females </persName>with
whom he was known to be in the habits of intimacy have declared
most solemnly that they never heard me say any thing at all relative
to <persName>Pilcher </persName>and that they never communicated anything to him
the <persName>females </persName>I allude to are <persName>Mrs E____ </persName> <persName>Mrs C. </persName>and <persName>Miss F____</persName>.</p>

<p>Sometime <date n="Winter - 1816">last winter</date> <persName>Pilcher </persName>observed that he expected I 
intended to court <persName>Miss F. </persName>I assured him on my honor that I did not
and some time after-wards he repeated the same thing and I again
assured him that I did not and asked him if [he] had any Such
<hi rend="italic">intentions</hi>&#8212;he [said] <hi rend="italic">no </hi>I have not&#8212;</p>

<p>My belief as to the cause of <persName>Pilcher </persName>conduct is <hi rend="italic">this</hi>&#8212;I think that
he suspected that I was courting <persName>Miss F.</persName> and therefore had 
deceived him in saying that [I] was not&#8212;and I think that he then 
became jealous and suspected that I had used some unfair means to 
supplant him with <persName>Miss F&#8212;&#8212;</persName> gealousy I believe is the sole and only
cause, and that the most unfounded for I never in my life had any
designs of courting the <persName>Girl </persName>he was then addressing, nor did I ever
in my life give her or any of her <persName>friends </persName>the least reason to suppose
that I intended to address her. And were they the last words I ever
expected to utter in the world I would say that I never did in any
manner, at any time, nor under any circumstances say or do 
anything to injure that man or to wound his feelings&#8212;</p>

<p>as to what the <placeName>Lodge </placeName>have done I consider their conduct to be
every thing but what <persName>Masonic </persName>duties inculcate, they have accused
me of refusing to submit the cause of dispute to them which is
absolutely <hi rend="italic">false</hi>. I did submit to their <persName>committee </persName>and in open <placeName>lodge</placeName>
<hi rend="italic">all </hi>and <hi rend="italic">everything </hi>I knew on the subject their conduct merits the
severest investigation and I require and injoin it on my <persName>friends </persName>that
the[y] Make a full statement of this transaction and send it to the
<placeName>Grand lodge</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>7.   REPORT OF COMMITTEE OF ARBITRATION</p>

<p><placeName>Saint Louis</placeName> <date when="1817-06-17">June 7th 1817</date></p>
<p>The undersigned to whom has been refer'd the matters of difference
between <persName>Mr Austin</persName> and <persName>Mr Pilcher</persName> having heard from <persName>Mr P </persName>the
causes why he had adopted that distant reserve and coolness of 
manner towards <persName>Mr A.</persName> "viz ". An impression that <persName>Mr A.</persName> had violated
the confidence which he had repos'd in him; And that he was under
the impression that <persName>Mr A.</persName> was aware of the cause, even at the time
he ask'd for explanations, that with such impressions, he consider'd
<persName>Mr A</persName>'s. demand for an explanation as adding to the injury 
particularly as that injury had not been complain'd of. he (<persName>Mr P</persName>) 
refus'd to give any, that during the conversation between <persName>Mr Austin</persName>
and himself he observed to <persName>Mr A.</persName> " that he had on a certain occasion<pb n="315"/>
acted officously and treacherously" Towards him and to <persName>Mr A</persName>'s
question of " how when and where " he replied " that he could not 
enter into verbal explanations" That his letter of the <date when="1817-05-13">13th</date> and <date when="1817-05-14">14th
May</date> was elicited by an observation of <persName>Mr Austin</persName>'s made at the
moment of separating in which was infer'd the probable cause of <persName>Mr.
P</persName>'s, coolness and the source from whence it originated but which
inference was incorrect, and being still under the impression that
he (<persName>Mr A</persName>) was well aware of the true cause, he (<persName>Mr P</persName>) addressed to
him the letter of the <date when="1817-05-13">13th</date> and <date when="1817-05-14">14th May</date> to which <persName>Mr A</persName> replied by
letter of the latter date, repeating his demand for explanations, and
clos'd by declining any further communications, unless his demands
were complied with <persName>Mr Pilcher</persName> still retaining the same impressions,
that <persName>Mr A</persName> was perfectly conscious of the circumstances which gave
rise to the coolness on his part, yet would not recognize those 
circumstances, but continued to press his demand. As also from the
tone of <persName>Mr A</persName>'s letter conceived that no other course was left him to
persue than that which he adopted.&#8212;</p>

<p>On the other part <persName>Mr Austin</persName> assures us that he never did 
intentionally give cause of offence to <persName>Mr Pilcher</persName>, and that the 
circumstance was inadvertant, and without any intention of wounding his
feelings, Consequently <persName>Mr P</persName>'s coolness arose from mistaken 
impressions of his intention. Also that at the time he call'd on <persName>Mr P</persName> for an
explanation, he was intirely unconscious of the cause of such 
coolness and that the inference he drew at the time he was leaving <persName>Mr P</persName>.
grew out of his denial to make any explanation. Consequently
<persName>Mr P</persName>'s. letter of the <date when="1817-05-13">13th</date> and <date when="1817-05-14">14th</date> was also written under wrong 
impressions, which letter has given rise to the subsequent events.&#8212;</p>

<p>We therefore the <persName>referees </persName>chosen by the <persName>parties </persName>from the 
declarations of <persName>Mr Austin</persName> that he never did either directly or indirectly 
intentionally wound or injure the feelings of <persName>Mr Pilcher</persName> and also his
declaration that at the time he ask'd for explanation he was totally
ignorant of the cause of <persName>Mr P</persName>'s. coolness, (<hi rend="italic">that cause</hi> having been
subsequently suggested.) Are unanimously of opinion that <persName>Mr
Pilcher</persName> should state in writing to <persName>Mr Austin</persName>, that he regrets having
attack'd him, and is sorry for the personal injury he has sustain'd.
And that he had acted under wrong impressions&#8212;Such statement
ought in our opinion to satisfy <persName>Mr Austin </persName>and <hi rend="italic">all previous</hi> 
communications which may have pass'd between them relative to this matter
shall be mutually withdrawn and destroyed&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>J [or T.] Hanson</persName></p>
<p><persName>J. G Brady</persName></p>
<p><persName>Stephen Rector</persName></p>
<p><persName>T. Douglass</persName><pb n="316"/></p>

<p>8. <persName>PILCHER</persName>'S APOLOGY</p>

<p><persName>Mr Stephen F Austin</persName>                                  <placeName>St Louis</placeName> <date when="1817-06-07">June 7th 1817</date></p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>The award of Messrs <persName>Hanson </persName><persName>Recter </persName><persName>Brady </persName>and <persName>Douglass</persName>
to whom was submitted the determination of the difference between
us has just been communicated to me. I lose no time in complying
with so much of that award as I find to be obligatory upon me by
stating to you in writing, that I regret having attacked you, and am
sorry for the personal injury you have received, and that I have acted
under wrong impressions</p>
<p>I am etc etc</p>

<p><persName>Joshua Piloher </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
