<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0393">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Joseph H. Hawkins to Maria Austin, 06-27-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Joseph H. Hawkins</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Maria Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, LA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Herculaneum, MO</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 397-398
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-06-27">06-27-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Stephen Austin gone to explore site of colony. Condolence. Interest in the Texan enterprise.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date when="1821-06-27">June 27, 1821</date></p>
<p>Dear Madam,</p>

<p>Your son <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName> has been a member of my family for
the last eight months&#8212;His amiable qualities of the heart combined
with his intelligence and acquirements will always secure him
friends&#8212;</p>

<p>And our intercourse has resulted in mutually warm and I trust
lasting attachment. He had set his heart on facilitating the views of
his <persName>father </persName>in his contemplated settlement in <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;And believing
the enterprise laudable, and perhaps promising some reward to those
who would toil in its prosecution, I agreed to meet the proposition<pb n="398"/>
of his <persName>Father</persName>, and take a joint interest in the grant and settlement&#8212;
Upon receiving your last letter enclosing one from your <persName>son</persName>, <persName>Mr.
Bryan</persName> enjoining so strongly on <persName>Stephen </persName>in the name of his <persName>father</persName>
the fulfilment of his objects (which indisposition then prevented his
doing,) <persName>Stephen </persName>and myself both concluded it was best for him to set
out immediately and meet the <persName>Spanish officers</persName> waiting at <placeName>Nachitoches</placeName>
to conduct him to the <placeName>grant</placeName>&#8212;and take a number of respectable 
persons along with him to explore the Country&#8212;He set out from this
place ten days ago to effect this object taking some 8 or 10 persons
with him&#8212;The <persName>Spanish Officers</persName> having been waiting some time they
have probably by this time set out for the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I have advanced <persName>Stephen </persName>all the funds he desired for the 
expedition and have promised to furnish more as he requires them&#8212;His
prospects seem flattering so far as the good feelings of the local 
<persName>officers </persName>and <persName>Government </persName>can promise success.</p>

<p>I had expected his <persName>father </persName>here as soon as his health would permit,
and was prepared to further his views by every friendly effort in my
power&#8212;Today I learn that that <persName>father</persName>&#8212;is no more&#8212;I have no 
consolation my dear madam for this afflictive dispensation&#8212; Your only
consolation is to be found in the resignation which we owe to the
will of Heaven&#8212; Blessed by the dear pledges of affection left behind,
you should for their sake meet this inroad upon your happiness with
the fortitude necessary to sustain it&#8212;¦</p>

<p>God still tempers the wind to the shorn lamb-&#8212;- It is the Cup of
afflication that chastens and brightens the pearls scattered before us
here, and sometimes prepares us for that hereafter, where " the
weary are at rest, and the wicked cease from troubling "&#8212;</p>

<p>Pardon the liberty I take in addressing you&#8212; My only object is
to fil the place of your <persName>Stephen </persName>until he shall return to you&#8212; Pray
look upon me as such&#8212; Will you allow me to ask if any remittance
of money or shipment of articles from this place is now necessary to
your comforts? I promised <persName>Stephen </persName>to write you if anything 
happened and would to God I could alleviate your sorrows&#8212;</p>
<p>Yrs truly and respty</p>

<p><persName>Jos: H Hawkins</persName></p>

<p>P. S. I shall forward an <persName>express </persName>to <persName>Stephen </persName>informing him of his
fatal loss&#8212;but shall urge him by all means to prosecute the objects
of his Enterprise.</p>

<p><persName>J. H. H</persName>.</p>

<p>[Addressed:]<persName> Mrs Austin Widow of the late M. Austin Esq</persName> Near
<placeName>Herculaneum State Missouri</placeName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
