<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0853">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Andrew Erwin to Stephen F. Austin, 09-11-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Andrew Erwin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Columbia, TN</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Nachitoches, AR</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 893-894
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-09-11">09-11-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Tennessee. Interest in Texas. Qualities of Jared E. Groce.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Columbia </placeName><date when="1824-09-11">Septem 11th 1824</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>Your esteemed favour of may last Come to hand in short time
in which you spoke of . . . [illegible] <persName>Caruthers </persName>having been with
you I have not as yet seen him&#8212;</p>

<p>I am truly glad to hear of your flattering prosspects as to a
healthy situation goods seasons the productiveness of the soil and
Improvement in government which when all Combined cannot fail
to realize your hopes if so all must be well with you and the Early
adventurers with you to that garden spot of <placeName>America</placeName></p>

<p>I presume <persName>Mr. Caruthers</persName> gave you the news of <placeName>Tennessee </placeName>etc
Politics and otherwise in which I have taken some part and may
again Engage&#8212;</p>

<p>you are good Enough to Express your satisfaction at what I had
done in Executing your commission with the <persName>fair one</persName> spoken of in
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>to wit <persName>Miss Williams</persName> of this country. She has seen your
letter I this morning, parted with her at her <persName>father</persName>s home in
possession of your letter to me and she indulges a hope of 
seeing you <date n="Spring-1825">next spring</date>, you will not Regret your vissit to her and
your Humble Servant I tharfore claim your promis.</p>

<p>I ardently hope your <persName>Mother </persName>and <persName>Sister </persName>arived Safe at your
abode as anticipated in your letter. I had allmost Started my <persName>Son</persName>
17 years of age to See you <date n="Fall-1824">last fall</date> with a hope you might be able
to give him Employment as a <persName>Surveyor </persName>and learn him or have him
taught the Spanish Language and the ways of the cuntry&#8212;</p>

<p>Your vissit here would be of great importance to yourself as I
believe</p>

<p>My old Friend <persName>Leftwich </persName>has never Returned I heard from him
in may last Still in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;-I presume you have become acquainted<pb n="894"/>
with <persName>J E. Groce of <placeName>Brassos</placeName></persName>. Who is an Interprising man and I hope
may do well in your Cuntry his Excentricities and Exalted 
notions of himself is his worst foibles, he is as you know if acquainted
a warm <persName>friend </persName>or bitter <persName>Enemy </persName>Just as his Immidiate Interest is
Effected, he lately wrote me a long letter and his <persName>clerk </persName>certifyed
the correctness of it founded in misstaken notions, both of me and
himself intended to injure me and cannot in any way bennifit 
himself and can in no-way be accounted for on the score of reason or
Propriety all of which you perhaps know or may See if acquainted
if you are not, it is not my wish to injure him in any manner nor
shape whatever and were I near him he would not asail me</p>

<p><persName>Andrew Erwin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] The <persName>Honble. Stephen F Austin</persName> <placeName>Nachitochez 
Arkansas Territory</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
