<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0548">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Robert Andrews to James E. B. Austin, 12-07-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Robert Andrews</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Saltillo</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 557-558
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-12-07">12-07-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reports from Stephen F. Austin.   Business in Saltillo.   Inclosure from James Hewitson.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Saltillo </placeName><date when="1822-12-07">December 7th 22</date></p>

<p>Dear <persName>James</persName></p>

<p>I this day recd a letter from your <persName>brother </persName>dated Mexico <date when="1822-11-27">Nov. 27th,</date>
he says that the colonization law is passed by the <persName>Junta</persName>, and that it
only waits the approbation of the <persName>Emperor </persName>who is at this time in
the <placeName>city of Xalapa</placeName> he thinks he will be able to set out in 2 or 3
weeks from the date of his letter with his business arrainged 
compleatly to his satisfaction, he says he has no doubt of the great 
anxiety and surprise, his long stay will produce among his <persName>friends </persName>and
<persName>acquaintances </persName>who are unacquainted with the <persName>Mexican </persName>character,
but to us who must by this time know something of them it cannot
be strange&#8212;he says he will spend the hollow days of Christmas
with me at this place if he can, however I write to him by this mail
least he should not set out so soon</p>

<p>My business at this place is not profitable and what little I had
made about 6 weeks ago was stolen from me, leaving me destitute
of anything but the clothes which were on me, however I remain
here and am making about 70 or 80 dollars a month&#8212; I understand<pb n="558"/>
by <persName>Mr Werzner</persName> that <persName>Mr Alley</persName> is on the <placeName>Collerado</placeName>, if so he will not
get my letter, I wrote him concerning a trip to the<placeName> U. S.</placeName> with Mules
etc. say to him if he is in your Town, that perhaps we may not go,
however if we do we will go by <placeName>St Antonio</placeName>, so soon as I ascertain
to a certainty I will write him, give my best respects to the 
<persName>governor</persName>, his <persName>lady</persName>, her <persName>sister</persName>, <persName>brother Mr Mires</persName>, <persName>Mr Splane</persName><persName> Mr Almonty</persName>
and other friends&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Andrews</persName></p>
<p>[Enclosure.]</p>
<p>Dear <persName>Brown</persName></p>

<p>I write you merely to congratulate you on the good news which
the <persName>Doctr</persName>. has communicated to you on the preceding page, which I
assure you gives me much satisfaction to hear that <persName>Mr Stephen</persName> has
succeeded in obtaining his objects fully to his wishes, a 
circumstance which no doubt will have the effect of removing all those
carking cares and anxieties which have so much annoyed your mind
on account of his long delay in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>Cheer up my boy Bob the
sun has once more appeard to illumine your darked horizon and
dissipate those thick heavy clouds that have so long hung hovering
over your <hi rend="italic">Juvenile </hi>brow&#8212;Adios&#8212;My compts to <persName>Mr Hawkins</persName>&#8212;
<persName>Dona. Antoa Rodg</persName> and <persName>Son </persName><persName>Mr Iturrie</persName> and <persName>Lady </persName>and all others of
my esteemed acquaintance who think well to inquire about me&#8212;
You may see by this where I am and after a while I shall let you
know where I shall be, so untill that period I continue uno de los
creados de V. M. Q. S. M. B.</p>

<p><persName>James Hewetson</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed] A <persName>D.n Santiago Austin</persName> [en] la <placeName>Provinc[i]a de
Texas</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
