<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0161">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Darius Shaw to Moses Austin, 01-24-1810</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Darius Shaw</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-30">06-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Moses Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 163-166
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1810-01-24">01-24-1810</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Deed to house. Tannery, cattle, etc.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>This Indenture made this <date when="1810-01-24">twenty fourth Day of Janry in the Year
of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and ten</date> between <persName>Moses<pb n="164"/>
Austin</persName> of <placeName>Breton Township</placeName>, <placeName>St Genevieve District</placeName> of the one Part
and <persName>Darius Shaw</persName> of Sd. <placeName>Township </placeName>and <placeName>District </placeName>of the other Part&#8212;
Witnesseth, that for and in consideration of the Sum of one 
hundred Dollars to the Sd. <persName>Darius Shaw</persName> in hand paid by the said <persName>Moses
Austin</persName> at or before the ensealing and [delivery] of these Presents,
the receipt whereof he [the said] <persName>Darius Shaw</persName> doth hereby 
acknowledge; he [the said] <persName>Darius Shaw</persName> hath granted, bargained, sold and
dem[itted] and by these Presents doth bargain, sell, grant and
Demitt unto the said <persName>Moses Austin</persName> his <persName>Executors </persName><persName>Administrators</persName>
and <persName>Assigns </persName>these several Messuages, Tenements, Improvements etc.
Situated in the <placeName>Township of Breton</placeName>, being the Same on which the
said <persName>Darius Shaw</persName> now lives, together with all Lands, tenements and
improvement thereunto belonging including the Tan Yard of the
Said <persName>Shaw </persName>with all the building and Appurtenances which belong
to said <placeName>Tan Yard</placeName> or in any wise connected therewith together 
therewith, all the right and share, belonging to the Said <persName>Shaw</persName>, of Leather
either taken out and finished or lying in the Vats of said <placeName>Tan Yard</placeName>
and the dry hides remaining on hand at said <placeName>Yard</placeName>&#8212;Also, the Said
Shaws Stock of Cattle, Hogs, and Sheep&#8212;V I Z, one Yoak of Oxen,
three Cows, one Yoak Steers four Years Old unbroke, One Bull four
Yearling and two Heifers. Also nine Sheep and fifty head of
Hogs&#8212;likewise the following Artic[les and] farming Utensils, one
Plough one Harrow one Chain three Hoes, one Ax one Iron spade,
and two Ox Yoaks&#8212;also of Kitchen Utensils one table two Iron
Pots one Bake Oven one large Iron Kettle one frying pan six pewter
plates six Knives and forks and three tin pans, With all and 
singular their Appurtenances and the Reversion and Reversions 
Remainder and Remainders Rents Issues and profits thereof, to have and to
hold the said Messuges, <placeName>Tenements Buildings</placeName>, Ground, 
Hereditaments, and all and Singular others the Premises with their and
every of their Appurtenances unto the said <persName>Moses Austin</persName>, his 
<persName>Executors </persName><persName>Administrators </persName>and <persName>Assigns </persName>from the Day next before the day
of the Date hereof for and during the full time and term, and unto
the full end and term of one thousand Years from thence next 
insuing and fully to be compleat and ended, yealding and paying 
therefor the rent [of one] Hundred Dollars therefor, on the <date n="01-01-xxxx">first Day [of]
Janry</date> in every Year if the same be lawfully demanded, Provided
always and upon condition that if the said <persName>Shaw </persName>his <persName>Heirs </persName><persName>Executors</persName>
or <persName>Administrators</persName>, shall and do well and truly pay or Cause to be
paid, unto the said <persName>Moses Austin</persName> his <persName>Executors</persName>, <persName>Administrators </persName>or
<persName>Assigns </persName>at the <placeName>Town ship of Breton</placeName> and <placeName>District of St Genevieve
</placeName>the full and just sum of twelve hundred and forty five Dollars
Money of the <placeName>United States</placeName> upon the <date when="1812-01-01">first day of Janry in the Year
one thousand eight hundred and twelve</date> ensuing the Date thereof
with Lawful Interest untill paid then and in such case these Presents<pb n="165"/>
and the term and Estate hereby granted and every Clause, and 
Sentence herein contained, shall cease determine, and be utterly void to
all intents and purposes, any thing herein contained to the contrary
notwithstanding&#8212;And the said <persName>Shaw </persName>hereby for himself, his <persName>heirs</persName>,
<persName>Executors </persName>and <persName>Administrators </persName>and <persName>assigns </persName>[does] covenant and agree
with the said <persName>Moses Austin</persName> his <persName>Executors</persName>, <persName>Administrators </persName>and <persName>Assigns</persName>
that the said <persName>Shaw</persName>, his <persName>Heirs </persName><persName>Executors </persName><persName>Administrators </persName>and <persName>Assigns</persName>,
shall and will well and truly pay or cause to be paid unto the said
<persName>Moses Austin</persName> his <persName>Executors</persName>, <persName>Administrators </persName>or <persName>Assigns </persName>the said sum
of twelve hundred and forty five Dollars at such time and place as
are herein before mentioned, and further that it shall and may be
lawful for the said <persName>Moses Austin</persName> his <persName>Executors </persName>and <persName>Administrators</persName>
and <persName>Assigns </persName>from time to time and at all times, from and after
Default shall happen to be made in the said Sum of twelve hundred
and forty five Dollars or any part thereof contrary to the form and
effect of the aforesaid proviso and covenant of the same peaceably
and quietly to enter into, have and hold occupy and possess and
enjoy the said <placeName>Messuages Buildings</placeName> <placeName>Hereditiments </placeName>and <placeName>Premises</placeName>, and
to receive and take [the] rent and Proffitts thereof for and During
all the [time] which shall be thereto come and unexpired of the said
term of one thousand Years without the lawful let suit or trouble
denial, eviction or interruption by the said <persName>Shaw </persName>his <persName>Heirs </persName>
<persName>Administrators </persName>or <persName>Assigns</persName>, or of or by any other Person or Persons 
whomsoever,&#8212;And it is hereby declared and agree'd by and between the
said <persName>Parties </persName>to these Presents, that in the mean time and untill 
Default shall happen to be made of or in payment of the said sum of
twelve hundred and forty five Dollars, contrary to the form and
effect of the aforesaid Provision and Covenant for payment of the
same it shall and may be lawful to and for the said <persName>Shaw </persName>and his
<persName>Heirs </persName>peaceably and quietly to have hold and enjoy all and singular
the said <placeName>Messuages buildings</placeName> <placeName>Hereditaments </placeName>and <placeName>Premises</placeName>, and to
receive and take the Proffit thereof and of every part thereof to use
for his and their use and Benefitt, without the lawful let suit, trouble
or Interruption from [the] said <persName>Moses Austin</persName>, his <persName>Executors </persName>
<persName>Administrators </persName>or <persName>Assigns</persName>, or of any other person or Persons lawfully
claiming or to claim from by or under him or them or any of them.
In Witness where of I have hereunto set my Hand and Seal at the
time and Place before mentioned</p>

<p><persName>Darius Shaw </persName>   [Seal]</p>

<p>Attest.    <persName>Cha. A. Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p><placeName>Breton Township</placeName> <date when="1810-01-31">31st Day of Janry in the Year 1810</date> personally
appeared before me a <persName>Justice of the peace</persName> in the <placeName>Township </placeName>aforesaid
<persName>Darius Shaw</persName> and acknowledged the within Instrument signed with
his Name and sealed with his seal to be his Act and deed.</p>

<p><persName>James Austin, J. P.</persName>    [Rubric]<pb n="166"/></p>

<p>This instrument of writing was Received into the office of the
Recorder of the Said district on the <date when="1810-02-27">Twenty-Seventh day of February
1810</date> for Record</p>

<p><persName>Tho Oliver Recorder</persName>
And the same is duly Recorded in Book B folio 36, 37 and 38</p>

<p><persName>Tho Oliver Recorder </persName>   [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
