<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0337">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to James E. B. Austin, 08-12-1819</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-08">07-08-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Herculaneum, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Nicholesville, KY</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 346-347
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="Private "/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1819-08-12">08-12-1819</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Panic of 1819. Local news.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Herculanium</placeName>, <date when="1819-08-02">Augt.2 1819</date></p>
<p>My Dear <persName>Son</persName></p>

<p>I was disappointed that I did not receive a letter from you last
mail, but contemplate the receipt of a letter the next mail. I 
mentioned in my last that <persName>Mrs Evens</persName> was verry sick, and that her life
was not expected, <date when="1819-08-09">last Monday</date> she left this <hi rend="italic">world</hi>, and went to meet
her <hi rend="italic"><persName>husband </persName></hi>who died only three weeks before hir&#8212; little <hi rend="italic"><persName>Willis</persName></hi>
is now with us and what will be don with him I cannot tell your
<persName>Mother </persName>cannot take care of him her Health is such that its as
much as she can do to take care of hirself. I also mentioned to you
that <persName>Mrs. Weber</persName> had left us or was about to do so she removed her
trunk last week to <persName>Wilkens </persName>and your Dear <persName>Mother </persName>is left with out
any <persName>female </persName>friend this change has been brought about in 
consiquence of the most unfounded abuse and those that have been 
instrumental in bringing the business about, are, now, to receive the benefit
of there Damanable, conduct. I see a man that left Your <persName>Brother</persName>
<date when="1819-07-11">three weeks from yesterday</date>, he said he was well and in good health
and that his prospects were great and that he was, in, high spirits,
and doing well    You ought to write him and Direct your letters to<pb n="347"/>
<placeName>Nachitoches</placeName>&#8212;<persName>Ira </persName>will get them. I have not heard any thing from
<persName>Mr Schoolcraft</persName> as yet but think I shall soon. I wish much to here
from <persName>Colo Walker</persName> from your account he must be in great Danger
of his life. I hope you make every Day some advancement in your
education lett me pray you to remember that now is the time to 
obtain you improvements a Day now lost is of the utmost consequence
to you and can never be, <hi rend="italic">recalled </hi>an educatione is of more 
consequence than money,   lett it be therefore your first care.</p>

<p>I hope you mantain a friendly understanding with <persName>Mr Holly</persName> and
family&#8212;I have not heard a word from him sence you arrived, If
you see him make my respects to him and family</p>

<p>Nothing can equal the General Distress for money&#8212;I hope to send
you Some Next mail I cannot this</p>

<p>Your Dear <persName>Mother </persName>is in as good health, as, common and I hope,
may, remain <hi rend="italic">so</hi>&#8212; the Town is in General Good health&#8212;altho <persName>Mr
and Mrs Evens</persName> have been taken of, not, a, steam boat has arrivd
sence you left this place except the Maid of Orleans and <persName>John W
Honey</persName>&#8212;has obtaind the command of her, and gon to <hi rend="italic">Orleans </hi>
expects to return in sixty Days I wish <persName>Mrs Holly</persName> would send for
<persName>Mary Austin</persName> it would be of great, advantage to hir</p>

<p>Your <persName>mother </persName>sends her love to you and prays you to be attentive
to your Studeis&#8212;</p>

<p>I read <persName>Mrs. Weber</persName> your letter and She says that she is sattisfied
that If other persons had left you to Judge for yourself your Opinion
would have been quite otherwise than what it was She sends you
her respects and wishes you all the good this world can give you and
may god Bless You my son your Affectionate <persName>father</persName></p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr James E B Austin</persName> <placeName>Nicholes Vill Kentucky</placeName>&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
