<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0928">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Timothy Flint to Stephen F. Austin, 11-29-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Timothy Flint</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Alexandria, LA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 979-980
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-11-29">11-29-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asks Austin for an article, Texas and the Provincias Internas, to be used in "Recollections of ten years spent in the valley of the Mississippi."</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Alexandria. Loui</placeName> <date when="1824-11-29">Nov. 29 1824</date></p>
<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I had formerly the honour in <placeName>Missouri </placeName>to be known to your late
<persName>father</persName>, and to have been introduced to you, when, I believe, a <persName>member
of the legislature</persName> of the then territory. The impressions, that 
remain of that acquaintance, and of conversations with my lamented
friends the late <persName>Mr Elliot of <placeName>St Genevieve</placeName></persName>, and <persName>Col Hawkins of
<placeName>N. Orleans</placeName></persName>, embolden me to make a request, which after all, I
feare, you will think extraordinary, teased, as I presume you are,
with numberless requests of a similar nature. But, perhaps, when
you shall have read my motives, you may think of my request
with more indulgence.</p>

<p>I have resided, as a <persName>missionary</persName>, and as an <persName>instructor</persName>, ten years
in different points of the <placeName>valley of the Missisippi</placeName>; two years of
which have been spent in different parts of this state. At the
request of many respectable friends, I am about to publish a work,
entitled <hi rend="italic">recollections of ten years spent in the <placeName>valley of the Missisippi
</placeName></hi>The very great interest, that your <placeName>settlement</placeName>, and the <placeName>province
of Texas</placeName> excites in this country, and elsewhere, induces me to wish
to append to my remarks upon this <placeName>state </placeName>and the <placeName>territory of
arkansas</placeName>, some authentic notices of the adjoining country of the
<placeName>provincias internas</placeName>. No person, I presume, is so well qualified
to impart that information, as yourself. If you would have the
goodness, by as early a conveyance to this place as may suit your
convenience, to give me some notices of your country, and of
your observations generally in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, it would be to me the highest
favor; and, possibly as various and contradictory representations
of the advantages, and disadvantages of emigration to your country,
have gone abroad authentick information by one, who has always
hitherto taken the favourable side in this discussions, may not be
disadvantageous to the interest of the <placeName>Settlement</placeName>.</p>

<p>The points upon which information is most earnestly desired
are <hi rend="italic">limits, form of the <placeName>coast</placeName>, soil climate health&#8212;government and
tenure of lands etc.</hi> But I would be exceedingly thankful for any
kind of information upon your <placeName>province</placeName>, and the country 
generally. I am promised from some very respectable gentleman notes
upon the ill fated expedition of <placeName>Toledo</placeName>. I would be glad of your
views upon that subject, as well, as the expedition of <persName>Long</persName>. In
short, any thing from you, or any authentic information from
any source, would be most thankfully accepted.</p>

<p>If my declining health admit, I expect to go <date n="Summer-1825">next summer</date> to
<placeName>Boston </placeName>to publish the work and in the mean time, Another 
gentleman and myself have talked strongly, if my avocations will admit,
of taking a journey to your <placeName>Settlement</placeName>.    Should you grant me<pb n="980"/>
the favour desired, I shall have, in that case, an opportunity of
thanking you in person.   And should I not have that pleasure, I
shall still be</p>

<p>gratefully  and respectfully your friend  and hum  servt.</p>

<p><persName>Timothy Flint</persName>,</p>

<p><persName>Stephen H. Austin, Esq</persName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
