<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0521">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Unknown, 06-26-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico City, MX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 527
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Power of Attorney</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-06-26">06-26-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">To form stock company in England to develop Austin's grant.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>A tract of land in the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName> being granted to me by
the <persName>Government of this Empire</persName> whose limits are not yet defined,
but the situation of which together with the state of my claims and
every thing relative to them <persName>Genl. Arthur G. Wavell</persName> is enabled fully
to explain; and being desirous of establishing a <persName>Company </persName>for 
Commercial, Mining and agricultural purposes, I hereby appoint said
<persName>Genl. Arthur G. Wavell</persName> my <persName>attorney </persName>to contract with a <persName>Merchant</persName>
or <persName>company of Merchants in <placeName>Europe</placeName></persName> and to form a <persName>Company </persName>and
such other connections for me and in my name either jointly with
him or seperately as he may deem proper, in order to carry into
effect the objects of speculation enumerated in papers and 
Memorandums furnished him and which I have in conversation made him
fully acquainted with&#8212;My said <persName>attorney </persName>is fully empowered to
mortgage, or put into the funds of the <persName>Company </persName>as stock all the
lands which I am to receive in <placeName>Texas </placeName>under the present application
now pending, except the one half of a concession for <persName>three hundred
families</persName> granted to my <persName>father M. A.</persName> which I have by contract 
conveyed under particular conditions to <persName>Col Joseph H. Hawkins</persName> of
<placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, and also there must be a stipulation in the contract,
that said <persName>Hawkins </persName>is at liberty to become one of the <persName>Company</persName>
should he wish it by furnishing his proportion of the capital&#8212;</p>

<p>The Basis on which said <persName>A. G. Wavell</persName> is authorised to form said
<persName>company </persName>is that the lands furnished by me and the capital furnished
by the <persName>persons in <placeName>Europe</placeName></persName> shall be the joint stock of the <persName>Company</persName>
the profits of which shall be divided in the proportions which my
said <persName>attorney </persName>and the <persName>contracting parties</persName> may agree on, All <placeName>Mines</placeName>,
<placeName>Salt springs</placeName> or <placeName>wells</placeName>, denounced by me as a <persName>citizen of this <placeName>Empire</placeName>
</persName>shall be for the joint use and benefit of the <persName>Company</persName>, also my time
and labour shall be devoted to the interests of the concern for which
such compensation shall be allowed me as may be agreed on by my
said <persName>attorney</persName>&#8212;hereby ratifying and confirming whatever my said
<persName>Attorney </persName>may lawfully do in the premises as fully as if done by
myself in person&#8212;</p>

<p><placeName>City of Mexico</placeName> <date when="1822-06-26">June 26. 1822</date></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin  </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p>Copy of Power to <persName>Genl. Wavell</persName></p>

<p>and as the said <persName>H.</persName> is a man of the first standing and connections
and may therefore be of material service to the company by 
attending to its affairs in <placeName>New O.</placeName> Where it will be necessary to have an
<persName>Agent</persName>. I wish a clause in the contract that said Haw[kins] may be
admitted into the concern on such terms as may be mutually agreed
to by all concerned&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
