<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0007">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses and Stephen F. Austin to John Blanchard and George Lauman, 03-16-1795</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses and Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-09">06-09-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        John Blanchard 
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        George Lauman
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Wythe County, VA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Philadelphia, PA</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 13-15
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Contract</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1795-03-16">03-16-1795</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Agreement in Virginia land speculations.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[Copy by Moses Austin.]</p>

<p>Agreement indented made and concluded upon this <date when="1795-03-16">sixteenth day
of March in the year of our Lord one thousand seven hundred and
Ninety five</date> Between <persName>Stephen and M Austin</persName> of <placeName>Wythe County State
of Virginia</placeName> <persName>Merchants </persName>of the one part and <persName>John D Blanchard</persName> and<pb n="14"/>
<persName>George Lauman of the City of <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></persName> in this State of 
<placeName>Pennsylvania </placeName><persName>Merchants </persName>of the other part</p>—

<p>Witnesseth that it is mutually covenanted stipulated promised and
agreed by and between the said <persName>Parties </persName>to these presents in manner
following, that is to say—That the said <persName>Stephen and Moses Austin</persName>
shall and will make discoveries of and take up and secure lands
lying within the State of <placeName>Virginia </placeName>or elsewhere on the joint account
of all the said <persName>parties </persName>hereto to be held in proportions following, to
wit the said <persName>Stephen and Moses Austin</persName> one equal third part thereof
the said <persName>John D Blanchard</persName> one equal third part thereof and the said
<persName>George Lauman</persName> the remaining one equal third part thereof as <persName>tenants</persName>
in common—</p>

<p>That all the purchase moneys for said Land, surveying and office
fees and other incidental charges and expenees in the prosecution of
the said business, shall be equally borne and paid by all the said
<persName>parties</persName>, each of them one equal third part thereof</p>

<p>On account whereof they the said <persName>Stephen and Moses Austin</persName> have
now received from the said <persName>John D Blanchard</persName> and <persName>George Lauman</persName>
the sum of one thousand dollars</p>

<p>That for all monies which may from time to time be necessary
and requisit in the said business they the said <persName>Stephen and Moses
Austin</persName> shall and may draw on the said <persName>John D. Blanchard</persName> and
<persName>George Lauman</persName> who hereby engage and agree without Delay to
honor and pay the same that all the warrants Surveys and patents
for the land to be taken up and secured in pursuance of these
presents shall be taken issued and made to and in the name of him
the said <persName>George Lauman</persName> in trust however for the use of All the said
parties to these presents</p>

<p>That the said <persName>Stephen and Moses Austin</persName> shall and will not 
during the continuance of the concern hereby created be interested or
connected with any other person or persons than the said <persName>John D
Blanchard</persName> and <persName>George Lauman</persName> in any Business of a similar Nature
and that upon the request of any two of the <persName>parties </persName>to these presents
a sale or Sales of the said land or a division thereof in the 
proportions aforesaid which ever may be deemed most to the advantage
of the said concern, shall be effected and made and they the said
<persName>parties </persName>of the first and second parts to these presents for themselves
their several and respective <persName>Heirs </persName><persName>Executors </persName>and <persName>Administraters </persName>do
hereby mutually and reciprocally convenant and agree promise
engage to and with each other and with each and every of their
<persName>Heirs </persName><persName>Executors </persName>and <persName>Administrators </persName>that they the said <persName>parties </persName>and
each of them shall and will well and faithfully stand to perform and
keep the several covenants stipulations engagements and agreements<pb n="15"/>
herein before mentioned and expressed—without any default or
delay—and for the true performance the said <persName>parties </persName>do hereby
mutually bind themselves their respective <persName>Heirs </persName><persName>Executors </persName>and
<persName>Administraters </persName>each unto the other of them in the penal sum of
Fifty Thousand pounds firmly by these presents In witness 
where-of they have interchangeably set their hands and Seals hereunto the
day and year first above written</p>

<p>Sealed and delivered in the presence of us</p>

<p>Coppy</p>

<p><persName>Joseph Bickey </persName>                                       <persName>Jn° D Blanchard</persName></p>

<p><persName>Charles Austin  </persName>                                   <persName>George Lauman</persName></p>
<p><persName>Stephen and M Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Endorsed:] Contract with <persName>Lauman </persName>and <persName>Blanchard</persName>.    (Copy.)</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
