<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0550">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Jose Felix Trespalacios to Stephen F. Austin, 12-15-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Jose Felix Trespalacios</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Antonio de Bexar, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 560
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-12-15">12-15-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Provisions for the welfare of Texas. Wants assistance in breaking up bands of thieves stealing horses and mules in Texas and selling them in the United States.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Antonio de Bexar</placeName> <date when="1822-12-15">December 15. 1822</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>as soon as I arrived here as <persName>Governor </persName>of this <placeName>province </placeName>I endeavored
to promote its welfare. I directed the <persName>inhabitants of the <placeName>Colorado</placeName></persName>
to appoint an <persName>alcalde </persName>of their own choice to administer justice, and
organize the <persName>militia </persName>to oppose the <persName>Karankawas </persName>or other <persName>intruders</persName>
who might attack their persons or their property. I provided the
wants of some distant <placeName>settlements </placeName>who petitioned for the protection
of the <persName>Government</persName>. The presence of several <persName>Indian chiefs</persName> in this
place gave me the opportunity to bring to an understanding nations
who had been heretofore at war. Though the plan of colonization
is not yet known. I am confident it shall be drawn up upon liberal
principles and will afford to industrious emigrants the advantage of
a rich soil fit for every kind of crops. I expect shortly a strong
reinforcement of <persName>troops </persName>and intend to visit with them the <placeName>province</placeName>
and leave <persName>detachments </persName>at the most important points to protect the
<persName>settlers </persName>and <persName>travellers</persName>. While I am waiting with anxiety the means
of contributing to the final happiness of this section of the <placeName>Empire</placeName>
I feel myself somewhat disappointed in my expectations in seeing a
band of <persName>villains </persName><persName>Spaniards </persName>and <persName>americans </persName>actually engaged in 
stealing mules and horses and so bring them with impunity to the <placeName>United
States</placeName>. The existence of this set of <persName>robbers </persName>cannot be but prejudicial
to the <persName>inhabitants </persName>of both countries, there fore I take the liberty
to ask your opinion upon the measures which are better calculated
to stop such criminal a traffic. Should you find yourself authorised
to help me in obtaining this desirable object, I shall have reason to
congratulate both your philanthropy and my own good fortune.&#8212;-If
you have any command for this place or for any other where my
credit might be of some service to you, sir, please dispose with 
confidence of</p>

<p>[José Felix Trespalacios.]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
