<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0730">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>George H. Robb to Stephen F. Austin, 04-24-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>George H. Robb</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brazos, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 778-779
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-04-24">04-24-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Commerce. Transportation. Judiciary.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><persName>Col. Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>
<p>Sir</p>
<p>I think it my duty to address you as early as possible as the <persName>head
magistrate</persName> and <persName>manager of the Colony</persName> informing you of my 
arrival in this river with my <persName>family </persName>with the intentions of becoming
a <persName>settler </persName>if you should approve of the same have brought with me
the most ample testimonial certificates of character etc which will
be presented as soon as I have the pleasure of seeing you which will
be so soon as possible as I have many Grievences to inform you of
which requires your advice and aid without which I am afraid I
cannot get along and it will always afford me pleasure to be guided
by [you], our mutual worthy friend <persName>Dr Sibly</persName> informed me of
your friendly and beloved character to every honest upright man,
in my well assorted cargoe I had a quantity of fine goods fit or
more for <persName>Spanish people</persName> than <persName>Americans </persName>and in order to dispose of
these goods the vessell was cleared out for Rio Grande or els where
in my name as owner and master but not knowing navigation I hired<pb n="779"/>
a man as mate and <persName>sailing-master</persName> at $40 pr month who has acted
like a deranged man and in conjunction with some deck <persName>passengers</persName>
have suffered much by it we left the <placeName>southwest pass of the 
Mississippi </placeName>on the <date when="1824-04-01">1st day of Aprail</date> toward night it began to blow very
fresh approatching to a gale I desired him to closs reeff all sails
for the night which he refused to do by cursing and swearing that
he was sailing master and he would do as he thought proper he
therefore carried all sail on the schooner and she deeply loaded 
running almost under water at the rate of nine miles an hour abcfut
the middle of the night it was discovered there was a good deal of
water in the hold Instantly the pump and bailing from a hatchway
in the cabin was had recourse to and we gained on the water in the
meantime this mate of mine in consist with his <persName>Irish countrymen</persName>
and two deck <persName>passengers </persName><persName>Americans </persName>without my knowledge or 
consent opened my latches and threw a great part of the cargoe all
my property overboard what my loss is I cannot at present 
assertain but is not less 3000 $ at sailing I did not intend to see the <placeName>Brazos</placeName>
until I had first seen <placeName>Rio Grande</placeName> and disposed of my Spanish goods
but the above Circumstance brought me in here excuse my 
imperfect letter as it is wrot in a hurry by a straing gentleman (<persName>Mr
Mitchell</persName>) who has promised to forward it to you This river is a verry
fine stream and excellent for steam boat navigation which I shall
try to have one on it within two years&#8212;not one shilling of my 
property was insured either on ship or goods but it will be necessary to
enter a protest before you as I have been threatened by a deck 
passenger&#8212;I know not for what except it be for the vessel springing a
leak a circumstance I could not account for&#8212;relying on your 
attention</p>

<p><persName>Geo. H. Robb</persName></p>
<p><placeName>Brazos </placeName>near <persName>Mr. Bell</persName> <date n="04-24-18xx">24th April 18</date></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
