<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0470">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Bryan to Stephen F. Austin, 01-15-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Bryan</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Hazel Run, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Colorado, TX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 465-466
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-01-15">01-15-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Hard times in Missouri. Great emigration from all the States to Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Hazel Run</placeName> <date when="1822-01-15">Janry 15th 1822</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Brother </persName><persName>Stephen</persName>,</p>

<p>I write you by our friend <persName>Bruffy</persName>, and you will also see your old
friend <persName>Majr Hawkins</persName>, I can assure you a great number will move
from this state some [time] next <date n="Spring-1822">spring </date>and others<date n="Fall-1822"> next fall</date> I
have no doubt the <placeName>Colony </placeName>will be filled up immediately, I have
answered all the letters on the subject of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, I flatter myself
you have arrived safe at the <placeName>Mouth of the Colorado</placeName> ere this, and the
Vessell has no doubt arrived some time since and I hope and trust
nothing unfavourable will happen relative to the Government and
if so the <placeName>Colony </placeName>will Prosper immediately and may God grant us a
happy Change in the said <placeName>Colony</placeName>, I hope <placeName>Brother </placeName>and <persName>Mr Henry
Elliott</persName> will arrive safe and the young men with them as they are
worthy men, I may Possibly come on myself in the <date n="Spring-1822">Spring </date>tho not
certain I will endeavor to send on some Provisions, and if all does
well with you and Life is spared us we will move <date n="Fall-1822">next autumn</date> and
I will expect you to make the selection of Land for me and if it is
Possible to have a Building of some sort put up I should be glad
as also to have an improvement made and stock procured, I will
bring on as much as I Possibly can to enable me to settle. I am
closing my business here and the Estate of <persName>Father </persName>will be insolvent
for $15,000. I hope our situations will shortly be changed for the
better, a number has failed here and all imbarrassed except the
<persName>Perrys</persName>. a large <persName>Company </persName>talks of moveing from the <placeName>Mines </placeName><date n="Fall-1822">next
fall</date> to your <placeName>Colony</placeName>, indeed they will move from all the states, I
have written by two gentlemen from <placeName>St Charles County </placeName>which I
have no doubt you will find to be worthy men, and I trust their will
be <persName>emigrants </persName>of that discription generally, I am Highly flattered in
anticipation as to the Prospects of your colony settleing and 
becoming a Town of importance do not fail to write me by every 
oppertunity and inform me your Prospects and give me a detale of
everything important I am daily hearing of peoples preparing to
move etc&#8212;you will have a number of your <persName>old acquaintances</persName> as
<persName>settlers </persName>I will do all I can for its welfare and will expect 
favourable News by every letter <persName>Mother</persName>s health is much better than it
has been for the last six Months and If she lives to settle at the
<placeName>colony </placeName>I have no doubt she will enjoy much better health than she
would here Your <persName>Sister </persName>and little <persName>Nephews </persName>are very well and all
anxious to see you and we flatter ourselves it will not be longer than
<date n="Fall-1822">next autumn</date> before we have that pleasure Your <persName>Uncles Family</persName> are
all well   .   •   •    ; he talks at times of <placeName>Texas </placeName>tho. says his <persName>Family</persName><pb n="466"/>
is so large he does not know if he can get there Our prayer is that
these may meet you in good health and Spirits and the <placeName>colony </placeName>in a
Prosperous way etc</p>

<p>May God bless you and <persName>Brother </persName>and preserve you from danger</p>

<p><persName>J Bryan</persName></p>

<p>N. B. <persName>Mr Bruffy</persName> and <persName>Majr Hawkins</persName> will give you the geneial
News.</p>

<p>P. S. I am in hopes you will secure the Title to all the Land we
can get as soon as Possible as I think very important should a change
of <persName>Government </persName>take place.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr Stephen F. Austin</persName> <placeName>Colorado Provence of Texas</placeName>
Politeness <persName>Mr Bruffy</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
