<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0777">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Gaines to Stephen F. Austin, 06-18-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Gaines</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Sabine, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 834-835
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-06-18">06-18-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Explaining restlessness of settlers in east Texas.  Bad characters on the Sabine.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Sabine </placeName><date when="1824-06-18">June 18th 1824</date></p>
<p><persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dr [Sir] your Two favas has come to hand, and the report
of your having finally  Setled the business  among your  <persName>Setlers</persName>,
numerous Reports are Circulated, that I Represented at <placeName>St. 
Antonio</placeName> against the <persName>Setlers </persName>here and that I here abused the people of
the <placeName>Colony </placeName>nothing Can be more notoriously false</p>

<p>Certain It is on my Return home I found the people Confused
and Exasperated on account of an answer to <persName>Quirk</persName>s Representation
by the Deputation sent in to <persName>Merimendez [Berrimendi]</persName> before I
arived at <placeName>St Antonia</placeName><pb n="835"/></p>

<p>as a number of people of this Country had imbibed Prejudices
against the Principles on which your <placeName>Colony </placeName>was founded when
I arived and asserted I had perused your Grant at <placeName>St Antonio</placeName> and
had it fully Explained by yourself at the <placeName>Brassos </placeName>and Give It fully
as my opinion that It was as Good as Could be made they then
became Restless and accused me of being Concerned in Braking up
this <placeName>Settlement </placeName>to fill your <placeName>Colony</placeName></p>

<p>I am also Told by a Late arival from the <placeName>Brasses </placeName>that <persName>Roberson</persName>
and <persName>Halls </persName>are Very active in Circulating Reports that I had spoken
Very much against the <persName>people of the <placeName>Colony</placeName></persName> no gentleman Can Say
but I have at all time Since my Return Spoken on the highest Terms
in favor of them, and as to what <persName>Vagabonds </persName>State I Dont feel
myself bound to answer</p>

<p>I Presume all the ill nature at the <placeName>Brasses </placeName>has Grown out of my
answers to Certain interegatories at the <placeName>Brassos </placeName>Respecting the <persName>Halls</persName>
and <persName>Roberson </persName>as I had Lived in this <placeName>Country </placeName>since <date n="xx-xx-1812">1812</date> numbers
of things has passed which when Calld on I Conceived my self bound
to answer, in <date n="xx-xx-1815">1815</date> <persName>Jack Hall</persName> and <persName>Cashly </persName>and some others Started a
Trading to the <persName>Tonquawas</persName>, It was Publickly stated here (as to
the Certainty I know not) that they mete a party of <persName>Spaniards </persName>with
a Cavilliad the <persName>Spaniards </persName>as these were <persName>americans </persName>felt themselves
safe and agreed to Travel together the morning following they fell
on the <persName>Spaniards </persName>Kild. them and Took the Cabillard, on their
way home <persName>Hall </persName>and <persName>Cashly </persName>fell out about a Divide and <persName>Hall </persName>Shot
him and Killd him Such is the fact the <persName>Spaniards </persName>nor <persName>Cashly </persName>was
Ever heard of again as to the Certainty I cant say,</p>

<p>In <date n="xx-xx-1822">1822 </date><persName>Bill Hall</persName> it apears Stold <persName>Danial McLain</persName>s horse at the
<placeName>nachez </placeName>which it apears was afterwards Proven at <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></p>

<p>Last year <persName>Jack and Bill Hall</persName> apeared in this <placeName>Settlement </placeName>at the
house of <persName>Jim Miller </persName>the Greatest Rogue in the world and they stood
accused of Joining a party to Rob <persName>Botts</persName> of his <persName>negroses </persName>I actually
found <persName>Jack Hall</persName> among the party armd but what was his intentions
I know not only from Report Probably Something was afterwards
Sworn to before <persName>McNeel</persName></p>

<p><persName>Jas Gaines </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>P. S. My news papers is sent to <persName>Col Cole</persName> intended also for your
perusal, I will Comply with the Request in your Letters and Send
a <persName>Surveyor </persName>so Soon as one Can be found I have urged a <persName>Jesse
Parker</persName> to go to your assistance who is a first Rate <persName>Black Smith</persName> I
am fitting out <persName>Wm Irwin</persName> a <persName>Gun Smith</persName>, and as far as I can serve
you Consistant with my duty and Limited abilities shall at all times
be at your service</p>

<p><persName>J.G.</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
