<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0390">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Maria Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 06-08-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Maria Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Hazel Run, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Natchitoches, LA</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 394-395
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-06-08">06-08-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Illness of Moses Austin. Interest in Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Hazel Run</placeName> <date when="1821-06-08">June the 8- 1821</date></p>

<p>I rote my dear <persName>Stephen </persName>by <persName>Mr Honey</persName> on the <date when="1821-06-03">third Inst</date> informing
him of his <persName>Father</persName>s Illness&#8212;and I now rite you by our old friend
<persName>Mr Bruffey</persName> and am truly sorry that I have nothing Encouraging to
communicate I found your poor <persName>Father </persName>very ill indeed, <persName>Dr. ben
Hiser [Bernhisel]</persName> thought his disorder dangerous, it being a Violent
attack of Inflamation on the brest and lungs, attended with a high
fever&#8212; the <persName>Dr</persName> staid a day and night blistered and bleed most
copiously and when he left us two days past I flatterd myself he was
much better&#8212; but oh my <persName>son </persName>I greatly fear it was only a delusion,
so apt are [we] to flatter ourselves with that which will contribute
to our happyness his fever has returned this day with great violence,
he breathes with much difficulty and seems in great distress boath in
body and mind&#8212;in short my son I feel much allarmed about him,
I shall send for the <persName>Dr</persName> by <persName>Mr B</persName> he is lately from <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
studied with <persName>Dr Physick</persName> and is well recommended by him and the
bord&#8212; his yoth and Inexperience is the only objection I have
against him, but our chief dependence must be in him who is only able
to save oh my god, thou has in thy great mercy heretofore 
supported him through many dangers&#8212;tryals and difficulties of various
kinds, extend thy mercys we beseech the and raise him once more
from a bed of sickness and thy grateful servants will sing praises
to thy name forever and ever&#8212; your <persName>Father </persName>had completed all his
business in this quarter much more to his satisfaction than he ever
expected to do&#8212;appeared to be surrounded with <persName>friends </persName>Anxious
for him to go on with his enerprise in the province <placeName>texes</placeName>&#8212; everyone
has the highest opinion of his plans and many only waiting till thay
know he has made the Establishment when they mean to follow him,
several young men has already gown and manjr now waiting to start<pb n="395"/>
with him all those things distracts his mind and increases his 
disordor he called me to his bed side and with much distress an 
difficulty of speech, beged me to tell you to take his place and if god in
his wisdom thought best to disappoint him in the accomplishment of
his wishes and plans formed for the benefit of his <persName>family</persName>, he prayed
him to extend his goodness to you and eneable you to go on with the
business in the same way he would have done had not sickness and oh
dreadful to think of perhaps death, prevented him from 
accomplishing&#8212; this my dear <persName>son </persName>is your fathers unhappy situation, and you
can better Judge of your <persName>Mother </persName>miserable feelings than she can
describe them, although my mind is filled with anxiety and my body
weied down with fatigue and distress&#8212; I will indulge the fond hope
of his recovery and communicate the pleasing intelligence to my dear
<persName>Stephen </persName>by the first opportunity&#8212; I was so disireous to be with your
<persName>Father </persName>when I heard of his illness&#8212;I did not take time to write to
your <persName>Brother</persName>, I inclosed his letter to you, by that you will know
his situation I hope the bill he sent on will be accepted in <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName>, when the poor fellow will be Liberated and once more
restored to his friends who will rejoice to see him tho poor and in
a different situation from what theay was when he left them. <persName>Emily</persName>
sends her moast affectionate love to you and would write if she had
time though you are a letter in debt&#8212; she has three lovely <persName>boys</persName>&#8212;
<persName>Austin </persName>grows very like you and is laying all parsiality aside the
most interesting child I ever saw&#8212; the infant is very butifull, I
only wish you could see it and you would thing so two, he is called
after <persName>Guy Morroson</persName>&#8212; farewell my son, heaven only knows what
events may take place before I write again the book of futurity is hid
from our eyes&#8212;for wise purposes and we ought to think it all for
the best&#8212; may god bless and prosper my dear son in every just and
Laudible undertaking is the sincere wishes of his ever affectionate but
unhappy anxious <persName>Mother </persName>                                                 </p>
<p> <persName>M Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed.]  <persName> Mr   Stephen   F.   Austin</persName>   <placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>   Attention
<persName>Mr Bruffy</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
