<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0128">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Timothy Phelps to Moses Austin, 09-28-1807</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Timothy Phelps</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-28">06-28-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Moses Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">St Genevieve, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 138-139
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1807-09-28">09-28-1807</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-28" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Lead business.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>St Genevieve</placeName> <date when="1807-09-28">28 Sept. 1807</date>&#8212;</p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>We arrived here safe <date when="1807-09-23">Friday 2 o.clock</date> we found <persName>Doctr Eliotts
Family</persName> much distressed on Account of their son <persName>Austin</persName>,s situation&#8212;
As he is removed from the Atmosphere of <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName>, I can,t but hope
his life may yet be spared. I was much surprised, to find that the
Load of lead, which I sent to you for (by <persName>P. Martan</persName>) was sent to
<persName>Charles Eliot</persName>, with directions to put with your Lead. I must depend
on receiving the Lead, due me from You, to make good the Payments
I have to make to <persName>Mr Spencer</persName>&#8212;and for the Hollow Ware. I find it
impossible to get any Carts to go after Lead at Present as they have
commenced getting in their Corn.   I have assured <persName>Mr. Spencer</persName> that I<pb n="139"/>
will pay him before he goes.&#8212;   <persName>Mr J. Pratt</persName>, I was told was the only
person in Town, who would pay Cash for Lead&#8212;I went to him with a
view to sell him some, the most he would offer me was $4. here-
said he has purchaced three Thousand at that&#8212;of course I said no
more_This afternoon a <persName>Gentleman from <placeName>St. Louis</placeName></persName> applied here to
purchase,   he wants from 20. to 25.000&#8212;1 offered him 2.000 at $5 for
<persName>Brother Daniel</persName>&#8212;I believe he will take it&#8212;and if he don,t supply
himself here will come out to the <persName>mines</persName>.   I shall direct him to you
had you not best sell him enough to Pay <persName>Madme Geronan</persName> or the <persName>French
Woman</persName> you owe?   there can then be no question with her about the
price   If he has it in three weeks, twill be soon enough   I have at last
gotten a laconic Answyer to my Letters from <persName>Mr. Haines</persName> N. York <date when="1807-08-10">10th
Aug.</date>&#8212;" the Drft. accepted by the <persName>Messrs. Austins</persName>, is accepted payable
in <placeName>N. York</placeName>,   they wrote me sometime ago that they were preparing
to send me the Amount of it by <persName>Elias A. Eliott</persName>&#8212;I recd. a letter this
day from <persName>John Jones, of <placeName>Vincennes</placeName></persName>, Informing me <persName>Mr. Eliott</persName> had
gone to <placeName>N. Orleans </placeName>with two boats laden with Lead and was bound
on to <placeName>N. York</placeName> and had express orders to pay me&#8212;I shall keep it, till
<date n="Fall-1807">fall</date>, if they do not discharge it by that time,   I then shull send it to
a friend in <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName> to collect for me&#8212;The Goods I had from you
is not sold, when they are sold, I will send you the particulars,   I
could not sell them without too great a sacrifice and have let them
lay."&#8212;I am a little surprised that <persName>Mr. Jones</persName> should have written him
on the subject&#8212;It may embarrass <persName>Austin </persName>(If he arrives there in
safety) very much.   I also fear <persName>Haines </persName>does not tell me true, 
respecting my furnature&#8212;Months before I left home, I gave him express
orders to sell it at auction, as it must be sold and unquestionably there
would be a loss&#8212;the sooner it was done the better,- as the articles
many of them would be injured by laying&#8212;besides I know he wanted
the Money under Such circumstances, is it not unaccountable he
should let them lay undisposed of.   It can not be so, he must want to
get into his hands all the Property he can,  I shall them be obliged to
take my leave of it.   I trust and believe you will join with me, in 
endeavoring to frustrate his Plans   However dishonest he might show
himself&#8212;   in this Business, nothing should induce me to withhold
from him one Cent of the Acceptance provided he would pay me the
Amount of sales of the furnature, which he origenally promised me.
this I believe to be Just and right and I think you will coincide in
Opinion                                                                        </p>

<p><persName>T. Phelps</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>NB. Please to hand the enclosed to <persName>Mrs. Austin</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Moses Austin Esqr-Merchant</persName>  <placeName>Mine a Burton</placeName>
By <persName>Mr H. Eliott</persName>&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
