<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0581">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Robert Leftwich to Stephen F. Austin, 04-30-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Robert Leftwich</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico City, MX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Monterey, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 633-634
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-04-30">04-30-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Thanks of Robert Leftwich and Haden Edwards for advice about procuring land grants. Mexican politics.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>City Mexico</placeName> <date when="1823-04-30">30th April [1823</date>]</p>
<p>Dear <persName>Friend</persName></p>

<p>I had the pleasure this morning to receive your esteemed favour
dated <placeName>Queretero </placeName><date when="1823-04-23">23d Instant</date>, and I am glad to hear that you are thus
far on your long journey.<pb n="634"/></p>

<p>I have to acknowledge your particular friendship for the enclosed
letter to <persName>Señor Arispe</persName> this is adding one more favour to the many
hundreds already received, I read your letter to <persName>Major Edwards</persName>
so far as it alluded to the land subject for which he begs to 
acknowledge your friendship, and we are both pleased with the advise you
have given for us to pursue in getting our business closed as the
highest proof that we could give you of our intense approbation of
your plan I need only say to you that we lost no time in presenting
your letter to Al <persName>Señor Arispe</persName> who appeared much pleased at 
receiving a line from you on receiving it he smiled and said it was
from you before he opened it, on reading it he gave the highest
assurances of his friendship and promised to use his exertions on our
behalf in which I believe him to be sincere. It is our intention to
reward him handsomely for his trouble which in addition to what
you said to him on that subject we have given him further assurance
to that effect what appeared perfectly congenial to his feelings.</p>

<p>The <persName>Emperor </persName>left <placeName>Tulancingo </placeName>on the <date when="1823-04-20">20th instant</date> and is to embark
in the <persName>British </persName>brig Thomas. Generals <persName>Bravo </persName>and <persName>Victoria </persName>are to set
for <placeName>Mexico </placeName>as soon as <persName>Iturbide </persName>sets sail.</p>

<p><persName>General Gurera</persName> arrived at <placeName>St Augustine</placeName> on the <date when="1823-04-28">28th</date> recovering of
his wound slowly.</p>

<p>business in <persName>congress </persName>goes on in the old stile business of every 
description slow and mañana and passado mañana as usual.</p>

<p>There is nothing transpired here since your departure, should
anything occur worthy of remark you shall receive it without delay.</p>

<p>I have the pleasure to inform you that I am enjoying perfect
health tho feel considerable weakness in my right arm which you
may perceive from my great imperfection in my hand writing.</p>

<p>Please write me from every point when it may be convenient for
you to do so. Should it be in my power to serve you before or on my
return to the <placeName>United States</placeName> I assure you that you have nothing more
to do than to advise me of your wishes.</p>

<p>In whatever part of the world that chance may take you, you have
my warmest wishes for your health prosperity and happiness.</p>

<p><persName>ROBERT LEFTWICH</persName></p>

<p>P. S. I regret that you should have met with any difficulty on
your departure from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>believing that the man who kept our
horses treated you rascally I have taken my horses away and <persName>Rogers</persName>
has attempted to see him to day to ask an explanation of his conduct
but did not see him he charged me for two days more than my horses
was under his care which I would not pay.</p>

<p><persName>R. L.</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] Al <persName>Señor Don Estovan Austin</persName> <placeName>Monterey </placeName>Tierra a
<placeName>Texas</placeName>.   <persName>Maj Burne</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
