<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0747">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Anthony R. Clarke to Stephen F. Austin, 05-22-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Anthony R. Clarke</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Atoyac, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, TX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 796-798
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-05-22">05-22-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Americans in east Texas object to the establishment of Catholicism as the State religion. Opposition to moving to the interior. Bastrop and Austin suspected of having selfish interest in this. Horse thieves.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Atoyac </placeName><date when="1824-05-22">22 May 1824</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>your favour of the <date when="1824-04-20">20 ultimo</date> was handed me by y[our] <persName>Brother</persName>
who spent the night here I read the out lines for the Federal 
Constitution, the <persName>Ammericans </persName>can find no fait with any part of it but<pb n="797"/>
the 4th Article,&#8212;<persName>Mr Dill</persName> and <persName>Capt Gains</persName> have returned from <placeName>St
Antonio</placeName> they speak very violently against the <persName>Counsel </persName>at that
place as being self created and having no power, etc <persName>Gains </persName>took
out a petition signed by about 150 men. I saw nothing in this that
would be considered wrong or improper in the <placeName>United States</placeName> but
<persName>Gains </persName>states that it was violently opposed in the <persName>Counsel </persName>
particularly by <persName>Baron de Bastrop</persName> who he states is opposed to this <placeName>District</placeName>
being settled by the <persName>Americans </persName>and that he rules the <persName>Counsel </persName>that
he <persName>Gains </persName>argued and disputed with the <persName>Counsel </persName>for 15 days but
could get nothing done owing to the opposition of the <persName>Barron</persName>, the
oppinion now circulating is that the <persName>Barron</persName>s opposition to this
<placeName>settlement </placeName>is owing to self interest that if he can break up this
settlement that numbers would go to the <placeName>Brassos </placeName>and the more
<persName>Setlers </persName>the more money for him as <persName>Survayor General</persName>&#8212;the answer
to the <persName>petitions </persName>and the insinuations of those persons returned from
<placeName>St Antonio</placeName> has caused much uneasiness to the <persName>setlers</persName>, as soon as I
learnt those things I proceeded with one of my <persName>neighbours </persName>to
<placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>and had sufficient influence with <persName>Juan Segean</persName> (who is
acknowledged by <persName>Sálceuda [Saucedo]</persName> as the first <persName>Alcade</persName>) to get
him to issue a notice to all the <persName>Setlers </persName>in the <placeName>District </placeName>who wished
to live in the <placeName>Mexican provinces</placeName> as quiet peaceable, citizens and to
hold themselves in obedience to the laws and regulations of said
Government to come forward on the <date when="1824-06-06">6th day of June</date> to swear to
support the Mexican Constitution&#8212;this will satisfy all parties and
produce peace and harmony in the Country <persName>Mr Dill</persName> I conclude
you are acquainted with if you have been in his company. As to
<persName>Capt Gains</persName> I can truly say that in thirty years intercours with
mankind I have never been so much deceived and cheated by any
person as him. I state to you in confidence and I wish you to 
consider my statement as confidential, that this discription is his true
carractor, that he is a bladder of wind seeking popularrity that he
possesses a very inventive genius is very deceatfull and a most
abominable lyer if you detect him in a lie he will deny it without
a blush and produce such argiments as to convince a person not
acquainted with him that it was impossible that he could make
such a statement he has told a different story at allmost every
house he stoped at since his return, he is becoming generally
known, under those circumstances you may rest assur'd that we will
not permit him to ruin the <placeName>settlement </placeName>by sowing the seeds of 
dissention among the <persName>Inhabitants</persName>,&#8212;I have been informed as a secret
that he has purchased a League of land of you but that he does
not wish the people of this <placeName>settlement </placeName>to know it&#8212;I have received<pb n="798"/>
a letter from <persName>Seceuda </persName>the <persName>firs alcade</persName> and <persName>president of the Counsel
at <placeName>St Antonio</placeName></persName> he informs me that no person but a <persName>native of the
provinces</persName> can hold any office in this <placeName>Country</placeName>, of course I am no
longer an <persName>Alcalde</persName>, this is unfortionate for the <placeName>settlements </placeName>for since
the election of <persName>American Alcaldes</persName> we have broke up two gangs of
<persName>theives</persName>, <persName>Jim Millan</persName> and his <persName>gang </persName>and one <persName>gang </persName>on the <placeName>Teneha</placeName> 
consisting of <persName>Ephraim Brown</persName> a <persName>Cousin </persName>of his by the name of <persName>Brown</persName>
from <placeName>Kentucky </placeName><persName>old Hogan</persName> and his <persName>nephew </persName><persName>Walter Hogan</persName> they
fled from justice and could not be taken some of their property was
brought in and sold to pay the cost of the guard and stolen 
property, since that time no property has been molested for a number
of months untill a few weeks past four Horses has been Stolen from
this <placeName>neighbourhood</placeName>, three <persName>Americans </persName>met a <persName>Spaniard </persName>on this side
the <placeName>Trinity </placeName>and traded to him two Gray mares one belongin to
a M<persName>r Carter</persName> the other to <persName>Mrs Brown</persName> one is still living the <persName>widow
Brown</persName>s is dead she had but one liors and mare, they had been
wrode to death, one of the men is supposed to be by the name of
Lane the other had red hair the third I have no description of,
<persName>Mr Fulcher</persName> has lost two creatures on the same night, he thinks
it possible that <persName>Brittian Bailey</persName> may have taken them as he left
this country about the same time and was not seen on the Rhoad
there is no evidence or other cause to susspect him than a knowledge
of his former carracter nor do I wish that the breath of suspetion
should light on him if inocent, I enclose a discription of <persName>Fulcher</persName>s
Mares and wish you to send it to <persName>Josiah H. Bell Esqr.</persName> I am 
informed he lives adjoining <placeName><persName>Bailey</persName>s</placeName> and could assertain if he has those
Horses or had traded them on the <placeName>Brassos</placeName>,&#8212;<persName>Mr Fulcher</persName> feals 
confident that if <persName>Mr Bell</persName> find the Mares that he will secure the property
you may think I have written a long letter but if you reflect that I
feel confident that I am writing to a man that feels an interest for
the settlement and a friend to all good <persName>Americans </persName>in the province
I know you will pardon me&#8212;</p>

<p>accept my best wishes for your health and happiness,</p>

<p><persName>Anthy R. Clarke </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Col Stephen. F. Austin</persName> <placeName>St Phillipe de Austin Brassos</placeName>&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
