<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0776">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>P. T. Dimmitt to Stephen F. Austin, 06-15-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>P. T. Dimmitt</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Bexar, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 832-834
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-06-15">06-15-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Defending Austin's right to collect payment for settling on lands in the colony. Hostility of certain agitators.   Father Garza wants a tax. Slavery. Bastrop.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Baxer </placeName><date n="06-xx-1824">June [about 15] 1824</date>.</p>

<p><persName>Mr Austin</persName> Sr Afew days sence I was inform that you had much troble
and difficulty with the <persName>Citizens of your <placeName>Coloney</placeName></persName> conserning thare
Lands but I am so badley informed on the Subject that I am not
able to from [form] an opinion I was informed that <persName>Lt. Branom
</persName>stated to the <persName>Inhabitants of the <placeName>Two Rivers</placeName></persName> that thay had not the
Eight to pay more than $30 Dollars for every League Square and
he went so fare as to Say that you ware deceving and swinling the
people and I have bin alarmed at your Situation nowing the men you
have to deal with, me and the <persName>Barron </persName>had a long Conversation on
the Subject I assure you I had some apprehenson that you would
have Much difficulty with those <persName>Gent</persName>. immediately after thay left
this place from a Grat maney observations which was maid before
thay left this plase for your plase, I believe <persName>Mr Peck</persName> and <persName>Price </persName>maid
maney observations to your disadvantage <persName>Mosqus </persName>and maney others<pb n="833"/>
in this plase are your <persName>enemeys </persName>Sr the <persName>Barron </persName>is your <persName>friend </persName>to every
extent Sr I am not in a situation to doo by him as he done by me</p>

<p>Sr your friendship towards me is that of acquaintance a <persName>friend </persName>and
that of a farther and I consider you as one Sr it is not necessary for
me to express my sentiments of my Grat Intres and friendship that
I hold for you Sr in the futur you must judge me by my acts and
conduct towards you and for you to find the rail sentiments and
principles of my boosum I will drop this Subject and let it live in
the brest of the worthey Sr since <persName>Lt Branom</persName> started down I felt 
desirous of Hering from you I have concluded he would play the devil
and I have thought that the fruits of your 3 Years hard labor
would be blasted by the envious and ambisious Sr I now the Grounds
on which you stand I Recd that information on my return to this
piase but that is with me as it is with you for you onley to Ree a
Beggers pension wich <persName>congress </persName>allowed you for 3 Years Hard, labor
and expences it is out of the qustion and befor I would be imposed
on by the ungratfull <persName>inhabitants of the <placeName>Coloney</placeName></persName> I would at once Dam
the Hole I would not permit the Interisted and ambicious Blood
Suckers live from the benifits of my exertions and labor that you
have spent in the 3 last Years pass, Sr you must forgyive my daring
Diction to you but say to your Self, that it is from the Reflection of
Good feelings and for a man to look around on and vew mankinds
ingratitude for what doe we hesitate or hop[e] to pay those 
carracters eavel for eavel and not comply with commanments as it is
not within our power to revenge our selves of envey and malice</p>

<p>I will say nothing more on this subject of this worlds 
unfathfulness and ingratitude one to each other may every Mans probity
end according as his Inward principles stand within him Leaving
those principles to be judgd by the Supream Power who is wise
just and impaseal, the ammount I am informed that you are bound
to recd for every League Square it will not pay the amt it has
cost you not onley that the Grat troble and time you have spent
in regulating each mans Track of land Sr if I had the conducting
of the <placeName>settlement </placeName>I would Settle only 200 <persName>famileys </persName>instead of 300
if the <persName>settlers of the <placeName>coloney</placeName></persName> would not comply with your terms. I
was informed the other day <persName>Lt Branom</persName> preposed settling one 
<persName>spanard </persName>betwen every <persName>american </persName>The <persName>B. [Baron]</persName> is your <persName>friend </persName>but
complains of some little first plase he says he wrote you to lay off
one league of land for his friend <persName>Laboom </persName>and one for each of his
<persName>children </persName>and him self which he says you did not and some other
things which I am not able to find out and from what I am able to
learn from him he wishes that the <persName>inhabitants </persName>to support him
while in the legislature, If the <persName>peple of the <placeName>Coloney</placeName></persName> doo not support
him I am of an opinion he will not be able to go   <persName>Mosques </persName>and<pb n="834"/>
many others in this plase are your open and dec[l]ared <persName>enemys </persName>
<persName>Padrey Garsey</persName> wishes to rais a tax or a contribution from the <persName>Settlers</persName>
I now not for what perpis he also stated as you were receiving a
high price for your lands he thought you could contribute to him?
this observation was maid from a suppose chat he had with <persName>Lt.
Branom</persName> on his return from your plase he would have bin asked
for an explination but for fere of some danger rising from an
Enquire it was delaid the <persName>Padry </persName>is your friend from what I am
able to assertain</p>

<p>There is no Political News in this plase the <persName>Barron </persName>would write
you but he [is] at present very much ocupied at presant he will
leve her[e] in 10 days for your plase, the <persName>Barron </persName>send his best
compliments to you</p>

<p>Sr you will be so good as not to for git my little busness I wish
you to reserve a league of land <placeName>below <persName>Bell</persName>s</placeName> some piase and one for
me farther   I want them as low down as possible</p>

<p>The non admishion of Slavery has distress me very much, The
<persName>B.</persName> preposes maney remadays and proposials to <persName>Congress </persName>for the
admishion of Slavry in this <placeName>Province </placeName>I cannot coincide with him
in opinion thay may possible be logical founded on the best, and
most mature reflection and experience, it will rest with you to
plan the present and future happiness and properiey [prosperity]
of the <placeName>coloney </placeName>(for the ingratitud of the <persName>inhabitance</persName>) which they
are about to pay you Sr you will forgive me for desiring you to
attend to my little busness with <persName>Pettus </persName>etc and my land</p>

<p><persName>P. T. DlMMITT</persName></p>

<p>NB my hand is very unstadey to write as Yet</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
