<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0414">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Antonio Martinez, 10-13-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Antonio Martinez
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nackitosh, LA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 419-421
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-10-13">10-13-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Hundreds from Missouri, Kentucky, and elsewhere want land in Texas. Suggests his own appointment as emigration agent for the Government. Protests against other grants within the limits assigned to him.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Nackitosh </placeName><date when="1821-10-13">October 13, 1821</date>&#8212;</p>
<p>His <persName>Excellency Governor Martinez</persName>,</p>

<p>Sir I had the honor of addressing you a letter dated on 
<date when="1821-10-12">yesterday</date>, giving an account of my proceedings relative to the <placeName>new Colony</placeName>.
I now write you on a Subject of deep interest to the progress of the
new <placeName>Settlements in Texas</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>On my arrival here I found near one hundred Letters from the
<placeName>neighbourhood </placeName>of where I formerly lived in <placeName>upper Louisiana</placeName> (now
called <placeName>Missouri</placeName>) and many from <placeName>Kentucky </placeName>and other places 
requesting information relative to settling in the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>,
and I am convinced that I could take on <persName>fifteen hundred families</persName>
as easily as <persName>three hundred</persName> if permitted to do so&#8212;</p>

<p>The distance to <placeName>St Antonio</placeName> is so great and the journey is 
considered so hazardous and expensive that men in moderate 
circumstances are deterred from going in person to apply for permission
to settle&#8212;and there are many other obstacles in the way, I have
therefore thought that the settlement of the Country wd be greatly
facilitated, and kind and character of those who emigrate would
be much better, if the whole superintendence of the Emigration
from the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> was intrusted to one <persName>agent </persName>whose general knowledge
of the American character, and particularly of the <persName>people of the
<placeName>western country</placeName></persName> and also of the situation and lands of the <placeName>Province
of Texas</placeName> would enable him to conduct the formation of the settle-<pb n="420"/>
ment with advantage to the <persName>Government </persName>and satisfaction to the
<placeName>Settlers</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Considering that the first effort towards Colonising the Proc. by
<persName>citizens from the <placeName>U. S,</placeName></persName> is made by me, and that after having 
explored the <placeName>sea coast</placeName> I shall have a full Knowledge of the Country,
and considering also that the public stations I have filled in <placeName>M.
[Missouri]</placeName> and <placeName>A. [Arkansas]</placeName> (having been for many years a 
Member of the legislature of the former and one of the Judges of the
Court in the latter) has enabled me to form very extensive and
general acquaintance with the <persName>people of the <placeName>western country</placeName></persName>, and
also that my former residence for many years under the <persName>Spanish
Govt</persName>, in <placeName>upper Louisiana</placeName> has made me some what familiar with the
laws and customs I have supposed that I could probably effect as
much towards settling <placeName>Texas </placeName>with useful citizens as any other man,
I therefore respectfully petition that I be permitted to extend the
settlements to the <placeName>Guadaloupe </placeName>and <placeName>St Marcos Rivers</placeName> on the west
and to the <placeName>Trinity </placeName>and <placeName>St. Jacinto</placeName> on the East-</p>

<p>Should this plan for the appointment of a <persName>general Commissioner</persName>
or <persName>Agent </persName>for the <placeName>Province </placeName>be adopted I would respectfully suggest
that it would greatly facilitate the objects of the appointment if
he was to have pretty extensive discretionary powers as to the 
distributing of lands, so as to save the delay and expense of applying
to the<persName> Gv.</persName> for instructions relative to each <persName>settler </persName>and that he be
authorized to issue certificates to the <placeName>settlers </placeName>stating (under such
limits as the <persName>Gv.</persName> may deem proper) the quantity of land and the
place where he is to receive it&#8212;these certificates could be a guide to
the <persName>Surveyor Genl of the <placeName>Province</placeName></persName> in laying off the lands, and the
returns would thus be all made by the <persName>surveyor Genl</persName> and the <persName>Comr</persName>
and the <persName>Gv </persName>would only have those two <persName>officers </persName>to transact the 
business with instead of the hundreds that would trouble them if each
<placeName>settler </placeName>was to apply for himself individually. I would also 
respectfully suggest that the <persName>commissioner </persName>be authorized to exact from
each <placeName>settler </placeName>a sufficient per cent on the land grantd to compensate
him for his trouble and expense in attending to the business&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Mr Davidson</persName> who returned a few days since from <persName>St Antonio</persName>
informs me that applications have been made for grants of two
and three leagues square on the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>. I would respectfully
suggest to your <persName>Excellency </persName>that it may create some confusion if
<placeName>grants </placeName>are made within the tract of country in which my settlement
is forming&#8212;    I have promised the <placeName>settlers </placeName>that the first who go<pb n="421"/>
on shall have the first choice, and if the same land which they are
occupying and actually improving is granted to others without any
notice to me, it will involve me in great difficulty with <persName>Emigrants</persName>,
and produce a degree of dissatisfaction amongst them which will
have an unfortunate influence with others, in retarding the 
settlement, I have no objection to the <persName>Genm </persName>who have applied and should
be happy to receive them as <persName>settlers</persName>, but unless the organization of
the colony is confined to one source some confusion will necessarily
arise</p>

<p><persName>S. F. A.</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
