<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0537">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Arthur G. Wavell to Stephen F. Austin, 09-10-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Arthur G. Wavell</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Mexico City, MX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 544-545
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-09-10">09-10-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Experience with pirates in the Gulf.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>On board french Brig L Azema</placeName> at Sea <date when="1822-09-10">10th Septr 1822</date>  </p>
<p>Dear <persName>Judge</persName></p>

<p>Fate has played me the most scurvy trick I ever yet suffered&#8212;
on the third being close to the <placeName>Island of Cuba</placeName> we perceived a small
Schooner standing toward us I proposed that we should prepare
to fight if as we suspected she proved a <persName>Pirate </persName>this however all
declared impossible indeed I found that we had only 4 small swivels
3 carbines 1 sabre and 1 Pistol she fired a gun and swept toward us
it being nearly calm to attempt to escape was useless she hoisted <placeName>Ud
States</placeName> Colors we ours (<placeName>French</placeName>) they boarded us armed with sabers
and knives   demanded all our cash saying if we find one dollar<pb n="545"/>
concealed we will burn the ship with you all in it which indeed we
would do were you of any other nation if of the <placeName>Ud States</placeName> you
would instantly be set on fire as soon as we had taken all we want.
We gave up all our cash since they opened the hold boxes cabins
lockers etc etc searched every where and took away as the <persName>Captn</persName>
tells me Cochineal, cash including (1700 mine), sails, ropes, Indigo,
all our stock arms, knives, Powder, Watches, Jewellery, etc etc to
the amount of 60,000 Drs they ordered us to stand off all night and
themselves stood in for the shore 2 days afterwards 5th being nearly
in the same place since the <persName>Captain </persName>notwithstanding my 
remonstrances would not stand out to sea and the current together with
our bad sailing prevented our getting to the Eastward they again
boarded us, called us Puñateros etc for not quitting the <placeName>coast </placeName>menaced
our lives particularly mine as an <persName>Englishman </persName>and <persName>Patriot Offr</persName>
tying ropes round the necks of me and the <persName>Captn </persName>almost half hanged
me as they swore they would and whilst in this situation stroke me
with the flat and iron scabbards of their sabers asking where our
money was concealed they then went carrying off all my cloathes
and several other things belonging to the ship with the exception
of one or two they are I believe all old <persName>Spaniards </persName>about 50 state
they have a <persName>companion </persName>far larger and as we saw two falúas such
<persName>scoundrels </persName>never before breathed nor was such a system of Piracy
ever before carried on or could be except amongst such villians as
<persName>Spaniards </persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><placeName>Charleston S C:</placeName> <date when="1822-09-20">20th Septr 22</date></p>
<p>We arrived here on the <date when="1822-09-17">17th</date> in order to repair [our ship be]fore
we proceed to <placeName>Europe </placeName>but I shall be [quit of] this dble [damnable] brig
which sails not so fast as a dungbarge and has every other 
disadvantage and go to <placeName>England </placeName>on board the English ship London a
noble bessel and very fine sailer wherefore I shall hope to reach
<placeName>Liverpool </placeName>about the <date when="1822-11-01">1st of Novr</date> Let me know constantly how you
get on and believe me ever yours</p>

<p><persName>A. Wavell.</persName></p>
<p>by the bye read if you can the <placeName>Charleston Gazette</placeName> of the <date when="1822-09-18">18th</date> or
<date when="1822-09-19">19th </date>of this month which gives a full detail of what has happened
to us &#8212;</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Sor Dn Estevan F. Austin</persName> en la <placeName>Ciudad de Mexico</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
