<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0376">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Baron de Bastrop, 01-26-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Baron de Bastrop
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nachitoches</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 379-380
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-01-26">01-26-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Loss through failure of Bank of St. Louis. Plans for return to Texas. Warns against illegal trade.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            
<p>Near <placeName>Nachitoches </placeName><date when="1821-01-26">Jany 26th, 1821</date></p>
<p>My Good Sr</p>

<p>On my arrival at <placeName><persName>Mr Castleman</persName>s</placeName> I wrote you both by <persName>Mr Quirk</persName>
and by the <persName>officer </persName>about to return inclosing you a <placeName>Newspaper </placeName>the
only one I could then command, being told <date when="1821-01-25">yesterday </date>that the 
<persName>Spanish officer</persName>&#8212;had not yet returned I again profit by the same oppory
to make further communications to you I have nothing of interests
to communicate of a Public nature except what you will find in the
<placeName>Daly papers</placeName>. As to myself&#8212;I have learned that the total failure of
the <persName>Bank of <placeName>St Louis</placeName></persName> has involved me in a loss of (30 000) thirty
thousand Dollars investments I had made in said <persName>Bank</persName>&#8212;this 
unhappy event has Compelled me to return to the <placeName>upper country</placeName> with
out Delay&#8212;and settle and save the balance of my property, I shall
return to <placeName>Nachitoches </placeName>by <date n="05-xx-1821">May next</date>.</p>

<p>I mentioned in my last that I wished a passport to leave with my
property at the <placeName>mouth of the Colorado</placeName> and Deposit my property
untill I could Visit <hi rend="italic"><placeName>St Antonio</placeName></hi> and receive the will of the <persName>Governor</persName>,
and further instructions the property I shall bring will be farming
<hi rend="italic">Utensils </hi>and other articles such as Iron Ware Tin Ware and Crates
of <placeName>Liverpool </placeName>ware and Salt only sufficient to purchase Stock for a
farm as to <persName>Indians </persName>in that quarter I can make myself safe in a few
days as I shall have 12 or 15 <persName>Hired hands</persName> for whose conduct, I will
be accountable If you can obtain a permit for me to land with my
property at the place I have requested to say <placeName>Mouth of the <hi rend="italic">Colorado</hi>
</placeName>and permission is given to Establish a Town and Settle <persName>300 families</persName>
One year would make a Change in the State and condition of <placeName>Saint
Antonio</placeName> beyond any thing, you can now believe I have a full 
confidence that a <placeName>Town at the Mouth of Colorado</placeName> in three years would
become of the utmost Consequence and an interest in this <placeName>Town</placeName>
would give some thousand of Dollars to the <placeName>friends </placeName>of this 
establishment without any violation of Confidence or injury to <persName>Government</persName>,
people of the first class would immediately Resort to this 
Establishment with property that would secure their fidelity to the <persName>King </persName>and
Constitution of <placeName>Spain</placeName>.</p>

<p>I shall, life and Health admiting most undoubtedly return from
the <placeName>upper Country</placeName> by <date n="05-xx-1821">May Next</date> whin I wish to remove with all my
property to the <placeName>Colorado </placeName>and I hope you will have the power to 
obtain a pasport for me, and my household to land at that place, the<pb n="380"/>
object of which will be to commence farming Tho <persName>Governor </persName>was
pleased to say that if I returned I might depend on his friendship&#8212;
on my part I assure you that I shall make use of every Exertion in
my power to promote the interest of the Government, that gives me
protection.</p>

<p>I hope my Dear Sr. you will pardon the liberty I have taken in this
calling on your friendship&#8212; I trust the day will arrive when&#8212; I
shall have it in my power to make full and <hi rend="italic">Satisfactory </hi>
compensation.</p>

<p>I cannot close this letter without again reminding you that both
Leut. Sandival and yourself are in danger of being drawn into 
difficulty from the extreem imprudence of Kirkham This unguarded
man has told with out reserve that any amount of goods he took to
St Anthonio would be received by Leut. Sandivall into his store
this language has been so many times told that I have been questioned
on the subject and altho I knew nothing of Kirkham ingagements
with Leut. Sandival yet I took the liberty to say that Kirkham had
misstated facts and that <hi rend="italic">no </hi>friend of his at Saint Antonio <hi rend="italic">would</hi>
expose himself to ruin, to serve <hi rend="italic">him </hi>he has as I am told stated that
his friends was to have 80 or 90 Mules ready for him in march
next&#8212; I have mentioned these things that every Necessary 
precaution may be made use of to prevent injury resulting therefrom</p>

<p>I have inclosed every paper I could collect that contained any 
information of moment to you or the Government you will see the
resolution of <placeName>Ky</placeName> on <placeName>Spain</placeName>s affairs altho the Legislature have 
instructed there Representatives in <persName>Congress </persName>to oppose the Trety 
between <placeName>Spain </placeName>and the <placeName>United States</placeName> yet it is the most general beleif
that it will be accepted if ratified by the <persName>Spanish Government</persName>, War
will not take place with the <placeName>U States</placeName> and <placeName>Spain </placeName>unless some of the
<placeName>Western States</placeName> have power to rule the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Union </placeName></hi>the <placeName>Eastern and Middle
States</placeName> are in opposition to extending the limits of the <placeName>United States</placeName>
and War with <placeName>Spain</placeName></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">MA</hi></p>

<p><date when="1821-01-28">Jany 28 Year 21</date></p>
<p>To the <persName>Honorable Baron Bastrop</persName></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">At the <placeName>Capital of the Province of Texas</placeName></hi></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
