<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0427">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Emigrants, 11-22-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Emigrants
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 432-433
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Agreement</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-11-22">11-22-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Agreement between Austin and 14 emigrants.  Sound coast and rivers of Texas, build cabins and a stockade, and cultivate and harvest corn in return for expenses and land.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Agreement with <persName>Emigrants</persName></p>

<p>Know all men, by these presents, that whereas <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
is about forming a <placeName>Colony </placeName>under the authority of the <persName>Government
of <placeName>New Spain</placeName></persName> in the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>; and that the Conditions and
compensations to be allowed to each person emigrating with Said
<persName>Austin</persName>, and who becoms a party to this agreement by signing his
name thereto, may be fully understood, the following conditions and
Stipulations are agreed upon&#8212;</p>

<p>In the first place it is agreed that each person who makes himself
a party to this agreement Shall place himself under the direction of
Said <persName>Austin</persName>, and as Soon as a vessel is provided, Shall go on board
the Same, and aid in taking the soundings of the <placeName>coast</placeName>, and <placeName>mouths
of the Rivers from Galveston</placeName> to the <placeName>Mouth of the Gaudaloupe River</placeName>,
Should it be deemed necessary to explore that far, and while on board
Said vessel to attend to the orders of the <persName>Captain</persName>, and Conduct 
themselves in an orderly manner, after the <placeName>Coast </placeName>is Sounded, the said
<persName>Emigrants </persName>will land under the directions of said <persName>Austin </persName>and remain
in his employ untill the first day of <date when="1822-12-01">December 1822</date> during which
time they are to assist in building Cabbins and a Stockade, should
one be deemed necessary, and to clear fence, and cultivate at least five
acres of corn Each of <placeName>Prairie </placeName>or <placeName>untimbered land</placeName>, and to gather the
crop into <placeName>Corn Houses</placeName>&#8212;Each <persName>Emigrant </persName>will furnish his own arms,
and agrees to conduct himself as becomes a good citizen, and to be
faithfull to the <persName>Government of the Country</persName> so long as he lives under
it&#8212;</p>

<p>Now in consideration of the above services, to be rendered in good
faith by each person becoming a party to this agreement, it is agreed
by the said <persName>Austin</persName>, on his part that he will furnish a vessel for the
transportation of said <persName>Emigrants </persName>to Said <placeName>Settlement</placeName>, that he will
furnish Farming Tools, Oxen, or Mules, and Provisions and Seeds<pb n="433"/>
for said establishment at his own Expenee, from the day the 
<persName>Emigrants </persName>leave <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> in said Vessel.</p>

<p>The said <persName>Austin </persName>also agrees and obligates himself to deliver Each
of Said <persName>Emigrants </persName>who fulfill this agreement, and duly cultivate
five or more acres of corn as before stated, the one half of all the corn
or other produce raised by them as aforesaid, and to Secure to each
of them a tract of land of Six hundred and forty acres to be laid
off in the Same manner that the lands for the other <persName>Emigrants </persName>is,
Which land shall be free of expences, also a Town lot shall be given
to each.</p>

<p>In testimony of their agreeing to the above stipulation, the 
undersigned have set their hands and Seals to this instrument this <date when="1821-11-22">22d day
of November 1821 Eighteen hundred and twenty one</date>. The word "or
more" in the 10th line of this page inserted, and the erasure after
the word "expences" in the last line made before signing&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>       [Seal]</p>

<p><persName>Patrick Toole </persName>              [Seal]</p>

<p><persName>John Muligen</persName>               [Seal]</p>

<p><persName>Peter Wing</persName>                   [Seal]</p>

<p><persName>John Hirst  </persName>                  [Seal]</p>

<p><persName>Thomas B Harrison</persName>    [Seal]</p>

<p><persName>Edw G Williams</persName></p>

<p><persName>Bernard Phillips</persName></p>

<p><persName>Isaiah M. Alexander</persName></p>

<p><persName>James Baird</persName></p>

<p><persName>Wm. S. Lewis</persName>            [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Hudson Hughes</persName></p>

<p><persName>William Prestage</persName></p>

<p><persName>Wm W Little</persName>            [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>James Nelson</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
