<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0035">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen Austin to James Austin, 01-24-1799</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-21">06-21-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Philadelphia, PA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Austin Ville, VA</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 45-46
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1799-01-24">01-24-1799</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Purchase of supplies.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Philada </placeName><date when="1799-01-14">24th Janry 1799</date>.</p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>your favor of the <date when="1799-01-14">14th Inst</date> is Just receivd and observe the 
Contents&#8212;I hear nothing of <persName>Frisbie </persName>he may Possibly be at the 
<placeName>Eastward</placeName>&#8212;unless I soon hear of him shall Send his Acct to have a Suit
Brot by <persName>Mr Woodward</persName>&#8212;I am glad to hear that <persName>Hall </persName>and <persName>Harry </persName>is
safe arivd&#8212;you Say nothing of the Horses&#8212;the Bay Horse <persName>Harry</persName>
Rode as I sopose him to be old I think you had best Sell unless<pb n="46"/>
his Performance out should Convince you of his Usefullness to us&#8212;
the other is a Tough beast I have no Doubt and will be a Match with
<persName>Ambrose </persName>Little Mare&#8212;I hope <persName>Hall </persName>will do well in the Shop with
<persName>Ambrose</persName>&#8212;I shall Send you Some steel or order <persName>Mr Pain</persName> to Send
you Some from <placeName>Richmond</placeName>&#8212;but the shot not haveing Come on so
that I Can get money from it has Quite Distress me&#8212;and I See
Now its Impossible to Send a Waggon from this as nothing but
Cash will Procure Waggon and Horses and My Demands here of
a Debt to <persName>Wycoff </persName>and <persName>Harrison </persName>I have been obligd to pay here of
<persName>Moses Austin</persName> has at this time of great Scarsity of Cash hurt me
Much&#8212; I advancd 100 Dollar for Salt in <date n="09-xx-1798">Sept Last</date> which is at Last
got to <placeName>Richmond</placeName>&#8212;Say 25 Sacks there is also a Large Box of Ready
Made Cloaths Coats vests and Breeches of the Latter 80 prs I
have also sent two Bushels of Red Clover Seed to <persName>Mr Pain</persName> these
things you want Extreemly and part of the Salt you Could Sell
for Cash&#8212;and the Cloverseed if Possible must be with you to Sow
in all <date n="03-xx-1800">March </date>which time I find will answer to Sow it as well as any
other in the year Amongst the Rye I expect you must sow it your
self or <persName>Mr Tanden </persName>as it [must] be sowed with the Greatest Care&#8212;
and one Bushels will sow Ten Acres so that you can sow 20 Acres
only and this of the best of the Land which is I Expect Round and
next the <placeName>Barn</placeName>&#8212;if any of the <placeName>Fields on the East of the Street</placeName> will
answer sow part of that My Intention was to have sent sufficient
to have Sowd both Fields and som for <persName>Capt Newell</persName> but want of
Cash to Purchese has Prevented me Sending but two Bushels which
Cost 10 Dollar Cash pr Bushel&#8212;when you sow it Divide your seed
into 20 or 40 parts&#8212; you Must sow a Little more than 3 Quarts to
one Acre which is 3 half pints to one Quarter of an Acre and to
begin Mark out one 4th of an acre and try how you can gage that
and by that sow all the other&#8212;as to the Hides get them Taned on
the best Terms you Can as I see I shall not be able to send out a
<persName>Tanner </persName>at all Cant you Hire a Waggon to go to <placeName>Lynchbourgh</placeName>
with a load of shot and Bring up the Box of Cloaths the Seed and
the Balance in Salt and pay them some goods some Lead and a
Little Salt&#8212;I wish this to be effected as I shall request <persName>Mr Pain</persName> to
forward all with him to <placeName>Lynchbourgh </placeName>which if the Weather is
moderate he will do when some Steel may be got we are all well
and hope this will find you all the Same with Compt to all I am
your</p>

<p><persName>S Austin</persName></p>

<p>if you can Hire one Team I think you Can Man[age] one Team
of your own and Send <persName>Ellick </persName>with it to bring up Salt&#8212;</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr James Austin Post Master <placeName>Austin Ville 
Virginia</placeName>.</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
