<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0458">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Daniel Dunklin to Stephen F. Austin, 12-25-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Daniel Dunklin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-12">07-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Burton Mine, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Colorado, TX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 455-456
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-12-25">12-25-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Wants information concerning form and stability of government, productions, attitude of people toward Americans, etc.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mine a Burton [Missouri]</placeName> <date when="1821-12-25">December 25th- 1821</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>This day, from its celebrity as a Holy-day, in the <persName>Christian </persName>
Religion, as also the inclemency of the weather, has become a leisure
day with me, in my usual avocations, and have concluded to employ
it in part in an address [to] you, which I hope you find as 
convenient to answer as me to ask.</p>

<p>The subject proposed is the <placeName>"Province of Texas"</placeName> It has become
a subject of considerable interest in this section of <placeName>Missouri</placeName>. All
those who once experienced the gratuity of the <persName>Spanish 
Government</persName> (a thing I never have done) speaks, generally, in favour of it
with a few exceptions of social inconveniences such as Soil, Climate,
its thin Population etc.</p>

<p>I wish to be informed, first of the principles of the <persName>Government</persName>,
I should be glad (should it not be too voluminous) to have a complete
copy of its Constitution; Second the Tranquility of the Public Mind,
and probability of the continuation of the present form of 
Government ; Thirdly the liberty of the <persName>Spanish Functionaries</persName> where they
have confidence in the subject; Fourthly their credulity in the fidelity
of the <persName>Americans</persName>, generally, who emigrate to that country; Fifthly
advantages and disadvantages generally Its commercial situation -
the Depth of the water at the <placeName>entrance into the Bay</placeName> at the most 
favourable point and where that point is situated, - The Staple of the 
country, both at present and what it may be likely to be hereafter -, in a
word any, and everything that could, in anywise, tend to an 
elucidation of such objects as would naturally induce <persName>emigrants </persName>to that
country. And Sixth and lastly your opinion what advantages I
could derive if I was to go there; I believe I could bring fifty, 
perhaps more, <persName>families </persName>with me from here and <placeName>Kentucky</placeName>. I don't mean
a participation of the advantages you expect to derive from the Grant,
which you have succeeded to; as I suppose you will have no 
difficulty in  affecting your purposes so far as relates to <persName>emigrants</persName>.<pb n="456"/>
I would also be very glad to know your prospects; (I have supposed
them Grand) and of your final Prosperity.</p>

<p><persName>Major Hawkins</persName> is to be the <persName>bearer </persName>of this and will also be the
<persName>bearer </persName>of your answer; from the safety of the conveyance I have
asked your opinion on one point to which you, perhaps, may have some
hesitation in answering, to wit, the second proposition, and should
you not deem the safety of the conveyance sufficient guard, you have
a <hi rend="italic">cypher which we once learned to gather which will elude any 
detection.</hi></p>

<p>I presume your prospects are very flattering, and that you are
very much pleased with the country, and under such circumstances
men are very apt to exagerate on their ideas, but I presume it is
hardly necessary to remark this to one who so well understands the
Phylosophy of the Human Mind.</p>

<p>It is unnecessary to undertake to give you any details of affairs
in your old Stamping-ground, as you will receive them in a more
satisfactory way by the <persName>bearer</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>D. Dunklin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Stephen F. Austin Esqr</persName> <placeName>Province of Texas Colorado</placeName>
Politeness of <persName>Majr Jn° Hawkins</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
