<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0644">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Unknown to Unknown, 10-30-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 705
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Procamation.</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-10-30">10-30-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Terms of settlement in Austin's Colony.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>The terms on which <persName>Settlers </persName>are admitted into the <placeName>Colony </placeName>
forming by <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName> in the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName> are as follows&#8212;</p>

<p>No one will be received as a <persName>Settler</persName>, or even be permitted to 
remain in the country longer than is absolutely necessary to prepare
for a removal who does not produce the most unequivocal and 
satisfactory evidence of unblemished character, good Morals, Sobriety,
and industrious habits, and he must also have sufficient property
to begin with either as a farmer or mechanic besides paying for his
land&#8212;No <persName>frontiersman </persName>who has no other occupation than that of a
hunter will be received&#8212;no <persName>drunkard</persName>, nor <persName>Gambler</persName>, nor profane
swearer no <persName>idler</persName>, nor any man against whom there is even probable
grounds of suspicion that he is a bad man, or even has been 
considered a bad or disorderly man will be received. Those who are
rejected on the grounds of bad character will be immediately ordered
out of the County and if the order is not obeyed they will be sent
off under guard and their property seized and sold to pay the
expences, and should forcible resistence be made by them, the guard
will be ordered to fire on and kill them&#8212;</p>

<p>Those who are received as <persName>Settlers </persName>will get one league of land
if so much is wanted, to be chosen by the <persName>emigrant</persName>, which land will
cost at the rate of twelve Dollars and fifty cents pr. hundred acres
payable in cash or Spanish Cattle or <persName>negros </persName>on receipt of title, which
will be in full for surveying, title deeds, recording, and all other
charges.</p>

<p>The above only applies to <persName>men of families</persName>&#8212;<persName>Single men</persName> will be
examined as to character more particularly than <persName>men of families</persName>
and ten of them must unite to form a family and they will be 
entitled to one League of land to be divided between them. An 
exception will be made to this rule in favor of <persName>single men</persName> who bring
a considerable capital into the country all such will be ranked as
a <persName>family </persName>and draw one League&#8212;</p>

<p>A person who brings in a large capital and who has a large <persName>family</persName>
will draw more than a league should he wish it. The <persName>head of each
family</persName> will be held personally responsible for the good conduct of
every member of his family.</p>

<p>The Roman Catholic is the established religion of the <placeName>Mexican
nation</placeName> and the law will not allow of any other in this <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212;
<date when="1823-10-30">October 30 1823</date>&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
