<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0704">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Jose Antonio Saucedo to Colonists, 03-18-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Jose Antonio Saucedo</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Colonists
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 753-754
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-03-18">03-18-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Beneficent intentions of the Government. Austin's authority.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[Translation by Austin.]</p>

<p>The <persName>Political Chief of the Province of Texas</persName> to the <persName>new Settlers on
the <placeName>Colorado and Brazos Rivers</placeName></persName> in Said <placeName>Province</placeName></p>
<p>Fallow Citizens,</p>

<p>I have again the Satisfaction of addressing you, which I do with
the more pleasure as I am convinced you will listen to me and do the
justice to believe me when I assure you that a Government, which has
received you into its bosom through the solicitudes that were 
commenced by <persName>Moses Austin</persName> and at great expense and labor continued
and successfully terminated by his <persName>Son </persName><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>, will watch<pb n="754"/>
over your interests and protect your rights by just and wise laws
which will enable you to enjoy in peace the fruits of your labors&#8212;If
the <persName>government </persName>of the nation is not yet fully and finally organized,
the causes which have produced the delay are well known, but in the
midst of these delays and convulsions they have given you a chief to
govern you untill you have within yourselves the necessary numbers
and elements for the formation of your municipal bodies&#8212;they have
given you a beneficial and liberal Colonization law,&#8212;they have given
you a member in the most Excellent Deputation of this province (the
<persName>Baron de Bastrop</persName>) and you will be entitled to an equal 
representation with other citizens in the Legislative, Executive, and Judicial
Departments of the State, according to the tenor of the 
Constitutional Act which you are now called on to Swear to. It is therefore
necessary that you should listen with attention and confidence to
your immediate <persName>Chief (Col. Austin)</persName> whose authority is from the
Supreme powers of the nation to which you now voluntarily belong,
and that you should disregard and dispise all those idle slanders and
vague stories which are put in circulation by the enemies of good
order for the sole purpose of creating confusion and discontent.</p>

<p>I trust that my words will have the impression on your minds that
I desire, and that convinced of their truth you will repose in 
confidence and peace under the authorities that govern you, for by so
doing you may attain that degree of prosperity you wish for and
which is ardently hoped for by your fellow citizen</p>

<p><persName>Jose Antonio Saucedo</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
