<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0733">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Unknown, 05-01-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 781-782
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Proclamation</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-05-01">05-01-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Austin to the settlers. Congratulations on adoption of federal system. His responsibility to the settlers. Attitude toward Indians.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Fellow <persName>Citizens</persName>,&#8212;With the most heartfelt and sincere 
congratulations I now have the pleasure of announcing to you officially the
form of Government which the <persName>Mexican Congress</persName> have adopted, and
which you are now called on to swear to And this I do with the
more satisfaction as I am convinced that there is not a breast
amongst you that will not palpitate with exultation and delight at
the prospects of Freedom, Happiness, and Prosperity which the
<hi rend="italic">Federal Republican System of Govenmment</hi> presents to your View.</p>

<p>Words cannot express to you the Satisfaction I feel from the
reflection that those whose fortunes I shall be instrumental in 
promoting in this Country can now enjoy them without the alloy, which
the fear of a despotic <persName>Government </persName>would have thrown into their
future hopes. The great <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName> is free&#8212;rational liberty
with all its concomitant blessings has opened to the view of the
world, a Nation which Despotism had hitherto enveloped in 
intellectual night&#8212;The Federal Republican System that last and 
glorious hope of persecuted freedom, first established by the great
<persName>fathers of North American Independence</persName> on the ruins of <persName>British</persName>
Colonial oppression, and which soon raised a new born nation to
a degree of prosperity and happiness unequaled in the history of
the world&#8212;Now Spreads its fostering arms over the vast 
dominions of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;The hitherto enslaved <placeName>Spanish Provinces</placeName> are now
free and independent States.</p>

<p>This <placeName>Province </placeName>forms a <placeName>State </placeName>in conjunction with <placeName>Cohahuila </placeName>and
<placeName>New León</placeName> the two adjoining ones&#8212; The convention is to meet at
the <placeName>City of Monterrey </placeName>early in the <date n="Summer-1824">Summer </date>to form our State 
Constitution&#8212; One year more will see the <persName>Government </persName>completely 
organized with the several departments of Executive, Legislative and
Judicial divided and clearly delineated, and the civil and Military
power forever seperated as in the <persName>Government of the <placeName>United States</placeName></persName>.
In the mean time fellow citizens we have nothing to disturb our
tranquility here unless we willfully create confusion and discontent
amongst ourselves&#8212; As regards your lands <hi rend="italic">I</hi> am responsible to
you&#8212;to the world, to my own honor and to My God that no 
difficulty or embarrassment can or ever will arise unless produced by
your own impatience or imprudence.</p>

<p>The task I have had before me has been a laborious and 
perplexing one, I have however never shrunk from the hardships, 
exposures or the responsibilities which it imposed upon me, nor never
shall,&#8212;I have endeavored to make the fortunes of every one who<pb n="782"/>
joined me in forming this <placeName>Colony </placeName>and the Greatest consolation I
derive from the enterprise is the conviction that I shall do so&#8212;</p>

<p>It has been my Study to treat all with equal justice and 
impartiality and if I have failed to do so it must be attributed to the 
imperfections of my judgement and not to those of my heart, and with
almost unlimited Authority in My hands I think you must say that
I have governed you with mildness&#8212;</p>

<p>It is our true interest to keep peace with the <persName>Indians </persName>as long as
we can do so consistent with our rights, but Should a war be 
unavoidable you will not find me backward in prosecuting it. I trust
however that you will all have too much prudence to commit any
act that would prematurely bring on hostilities.</p>

<p>I hope fellow citizens you will attend to the words of the <persName>Political
Chief of this Province</persName> and in future disregard those vague rumors 
that are only put in circulation by the enemies of good order for
the sole purpose of creating confusion and discontent, and that
you will repose with confidence under the Authority that governs,
being assured that the <persName>Government </persName>will always cherish and protect
you, and that every thing in my feeble power to do for your benefit
will be cheerfully done, for as I before observed, the greatest 
consolation I ever expect to derive from My labors in the <placeName>wilderness of
this Province</placeName> will arise from the conviction that I have benefited
many of my fellow beings, and laid the foundation for the settlement
of one of the finest countries in the world&#8212;</p>

<p>Your fellow Citizens,</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p><date when="1824-05-01">May 1, 1824</date></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
