<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0171">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Isaac L. Baker to Stephen F. Austin, 07-01-1810</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Isaac L. Baker</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-30">06-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Lexington, KY</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">St Genevieve, LA</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 174-176
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1810-07-01">07-01-1810</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Transylvania University. Biographical.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><persName>Isaac Lewis Baker</persName> residing in <placeName>Lexington Kentucky</placeName> to <persName>Stephen Fuller
Austin</persName> of <placeName>Upper Louisiana</placeName>, health-</p>
<p><placeName>Transylvania University</placeName>, <date when="1810-07-01">July 1st 1810</date></p>
<p>Friend <persName>Stepen</persName>,</p>

<p>Whether it is your design to corospond with me or not I am not
able to tell, but if you do not answer this letter shortly after you
receive it I shall conclude you are for a non intercourse and act
accordingly&#8212;</p>

<p>From our intimacy during the time you staid here and being 
informed by the person who delivered you the letter that I wrote to you
a few days previous to your leaving <placeName>Lexington</placeName>, I concluded I should
hear from you as soon as the mail could come from <placeName>St Geneveive</placeName>
to this place after you got home&#8212;but how much have I been 
disappointed. Two months of posts have come and not a scrall from
little <persName>Stephen</persName>. This agitated my Irish Blood very much and I was
about swearing I never would write to you when the other evening
taking a small breezing towards " <placeName>old Fowler's place</placeName> " with a certain
young <persName>lady </persName>who lives <placeName>near the upper end of the south side of the
Courthouse</placeName> or <placeName>Public-Square</placeName>&#8212;also another who lives one door or
two or three from where you formerly lived and several other <persName>lasses</persName>
with some <persName>lads </persName>of the town, the two first mentioned told me I must
write to you immediately and inform you of a certain affair which
[they] think may militate to your disadvantage or I would be sunk
in their esteem for ever and ever&#8212;</p>

<p>The impressive and commanding manner in which they delivered
this chilld all the <hi rend="italic">"Irish blood"</hi> in my veins So to oblige two young
<persName>ladies </persName>whom I greatly esteem&#8212;and from other considerations I am
induced to write to you and if the sequel holds out in proportion
to the Introduction you will have a confounded long letter of it&#8212;
but now to tell the affair the <persName>ladies </persName>have told me of&#8212; Those <persName>ladies</persName>
aforementioned tell me that our old <persName>comrade <hi rend="italic">Butcher</persName> </hi>that Bloody
minded soul is about to supplant you one mile from <placeName>Lexington </placeName>i. e.
at the <placeName>Lombardy </placeName>poplar <placeName>Nursery</placeName>&#8212; They told me to tell you if
you wished to save deal at that place you must make great exertions
or you would be done over tailor' as the vulgar express it. I have
ever since had a particular eye on his actions and from my own 
observation and information received from <persName>Major John Mclntire</persName> 
another <persName>rival </persName>can safely assert that <persName>Butcher </persName>has been to see her every
evening for one week past. Thus stands the affair. Times are
squally&#8212; If you cannot or will not repair to this place 
immediately to support your claim recollect I am your sworn friend and
if you will send me a power of Attorney and instructions how to act<pb n="175"/>
I will do the best I can for you&#8212;   Now for other matters&#8212;   As
to an entry you made out at the <placeName>Cave Fielding B------d</placeName> [sic] having
the oldest patent will certainly non-suit you&#8212; And now to lump
your other <persName>sweethearts </persName>for I cannot notice them all singly, all of
them are surrounded by <persName>beaux</persName>. I have heard a report that I am
making at two or three of them and no doubt envy or disappointed
has signified as much to you by letter before this by [but] believe
me to be earnest when I say I will not intrude on the premises of
any friends if I know the ground they occupy&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S------</persName>that sweet provoking girl the other evening when we were
in chit-chat no one else near thus address'd me&#8212;" No young man from
<placeName>Orleans</placeName>, <placeName>Mississippi </placeName>or <placeName>Louisianna Terretory</placeName> ever lived here 
without engaging himself to be married to some young <persName>lady </persName>and amongst
a very great number not one ever returned to discharge his 
engagement, and I be bound (Listen well <persName>Stephen </persName>for indeed-she said it)
that I never will give any of them the opportunity of thus 
deceiving me!!" " Oh, gods," As from the agitated ether the swift hurld
Thunderbolt strikes the astounded earth, fell those dire words on
my ear&#8212; At length my Irish Blood mounted high in my veins, and
as it passed through my heart washed away every particle of 
affection for the ungrateful girl that had gathered round it.&#8212;but quick
was her place [possessed by] one who long my bosom has cherished
but [whose] name my tonge would never reveal. She is a beauty
Love&#8212;and divinity&#8212;but now it is time to quit the affairs of the
heart for those of the head&#8212;</p>

<p>I am engaged in studying Rhetoric, Logic Algebra and the reading
of history. I am more studious than ever and enjoying every 
advantage my advancement in science is rapid. I will [not] 
graduate, but will leave <placeName>Lexington </placeName>if I am well and nothing unforeseen
intervenes about the <date when="1810-10-12">12th of October</date> for the <placeName>Mississippi Territory</placeName>.
At that season it would be impracticable to go down the <placeName>Ohio </placeName>so I
will have to go all or part of my way by land. If I were sure of
getting a passage from <placeName>St Louis</placeName> or <placeName>Kaskaska </placeName>I would go through
<placeName>Vincennes </placeName>etc to one of these places and so on as I am axious to see
the country. Please write to me and let me know [if] a passage
at the time I want one can be had Enquire of the officers of <persName>Bell
canton</persName> and therabouts for the <persName>soldiers </persName>frequenly pass down about
that time</p>

<p>If no passage can be had or the road from <placeName>St. Geneveive</placeName> to the
<placeName>Chickesaw Bluffs</placeName> is unpracticable at that season I will go via 
<placeName>Knoxville </placeName><placeName>Savannah </placeName>and <placeName>Mobile </placeName>for the old beaten track I have seen often
enough&#8212;</p>

<p>With every sentiment of respect and esteem Your sincere Friend&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Isaac Lewis Baker</persName><pb n="176"/></p>

<p><hi rend="italic"><persName>Mr. Stephen Fuller Austin</persName></hi></p>

<p>P. S. The <persName>professor</persName>s in good health&#8212;The <persName>students </persName>in number
Sixty two&#8212;, <persName>McCalla </persName><persName>Smith </persName>and <persName>Lee </persName>will Push for degrees at the
close of this session&#8212;Your <persName>female acquaintances</persName> are all in good
health and desire to let little <persName>Stephen </persName>be told so&#8212;<persName>Wm Butler</persName> 
coresponds with me. He was well a few days since. He will be here in
a few days and go to <placeName>University </placeName>the rest of the session. <persName>J. Bickley</persName>
is at home reading history and soon will commence the study of Law
<persName>Shannon </persName>started to <placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>the <date when="1810-06-12">12th ult</date></p>

<p>TOUCH  OF THE  TIMES</p>

<p><persName>Dr. J. W.</persName> takes the rag off the bush a door below your <placeName>old place
of residence</placeName>. <persName>Dr. McCollough</persName> as usual. <persName>Charles Morton</persName> and <persName>Miss
Bright</persName> will be married the <date when="1810-07-01">5th inst</date>. <persName>Mrs. Beck</persName> is still crazed <persName>Miss
E Price</persName> will go to <placeName>Washington City</placeName> in <date n="11-xx-1810">November </date>with <persName>Mrs Clay</persName>
and return in <date n="03-xx-1811">March</date>. A certain <persName>Miss Edminton</persName> niece of <persName>Major
Morrison</persName> is reigning beauty. <persName>Miss M. Parker</persName> has returned. <persName>Mrs.
Pope</persName> introduced many new fashions etc. The <persName>Singing School
Scholars</persName> who remain here appear reorganized and we frequently
take airings of an evening. You are expected back <date n="Fall-1810">next fall</date>. I
expect I will live in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date n="Winter-1810">next winter</date> and Study french
and Law. In the <date n="Spring-1811">Spring </date>I will return to this place via <placeName>New York</placeName>
and <placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>and complete the study of law here. In the <date n="Spring-1812">Spring
of 1812</date> I expect to get married descend the river and settle some
where in the (Mans or <placeName>Mississippi Territories</placeName> etc. All this I intend
doing if [I] live and any young <persName>lady </persName>will be so good as to enter into
a matrimonial partnership with me. I hope to find such a one in
your parts <date n="Fall-1810">next fall</date>. <persName>Mr. Bradford</persName>s and <persName>Genl. Russell</persName>s <persName>families</persName>
well likewise <persName>Mrs. Hart</persName>s and all the <persName>Price</persName>'s. <persName>Maria </persName>is with us Big
doings to be over on the <date when="1810-07-04">4th</date> <persName>Father Cunningham</persName> is now preaching
and it being Sabbath I have taken my time in writing so no more</p>

<p><persName>Isaac Baker</persName></p>

<p>I have quit <persName>Betsy </persName>for a few months</p>
<p>[Addressed:]   <persName>Mr Stephen   Fuller   Austin</persName>   <placeName>St.   Geneveive   Upper
Louisiana</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
