<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0180">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Isaac Baker to Stephen F. Austin, 02-25-1811</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Isaac Baker</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-30">06-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Cane Hill, Fort Adams, Mississippi Territory</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Burton Mine, St Genevieve, LA</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 183-185
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1811-02-25">02-25-1811</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Student friendship. Slave insurrection in New Orleans.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><persName>Eliz------a!</persName> partner of my every thought! why is thy lovely form
e'er flitting in my view ? Yes the cause I fain must ken&#8212;I have seen
thee in the days of thy youth arrayd in charms divine&#8212;. thy form
thy visage sunk deep into my mind&#8212;and fondly does my soul cherish
each vestage that mem'ry can retain.&#8212;</p>

<p><placeName>Cane Hill near Fort Adams M T [Mississippi Territory]</placeName></p>

<p><date n="02-5-1811">Febry 25th 1811</date></p>
<p>My Dear Friend <persName>Stephen</persName>,</p>

<p>Your friendly letter of the <date when="1811-01-12">12th ult.</date> I had the good luck of getting
into my clutches about two hours since and must answer it by the
<date when="1811-02-26">morrow</date> morning's mail. From your long silence I began to 
conclude you had forgotten the poor lank jawed poet. You must not
be surprised at the manner I commence my letter as it is your 
injunction to begin and finish with <persName>E------a </persName>  This I do most cheerfully both
because I feel a pleasing thrill agitate my frame at the sound or
sight of the name but more <hi rend="italic">particularly </hi>because it is the request of
one I esteem.</p>

<p>I left <placeName>Lexington </placeName>on the <date when="1810-10-09">9th of October</date> and after a pleasant 
journey I arrived at this place on the <date when="1810-10-30">30th</date> of the same month and had the
pleasure of finding may <persName>parents </persName><persName>brothers </persName>and <persName>sisters </persName>in good health
and happy to see my ugly visage once more. I took <placeName>Russellville </placeName>in
my route and had the satisfaction of a few hours confab with <persName>Quack</persName>
and <persName>Quaker</persName>. <persName>Quack </persName>is studying law and says he has forgotten her.
<persName>Quaker </persName>has turned <persName>merchant </persName>I detained a few days at <placeName>Nashville</placeName>
for company and there had the pleasure of seeing the <persName>Miss Kerrs</persName>&#8212;
While at <placeName>Nashville </placeName>the weather was indescribably fine and one day<pb n="184"/>
as I strolled amongst some rocky hills near the <placeName>suburbs </placeName>meditating
on those I had lately left I wrote these lines which I beg leave to
transcribe&#8212;</p>

<p>How sweet when lonesome in an unknown land
To think of those whose friendship we command
But still more dear to inem'ry are the dames,
Who fill our hearts with loves unceasing flames
To bring their beauteous forms again to view
Dwell on their charmes and our fond flames renew.
Tis thus beneath a friendly cedar's shade
On a rock couch with moss and tuft array'd
While all around are lost in sportive g[I]ee
My heart <persName>Eliza </persName>turns me all to thee
To thee sweet girl who hast my bosom warm'd
To nobler views than int'resl ever formed
To views which I unceasing will pursue
Till you are mine or I am lost to you.&#8212;
Oh sweet <persName>E------a</persName> could thy bosom rise
With haft that fervor which mine now supplies
I'd bid all other cares of bliss adieu
My hopes of bliss I place alone in you&#8212;</p>

<p>But where in the name of god do I wander. I intended to fill up
this side with something of moment and here it is almost written up
aboute the old broken down hobby horse love&#8212;but now I'll try to do
better&#8212;</p>

<p>Upon my arrival <placeName>home </placeName>I stuck to the turf about six weeks and
then started to see some of the country to <placeName>west of the Mississippi</placeName>. I
visited the <placeName>Avoyelles </placeName><placeName>Rapide </placeName><placeName>Appalousas </placeName>and <placeName>Attakapas </placeName>districts
and returned home about <date when="1810-12-25">Christmas </date>well pleased with most of what
I had seen.</p>

<p>I have since been twice to <placeName>NOrleans</placeName> and happened there at the
time the <persName>Negroe </persName>insurrection broke out. About <persName>150 negroes</persName> have
been killed in various ways&#8212;Only two <persName>white men</persName> killed and three
good dwelling <placeName>houses </placeName>burnt twenty miles of country on the <placeName>left bank
of the River</placeName> was ravaged by them. Since the 1st inst I have been at
home and have employed my time in reading. By the <date when="1811-04-01">lst of April</date> at
farthest I expect to start back to <placeName>Lexington </placeName>for the purpose of
Studying law. I expect to be absent from home about two years
and a half&#8212;18&#8212;months at <placeName>Lexington </placeName>and one year at <placeName>Litchfield </placeName>or
<placeName>William and Mary</placeName>&#8212;<date n="10-xx-1811">Next October</date> and the gods propitious I will
visit <placeName>Upper Louisiana</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I am sorry that I have to leave this <placeName>country </placeName>before you come to it
but if you should visit the <placeName>district of Attakapas</placeName> you will find my
<persName>father </persName>and on the <placeName>Teshe </placeName><placeName>30 miles below Newtown</placeName> where you may
expect a hearty welcome.    Our <persName>family </persName>moves to <placeName>Attakapas </placeName>in the<pb n="185"/>
course of a few days&#8212;The uncertainty of the cotton market has 
induced my <persName>father </persName>to give up the culture. He intends trying sugar&#8212;</p>

<p>A few days ago I rec'd a letter from <persName>Wm A Butler</persName> He was well
and engaged in the study of Law He informed me that the sound of
the " dulcet Piano " was heard in the row no more for grievous to
relate <persName>E</persName> has gone to <persName>Congress </persName>and left <placeName>Lexington </placeName>in sack cloth and
ashes,   but d&#8212;n it I'm from my purpose again</p>

<p>When I get to <placeName>Lexington </placeName>again <persName>Stephen </persName>I will not turn fool and
cabous about as formerly but will be a staid sober chap, write no
more poetry but read prose even from the rising to the going down
of the sun&#8212;When I get my studies completed maybe if some of the
<persName>lasses </persName>feel in the notion I may satisfy some one of them i. e. if they
long for Matrimony. Wherever you are <persName>Pedlar </persName>You must write to
me and let me know how you stem the tide of life.</p>

<p>For several reasons which I have no room to state I am glad you
have fallen in love in <placeName>U. Louisiana</placeName>. Dont grin <persName>Steve </persName>and say I am
glad because I thought you would rival me for if you recollect in a
former letter I told you I would interfere with none of your claims&#8212;
As I calculate on going to your part of the world <date n="10-xx-11">next Oct</date>. Please
hunt out for me some clever decent <persName>girl </persName>and I will make at her by
the holy wig of my <persName>ancestors</persName>. But now I must stop, etc adieu my
friend may the <hi rend="italic">holy </hi>Virgin protect you may heaven bless you and
your days be peace and prosperity&#8212;This from your since [re] friend</p>

<p><persName>Isaac L Baker</persName></p>

<p>By-gum I had almost forgot to tell you that I have written [our
New?] Years gift to send to <placeName>Lexington </placeName>next [New Year?] it is a
clever one</p>

<p>P. S. It is here rumored that Cols <persName>Sparks </persName>and <persName>Cushing </persName>have been
arrested at <placeName>Mobile </placeName>by order of <persName>Genl. Hampton</persName>&#8212;particulars unknown
all tranquil in <placeName>Florida</placeName>. <persName>Col Kemper</persName> dined with us <date when="1811-02-24">yesterday </date>but
now adieu but for the last word this from one to one who loves
<persName>E&#8212;a</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr Stephen Fuller Austin</persName> <placeName>Mine at Beriton near St
Genevive Upper Louisiana</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
