<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0258">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Isaac L. Baker to Stephen F. Austin, 01-05-1815</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Isaac L. Baker</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-02">07-02-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Camp 4 miles below New Orleans, LA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Burton Mine, LA</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 245-247
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1815-01-05">01-05-1815</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-02" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Battles.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Camp 4 miles below <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></p>

<p><date when="1815-01-05">Jany 5th 1815</date></p>
<p>My dear fellow,</p>

<p>Has fate formed me jealous and suspicious or have my failures in
Life rendered me less sanguine and more doubtful of what is to be
the issue of my fortunes. Perhaps the clouded destinies that hang
over my fate and my country's fortunes may have rendered me Morose
and severe and jealous of my <hi rend="italic">friend</hi>&#8212; What is the cause I cannot
divine, yet not withstanding your Magnamimity induced you to
transfer all your right and title to <hi rend="italic">Paradise to me</hi>&#8212; yet in that
letter while you darkly hint at <hi rend="italic">hopes </hi>that infuse new life into you<pb n="246"/>
studiously avoiding the object's name and yet I have some how or
other conceived a most insiduous idea that your taste passions and
character are so similar to my own and the beautiful soothing 
interesting and angelic <persName>Emily </persName>so much the favorite theme of your pen
Yes <persName>Austin </persName>I have been suspicious enough to fear that you are again
my rival and that the <hi rend="italic">Phoenix </hi>flame which has resuscitated with
chastened vigour in my bosom still burns in yours and for the same
object</p>

<p>But to be plain with you I have long known and regarded <persName>E&#8212;y</persName>
in a peculiar manner&#8212; When my old flame was at its zenith she
was my confident and has for years been my most intimate friend.
What think you is the product of such intimacy&#8212;I cannot say I
love her&#8212;yet I know not a perfection I must not ascribe to her&#8212;
Am I sick?&#8212; worn down by toil and Marching? Do the chances
of war threaten my dissolution? Then I think of <persName>Emily</persName>&#8212;then
I look to her as one of the objects fate has given to attach me most
strongly to life and fame&#8212; I am vain enough to say&#8212;(I boast
because I prize it above all my worldly store)&#8212;-she in a small
degree reciprocates my feelings&#8212; We have often acknowledged our
feelings&#8212;How far my old attachment prevented me from rising
from the claims of a <persName>friend </persName>to a <persName>lover </persName>I cannot tell but surely I
could not have gazed so long on an object of her worth without
thirsting for possession were it not <persName>Austin </persName>that since I know <persName>E&#8212;a</persName>
first as if the passion was baleful my other better feelings have All
been swallowed in that vortex and my sensibilities for others 
measurably suspended&#8212; That I have some slight traces of affection left
for her I will not cannot deny&#8212;but as it would require the 
unravelling of more circumstances than I ever expect explained to
bring about a reconciliation I think no more about it only to
obliterate it forever.&#8212;</p>

<p>Of the landing of the <persName>English </persName>in this country our battle with
them etc you have no doubt heard for the last 12 days our <persName>armies</persName>
have been laying within sight of each other. They have twice
attempted to cannonade us from our <placeName>works</placeName> and force them but in
the end retired with loss&#8212;</p>

<p>I led the <persName>44th Regt</persName> in this Action and [mutilated] had command
of it. It has suffered severely and acquitted itself well. How long
this state of things will remain I cannot tell&#8212; We are well fortified
but not strong enough to give them a field fight&#8212; They have about
8,000 <persName>Regulars</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>If I live through the scene I will visit <placeName>Kentucky </placeName>immediately
afterward;&#8212;I wish much to see you and would be glad to meet you<pb n="247"/>
there&#8212;   I will be generous and if <persName>E&#8212;y </persName>prefers you to me my
influence with her shall be yours&#8212;i. e. if she is your object.   Write
me the explanation you promise&#8212;</p>

<p>Excuse this scrip manner and matter   I am sick&#8212;toil worn full
of Business</p>

<p>Adieu my dear fellow and if <persName>John Bull </persName>will give me his quietus
beleive I die as I live</p>

<p>Your friend                                                 <persName> Isaac L. Baker</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:]   <persName>Stephen Fuller Austin, esquire</persName> <placeName>Mine au Burton
Upper Louisiana</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
