<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0047">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Charles Austin to Moses Austin, 12-08-1800</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Charles Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-21">06-21-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Moses Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin Ville, VA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 57-59
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1800-12-08">12-08-1800</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Value of property at lead mines.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Austin Ville</placeName> <date when="1800-12-08">December 8. 1800</date>.</p>
<p>Dear <persName>Uncle</persName></p>

<p>I received your favors not long since and am very Sorry to hear
of the Difficulties you have met with in the progress of your bussi-<pb n="58"/>
ness but hope you will yet be well repaid for all your trouble, I
should have wrote you long since but as I supposed from the 
frequent communications from my <persName>father </persName>and <persName>Mr. Jas Austin</persName> you were
informed of our proceedings generally in this <placeName>Country</placeName>. Your 
objections as to the Sale of some of the property sold me by my <persName>father</persName>, I
am sorry to hear of as I rested perfectly satisfied as to my right of
all the Property and Still shall as I am certain you must be much
deceived as to the Value of the Property, by a letter from my <persName>father</persName>
I am informed that you write by the appraisement of myself and <persName>Jas
Austin</persName> the Property at the <placeName>Lead Mines</placeName> Amounts to 25,000 Dollars,
as to myself I think I can with certainty say I never made such a
Statement nor had such an Idea, if <persName>Mr. James Austin</persName> did so I think
you must have misunderstood each other very much Indeed, I rely
much on his judgment and integrity and as he has wrote his <persName>wife </persName>he
intends going to your Country from <placeName>Kentucky </placeName>you will verbally 
receive more accurate information from him I should long before this
have had all the Property Valued but on my own account rested easy,
but for the better adjustment of Accounts between yourself and my
<persName>father </persName>I shall in a few days have all the Property valued by <persName>Mr.
James McGarock, Senr</persName>, <persName>Mr. Hugh McGarock</persName>, <persName>Mr. Joseph Kent</persName> and
<persName>Capt. James Newell</persName> four persons in whom I place much 
confidence and who I think will do justice to both parties. I shall State
to them (by the direction of <persName>S. Austin</persName>) that the Property is to be
valued at cash which he (<persName>S. A.</persName>) says ought to have been sold to 
discharge your assumset to him some time since, I have hereunto 
annexed a Statement of the most I think the Property would bring in
the common way of Trade in this <placeName>Country </placeName>which can be compared
with the balance due <persName>S. Austin and Co. of <placeName>Philada</placeName></persName> by <persName>Mosses Austin
and Co</persName>. and <persName>S &amp; M Austin of <placeName>Virginia</placeName></persName> which I think will not be
more than adequate to the sum due. Since the adjustment of your
accounts in <placeName>Philada </placeName>with my <persName>father </persName>(with the interest which he may
or may not be intitled to) he has paid a very considerable debt and
advanced some money for this place. Should I have erred in any
Statement I have made above or any opinion I have advanced, in the
manner in which they are made, I beg to be corrected, my wish and
most ernest desire is that no difference or litigation should take place
in any bussiness I may have that has any relation to yourself.</p>

<p>Since the <date when="1800-06-18">18 of June last</date> on my Lease for one Year of the <placeName>Lead
Mines</placeName>, I have been pursuing the Bussiness with as much Prudence,
caution and care as my moderate abillities has enabled me and
fear at the close of the year I shall barely be able to pay all 
expenses, I have not raised any ore of consequence for many months,
but the prospect holding good has prevented my abandoning some
time back but since I have built a Slag Hourth which I erected at
the  <placeName>Grist Mills</placeName> notwithstanding the  quantity  of  water  does  not<pb n="59"/>
answer my expectations we work nearly one half of the time. I shall
hold on untile the expiration of my year and shall then remain
the ballance of the <date n="Summer - 1801">summer </date>to adjust my accounts when with what
little I may have after my four Years labour I shall seek some 
employment near my <persName>friends</persName>, my <placeName>plantation (B. Bottom</placeName>) I shall leave
in the care of some trusty person with several <persName>hands </persName>and shall return
to this <placeName>Country </placeName>as my <persName>father</persName>s and my own interest may require.</p>

<p>In the Statement which follows I have not included for 2 Small
Pieces of Land or <placeName>B. Bottom </placeName>nor the Tolls or Debts due the place
which will not discharge the debts due from it in this Country.</p>

<p>Remember me to <persName>Aunt </persName>and the <persName>Children </persName>and all <persName>friends </persName>with you.</p>

<p>With respect.</p>

<p>Your <persName>Nephew</persName></p>

<p><persName>Charles Austin</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>Mrs J. Austin</persName> Sends her love to you all, herself and <persName>Son </persName>are in
Good health and a fair prospect of increase in our <persName>family</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>C. A</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>Prince </persName><persName>Patty </persName><persName>Nelly </persName><persName>Jerry </persName>and 2 <persName>children</persName>________________________  £350</p>

<p><persName>James </persName><persName>Kesiah </persName>and 5 <persName>children</persName>-_________________________________    350</p>

<p><persName>Ambrose </persName><persName>Mary </persName>and 3 <persName>Sons</persName>____________________________________    380</p>

<p><persName>David</persName>, <persName>Alex </persName><persName>Frank </persName><persName>Joe </persName><persName>Tom </persName>and <persName>Wat</persName>___________________________    500</p>

<p><persName>Gowin </persName>and <persName>Peter</persName>____________________________________________    150</p>

<p><placeName><persName>Bohannon </persName> and <persName>Forbus </persName>plantation</placeName>_______________________________    470</p>

<p>House and Lot in <placeName>Lynehburgh</placeName>_________________________________    450</p>

<p>7 Mules_______________________________________________________   108</p>

<p>2758</p>

<p>4 Mules I sold a year ago but a very small part of the money is
received and I fear the balance will not be had soon, as a suit must
take place, such is the precarious, Situation of the Sale of property.</p>

<p>The above Statements I have shewn to persons who know the
property who think I have exceeded what it will bring.</p>

<p>[Addressed] <persName>Mr. Moses Austin</persName> at the <placeName>Lead Mines</placeName> <placeName>on the Spanish
Side of the Mississipi, Kaskaskia.</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
