<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0383">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to James E. B. Austin, 04-08-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">St. Louis, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Lexington, KY</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 385-387
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-04-08">04-08-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Future in Texas. Sends Kentucky currency to discharge son's debts.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>St Louis</placeName> <date when="1821-04-08">Apr 8 1821</date></p>
<p>My Dear <persName>Son</persName></p>

<p>I wrote you from <placeName>Herculaneum </placeName>a few days after my return from
<placeName>St Antonio </placeName>and inclosed you a Draft on your <persName>brother </persName>for 150 
dollars at <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> I was in hopes to have sent you 50 Dollars of
<placeName>Kentucky </placeName>money from this place but as yet I have not been able to
obtain shall continue making exertions until I can obtain as much as
will releave you I much wish to see you return to this country 
before I leave it for the <placeName>Spanish province of <hi rend="italic">Texas</hi></placeName>. I have made a
visit to <placeName>St Antonio</placeName> and obtained liberty to settle in that country&#8212;
<hi rend="italic">as I am, ruined, in this</hi>, I found nothing I could do would bring back
my property again and to remain in a <placeName>Country </placeName>where I had enjoyed
<hi rend="italic">welth </hi>in a state of <hi rend="italic">poverty </hi>I could Not submit to I therefore made<pb n="386"/>
an <hi rend="italic">exertion </hi>and obtained what I asked for a right of settlement for
myself and family the situation I have marked out is on the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Colorado</placeName></hi>
about 3 Days sale from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> or rather from <hi rend="italic">the <placeName>Belise</placeName></hi> a
<hi rend="italic">most </hi>delightful situation and on the <placeName>Bay of <hi rend="italic">San Bernard</hi> </placeName>the 
<placeName>Harbour </placeName>is good with 12 or 13 feet water over the Barr after which&#8212;
25 or 30 feet for some miles up the <placeName>river </placeName>with boat Navigation, <hi rend="italic">150
miles</hi>&#8212;I have asked for leave of settlement for <persName>300 families</persName> and
<placeName>(200) Thousand Acres of Land</placeName> to open a <placeName>Port </placeName><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Town </placeName></hi>at the <placeName><hi rend="italic">mouth
of the River</hi></placeName> which has been granted me by the <persName>Governor of the
<placeName>Province of Texas</placeName></persName> and has gone on to the <persName>Vice King </persName>for his 
confirmation, I have been offered as many <hi rend="italic">Names </hi>of <persName>respectable families</persName>
as will make up the Number but untill I return I shall not admitt
any as my wish is to have the lands survey'd before I introduce any
<persName>families </persName>at all. I shall take with me about <persName>30 young men</persName> to 
commence the <placeName>settlement </placeName>and return after your <persName>mother </persName><date n="xx-xx-1822">next year</date>. I
have now a proposition to mention to you which is this you are a
<persName>Spanish subject</persName> born and was baptised by a <hi rend="italic"><persName>Roman Priest</persName></hi> and are
recorded as such at the <placeName>church of St. Genevieve</placeName>, I shall obtain a
Record of this fact and if you will go with me I can get you 
introduced at the <placeName>College at <hi rend="italic">Monterey </hi></placeName>a large City about <placeName><hi rend="italic">500</hi> miles south
of <hi rend="italic">St Antonio</hi></placeName> at this place I shall be able to support you a year or
more and you will there learn the <persName>Spanish </persName>language which will be of
more Consiquence to you than you can now conceive of and as its not
likely you will be called for to join the <persName>Navy of the United States</persName>
for some time you cannot be better imployed&#8212;the <placeName>college at 
<hi rend="italic">Monterrey </hi></placeName>or <placeName><hi rend="italic">Royal Mountain</hi></placeName> has now <persName><hi rend="italic">400 students</hi></persName> from every part of the
<placeName>Spanish provinces</placeName>, by which means you will have an opportunity to
visit the <placeName>City of Mexico</placeName> and become acquainted with the <placeName>Country</placeName>
generally and make friends with the <persName>young men of first families in
that Country</persName>. <persName>Mr Woodson</persName> who will hand you this letter can tell
you much more than I can write you and what is more he has this
moment offered to lend me <hi rend="italic">50 or 60</hi> Dollars <placeName>Kentucky </placeName>Bank paper
to pay the balance of your Expenses so that you may return home
to your Dear <persName>mother </persName>and also to a <persName>father </persName>that has felt for your 
situation but could not until <hi rend="italic">now </hi>help you, when you receive the money
from <persName>Mr Woodson</persName> you must give him a Receipt to be repaid Dollar
for Dollar and return him thanks for his uncommon Kindness for
without his friendship I do not know how I should have made up the
money I hope you will not loose a moment after you have paid your
Bills but leave <placeName>Kentucky </placeName>without delay. <persName>Mr Woodson</persName> can tell you
of my prospects in the <placeName>Spanish country</placeName> and his opinion of your
visiting <placeName>Monterrey </placeName>you may also obtain the opinion of <persName>Mr Holly</persName> if
you please.    If you examin <persName>Melishe</persName>s <placeName>Map of the United States</placeName> you<pb n="387"/>
will find the <placeName>Bay of San Bernard</placeName> and the <placeName>River Colorado</placeName> at the
mouth of which I calculate to lay of the <placeName>Town of <hi rend="italic">Austina</hi></placeName>, which
will be in a few years equal to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> in Consequence if not in
wealth.</p>

<p>God bless you my <persName>son</persName></p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:]<persName> Mr James E. B. Austin</persName> Near <persName>Lexington Kty</persName>&#8212;
Politeness&#8212;<persName>Mr Woodson</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
