<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0576">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Congress, 04-05-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Congress
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 628-630
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-04-05">04-05-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asks confirmation of Iturbide's decree of February 18.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName> a Native of <placeName>Virginia </placeName>of the <placeName>United States of
America</placeName> and a <persName>Settler </persName>in the <placeName>province of Texas</placeName>, one of the <placeName>Eastern
Interior Provinces</placeName>, with due respect represents to your August
Body, That in the year <date n="xx-xx-1820">1820 </date>my father <persName>Moses Austin</persName> entered into
a contract with the <placeName>Provincial Assembly of the New Kingdom of
Leon</placeName>, then comprising the <placeName>four Eastern Interior provinces</placeName> to bring
into this country at his own expence and settle in the <placeName>province
of Texas</placeName> <persName>three hundred families</persName> of the Catholic religion, farmers<pb n="629"/>
by profession, and of industrious habits. The <persName>Assembly </persName>aforesaid
admitted the contract on the terms specified in the file of documents,
on record in the <placeName>Archives of this Government</placeName>, soon after which
my <persName>father </persName>died, leaving me charged with the duty entrusted to him;
this I have performed by bringing into the country the aforesaid
number of <persName>families</persName>, which with the permission of the <persName>Governor</persName>
of said <placeName>province</placeName>, I have located on the <placeName>banks of the Rivers Colorado
and Brazos</placeName>. By this time the independence and emancipation of
this part of <placeName>America </placeName>had fortunately taken place, and remitting
through the said <persName>Assembly </persName>to this Government an Account of all
I had done, up to that date, I deemed it necessary to present myself
in person, with a view to obtain in the most legal form a ratification
of my acts, in regard to that <placeName>settlement</placeName>. But, the consummation
of this hope has been delayed more than a year, awaiting your
Supreme pleasure to enact the General Colonization Law.</p>

<p>The <persName>Junta Instituyente</persName> at last determined upon the Colonization
Law, on the <date when="1823-01-03">3rd of January of the present year</date>, which being 
sanctioned by the <persName>Emperor</persName>, was published on the <date when="1823-01-04">4th</date> of the same.
Until the present time I have been unable to progress with better
hopes of success, in the only business which for so great a length of
time has detained me in this <placeName>Capital</placeName>, and in which so many <persName>families</persName>
are interested, obtaining at last of the Government on the <date when="1823-02-18">18th 
February last</date> the enclosed commission which I have the honor 
herewith to present to your August Body: I am informed that under
the same date copies of this were transmitted to the <persName>Political Chief</persName>,
and to the <persName>Commanding General Pro tem</persName>, of these provinces and
also to the <persName>Governor of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>; and although confiding in the good
faith guaranteed by those documents and by this which I now lay
before your Honors, I could have proceeded on to be put in 
possession of that <placeName>settlement</placeName>, yet I deemed it more to the purpose to
await the favorable and happy re-establishment of your August
Body, and the liberal form of government, which has been
enthusiastically proclaimed by the <persName>Liberating Army</persName> and this 
honorable <placeName>Nation</placeName>: I have already witnessed, with the greatest pleasure,
the consummation of this happy event, and the entire change of the
Government, and desirous therefore to insure and secure my own
welfare and permanency in this part of <placeName>America</placeName>, as well as that
of the <persName>families </persName>that I have conveyed thither, at my own expense,
I present said <persName>Commission</persName>, praying your <persName>Honors </persName>to confirm it,
or decide in the matter according to the Sovereign will and pleasure
of your Honbl Body, condescending to take into consideration the
very great expenses I have incurred in conveying said <persName>families</persName>, in
effecting their <placeName>settlement</placeName>, and in having been myself detained 
attending on this court for upwards of a year, as well as the state<pb n="630"/>
of uncertainty and exasperation of those <persName>settlers</persName>, caused by so much
delay in the termination of my mission, while they have dedicated
themselves, with so much ardor and diligence, to the cultivation
of those lands, amidst the dangers and ravages of the tribes of
<persName>savages</persName>, whom they have successfully resisted, and severely chastised,
as is evident by the reports which have been transmitted to the
<persName>Government</persName>. Therefore I humbly pray your <persName>Honors </persName>for a prompt
decree favorable to this my petition and agreeable to your supreme
wiil <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, <date when="1823-04-05">April 5th 1823</date>.</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
