<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0502">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>T. [or J.] Reilly to J. H. Hawkins, 04-26-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>T. [or J.] Reilly</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J. H. Hawkins
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">New Orleans, LA</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 498-500
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-04-26">04-26-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Trespalacios appointed governor of Texas. He is cool toward Austin, but says he favors the colony. The subject progressing satisfactorily in Congress, but requires vigilant attention. Many other applicants for grants, and the Austin colony has much to fear from their encroachments.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1822-04-26">April 26 1822</date></p>
<p>Dear Sr</p>

<p>I addressed you from <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> a hasty Letter dated early in this
month, it was not, at that time, in my power to say any thing of
Import, on the Subject of the <placeName>Texas </placeName>Settlement, for altho' I had
conversed with some Persons thereon, their Opinions or Influence
was but of little consequence.</p>

<p>Your Letter of Introduction was handed me by <persName>Mr Erwin</persName>, with
whom I have traveled from <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> to this City, it will always
afford me much Pleasure to serve any Person you may recommend -
I wish to say Nothing of <persName>Mr E------n</persName></p>

<p><persName>General Trespalacios</persName> of whom you must know something is 
appointed <persName>Governor </persName>over the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>, his second in 
command is <persName>Mr Mileham [Milam]</persName> formerly of <placeName>Kentucky</placeName>, now a <placeName>Colonel</placeName>
in the Mexican Service, he will be also accompanied by a <persName>Colonel
Burns</persName> (English) and a <persName>Captain Austin</persName> formerly of <placeName>Newyork </placeName>- these
two last were with <persName>General Long</persName> who, by an unfortunate accident
lost his life in this City a few days since; the <persName>Governor </persName>sets off in a
few days for his <placeName>Province </placeName>accompanied (as is said) by some 
<persName>Calvalry </persName>-</p>

<p>Having had several Interviews and Conversations with 
<persName>Trespalacios </persName>I did not fail to introduce the <placeName>Austin Settlement</placeName>, the 
<persName>General </persName>who is very collected and wary in Discourse, has always 
expressed his wish to protect and encourage the Establishment; as I
had heard from those who surround Him some Hints unfavourable
to <persName>Mr Austin</persName>, and assertions that he had some time past acted a
Part unfriendly to the <persName>Revolutionary Party</persName> as well as disrespectful
to the <persName>General</persName>, I felt a desire to elucidate this Matter and in a 
subsequent conversation hinted to Him that notwithstanding <hi rend="italic">his </hi>friendly
views I had found in the City some Persons who were ill disposed<pb n="499"/>
towards <persName>Mr A.</persName> He replied that it was true he had himself cause to
Complain of <persName>Mr A</persName> for his conduct at <placeName>N. O.</placeName> but that this should not
influence his Procedings in the business; that he did not know
whether those about Him had made any unfriendly observations,
but He would continue favorable and proposed giving me an 
opportunity of mentioning the Subject to the <persName>Generalissimo Iturvide </persName>-
This is the Purport of the Conversation held with him <date when="1822-04-25">Yesterday</date>.</p>

<p>With other Persons high in Publick Esteem I have also entered
on this matter, and particularly with <persName>Don Leandro Echenique</persName> a
<persName>leading member of this Congress</persName> and of the <persName>Committee of 
Colonization</persName>, he shewed me a large package of Papers, which He assured me
were Documents and Petitions etc. etc. relating to the <placeName>Austin Grant</placeName>,
and gave me explicitly to understand that all was in a favorable
Train, and the Disposition of <persName>Congress </persName>amicable to the Subject.
Notwithstanding all this I believe that great Vigilance, 
Circumspection and Policy will be required to place the Settlement on a
solid foundation&#8212;the good will of <persName>Trespalacios </persName>is very desirable
the Favor of the <persName>Governor General</persName> is also necessary at least until
the <placeName>Grant </placeName>be confirmed by the <persName>General Government</persName> here, the 
<persName>Captain General of the <placeName>four Provinces</placeName></persName> is now in this <placeName>City</placeName></p>

<p>With this information which I think may be relied on, the <persName>patrons
of the <placeName>A. Settlement</placeName></persName>, should take such measures as will secure their
object, the <persName>Governor Tresp____s</persName> will probably be at <placeName>San Antonio</placeName>
his <placeName>Head Quarters</placeName>, in fifty days from this date.</p>

<p>Three days since the <persName>Government </persName>received by <persName>Express </persName>the 
Intelligence of the acknowledgment by the <placeName>U S</placeName> of the Independence of
<placeName>Spanish America</placeName>, and of the Arrival at <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> of an <persName>American
Consul</persName>, my Disappointment on this Subject is very slight and my
only regret is in having made the Application for an office, which
could not fail to embarrass my Commercial Movements &#8212;</p>

<p>There is every probability that <persName>Mr. Robert Leftwich</persName> will receive a
<placeName>Grant </placeName>of Land &#8212; I cannot refrain from expressing my opinion of
the whole Transaction that it is a Most singular and extraordinary
One. In my Opinion the <placeName>Austin Grant</placeName> will have as much to fear
from the encroachment of new <persName>grantees </persName>as from any other cause.</p>

<p>It is not at present in my power to say much on Political Subjects.
The <persName>Congress </persName>in session here is a respectable body and its 
Transactions are conducted with great Decorum and Order The treasury
of the State is empty, its Resources in a deplorable state and withall<pb n="500"/>
but little Economy in the Administration a Better State of Things
must be hoped for</p>

<p><persName>T. [or J.] Reilly</persName></p>

<p><persName>Gn Wilkinson</persName> has stopped at <placeName>Puebla </placeName>to recover from an 
indisposition produced by fatigue.   He will probably be here in a day or two
[Addressed:] <persName>J. H. Hawkins</persName> <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
