<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0478">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Joseph H. Hawkins to Stephen F. Austin, 02-06-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Joseph H. Hawkins</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, LA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 476-478
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-02-06">02-06-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Vessels and emigrants on the way to Texas. Thousands ready to go with "one word of encouragement from you." Presents for Texan officials. His own financial distress.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><hi rend="italic"><placeName>New Orleans</placeName></hi></p>
<p><date when="1822-02-06">Feby. 6. 1822</date></p>
<p>My dear Sir&#8212;</p>

<p>I have been struggling for a week past to find an hour to devote to
this purpose. It is now eleven oclock at night and as usual I am almost
too much exhausted to hold my pen&#8212;</p>

<p>The "only Son " <persName>Mr. Kincheloe</persName> owner carries several of my <persName>friends</persName>
and a number of valuable <persName>settlers</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Three other vessels have recently sailed for the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>, and in
fact my dear Sir had the Lively returned with a good account of
her voyage, your country would be crowded to overflowing&#8212;</p>

<p>I have recently received a letter from a <persName>Mr Ross</persName> in <placeName>Tennessee </placeName>
(forwarding good letters of recommendation) proposing to <hi rend="italic">"deliver you
<persName>three hundred families</persName> by contract"</hi> There are hundreds on the way
and thousands ready to go if one word of encouragement could now be
had from you.</p>

<p>I begin to fear the jealousy of the <persName>Spanish Government</persName> may be
excited and some prohibition interposed&#8212;At all events the most
should be made of a cloudless sky.</p>

<p>After your <persName>300 families</persName> are introduced would it not be well to raise
the price of your land? Would you not be justified in asking 50 cents
or even a dollar and by and by still more for lands?</p>

<p>These are mere suggestions&#8212;Your own better Judgment will 
govern and I know guide correctly&#8212;Perhaps my own necessities may
have led to this view of the subject.</p>

<p>I am bent down almost to the very ground. Of the $7,000 advanced
for the Providence I have not one cent return&#8212;In fact my dear Sir
I turn my mind towards you as the wrecked mariner does towards
the glimerings of the light house which promises a Haven of safety-
Were it not for you my path would now be cheerless if not hopeless.</p>

<p>If I could obtain through your efforts the means to pay my debts
I would join you immediately and spend my life in plowing the
soil&#8212;and teaching our <persName>children </persName>the ways of virtue.</p>

<p>You can form no idea of my anxiety to hear from you&#8212;The only
information I have received was from <persName>Mr Kincheloe</persName>&#8212;-He informed
me you were not far from the <placeName>mouth of the Cola</placeName> and where you 
expected to meet the Lively&#8212;I have derived more satisfaction as to
the value of your <placeName>country </placeName>from <persName>Mr K</persName> than any other individual I
have seen.</p>

<p>And his account would reconcile even some little <hi rend="italic">remnants of
aristocracy</hi> where the boone they purchased was otherwise so ines-<pb n="477"/>
timable&#8212;I have relinquished altogether the idea of answering the
many letters that are wrote me&#8212;In fact I almost tremble at some
moments least some untoward event should entail misfortunes on
those who have relied more on you and myself and upon our names
than upon their own judgment&#8212;However sufficient for the day be
the evil thereof.</p>

<p>All our concerns here would be stale flat and unprofitable to you&#8212;
You and your <placeName>Colony </placeName>excite more interest than the assembled sages
of the nation.</p>

<p>Why should we not stake our good names as well as all our fortune
on such an enterprise?</p>

<p>Even those who would censure would be compelled to mingle 
respect with their reproaches.</p>

<p>Pray write me often and fully&#8212;Say what shall go to the public
eye and what not&#8212;Tell me if I am yet doomed to be a slave or if
fate promises to redeem and disenthral&#8212;Need I remind you that
charity begins at home&#8212;Towns mill seats&#8212;choice of lands&#8212;
Augmented prices they all rise in judgment before me, and buisy self
sometimes pencils the picture with the warm tints on which fond
fancy delights to dwell.</p>

<p>Having touched the chord which charms pray how were you last
recd by those whose friendship we most need? Did the little 
presents to our friends meet the welcome hoped for? Did they please?
Do they begin to believe we are something more than mere swinish
multitude? Did the fair ones grow more fair and the kind ones
more kind?</p>

<p>These are small affairs abstractly but mingled with others they
become affairs of State&#8212;Do not suffer yourself to be supplanted in
the esteem of those who Govern by lawful rule or those who Govern
by the magic wand which dame nature has bestowed on the weaker
yet most lovely of her works.</p>

<p><persName>Mrs. Hawkins</persName> desires to be remembered to you&#8212;-Do not forget
<persName>Rucker </persName>and <persName>Duncan</persName>&#8212;Write what shall be sent you for your Comfort
I send you some <placeName>papers </placeName>for your leisure moments if you have any.</p>

<p><persName>J. H. Hawkins</persName></p>

<p>A flaming publication is going the rounds stating that <placeName>Long </placeName>had
been recd into the republican service and his men paid from the first
adherance to their gallant <persName>Genl.</persName></p>

<p>I triumphed in the case of <persName>Marigny </persName>(?) they dismissed their suit
vs. ? me&#8212;In my case of the pattent (?) Seven of the <persName>jury </persName>were for
finding the property in the public&#8212;The wise ones were thunder struck.<pb n="478"/></p>

<p>Confidential. Unless I can obtain monied aid before <date n="Fall-1822">next fall</date> I
shall not be able to stand it here&#8212;my house and <persName>negroes </persName>and 
perhaps all will go&#8212;I will if possible come and see you in the <date n="Summer-1822">summer</date>,
again write and write fully.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Judge Austin</persName>, <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>   <persName>Mr. Hawkins</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
