<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0515">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Samuel Ayers and Others to Stephen F. Austin, 06-06-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Samuel Ayers and Others</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Lexington, KY</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 521-523
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-06-06">06-06-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Formed a "Texas Emigrating Society" to investigate conditions in Texas and Mexico and terms of settlement. Will the Government be a republic, will freedom of worship be allowed, etc.?</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Lexington (Ky)</placeName> <date when="1822-06-06">June 6th 1822</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir.</p>

<p>We the undersigned, being appointed a <persName>Committee </persName>by the <persName>Texas
Emigrating Society</persName> of this place, for the purpose of writing letters
to you and <persName>Joseph H. Hawkins Esqr</persName> of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, by our <persName>agent
Mr Elijah Noble</persName>, who is also one of the <persName>members of our Society</persName>;
Beg leave to state that the object of the <persName>Society </persName>is to receive and<pb n="522"/>
obtain through him, such Information as we can certainly depend
on, relative to the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>, and whether it would be 
advisable for us to settle there.   The Individual <persName>members of this Society
</persName>have been Informed, more than twelve months ago, of the existence
of a large <placeName>Grant of Land</placeName> made to you by the <persName>King of <placeName>Spain</placeName></persName>, on the
Condition of your settling on the <placeName>Grant</placeName>, a Certain Number of
<persName>American Families</persName>; such as <persName>Farmers</persName>, <persName>Mechanics </persName>etc; Since, or about
that time, we have seen Published in some of our <placeName>News Papers</placeName> 
abstracts of letters said to be from yourself and others, stating that
great offers in land were made to <persName>settlers </persName>who would emigrate to that
<placeName>Country</placeName>, being However, unwilling to Venture so Important an
undertaking, without a Certainty(having heard various and 
contradictory accounts from there, both as to its local situation and 
advantages, and its political situation.) The <persName>Company </persName>determined to
send a <persName>Commissioner</persName>, on whom they can depend for all the necessary
Information. We would therefore feel ourselves under great 
obligations to you, for such Information as you may deem necessary as
well as satisfactory answers to the following questions.  Is it a Rich
and Healthy Country possessed of the advantages of Navigation?
and to what extent?   Is your Grant an Indisputable Title, and how
large is Its Boundary? Have you yet made up the Number of <persName>settlers</persName>
which you designed to receive? If so, can other grants be obtained,
and upon what terms? If your Number is not made up, what quantity
of Good Land do you offer to <persName>settlers</persName>, and their <persName>Families </persName>and upon
what Terms? What is the present Policy of your Country, and what
the future prospects? Will it ever become a <placeName>republic</placeName>, so desirable
generally to the people of the <placeName>United States</placeName>? Will the Liberty of
Conscience, and of speech, be Granted to the present <persName>settlers</persName>, and the
Hight of worshiping their God according to the dictates of their own
consciences? Will the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName> be a separate Government
or will it be under the same government and Laws, as that of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>?
and will free access through the Country be Granted to <persName>Travellers</persName>
and <persName>Traders</persName>. Your full and unreserv'd answer to the foregoing
Interrogatories, together with such other Information as you may
think Interesting to the society; in writing, will be Very Desirable,
and thankfully received. This <persName>society </persName>is Composed of <persName>Farmers</persName>, and
<persName>Mechanics </persName>and <persName>Manufacturers</persName>, with a few <persName>Merchants </persName>and 
<persName>Professional Characters</persName>. Some of them are  wealthy, others have been
wealthy, but have fallen Victims to the Changes and difficulties of the
time, through the unguarded Policy of our Country, and some are
young beginers: all of whom are respectable and industrious, and
will carry with them such letters of recommendation as you may 
require (for we will not receive any but such as we believe are such)
and would if encouraged be a great acquisition to any new Country.<pb n="523"/>
We formed ourselves into a <persName>society </persName>with a Constitution and Laws
for our <persName>Government </persName>subject to the laws of the Land to which we may
emigrate, which we think will not only Facilitate our Journey and
safety in moving; but will very much add to our security and 
Happiness, when we reach there. Should your answers be satisfactory to
<persName>Mr Noble</persName>, our <persName>Friend </persName>and <persName>agent</persName>, and he should be pleased with the
country generally we have authorized him to make arrangements
for at least from Thirty to Fifty <persName>Familys</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>Saml Ayers</persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Richd Sharpe</persName></p>
<p><persName>Dane Halstead </persName>   [Rubric]</p>
<p><persName>Wm. Hanson</persName> (?)</p>
<p><persName>Members of the Comte</persName></p>
<p>[Addressed:] The <persName>Honorable Stephen F. Austin</persName>  <placeName>Province of
Texas</placeName><persName> Mr E. Noble</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
