<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0423">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Joseph H. Hawkins, 11-14-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Joseph H. Hawkins
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, LA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 428-429
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Agreement</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-11-14">11-14-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Hawkins advances $4,000 and becomes partner with half interest in profits from colonization.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p>Articles of agreement made and concluded this <date when="1821-11-14">14 day of Novr 1821</date>,
between <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName> and <persName>Joseph H. Hawkins</persName> of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></p>

<p>witnesseth:</p>

<p>That whereas a contract was heretofore entered into between the
parties hereto, The said <persName>Austin </persName>acting for and in behalf of his <persName>father</persName>
<persName>Moses Austin</persName>, and in virtue of authority from him, whereby the said
<persName>Moses Austin</persName> by his <persName>agent </persName>and <persName>son</persName>, covenanted and agreed to sell, and
did sell to <persName>Jos. H. Hawkins</persName> one equal half part of all lands granted
by the <persName>Spanish govt</persName> to said <persName>Moses Austin</persName> in the <placeName>province of Texas</placeName>,
together with one equal half part of <placeName>town lotts</placeName>, emoluments, profits,
monies or effects derivable by the settlement and sale of the lands and
lotts so agreed to be settled by said <persName>Moses Austin</persName>, and whereas since the
death of said <persName>Moses Austin</persName> the <persName>Spanish govt</persName> in <placeName>Texas </placeName>have confirmed
to said <persName>S. F. Austin</persName> the grant of lands originally contemplated to
be granted his <persName>father</persName>, the said <persName>Stephen F.</persName> having resolved to effect
the Settlement and carry the <placeName>grant </placeName>into execution upon the same
principles stipulated and agreed by his said deceased <persName>father </persName>and
whereas the consideration to be paid by said <persName>Hawkins </persName>to said <persName>Moses
Austin</persName> was the advance of the monies necessary to defray the 
expences incured in obtaining said <placeName>grant</placeName>. And which have been already
advanced by said <persName>Hawkins </persName>and the <persName>parties </persName>hereto covenant and agree
as follows.</p>

<p>The said <persName>S. F. Austin</persName> hereby acknowledges to have recd from said
<persName>Hawkins </persName>the sum of Four thousand dollars in full of all monies to
be advanced by him under this contract, or the contract before 
referred to, made by said <persName>S. F. Austin</persName> under the direction and 
authority of and for his <persName>father </persName>as aforesaid, And for and in 
consideration of the said sum of four thousand dollars so paid by said 
<persName>Hawkins</persName>, the said <persName>S. F. Austin</persName> doth hereby for himself and the other legal
representatives of his said <persName>Father </persName>covenant and agree, that after
meeting the necessary expenses of surveying the said <persName>Hawkins </persName>shall
be entitled to and receive one equal half part of the monies, effects,
property and profits arising from the sale of lands, lotts, or from
any other sources growing out of the <placeName>grant of lands</placeName> before referred
to, or the settlement thereof, And all lands lotts and other property<pb n="429"/>
so derived shall be from time to time divided between said <persName>parties</persName>
hereto in equal moities.</p>

<p>And it is furthermore covenanted and agreed by and between the
<persName>parties </persName>hereto that a joint and equal copartnecy is established between
said <persName>S. F. Austin </persName>and said <persName>Hawkins </persName>in all matters and concerns 
touching the lands to be granted to them or either of them, or touching
the emoluments or profits claimable from said <placeName>Grant of lands</placeName> or to
the sale or settlement thereof, and all other purposes and objects in
which they may embark in said <placeName>province of Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>The said <persName>Austin </persName>furthermore covenants and agrees to cause as
many individual grants of lands to be made to said <persName>Hawkins </persName>and
himself and to such persons as they shall name as can be obtained
from the proper and legal authority in said <placeName>province of Texas</placeName>, and
in all lands, granted to said <persName>Austin </persName>and <persName>Hawkins </persName>either party is at
liberty to consider himself a joint owner should he elect to do so.</p>

<p>In embarking in objects requiring additional disburcements of
monies or monied responsibilities it must be done by joint and 
mutual consent.</p>

<p>Witness our hands and Seals this <date when="1821-11-14">14 Novr 1821.</date></p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>
<p><persName>Joseph H. Hawkins</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
