<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0392">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William Eads to James Bryan and Mrs. Mary Austin, 06-23-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William Eads</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James Bryan 
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mrs. Mary Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Sangamo Clear Lake</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Hazel Run, MO</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 396-397
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-06-23">06-23-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Condolence upon the death of Moses Austin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Sangamo Clear Lake</placeName> <date when="1821-06-23">June 23d-1821</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr J Bryan</persName></p>

<p>Sir I recvd yours of the <date when="1821-06-16">16th Instant</date> which I was very sorry to
hear of the Death of your <persName>father </persName>and illness of your <persName>mother </persName>but
happy to find your <persName>family </persName>in a reasonable stait of helth we are all
in a good stait of helth in this section of the Country you desire
to know something of our country as for my part I am well pleased
With this part as to the soil none to exceed it we have good water
and timber none to exceed our Country on the <placeName>North side of the
Sangamo</placeName> is high dry soil handsome for farming well furnished with
good <placeName>mill streams</placeName> this on the South side is not thus furnished in no
respect the Cuntry is low and wet on two much of a ded leavele the
water is Confined in ponds in the wet season and makes bad 
traveling In the spring&#8212;I think I can say as it Respects the helth of the
people in this part I dont apprehend the least dangere heare more
than their from the appearance of the Cuntry and people last season
and this&#8212;I have nothing of grait importance only we air brought in
to a Cuntry our first court in this infant part was held on the <date when="1821-05-07">first
Monday of May</date> so that it put it out of my power to answer your first
by haveing a new County all that was in commission was thrown
out and remained untill very recently so that the business could not
be dun as it respects that business of yours and <persName>Mr Alley</persName>s this has
been transacted so long that I Cannot be positive about the time nor
number of bushels   I remember hailing the Corn and delivering it<pb n="397"/>
at the still house neither can I remember the dates stated in the 
accounts only it was in <date n="xx-xx-1818">1818 </date>I have not Convirsd with <persName>Mr Alley</persName> on
the subject yet it may be on Examination things may occur to my
mmd that dose not at this time so no more on this subject my <persName>family</persName>
send their respect to you and your lady</p>

<p><persName>Wm Eads</persName></p>
<p>We wish to drop a line to your <persName>mother</persName>.   Dier madam we air very
sory to hear of the loss of your Companion   it is a natural case for
us to morn after a friend But we only Come to gather for life   the
lord giveth and the lord taketh a way   we ought to Bless the name
ot the lord   I dont Consider your Case in life Bad   you have an
affectionate sone and daughter that I am well satisfied will go any
length to make you happy   let us look forward and be faithful and
we have a friend that sticketh closer than a brother   we will 
remember you at a throan of grase and prey god to give you suffering grase
tor suffering times   let us looke to god for help to beare us up under
all our difficulties that we have to incounter in this world and if we
live faithfull in this world haveing a consiance void of offenc to god
and man   we shall meet to part no more whare all teers shall be
wipt from your eyes and go to receive a never faiding crown of life
bee faithful until death preys your unworthy friend untill death   I
hope you and <persName>Mr Bryan</persName> will not for get to wright to me    if not
pnvit opportunity offer direct your letters to <placeName>Edwardsville postoffis</placeName>
and I will call for them   give our compliments to <persName>Mr J Austin </persName>and
family</p>

                                                                    <p><persName>WmEADS</persName></p>

<p><persName>Mrs Moses Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] To <persName>Mr J Bryan</persName> <placeName>Hazel Run St Genevieve County
Stait of Missouri</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
