<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0459">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>E. A. Elliott to James Bryan, 12-26-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>E. A. Elliott</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-12">07-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Mr Grafton
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James Bryan
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">St. Genevieve, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 456-458
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-12-26">12-26-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Political and family news.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>St Genevieve</placeName> <date when="1821-12-26">Decr 26 [1821]</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr James Bryan</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir <persName>Mr Hatch</persName> from the <placeName>Little Rock</placeName> caleled on me <date when="1821-12-25">yesterday</date>
Eight days from that place&#8212; I am happy to Inform you he passed
<persName>Brother Henry</persName> and party Friday morning <placeName>near the Crossing of St
Francis River</placeName>&#8212; all in good health and high glee&#8212; <persName>Henry </persName>
inform[e]d you of the proposed arrangements for Quieting all 
further altercation between the contending <persName>parties</persName>&#8212;<persName>Hatch </persName>says the
<persName>oppisite party</persName> are much chagrind at the result, while our party
exult at the prospect of peace and rapid Improvements, the <placeName>printing
office</placeName> is to be extablished imediately and many <persName>respectable Familys</persName>
will soon move in, particular our <placeName>Officers of Government</placeName> and our
<persName>Judges </persName><persName>Lawyers </persName>etc&#8212;, another circumstance will eventuly be in
our favour the <persName>Surveyors </persName>appointed by our <persName>Government </persName>to run the
line of the <persName>Choctaw </persName>Treaty have by <persName>express </persName>from <placeName>Washington </placeName>been
ordered to stop any further proceedings on that line and have come
in&#8212; <persName>Hugh Bradley from <placeName>Long Prarie</placeName></persName> also came in as <persName>express</persName>
stopping all Further surveys of Public Lands <placeName>South of the Arkansas</placeName>
untill the actual line <placeName>between the U States and Texas</placeName> have been<pb n="457"/>
assertained and run&#8212;which is to be done soon; I think it will be the
means of giveing a sure and profitable Job to my <persName>Brother </persName>a large
number of <placeName>Settlements </placeName>will be made on the <placeName>Arkansas </placeName>this coming
season a number of waggons and <persName>family from <placeName>Kentucky</placeName></persName> and 
<placeName>Tennesse </placeName>have also passed the rock lately on their way to <placeName>Texes </placeName>and by
their report their will be an immence Emigration this comeing 
season&#8212;, <persName>General Hogan</persName> has run through most of his property has
been compelled to part with his most valuable <persName>negros </persName>but I flatter
myself that <persName>Mr Ashley</persName> has secured our debt against him&#8212; we had a
letter from <persName>Cousin Mary</persName>, in good health&#8212; <persName>Mr Ashly</persName> had not 
returned from the <placeName>Courts at Hempstead and Miller countys</placeName> but was
dayly expected,&#8212; a Number of <persName>familys from <placeName>Mount Praarie</placeName></persName> are
preparing to Start and Join <persName>S. F. A </persName>as soon as possible but a 
number of those who talked of going have declined as they can not
swallow the Spanish Oath&#8212; <persName>Mr Vaughn</persName> and <persName>Mr Scallings</persName> at the
<placeName>Little Missouria</placeName> are both dead with a number more in that 
<placeName>neighbourhood</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>With regret I inform you of the unfortunate death of our Friend
<persName>Colo. English of <placeName>Hempsted</placeName></persName>, he had the last season Erected a 
complete <placeName>Cotton Gin</placeName> <date n="Fall-1821">this fall</date> he went to the post of <placeName>Washington </placeName>to 
purchase ropes and Bagging for his Establishment, (he by accident met
there with <persName>Mrs English</persName> Sick and destitute of the common necessarys
of life&#8212;although he had been so deeply injured by her he hired a
House and <persName>Servant </persName>to attend her during her sickness and left funds
for her future subsistance on Condition she should never again see his
<persName>children </persName>for as a <persName>Mother </persName>she could have no further claim to them,)
a few days after he returned while engaged at the <placeName>Gin</placeName> the Sleve
of his shirt caught by the Saw Cylender and drew in his arm which
was torn to peicies, in trying to extricate it his other hand was
caught most of the hand was torn off and other ways much wounded
the consequence was a mortification and he died in great misery&#8212;
I have also heard that the Vessells and Familys which were to go
from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> to Join <persName>S. F. A.</persName> had started and that their was
others in preparation&#8212;and also that <persName>Stephen </persName>was engaged in Survey-
and takeing Soundings of the <placeName>Bay of St. Bernard</placeName> for the purpose of
assert [ainjing the best Chanells etc.&#8212;</p>

<p>My health is some better yet I suffer much pain; from the presant
appearance of the weather I have but little prospect of getting to <placeName>St
Louis</placeName> one of my legs is very much swelled the Cords of the knee 
appear to be much contracted and fear will never regain their
Elastic[i]ty&#8212; have not yet been out&#8212; but enough of my 
Complaints<pb n="458"/></p>

<p>the <persName>family </persName>are all well   <persName>Sister Mary</persName> joins in love to <persName>Emily </persName>and
little ones</p>

<p>this will be handed you by <persName>Mr Grafton</persName>&#8212;if you have any news
please write me</p>

<p><persName>E A Elliott</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
