<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0399">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Maria Austin to James E. B. Austin, 08-03-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Maria Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Herculaneum, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Nicholasville, KY</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 404-406
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-08-03">08-03-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Death of his father. Finances.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Herculan[e]um</placeName> <date when="1821-08-03">August the 3&#8212;1821</date></p>
<p>my dear <persName>Son</persName></p>

<p>I wrote you in <date n="06-xx-1821">June</date>, giving, you an account of your dear <persName>Father</persName>s
death, Since that period my health has been so bad I have not been
able to visit this place till about ten days ago&#8212; I got your <persName>Brother
B</persName> to write you by the firs[t] mail that went out, also to <persName>Mr Walker</persName>&#8212;
it tis impossible for me to discribe the anxiety and many painfull
felings I experience in Consequence of your detention in <placeName>Kentuckey</placeName>
and not haveing it in my power to releive you, I now flatter myself
I have a prospect before me of releiveing you and puting it in your
power to return once more to your unhappy <persName>mother</persName>&#8212; I find from a
letter I have lately received from my ancient <persName>G-Mother</persName>, that I am
intitled to $100, 50 [$150]&#8212;and perhaps more, from the men that
purchased the land I sold in <placeName>Jersey </placeName>some years ago&#8212;Emeditly, on
the receipt of this information, I wrote to <persName>Mr W C-Carr</persName>, requesting
him to Sattisfy <persName>Mr Morton</persName>&#8212;and I would write on to <persName>Couzen E Sharp</persName>
to transmit the money to him&#8212; I have not received an answer to
my letter, neither can I&#8212;as I wrote <date when="1821-08-02">yesterday</date>; let you know whether
he agrees to my proposition, by this Mail however you will probably
know Soon after you receive this&#8212;as I requested him to write by
the first mail to <persName>Mr Morton</persName>, provided he thought proper to Comply
<pb n="405"/>
with my request, <persName>Mr Bryan</persName> is mackeing every Arrangement in his
power to Settle his business So as to leeve this <placeName>Country </placeName>by the last
of <date when="1821-09-20">Septr</date>. or <date when="1821-10-30">October </date>and Joine your <persName>Brother S </persName>on the <placeName>Collorado</placeName>,
where I expect he has, by this time arrived&#8212; I received a letter by
the last <placeName>Arkanw </placeName>mail dated the <date when="1821-06-28">28 of June</date> from <placeName>Nacotoches</placeName>, he was
waiting the arrival of his dear departed <persName>Father</persName>, not being acquainted
with the meloncholy event, as he had left <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> ten days
previous to my letters reatching that place&#8212;however he left 
directions with his friend <persName>Mr Hawkins</persName> to open my letters and if his
<persName>Father</persName>s illniss terminated in death, to Send on an <persName>express </persName>to overtake
him; which he writes me he did, in a few hours after learning the
distressing truth, so I flatter myself he knows ere this, the great and
Irreparable loss he has Sustaind in the death of such a <persName>parent</persName>, at
this Important time&#8212; I have every reason to hope dear <persName>Stephen</persName>
will Succeed in the enterpprise, as the representitive of his <persName>Father</persName>
the <placeName>grant </placeName>will be transferd to him, he will be oblighed, to go to <placeName>St
Antone</placeName> to see the <persName>Govornor </persName>instead of going strait to the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>,
Several <persName>Officers </persName>with a guard was Sent in, with a Confermation of
the <placeName>grant for 300,000 acers</placeName> of land, with the privalage of taking <persName>three
hundred famalys </persName>with him and theay had ordors to conduct him
and as many of his folloers as chose to go, at this time, with him,
to the place and tacke possesion&#8212; oh my <persName>Son</persName>, how it greives my
heart when I reflect on the hardships Sufferings and fatigue he had
to go through to effect this great object and now to know that all
his fond and flattering expectations of realizeing future welth and
indipendence are now buried in the Silent tomb&#8212;for this afflictive,
dispensation we can find but little Consolation, though we should
endeavour to Seeke it&#8212;in that resignation which we owe to the will
of heavan withe me life is hardly worth asking for, my health is
so poor but for the sake of my dear <persName>Children </persName>I shall exert myself
to meet this and every other inrode upon my happyniss with the
fortitude Necessary to sustain it, I am sorry to tell you this place
is geting very sickly, <persName>E Bates famaly</persName> has been very ill with the
fever also <persName>H Austin</persName>s and allmost every other in the place, I shall
shortly return to <placeName>Hazel run</placeName> as your <persName>Sister </persName>is very lonesome without
her <persName>mother</persName>&#8212; I Sincearly pray this may be the last letter I shall
write vou in <placeName>Ky</placeName>&#8212;if <persName>Mr Carr</persName> will settle your bill with <persName>Mr Morton</persName>, we
shall be able to Sattisfy <persName>Mr Walker</persName> before your <persName>brother B[ryan]</persName>
leaves this&#8212;you must at all events return in time to go down with
him in <date n="10-xx-1821">October</date>, if I receive a letter to my sattisfaction from <persName>Mr
Car[r]</persName>, I will write you by the next mail and I hope you will not
loose a moment but get on to<placeName> Louisvell[e]</placeName> and get a passage on the
best terms you can, the money will be paid on your arrival here&#8212;
your old <persName>friends </persName>appear very anxious to see you and I think will<pb n="406"/>
give you a sincear welcome&#8212; <persName>Mr Honey</persName> arrived in his steam boat
two days ago from <placeName>New O</placeName>&#8212;he saw <persName>Stephen </persName>the day he started for
<placeName>Nacs</placeName>&#8212;Says he loocks well and is highly esteemd no young man has
more <persName>friends</persName>, and that he will be aided by the <persName>first people in <placeName>N O&#8212;</placeName></persName><persName>Mr Honey</persName> is very friendly indeed so you must get the better of your
prejudice to him he is now connected in the <persName>famaly </persName>and surely it
tis better to live in friendship than otherwise, I have filled my paper
before I knew it, farewell</p>

<p><persName>M Austin</persName>&#8212;</p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr James B Austin</persName> <placeName>NicholasVill Kentucky</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
