<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0574">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Unknown, 03-29-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico City, MX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 601-627
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Constitution Project</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-03-29">03-29-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Project of a constitution for the Republic of Mexico.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>City of Mexico</placeName> <date when="1823-03-29">March 29, 1823</date></p>
<p>We, the <persName>People of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName></persName>, having assumed those
natural and imprescriptable rights which appertain to us as members
of the great human family, an[d] in virtue thereof declared 
ourselves an independent nation, free from the dominion of old <placeName>Spain</placeName>
and all other powers whatever; and being desirous of establishing
and consolidating a system of Government founded on the solid basis
of Natural justice, equal rights, and common good, in order to
insure union, strength, safety, harmony, equity, and the blessings
of liberty to ourselves and posterity; do ordain, decree, and 
establish, this Constitution, for the <persName>Government of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName></persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Chapter I</p>

<p>CONSTITUTIONAL AND FUNDAMENTAL MAXIMS</p>

<p>Article 1. The <persName>People of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName></persName> are independent of
<placeName>Spain </placeName>and all other powers whatever, and have the sole, absolute,
and exclusive right of governing themselves as a free, Sovereign, and
independent Nation.</p>

<p>Article 2. All men as individuals, have certain natural, essential
and inherent rights; among which are the enjoying and defending
life and liberty, acquiring possessing and protecting property, and
in a word of seeking and obtaining happiness.</p>

<p>Art. 3. When men enter into a State of Society they surrender
up some of their natural rights to that Society, in order to insure the
protection of others; and without such an equivalent the surrender
is void.<pb n="602"/></p>

<p>Art. 4. The surrender of these rights must also be free, voluntary,
and without coertion, or it is void.</p>

<p>Art. 5 The rights thus surrendered are deposited in the hands of
the agents of the People, to be exercised for the common good, 
common security, and General happiness of all.</p>

<p>Art. 6 These agents constitute, and administer the national 
Government.</p>

<p>Art. 7 The sovereignty resides essentially and originally in the
<persName>People</persName>, and from its nature is unalienable, imprescriptable, and 
indivisible ; the national agents are therefore at all times accountable to
the <persName>People</persName>.</p>

<p>Art. 8 Government being instituted for the common benefit, 
protection and happiness of the whole community, and not for the
private interest, or agrandisement of any one man, family or class
of men; therefore whenever its objects are perverted, or public 
liberty manifestly endangered and all other means of redress are 
ineffectual, the people may, and of right ought to reform the old, or
establish a new Government. The doctrine of non-resistance to
arbitrary power is absurd, degrading, and distructive of the 
happiness of mankind.</p>

<p>Art. 9 The people have a right to assemble in an orderly and
peacible manner, to consult upon the public weal, give instructions
to their deputies and petition <persName>Congress </persName>for redress of grievances.</p>

<p>Art. 10 A well regulated <persName>national Militia</persName> is the proper, and
natural defence of a <placeName>Nation</placeName>, and no <persName>citizen </persName>shall be deprived of the
right of keeping and carrying arms; except in such cases, to be 
specially provided for by law, in which the public tranquility may render
it necessary.</p>

<p>Art. 11 All elections ought to be free, and every <persName>inhabitant of the
<placeName>nation</placeName></persName>, having the qualifications required by law, has an equal right
to elect and be elected into office.</p>

<p>Art. 12 Every <persName>citizen </persName>is entitled to a certain remidy, by having
recourse to the laws for all injuries he may receive in his person,
property or character; to obtain right and justice freely, without
being obliged to purchase it, and promptly according to the laws.</p>

<p>Art. 13 Every person hath a right to be secure from unreasonable
searches, and seizures of his person, his houses, his papers, and 
possessions, none of which shall be molested except in the cases and
with the formalities prescribed by law.</p>

<p>Art. 14 No part of a mans property shall be taken and applied
to public use except by his own consent, or by virtue of a law 
regularly enacted by <persName>Congress</persName>, and no duty, or contribution of any
description shall be levied or collected without due authority by law
of <persName>Congress</persName>.<pb n="603"/></p>

<p>Art. 15 The liberty of the Press and of Speech is so essential to
the freedom and improvement of the nation, that it shall be 
inviolably preserved, and can only be restricted by <persName>Congress </persName>so as to
prevent scandalous attacks on private character.</p>

<p>Art. 16 <hi rend="italic">Ex post facto</hi>, or retrospective laws are oppressive and
unjust, and no such law shall be passed</p>

<p>Art. 17 In all cases and at all times the <persName>Military </persName>ought and shall
be under strict subordination to the civil power, except in the cases
to be provided for by law in time of war, or invasion</p>

<p>Art. 18 No <persName>soldier </persName>in time of peace shall be quartered in any house
or hacienda without the consent of the owner, and in time of war such
quarters ought to be made in the manner to be prescribed by law.</p>

<p>Art. 19 No person shall be subject to Martial law except those 
employed in the <persName>army </persName>or <persName>navy</persName>, or in the <persName>Militia </persName>in actual Service.</p>

<p>Art. 20 The basis of the national representation is the population
including all native free born citizens of whatever descent, wheither
<persName>American</persName>, <persName>European </persName>or <persName>african</persName>, and <persName>foreigners </persName>who are considered
as <persName>Citizens</persName>.</p>

<p>Art. 21 Monopolies, and exclusive and special previliges, wheither
in favour of an individual, or an association, of <persName>eclesiastics </persName>or 
<persName>laymen</persName>, are prejudicial to the true interests of the nation contrary to
natural justice, and are absolutely prohibited; except when granted
according to the formalities of the law, for a limited period, as a
compensation for new inventions and improvements in the arts or
sciences.</p>

<p>Art. 22 No hereditary office, honors, titles of nobility, or any other
titles except those of office shall be granted.</p>

<p>Art. 23 No public money shall be drawn from the treasury or in
any manner appropriated except by virtue of a law of <persName>Congress</persName>; and
the <persName>President of Mexico</persName>, <persName>Minister </persName>or any other person who violates
this article shall be guilty of a high crime and punished according to
law.</p>

<p>Art. 24 The power of suspending the laws or the execution of them
shall alone be exercised by <persName>Congress</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 25 The entail of estates by primogeniture to the exclusion of
younger children (<persName>Mayorasgos</persName>) is calculated, arbitrarily to prevent
the distribution of property, thereby, in violation of justice 
enriching the few, and empoverishing the many, to create and 
perpetuate <persName>aristocracy</persName>, and to engender indolence, arrogance, vice, and
corruption, and is therefore distructive of individual happiness, 
subversive of national prosperity, at variance with the principles of a
free Government, and dangerous to the liberties of the people; all
such entails shall therefore be distroyed, and an equitable system of<pb n="604"/>
inheritance established by law, founded on the basis of equal justice
and national prosperity.</p>

<p>Art. 26 Despotic Governments have endeavored to keep the minds
of the people in darkness by prohibiting the introduction of books
proscribed for their liberal principles. Free Governments on the
contrary have thrown open the door for the admission of all without
exception, and experience has fully proved the beneficial effects of
this liberal policy in enlightening the people, who, very soon 
discriminate between any evil, irreligious, or immoral doctrines which such
books may contain, and the pure and virtuous ones; rejecting the
former, and profiting by the latter. All restrictions or prohibitions
therefore on the introduction, sale or reading of books, are calculated
to prevent the diffusion of intellectual light, and knowledge; to retard
the improvement of the Nation, by perpetuating ignorance, 
superstition and servile principles, and are at variance with the genius of
free institutions, and shall never be imposed under any pretext 
whatever.</p>

<p>Art. 27 A nation can only be free, happy and great in proportion
to the virtue and intelligence of the people; the dessimination of
usefull knowledge and of the arts and sciences is therefore of 
primary importance to national liberty and prosperity, and to effect
this great object, it shall be the duty of <persName>Congress </persName>to provide by every
means in their power for the speedy establishment of <placeName>schools</placeName>, 
<placeName>academies </placeName>and <placeName>colleges </placeName>throughout the whole nation for the instruction of
youth and <persName>children</persName>.</p>

<p>Art. 28 In order to prevent those who are invested with authority
from becoming oppresors; the people have a right, at such tinier
and in such manner as they shall establish by the frame of 
Government, to cause their public officers to return to private life, and to
fill up vacant places by regular elections and appointments.</p>

<p>Art. 29 A frequent recurrence to the fundamental principles of
the Constitution; a rigid obedience to the laws; and a strict 
adherance to justice, temperance, industry, frugality and all the social and
civil virtues is necessary to preserve the blessings of liberty and
good Government.</p>

<p>ADDITIONAL  ARTICLE</p>

<p>The Govt debts contracted in the name of the Nation by its legal
agents for the use of the cause of independence since the declaration
in the year <date n="xx-xx-1810">1810</date>, shall be acknowledged as a part of the National debt
of the <placeName>Republic of Mexico</placeName>, in the manner which <persName>Congress </persName>may 
determine by law&#8212;</p>

<p>All <persName>officers </persName>and <persName>soldiers </persName>who have fought for the cause of 
independence since the first epoch, and the <persName>widows </persName>and <persName>children </persName>of those<pb n="605"/>
who have been slain in the same cause deserve the gratitude and
thanks of the nation and ought to be rewarded so far as is 
consistent with justice and the state of the finances of the nation.</p>

<p>Chapter II</p>

<p>OF  THE  RELIGION</p>

<p>Art. 80 The Roman Catholic apostolic is the religion of the 
<placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName>.</p>

<p>Chapter III</p>

<p>OF THE TERRITORY OF THE <placeName>MEXICAN  NATION</placeName>  AND ITS  <persName>CITIZENS</persName></p>

<p>Art. 31 The <placeName>Territory of the Mexican Nation</placeName> is composed of the
whole country extending, from the division line established on the
north by the <placeName>united States of North America</placeName> and <placeName>Spain</placeName>, in the treaty
of limits negociated by <persName>Don Luis de Onis</persName>; to the <placeName>isthmus of Darien</placeName>
on the South; including all the <placeName>islands bays</placeName>, and <placeName>ports </placeName>appertaining
to the <placeName>Atlantic </placeName>or <placeName>Pacific coast</placeName> within said limits.</p>

<p>Art. 32. All free persons born in this nation of whatever descent
are citizens; also all <persName>foreigners </persName>who are naturalised according to law.</p>

<p>ADDITIONAL ARTICLE AFTER ART.   32</p>

<p>Every <persName>Mexican </persName>shall be faithful to the Constitution, obey the laws,
and respect the established and legal authorities&#8212;and shall 
contribute in proportion to his means toward the public expences, and
shall take up arms in defence of his country whenever called on
agreeably to law&#8212;he shall also be bound to serve in any office to
which he may be elected by the votes of the people&#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 33. The right of Citizenship may be lost by voluntary 
expatriation, by acquiring naturalization in a foreign Government, for
crimes according to the laws and for not being able to read and write
at the age of twenty years&#8212;</p>

<p>Chapter IV</p>

<p>OF THE GOVERNMENT, AND STILE OF THE NATION</p>

<p>Art. 34 The stile of this community shall be the <placeName>Republic of
Mexico</placeName>.</p>

<p>Art. 35 The Government is a representative Republic.</p>

<p>Art 36 The powers of Government defined and granted in this
Constitution shall be vested in three seperate and distinct branches,
to wit, the <persName>Legislative</persName>, the <persName>Executive</persName>, and <persName>Judicial</persName>, each of which
shall be kept as seperate from and independent of each other, as is
consistent with that connection which binds the whole fabrick of the
Constitution together.<pb n="606"/></p>

<p>Chapter V</p>

<p>OF   THE   <persName>LEGISLATURE</persName></p>

<p>Art. 37 The legislative powers herein granted shall be vested in
a <persName>Congress </persName>to be composed of a <persName>Chamber of Deputies</persName>, and a <persName>Senate</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>CHAMBER OF DEPUTIES</persName></p>

<p>Art. 38 The <persName>chamber of Deputies</persName> shall be composed of members
elected every two years by the <persName>people</persName>.</p>

<p>Art. 39 The number of <persName>Deputies</persName> shall be one for every 30000
<persName>inhabitants</persName>: but every <placeName>Province </placeName>shall have at least one deputy.</p>

<p>Art. 40 <persName>Congress </persName>have power to alter the ratio established in the
last article as they think proper.</p>

<p>Art. 41 To be a <persName>Deputy </persName>in this chamber it requires to be a <persName>citizen</persName>
in the enjoyment of his rights, over twenty five years of age, a native
or <persName>inhabitant </persName>of the <placeName>province </placeName>for which elected, of sound morality
good reputation, accredited patriotism, posessed of sufficient real
estate for a decent maintenance, instructed in the principles of
national and civil jurisprudence, or in the elements of agriculture,
Mining, Manufactures, or Commerce, in order to the more successfull
discharge of the high and sacred duties of the Station.</p>

<p>Art. 42 Provinces which send not more than ten <persName>Deputies </persName>may
elect one secular <persName>eclesiastic</persName>; <placeName>Provinces </placeName>which send more than ten,
and not over twenty <persName>deputies</persName>, may elect two secular <persName>eclesiastics</persName>;
<placeName>Provinces </placeName>which send more than twenty, and not over thirty 
<persName>deputies </persName>may elect three secular <persName>eclesiastics</persName>; and so on in the same 
proportion; but a greater number of <persName>eclesiastics </persName>than this shall never
be sent by any <placeName>Province</placeName></p>

<p>Art. 43 Should a greater number of <persName>eclesiastics </persName>be elected than is
permitted in the preceding article, the chamber of <persName>deputies </persName>shall 
decide which shall be dismissed, so as to reduce the number to that
prescribed, &#8212; The corresponding suplenties shall fill the cavancies
[vacancies?] thus occasioned; but should the suplente also be an
eclesiastic, the chamber shall order a new election for the district
which is thus left without a representative, declaring in said order
that an eclesiastic should not be elected for said district for that 
<persName>congress</persName>.</p>

<p>Art 44 Should it happen that a person is elected for the <placeName>Province</placeName>
in which he was born, and also for that in which he resides; he shall
take the seat for the latter, and the corresponding suplente shall
represent the former. The same shall be done in case a person should
be elected for two districts of the same <placeName>Province </placeName>when he resides in
one of them; but should he reside in neither of the districts for<pb n="607"/>
which elected he may choose which he will represent, and notify the
corrisponding Suplente accordingly.</p>

<p>Art 45 The qualifications of <persName>Suplenties </persName>shall be the same as the
<persName>proprietors</persName>.</p>

<p>ELECTION OF <persName>DEPUTIES</persName></p>

<p>Art 46 The Provincial deputations shall from time to time take
an exact enumeration of the <persName>inhabitants </persName>of their respective provinces
in the manner prescribed by law. This being done they shall divide
them into as many <placeName>election districts</placeName> as they may be entitled to 
<persName>deputies in Congress</persName>, so as to include as nearly as may be practiable
thirty thousand <persName>inhabitants </persName>in each district. The said <placeName>districts </placeName>shall
be designated by numbers where there is more than one in a 
<placeName>Province </placeName>; as the first, second, or third district of such a <placeName>Province </placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Art 47. The limits and bounds of the <placeName>elective districts</placeName> established
in the proceeding article, shall be clearly defined and made known by
the proclamation of the <persName>Political chief of the <placeName>Province</placeName></persName>, posted up in
the most public places in each <placeName>Parish</placeName>; which proclamation shall also
designate the capital of each district, or place where the electoral
<persName>Juntas </persName>of districts hereinafter mentioned are to meet.</p>

<p>Art 48 After dividing the population of each <placeName>Province </placeName>into 
<placeName>districts </placeName>as above stated, should there remain a fraction of more than
20,000, it shall form a seperate district and elect a deputy as the
others, but fractions less than 20,000 shall be added to other districts.</p>

<p>Art. 49 There shall be one <persName>deputy </persName>to the chamber of this name,
and one suplente elected from each of said <placeName>districts</placeName>.</p>

<p>Art 50 In order to carry the last article into effect, when an 
election is required either by the Constitution, or by an order for a 
special election to fill a vacancy; the <persName>Political Chiefs of the <placeName>Provinces</placeName></persName>
shall give public notice thereof by proclamation in every <placeName>parish </placeName>and
public place of the <placeName>Parish </placeName>designating the day or days of the 
election, which days must be the same throughout the whole <placeName>Province</placeName>;
in which proclamation the objects of the election must be stated and
that part of the Constitution prescribing the qualifications of 
deputies, quoted; it shall also name one <persName>alcalde </persName>and two assistents to 
preside as <persName>Judges </persName>at the election in each <placeName>Parish</placeName>, and one <persName>Alcalde </persName>to
preside at the <persName>electoral Junta</persName> of the district.</p>

<p>Art. 51. The Proclamations spoken of in the last article must be
issued and posted at least three months previous to regular elections
and lit least one month previous to special elections.</p>

<p>Art. 52 On the day thus designated the <persName>Alcalde </persName>and assistants 
appointed to preside at the parish elections, shall assemble at the most
convenient and central place in the <placeName>Parish</placeName>, which place must have
been designated by them by public proclamation posted up at least<pb n="608"/>
15 days before the day of election, and being thus assembled they
shall appoint three secretaries to record the proceedings of the
election</p>

<p>Art. 53 The election shall then commence and the name of each
<persName>voter </persName>recorded by the <persName>secretaries</persName>, elections must be opened at 9
oclock A. M. and closed at 6. P. M. The law shall determine wheither
the votes shall be given <hi rend="italic">viva voce</hi> or by ballot, and shall regulate all
the necessary formalties of elections not herein provided for&#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 54. Each of the <persName>secretaries </persName>shall make a complete record of
the election, which shall be signed by the presiding <persName>alcalde </persName>and the
two <persName>assistents </persName>and witnessed by all the <persName>secretaries</persName>.</p>

<p>Art. 55 The caption of the records mentioned in the last article
shall state the name of the <placeName>Parish</placeName>, number of the district name of
the <placeName>Province</placeName>, time, and object of the election, names of the presiding
<persName>alcalde </persName>and <persName>assistents</persName>, and name of the <persName>Secretary </persName>by whom made.</p>

<p>Art. 56 Two of said records shall be sealed up in presence of the
said <persName>Alcalde</persName>, the two <persName>assistents </persName>and the <persName>clerks</persName>, one of which shall be
sent to the <persName>Secretary of the Provincial Deputation</persName> or <persName>Political Chief
of the <placeName>Province</placeName></persName> and the other shall be taken by the said <persName>Alcalde</persName>
or one of the <persName>assistents to the President of the Electoral Junta</persName> of
the district, and the remaining record shall be deposited in the
archives of the <placeName>Parish church</placeName> for the inspection of any person.</p>

<p>Art. 57 On the fifth day after the Parish election the <persName>electoral
Junta</persName> of the district shall meet at the place designated as the capital
of the district agreeably to the 47th article and at such house as the
<persName>president of the Junta</persName> may appoint.</p>

<p>Art. 58 The <persName>electoral Juntas of <placeName>districts</placeName></persName> shall be composed of the
<persName>Alcaldes</persName>, or one of the <persName>assistents </persName>who presided at each of the <placeName>Parish</placeName>
elections; and the <persName>Alcalde </persName>appointed agreeably to the last clause of
the 50th Article, who shall be <persName>President of the Junta</persName>.</p>

<p>Art. 59 The <persName>electoral Junta of the <placeName>District</placeName></persName> being assembled the
<persName>President </persName>shall in presence of the <persName>Junta </persName>open the records and add up
the votes taken at the parish elections within the district, and the
person who may have received the greatest number of votes in the
district, shall be elected a <persName>Member of the Chamber of Deputies</persName>.</p>

<p>Art. 60 Triplicate certificates of said election shall then be made
out by the <persName>electoral Junta</persName>, stating the name of the Province, number
of the district, time and object of the election and name of the person
elected; which certificates shall be signed by all the <persName>members of the
Junta</persName> present and attested by the <persName>President</persName>.</p>

<p>Art. 61. Two of the certificates mentioned in the last art. shall be
sealed up in presence of the Junta and endorsed on the back 
"certificate of the election for deputy in the _______  District of the Province
0f ________ (stating the number of the District and name of the<pb n="609"/>
Province) which endorsement shall be signed by the <persName>President of
the Junta</persName>. One of them be directed to the <persName>President of the chamber
of Deputies</persName> of the <persName>Congress of Mexico</persName>, and the other shall be
directed to the <persName>Political chief of the <placeName>Province</placeName></persName> to whom they shall
both be sent. The third certificate shall be deposited in the <placeName>archives
of the principal Church</placeName> of the place for the inspection of any one&#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 62 The <persName>Political chief of the <placeName>Province</placeName></persName> on receipt of said
certificates shall immediately send the one directed to the <persName>President
of the Chamber of Deputies</persName> to the <persName>Secretary of State for interior
relations</persName>, to be delivered as directed on the first day that said
Chamber meets after its receipt, and shall without delay 
communicate the contents of the other to the persons elected in an official
letter depositing the original in the <placeName>archives of the Province</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 63 When vacancies happen in any <placeName>Province </placeName>the <persName>Political
Chief</persName> on being officially notified thereof shall issue orders for an
election in the corrisponding district to fill such vacancy-</p>

<p>Art 64. The <persName>Chamber of Deputies</persName> shall choose its <persName>President </persName>and
<persName>secretaries </persName>and other officers and remove or change them when they
think proper-</p>

<p>Art. 65 The <persName>chamber of deputies</persName> shall have the sole right of
impeachment, or accusation against the <persName>President </persName>and <persName>Vice 
President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>; the <persName>Judges of the high tribunal of Justice</persName>; the 
<persName>secretaries of despatch</persName>; <persName>ambasadors to foreign Courts</persName>; <persName>Archbishops</persName>
and <persName>Bishops</persName>; <persName>Generals of the Army</persName>; <persName>Governors</persName>, <persName>Judges of the 
Supreme Provincial tribunals</persName> and all other officers not of less rank to
those above mentioned. A majority of two thirds of the members
present shall be required to form an accusation, which being decreed
the senate and accused party shall be notified thereof, and the 
chamber shall appoint a committee to conduct and manage the prosecution
before the <persName>Senate</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>SENATE</persName></p>

<p>Art. 66. The <persName>Senate </persName>shall be composed of two <persName>senators from each
<placeName>Province</placeName></persName> elected for eight years by the <persName>Provincial Deputations</persName>, and
one <persName>Bishop </persName>to be elected together with a suplente by the several
churches of the nation in the mode to be prescribed by law.</p>

<p>Art. 67 The oldest <persName>Bishop </persName>in rank shall be the first senator untill
another is elected according to law.</p>

<p>Art. 68 No other <persName>eclesiastic </persName>whatever except the <persName>Bishop </persName>or his
suplente mentioned in the two last articles shall be a <persName>Senator</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 69 To be a <persName>Senator </persName>it requires, in addition to the qualifications
for a deputy to the chamber of deputies, to be over thirty five years
of age</p>

<p>Art. 70 There shall be one suplente elected by the Provincial 
deputacions from each <placeName>Province</placeName><pb n="610"/></p>

<p>Art. 71 At the first session of the <persName>Senate </persName>they shall divide 
themselves into four classes; the seats of the senators of the first class
shall be vacated at the end of the second year; the seats of those of
the second class at the end of the fourth year, those of the third
class at the end of the sixth year, and those of the fourth class at
the end of the eighth year, so that one fourth may be chosen every
second year.</p>

<p>Art. 72 The <persName>Senate </persName>shall have the sole power to try all 
impeachments made by the <persName>chamber of Deputies</persName>. When the <persName>President </persName>or
<persName>Vice President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> are tried the <persName>President of the tribunal
of Justice</persName> shall preside. No person shall be convicted unless 
condemned by a majority of two thirds of the senators present.</p>

<p>Art. 73 Judgement in the cases referred to in the last article
may extend to removal from office, disqualification to hold any office
in the Government; banishment or death; but shall never decree
confiscation of property, or extend to the <persName>family</persName>, <persName>children</persName>, or <persName>friends</persName>
of the condemned, unless they should be accomplices, in which case
they shall be liable to be tried and condemned by the proper 
tribunal. The property of the convicted shall however be liable should
the judgement include embezlement, or deficiency of public money.</p>

<p>Art. 74 The party condemned agreeably to the last article shall
notwithstanding be liable to be prosecuted for damages by 
individuals who may feel themselves injured, and also to be tried and 
punished according to the laws in the tribunals of justice.</p>

<p>Art. 75 The <persName>Vice President of Mexico</persName> shall be <persName>President of the
Senate</persName> and shall have the casting vote in case of a tie: In the 
absence of the <persName>Vice President</persName>, or when he is acting as <persName>President of
<placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>, the <persName>Senate </persName>shall choose a <persName>Sub President</persName> to preside in his
place.</p>

<p>Art. 76 The <persName>Senate </persName>shall choose its secretaries and other officers</p>

<p>OF THE TWO CHAMBLRS OF <persName>CONGRESS</persName></p>

<p>Art. 77 No person shall be a <persName>Deputy</persName> or <persName>Senator </persName>in Congress who
holds any office under the Government, except in the <persName>Milicia</persName>.;
Neither shall any <persName>Deputy</persName>, or <persName>Senator </persName>receive any appointment
whatever from the <persName>Executive </persName>during the term for which he is
elected, without the consent of <persName>Congress </persName>being first obtained.</p>

<p>Art. 78 Each Chamber shall be the Judges of the elections, 
returns, and qualifications of its members and by a majority of two
thirds expel a member The one half and one more of each shall
be required to do business, but a smaller number may adjourn from
day to day and compel the attendance of absent members.</p>

<p>Art. 79 Each member shall keep a journal of its proceedings
which shall be published except such parts as may require secrecy.<pb n="611"/></p>

<p>Art 80 Each chamber may determine the rules of its 
proceedings, punish its members for disorderly and improper conduct and
with a majority of two thirds expel a member.</p>

<p>Art. 81 Neither Chamber shall during the session of <persName>Congress</persName>
adjourn for more than three days at a time without the consent
of the other</p>

<p>Art. 82 The Sessions of the two Chambers shall be held in 
seperate Halls, and shall be public, except when secrecy is required.</p>

<p>Art. 83 The two chambers may assemble in one Hall to receive
the communications of the <persName>Executive </persName>at the opening of <persName>Congress</persName>
and to elect the <persName>judges </persName>of the high tribunal of justice, or for any
other extraordinary purpose for the object of consultation alone,
but no law shall be passed while thus united.</p>

<p>Art. 84 There shall be at least one session of <persName>Congress </persName>every two
years; and the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> may by proclamation convoke
<persName>congress </persName>when he thinks proper.</p>

<p>Art 85 In the election of <persName>Deputies </persName>and <persName>Senators </persName>to <persName>Congress </persName>there
ought to be a due proportion of <persName>lawyers</persName>, <persName>agriculturists</persName>, <persName>Miners</persName>,
<persName>artists</persName>, and <persName>Merchants </persName>elected so as to combine in the national 
legislature the collective intelligence and experience of those great sources
and foundations of the nations independence, prosperity and wealth.</p>

<p>Art 86 The <persName>Members </persName>of each chamber shall take an oath previous
to entering on their duties, rigidly to support and defend the
Constitution of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and to discharge their duties faithfully to the
best of their abilities.</p>

<p>Art 87 Each chamber shall have power to punish contempts or 
insults offered to it&#8212;</p>

<p>Art 88 The freedom of speech and of debate in Congress shall be
absolute unlimited and inviolable and no <persName>Deputy </persName>or <persName>Senator </persName>shall be
questioned or called to account else where for what he may say or do
in Congress, they shall however be liable to be arrested and tried
for treason, corruption or any crime according to law__</p>

<p>Art 89 The <persName>Senators </persName>and <persName>Deputies </persName>in Congress shall receive a 
compensation to be fixed by law which shall be paid out of the National
Treasury.</p>

<p>OF THE POWEBS OF <persName>CONGRESS</persName></p>

<p>Art 90 The powers of <persName>Congress </persName>are                         ,</p>

<p>1.&#8212;To decree, amend and repeal laws.</p>

<p>2.&#8212;To levy and collect contributions and duties of every 
discretion.</p>

<p>3.&#8212;To declare war and dictate the basis and instructions for
making peace.</p>

<p>4.&#8212;To grant or deney the admission of <persName>foreign troops</persName> into the
<placeName>nation</placeName>.<pb n="612"/></p>

<p>5. &#8212;To raise and support an <persName>Army </persName>and <persName>Navy</persName>, and to declare the
military and naval force which shall be continued in service during
peace or war.</p>

<p>6. - To declare the grade and pay of the officers <persName>Marines </persName>and <persName>troops</persName>
employed in the land and sea service and to make rules and 
regulations for their government.</p>

<p>7.- To borrow money on the credit of the nation, and to provide
the mode of examining and acknowledging the debts contracted in
the name of the nation by the legal agents of the independent 
Government of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>since the proclamation of independence in the
year <date n="xx-xx-1810">1810</date>.</p>

<p>8. -To regulate Commerce with <placeName>foreign nations</placeName>, and to approve
of all treaties and alliances previous to their ratification.</p>

<p>9.&#8212;To establish and regulate the mails.</p>

<p>10.&#8212;To coin money and regulate the devise and value thereof,
and of foreign coin and to provide for the punishment of 
counterfeiting.</p>

<p>11. - To regulate weights and measures.</p>

<p>12. - To establish by law the mode of becoming naturalised and 
acquiring the right of citizenship.</p>

<p>13.- To promote the progress of the arts and sciences by securing
for a limited time to authors the exclusive privilege to their 
respective writings and discoveries&#8212;</p>

<p>14.&#8212;To constitute or distroy any tribunals or offices not specially
provided for in this Constitution and to regulate and establish the
forms and mode of judicial proceedings. And to establish the
form of tryal known in the <placeName>United States of North America</placeName> by the
name of tryal by <hi rend="italic"><persName>Jury </persName></hi>under such regulations as may be deemed
proper</p>

<p>15.&#8212;To define and punish pyracies and fenolies (sic) committed on
the high seas, and offences against the public rights of nations.</p>

<p>16 &#8212;To define and punish treason or Sedition</p>

<p>17.&#8212;To limit the freedom of the Press so as to prevent scandalous
attacks on private characters but no further.</p>

<p>18.&#8212;To provide for arming, organizing and disciplining the
Militia</p>

<p>19. To regulate the expences of the administration of Government
in all its branches.</p>

<p>20&#8212;To grant pensions for services actually rendered to the Nation.</p>

<p>21&#8212;To pass the necessary laws for granting, selling, renting, or
otherwise using the <placeName>public lands</placeName>, <placeName>mines </placeName>and all other public 
property.</p>

<p>22.&#8212;To adopt necessary and equitable measures by law, to keep
the <placeName>Mines </placeName>now occupied or possessed by individuals, in operation</p>

<p>23.&#8212;To establish <placeName>ports of entry</placeName> and <placeName>custom houses</placeName>.<pb n="613"/></p>

<p>24.&#8212;To promote and encourage every species of industry and 
improvement;</p>

<p>25.&#8212;To establish a general system of education and to appropriate
the public funds or any public property for the endowment and
support of <placeName>schools </placeName><placeName>academies </placeName>and <placeName>colleges</placeName>, or other literary 
institutions.&#8212;</p>

<p>26. - To appropriate the public funds for internal improvements
in roads, canals, or other works of public utility.&#8212;</p>

<p>27.&#8212;To grant incorporations to Companies, cities, villages or
individuals for limited periods for the purpose of Commerce, 
Banking, Mining, Municipal Government or any other usefull object;
provided no grants shall be made contravening the 21st Article of
this Constitution&#8212;</p>

<p>28.&#8212;To adopt all necessary measures for the preservation of the
public health, tranquility and safety</p>

<p>29. &#8212;To exclude <persName>ecclesiastics </persName>altogether from either chamber of
Congress and from all civil employment whatever. To establish or
distroy any religious order and to endow those established out of
the public property, or to divide or dispose of the property of those
distroyed as may be most conducive to the public good&#8212;</p>

<p>30. - To grant legislative or other powers to the <persName>Provincial 
Deputations</persName> relative to the internal affairs of the <placeName>Provinces</placeName>.</p>

<p>31. - To make such a division of the territory of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName>
into <placeName>Provinces </placeName>and <placeName>partidos </placeName>as may be deemed most convenient ana
just, which division when made shall be permanent as regards 
<placeName>Provinces</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>32. &#8212; To suspend for a limited time such parts of this Constitution
as may be absolutely necessary to the public safety in case of 
invation, treason, or other eminent danger to the State; provided that
such suspension shall cease the moment the cause ceases; and 
provided also that three fourths of each chamber of Congress concur
therein.</p>

<p>33. - To declare, define and limit the power which the <persName>Pope </persName>shall
exercise over the <persName>eclesiastics </persName>and <placeName>churches of this Nation</placeName> and to
reform the eclesiastic laws and distroy or remove all abuses which
may exist in the church. And to regulate and fix the salaries of the
<persName>curates Canónigos Bishops</persName> and all other dignataries or 
employments of the churches in the nation&#8212;</p>

<p>34. - To annul or prohibit excommunications or other censures of the
church or restrict them as they may deem proper.</p>

<p>35. -  To make all laws which may be necessary and proper for 
carrying into effect the foregoing powers, and the provisions of this 
Constitution generally.<pb n="614"/></p>

<p>Chaptee  VI</p>

<p>OF THE FORMATION OF LAWS</p>

<p>Art. 91 The power of forming laws resides in the two chambers of
Congress.</p>

<p>Art. 92 Any Deputy or Senator has a right to propose a project
of a law, doing so in writing and explaining the reasons on which it
is founded.</p>

<p>Art. 93 take 133 article of Spanish Constitution</p>
<p>Art. 94 take 134 Art of         do             do</p>

<p>Art. 95 take 135 Art. do        do             do</p>

<p>Art. 96 take 136    do               do             do</p>

<p>Art. 97 take 137   do               do             do</p>

<p>Art. 98 take 138    do               do             do</p>

<p>Art. 99 take 139    do               do             do</p>

<p>Art. 100 If either chamber reject a project of a law in any of its
stages it shall not be moved again that year.</p>

<p>Art. 101 Should the project be adopted it shall be engrossed so as
to include all the amendments or additions which may have been
made during the discussion, and then read in the chamber for the
last time, and if found to be correctly extended it shall be signed by
the <persName>Secretaries </persName>and sent to the other chamber.</p>

<p>Art. 102 When the project reaches the other chamber it shall pass
through the same formalities as in the first, and if approved without
amendments or alteration, it shall be Signed by the <persName>Presidents of
each house</persName> and immediately presented to the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>
</persName>for his approbation.</p>

<p>Art. 103 But should the project be amended in the other chamber
it shall be sent back with the amendments to that in which it 
originated where the amendments shall be examined and approved or 
rejected as the majority may decide</p>

<p>Art. 104 Should the amendments be approved, the project shall
be reextended so as to include them, but should they be amended or
rejected, they shall be sent back together with the project to the
chamber where they were made, with a request that they should be
relinquished, or that the new amendments should be agreed to.</p>

<p>Art 105. In case of a total disagreement between the two chambers,
a <persName>committee </persName>may be appointed by each to confer relative to the 
disagreement, who shall report to their respective chambers, and such
measures shall then be adopted as the majority in each chamber
may decide&#8212;</p>

<p>Art, 106 Every project of a law, resolution, order or ordinance to
which the concurrence of the <persName>Senate </persName>and <persName>Chamber of deputies</persName> is
necessary, (except a question of adjournment) shall be presented to
the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> for his approbation before the same shall<pb n="615"/>
take effect; if he approves it, he shall write at the bottom 
"approved " date it and sign his name: but should he disapprove it he
shall return it with his objections to the Chamber in which it 
originated who shall enter the objections on their journal and proceed to
reconsider it.</p>

<p>Art. 107 If after such a reconsideration two thirds of that 
chamber shall reapprove of the project as originally passed, it shall be
sent to the other chamber, and if approved in like manner by two
thirds of that chamber it shall be a law and the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>
shall sign and publish it as such.</p>

<p>Art. 108 If any project of a law is not returned by the <persName>President
of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> within thirty days after it is presented to him, it shall be
a law and immediately published as such.</p>

<p>Art. 109 The laws after being signed by the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>
shall be attested by the <persName>Secretary of State</persName> for interior and exterior
relations, and immediately published throughout the nation in the
manner and with the formalities which <persName>Congress </persName>may prescribe.</p>

<p>Chapter VII</p>
<p>executive</p>

<p>Art. 110 The Executive power shall be exercised by a <persName>President</persName>
to be stiled "the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>."</p>

<p>Art. Ill There shall also be a <persName>Vice President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>, who in
case of the death, removal from office, resignation, or inability to act
of the <persName>President</persName>, shall exercise his duties.</p>

<p>Art. 112 <persName>Congress </persName>shall declare by law, who shall exercise the
executive power in case of the death, resignation, removal, or 
inability to act of the <persName>President </persName>and <persName>Vice President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> at the same
time; provided that in such a case the exercise of said power shall
only be <hi rend="italic">pro tempore</hi> and until a new election is ordered by Congress
which shall be done as soon as practicable, to fill the vacancies thus
occasioned in those two offices, which elections shall be in the same
manner prescribed for regular Presidential elections, and the 
persons elected shall serve for the residue of the presidential term, and
no longer.</p>

<p>Art 113 The persons elected to fill the vacancies mentioned in the
last article may be eligible to be reelected for the same offices at the
regular Presidential election provided they should not have served
for more than 4 years</p>

<p>Art. 114 <persName>Congress </persName>shall by law establish the titles (tratamiento) of
the <persName>President </persName>and <persName>Vice President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> and of all other officers
and departments of the Government in all its branches.<pb n="616"/></p>

<p>Art. 115 The <persName>President </persName>and <persName>Vice President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> shall be
elected for the term of 8 years in the following manner&#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 116 The <persName>Provincial Deputations of each <placeName>Province</placeName></persName> shall give
as many votes for <persName>President </persName>and <persName>Vice President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>, as the
<placeName>Province </placeName>may be entitled to <persName>deputies </persName>and <persName>Senators </persName>in Congress.</p>

<p>Art. 117 The one half and one more of all the members must be
present to render the <persName>Provincial deputation</persName> competent to vote for
<persName>P.</persName> and <persName>V. P. of Mexico</persName>, to elect <persName>Senators</persName>, to pass petitions for the
removal or impeachment of <persName>officers</persName>, to exercise legislative powers,
and for all other business of an important nature, but <persName>congress </persName>may
by law authorise a less number to dispatch affairs of minor 
consequence&#8212;[This is the same as article 220 on Government of the
Provinces]</p>

<p>Art. 118 The votes for <persName>President </persName>and <persName>Vice President</persName> being thus
agreed on, four certificates thereof shall be made out and signed by
the <persName>President of the Deputation</persName> and the <persName>secretary </persName>and then sealed
up, all of which shall be done in open and public session, and 
completely concluded before any adjournment shall be allowed.</p>

<p>Art. 119 One of the certificates mentioned in the last article shall
be sent to the <persName>Secretary of State of interior relations</persName>, one to the
<persName>President of the Senate</persName>, one to the <persName>President of the Chamber of
Deputies</persName>, and the fourth shall be deposited in the respective <placeName>archives
of the Provincial Deputations </placeName>for the purpose herein after mentioned.</p>

<p>Art. 120 The returns seat as directed in the last article shall be
enclosed in an official letter, and shall not be opened except as 
hereinafter ordered.</p>

<p>Art. 121 The Said elections by the <persName>Provincial Deputations</persName> shall
be on a day, which shall be exactly 6 months previous to the 
expiration of the term of the <persName>President </persName>then in office.</p>

<p>Art. 122 On a day which shall be exactly six months previous
to the expiration of the term of the <persName>President </persName>then in office the
<persName>Senate </persName>and <persName>Chamber of Deputies</persName> shall meet in one chamber, and
the <persName>Secretaries of dispatch</persName> and <persName>Judges of the high tribunal of Justice</persName>
shall be notified to attend. &#8212;The <persName>Secretary of State of relations</persName> shall
then in presence of both chambers, the Other <persName>Ministers of State</persName>, the
<persName>Judges</persName>, and <persName>Spectators in the Galleries</persName>, hold up the election returns
received by him, that all might see that they are sealed, and had not
been opened; he shall then open them, and declare their contents
which shall be recorded by the <persName>Secretaries </persName>and entered on the 
journals of each chamber, The <persName>President of the Senate</persName> shall then 
proceed in the same manner with the returns received by him, and the
<persName>President of the Chamber of Deputies</persName> shall then do the same.</p>

<p>Art. 123 All the returns recd having been thus opened and found
to correspond with each other shall be added together, and the per-<pb n="617"/>
son who may have received the greatest number of votes for
<persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> shall be declared to be duly elected and the
person who may have received the greatest number of votes for
<persName>Vice President of <placeName>Mexico </placeName></persName>shall be declared duly elected for eight
years next after the expiration of the term of the <persName>President </persName>then
in office.</p>

<p>Art. 124 Should the three returns sent to the <persName>Secretary of State</persName>,
the <persName>Presidents of the Senate</persName>, and of the <persName>deputies </persName>not agree with
each other, an <persName>express </persName>shall be sent to the corresponding <placeName>province</placeName>
for the original deposited in the archives of the deputation as
stated in the 119th article. And the two chambers shall then decide
on an examination which return shall be admitted, and wheither
the difference proceeded from accident, neglect or intention, and
take such further measures in the case as they may deem proper
to punish the person or persons concerned in such neglect or 
intentional alteration.</p>

<p>Art. 125 The election being concluded the two chambers, 
accompanied by the <persName>Judges of the high tribunal of Justice</persName>, and 
<persName>secretaries of State</persName> shall proceed to the <placeName>cathedral </placeName>or<placeName> principal church</placeName>,
and the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> then in office, the members of the
<persName>Provincial deputations</persName>, Generals and other officers of rank then in
the city having been notified to attend, the result of the election shall
be again proclaimed in the church and a solemn Te deum shall
be celebrated.</p>

<p>Art. 126 In case of a tie for <persName>President </persName>and <persName>Vice President of
<placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> the two chambers of <persName>Congress </persName>shall decide which shall be
elected.</p>

<p>Art. 127 To be <persName>President </persName>or <persName>vice President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>, it requires
to be a <persName>native of the Mexican Nation</persName>, or a citizen thereof at the
declaration of Independence in <placeName>Iguala </placeName>on the <date when="1821-02-24">24 of February 1821</date>;
to have been at least 10 years a resident within this <placeName>nation </placeName>next
previous to the election; to have attained the age of forty years, and
to be of distinguished and well known patriotism virtue and 
intelligence.</p>

<p>Art. 128 No <persName>eclesiastic </persName>shall be <placeName>President </placeName>or <persName>Vice President of
<placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>, neither shall the same person be elected to either of those
offices twice except in the case mentioned in the 113th article.</p>

<p>Art. 129 before entering on the duties of his office the <persName>President</persName>
shall take the following oath to be publickly administered by the
<persName>President of the high tribunal of Justice</persName> in the <placeName>principal church of
the capital</placeName>.</p>

<p>"I ____ do solemnly swear by God our Lord and on those holy
"<persName>evangelists </persName>that I will defend, fulfill, and support the Constitution<pb n="618"/>
"of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and so far as is in my power cause all others to do the
"same; and that I will well and truly discharge the duties of 
"<persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> according to the best of my ability so help me God."</p>

<p>POWERS OF THE EXECUTIVE</p>

<p>Art. 180 The powers of the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> are as follows&#8212;</p>

<p>1.-he is <persName>commander in chief of the army navy and militia of the
Republic of Mexico.</persName></p>

<p>2.&#8212;he shall nominate, and with the advice and consent of the 
<persName>Senate </persName>appoint all the <persName>Generals </persName>and <persName>officers of the land and sea forces</persName>,
the <persName>Secretaries of dispatch</persName>, <persName>Ambasadors</persName>, <persName>envoys</persName>, <persName>consuls </persName>and all
other <persName>public Ministers</persName>, <persName>Judges of the Supreme Provincial</persName>, and 
<persName>inferior tribunals of Justice</persName>, and all other <persName>officers of the Mexican 
Government</persName> not specially provided for herein; but <persName>Congress </persName>may by law
vest the appointment of such <persName>inferior officers</persName> as they may deem
proper in the <persName>President </persName>alone, or in the <persName>Governors </persName>and <persName>Provincial
Deputations of <placeName>Provinces</placeName></persName> or in the tribunals of Justice</p>

<p>3&#8212;he shall have power to fill all vacancies during the recess of
the <persName>Senate </persName>subject to its approbation or rejection at their first
session&#8212;</p>

<p>4.&#8212;he shall open the sessions of <persName>Congress </persName>at the periods of the
renovation of the Chamber of Deputies, at which time he shall give
an exposition of the State of the Nation, suggest such new laws
and amendments as he may deem necessary, and give every other
information relative to the national affairs proper to be made 
public, all which shall be entered on the journals and published by the
press for the information of the people&#8212;Subjects requiring secrecy
shall be communicated in special messages.&#8212;</p>

<p>5. he shall publish and execute the laws</p>

<p>6.-he may convoke an extraordinary meeting of <persName>Congress </persName>
whenever he thinks proper.</p>

<p>7.-he shall publish declarations of war, and peace</p>

<p>8.&#8212;he shall give direction and destination to the land and sea
forces so as to defend the nation from foreign invations, internal
commotions or any other threatend danger, and for the protection
of commerce, giving an account to <persName>Congress </persName>thereof.</p>

<p>9.-he shall quell treasonable insurrections and conspiracies
against the nation, or the public tranquility, and arrest conspirators
and disturbers of the public peace, observing all the formalities of
the laws, and rendering an account to either chamber of <persName>Congress</persName>
of all measures adopted in virtue of this power</p>

<p>10. he may convene the <persName>Secretaries of dispatch</persName>, for the purpose
of consulting them relative to the public weal; and may require<pb n="618"/>
their opinion in writing relative to any important subject connected
with their several departments;</p>

<p>11&#8212;he may require the opinion of the Provincial Deputation of
any <placeName>Province </placeName>relative to any subject interesting to such <placeName>Province</placeName>.</p>

<p>12. he may grant pardons for all capital or other crimes, or 
mitigate the punishment when strong reasons of equity or national policy
will justify it, except in condemnation by the <persName>Senate </persName>or high tribunal
of justice in cases of impeachment against public officers.</p>

<p>13&#8212;he shall approve or revoke sentences of court martial, 
agreeably to the provisions of the laws regulating those tribunals</p>

<p>14.&#8212;All the objects and branches of the public revenue and 
political economy of the nation, all scientific, charitable or other public
institutions principally founded and supported by the public funds;
the mints; national roads, canals and mines; mails; and other public
property shall be under the inspection and protection of the 
<persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>, according to the laws, ordinances and regulations
now in force, or which may hereafter be enacted relative thereto</p>

<p>15.&#8212;With the advise and consent of the <persName>Senate </persName>he shall nominate
the <persName>Archbishops</persName>, and <persName>bishops</persName>, and present for all dignitaries and
benefices of the <placeName>cathedral</placeName>, parochial and other churches, conformably
to the laws.</p>

<p>16.&#8212;he may make treaties with <placeName>foreign nations</placeName>, which after being
approved by the two chambers of <placeName>Congress</placeName>, he shall ratify and
publish.</p>

<p>17&#8212;he shall receive all <persName>Ambassadors </persName>and other <persName>public Ministers</persName>
and <persName>agents</persName>, and direct all diplomatic relations and correspondence,
rendering an account thereof to <persName>Congress </persName>from time to time.&#8212;</p>

<p>18.&#8212;he shall commission all officers of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName>, and
dismiss the same from service at his pleasure, except in the cases
stated in this Constitution, or those otherwise provided for by law.</p>

<p>19.__With the consent of <persName>Congress </persName>first obtained he shall permit
or prohibit the publication of the <persName>Pope</persName>s Bulls, and decree of the
<persName>Eclesiastic councils</persName></p>

<p>Art. 131 The <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> shall give to <persName>Congress </persName>every
information in his power relative to any subject whenever called
on by either Chamber, and it shall be his duty to cause the 
Constitution and laws to be rigidly and faithfully obeyed throughout the
nation&#8212;</p>

<p>He may request the advice of the <persName>Senate </persName>on any subject relative to
the national affairs</p>

<p>Art. 132 The <persName>President </persName>and <persName>Vice President</persName> and all other officers
of the Mexican Nation may be removed from office and punished
on accusation and conviction before the proper tribunal, of treason,
bribery, violation of the constitution or laws, embezzlement or fraud-<pb n="620"/>
ulent waste of public money or other high crimes, according to the
laws.</p>

<p>Art. 133 Every <persName>officer of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName></persName> below the rank of
the <persName>Vice President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> shall be removed from office by the
<persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> on the petition of 2/3ds of each chamber of
congress to that effect, in which petition the causes for wishing the
removal shall be assigned.</p>

<p>Art. 134 Every <persName>officer of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName></persName> appertaining either
to the general Government or the Government of <placeName>Provinces </placeName>or 
<placeName>Pueblos</placeName>, shall, before entering on the duties of his office, take an oath,
before some <persName>Judge</persName>, <persName>Governor</persName>, or other officer duly authorised for the
purpose, to defend, observe and support the Constitution of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>,
and faithfully to discharge the duties of his office according to law
and to the best of his ability.</p>

<p>Art. 135 Every person shall be disqualified from serving as 
<persName>President</persName>, <persName>Vice President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>, <persName>Senator </persName>or <persName>deputy in Congress</persName>,
<persName>Members of the Provincial Deputations</persName> or any other office whatever
who shall be convicted of having offered or given a bribe or reward
of any description to procure his election or appointment.</p>

<p>Chapter VIII</p>

<p>OF THE  SECRETARIES OF  STATE OF DISPATCH</p>

<p>Art. 136 There shall be five secretaries of Dispatch, to wit&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>Secretary of State for interior and exterior relations</persName>.</p>

<p>The <persName>Secretary of State for the Treasury (Hacienda)</persName>.</p>

<p>The <persName>Secretary of State of Grace and Justice</persName>.</p>

<p>The <persName>Secretary of State of the war department</persName>.</p>

<p>The <persName>Secretary of State of the Navy</persName>.</p>

<p>Art. 137 Congress may vary this system of dispatch as 
circumstances and experience may require.</p>

<p>Art. 138 To be a <persName>Secretary of State of dispatch</persName> it requires to be a
Citizen in the exercise of his rights, and over thirty years of age.</p>

<p>Art. 139 No <persName>Eclesiastic </persName>shall be a <persName>Secretary of dispatch</persName>, nor any
person related nearer than the third degree to the <persName>President </persName>or <persName>Vice
President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>.</p>

<p>Art. 140 <persName>Congress </persName>shall by law designate and fix the duties and
kind of business which shall appertain to each of the Secretaryships
and define the nature and extent of their responsibility.</p>

<p>Art. 141 X take article 225 of the Spanish Contn</p>

<p>Art. 142 X take Art. 226 of the Sp. Constitution</p>

<p>Art. 143 X take Art. 227 of the do- do-<pb n="621"/></p>

<p>Art. 144 X The estimates of the public expenees made in 
conformity with the last article shall be consolidated and reported to
Congress by the <persName>Secretary of the Treasury (Hacienda)</persName> who shall
at the same time give such information and make such suggestions
relative thereto, and to the public revenue and means of raising
money, as he may deem proper.</p>

<p>Art. 145 X The <persName>Secretaries of Dispatch</persName> shall be removed from
office should three fourths of each chamber of Congress request the
<persName>President </persName>to that effect, with out its being necessary to assign any
reason therefor.</p>

<p>Art 146 The <persName>Secretaries of Dispatch</persName> or a majority of them have
power to convoke an extraordinary meeting of <persName>Congress </persName>in case of
a total vacancy of the Executive power during the recess of that
body.</p>

<p>Chapteb IX</p>

<p>OF THE JUDICIAL POWER</p>

<p>Art. 147 The Judicial power of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>shall be vested in one high
tribunal of Justice to be located in the <placeName>capital of the nation</placeName>, One
<persName>Supreme Provincial tribunal of Justice</persName> for each <placeName>Province </placeName>to be
located in the <placeName>capitals of the Provinces</placeName>, and such other tribunals as
<persName>Congress </persName>may by law establish</p>

<p>Additional Article) The <persName>Judges of the high tribunal of Justice</persName>
shall be elected by the joint ballot of the two chambers of Congress
and commissioned by the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 148 To be a <persName>Judge of the high tribunal of Justice</persName>, or of the
<persName>Supreme Provincial tribunals</persName>, it is necessary to be a citizen in the
full exercise of his rights, more than thirty five years of age and
to have been a licensed <persName>lawyer </persName>with at least six years practice.</p>

<p>Art. 149 <persName>Congress </persName>shall by law determine the number of the
<persName>Judges </persName>and other <persName>officers of the high tribunal of Justice</persName> and the
mode of electing its <persName>President</persName>, and establish the rules of its 
proceedings and may extend or modify its powers.</p>

<p>Art. 150 The <persName>high tribunal of justice</persName> shall have jurisdiction</p>

<p>1&#8212;in all cases affecting <persName>ambasadors </persName>or other <persName>public Ministers</persName> or
<persName>agents</persName>.</p>

<p>2&#8212;in all admiralty and maritime cases, and infractions of the 
revenue laws.</p>

<p>3&#8212;in all cases of crimes committed against the laws of Nations</p>

<p>4&#8212;in all cases arising out of public treaties.</p>

<p>5.&#8212;in all cases where the <placeName>nation </placeName>or a <placeName>Province </placeName>is a party, or 
between one <placeName>Province </placeName>and another, or between <placeName>cities </placeName>or <placeName>Pueblos </placeName>of
the same or different <placeName>Province </placeName>relative to limits, or any other litigated
matter.<pb n="622"/></p>

<p>6.  in all cases of a criminal prosecution against any <persName>officer of the
nation</persName> for a violation of his official duties.</p>

<p>7.  in all cases of appeals from the <persName>Supreme Provincial tribunal</persName> or
<persName>Provincial courts of admiralty</persName>.</p>

<p>8.  it shall have a general inspection over all the tribunals of the
nation in the manner and according to the forms precribed by law.</p>

<p>9.&#8212;it shall decide on the constitutionality of the laws of congress
and in all cases of doubt as to the constitutionality or interpretation
of any law or other act of congress or of the provincial deputations
or any <persName>officer </persName>or department of the Govt provided that should it
decree any law of congress to be unconstitutional, such law shall be
immediately sent back to the chamber of Deputies together with
the reasons of the clecission and shall be reconsidered, and should the
two chambers pass it again by a majority of two thirds, it shall be a
law notwithstanding the opinion of the high tribunal</p>

<p>SUPREME   PROVINCIAL   TRIBUNALS</p>

<p>Art. 151 The <persName>Supreme Provincial tribunals</persName> shall be composed of
one <persName>Supreme Judge for each <placeName>Province</placeName></persName>, and the <hi rend="italic">"Jueces de letras</hi>
of the <placeName>Province</placeName>.</p>

<p>Art. 152 This <persName>tribunal </persName>shall have appellate jurisdiction in all
cases sent up from the <persName>jueces de letras</persName> or other inferior tribunals,
and shall have a general inspection and Superintendence over the
proceedings of all the <persName>inferior tribunals of the Province</persName>, in order to
see that justice is administered impartially, speedily, and equitably</p>

<p>Art. 153 The law shall prescribe the forms and manner of 
rendering effective the inspection and superintendence spoken of in the
last article, and also determine the rules of proceedings of this
<persName>tribunal </persName>and the number, names and powers of the officers to be 
attached to it, and mode of appointing them.</p>

<p>Art. 154 There must be at least five <hi rend="italic"><persName>jueces de letras</persName></hi> present to
make this <persName>tribunal </persName>competent to act, and should a <placeName>Province </placeName>not have
sufficient population to entitle it to that number of <hi rend="italic"><persName>Jueces de letras</persName>,</hi>
<persName>Congress </persName>shall by law order the <hi rend="italic"><persName>Jueces de letras</persName></hi> of two or more
<placeName>Provinces </placeName>to unite so as to form the necessary number, in which
case there shall be but one <persName>Supreme Provincial Judge</persName> for all the
<placeName>Provinces </placeName>thus united.</p>

<p>Art. 155 This <persName>tribunal </persName>shall hold at least two sessions each year,
and as many more as <persName>Congress </persName>shall by law direct, at such times,
and places, and with such formalities as the law may require.</p>

<p>Art. 156 The <hi rend="italic"><persName>Jueces de letras</persName></hi> before whom any cause pending
before this <persName>tribunal </persName>may have been judged in the first instance, shall
retire from the bench during the revision of such cause.<pb n="623"/></p>

<p>OF   PROVINCIAL   ADMIRALTY   TRIBUNALS</p>

<p>Art. 157 The <persName>Supreme Judge of the Provincial tribunals</persName> shall
also be <persName>judge </persName>of all admiralty Maritime and revenue cases which may
occur within their Territorial Jurisdiction</p>

<p>Art. 158 The number, names, powers and emoluments of the officers
to be attached to the <persName>Provincial Admiralty Courts</persName> shall be 
determined by law, also the times and formalities of holding their 
sessions, and the general rules of their proceedings.</p>

<p>Art. 159 In <placeName>Provinces </placeName>where there is no <persName>Supreme Provincial
Judge</persName>, <persName>Congress </persName>may by law empower one of the <persName>Jueces de letras</persName>, or
establish some other special tribunal to adjudicate the admiralty,
Maritime and revenue cases of such <placeName>Province</placeName>, under such rules as
the law may direct.</p>

<p>Art. 160 There may be an appeal from the <persName>Supreme Provincial,
and Admiralty tribunals</persName> to the high tribunal of Justice, under such
formalities and restrictions as <persName>Congress </persName>may by law determine.</p>

<p>Art 161 <persName>Congress </persName>may extend or modify the powers of the <persName>Supreme
provincial and admiralty tribunals</persName> as they may deem proper.</p>

<p><persName>JUECES  DE  LETRAS</persName></p>

<p>Art. 162 There shall be as many <hi rend="italic"><persName>Jueces de letras </persName></hi>appointed in each
<placeName>Province </placeName>as may be necessary to render the administration of justice
prompt and convenient to the people.</p>

<p>Art. 163 To render effective the last article Congress shall 
determine the number of inhabitants who shall be entitled to demand
the appointment of a Juez de letras as a matter of right which 
number shall not exceed 5000&#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 164 The Jurisdiction of the <persName>Jueces de letras</persName> as to territory
shall be designated in the mode to be prescribed by law, and shall
form a Judicial partido.</p>

<p>Art. 165 In the formation of the Judicial partidos mentioned in
the last article care should be taken not to divide <placeName>Parishes </placeName>if it can
be avoided.</p>

<p>Art 166 The <persName>Jueces de letras</persName> shall form the <persName>tribunals </persName>of first 
instance in their respective partidos, and shall have a general 
inspection and'superintendence over the administration of Justice by the
<persName>Alcaldes </persName>in the mode which the law may prescribe.</p>

<p>Art. 167 <persName>Congress </persName>shall by law determine the powers of this 
<persName>tribunal</persName>, the number, names, powers, and emoluments of the officers 
attached to it, and establish the general rules of its proceedings.</p>

<p>Art. 168 There may be an appeal from this tribunal to the 
Supreme Provincial tribunal in the manner and with the formalities
required by law.<pb n="624"/></p>

<p>Art. 169. The <persName>Judges </persName>of the high, and Supreme Provincial 
tribunals of Justice and the <persName>Jueces de letras</persName> shall be appointed during
good behaviour.</p>

<p>ALCALDES</p>

<p>Art. 170 <persName>Alcaldes </persName>shall be elected in each <placeName>Pueblo </placeName>in the same 
manner established by the Spanish Constitution and existing laws</p>

<p>Art 171 The powers and duties of the <persName>alcaldes </persName>shall be the same
prescribed by the Spanish Constitution and existing laws.</p>

<p>Art 172 Deputations may by law extend and modify the powers of
the <persName>alcaldes </persName>as they may think proper.</p>

<p>ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE</p>

<p>Art. 173 take article 242. Spanish Constitution</p>

<p>Art. 174  do    do    243.   do        do</p>

<p>Art. 175  do    do    244.   do        do</p>
	
<p>Art. 176  do    do    245.   do        do</p>
	
<p>Art. 177  do    do    246.   do        do</p>
	
<p>Art. 178  do    do    247.   do        do</p>

<p>Art. 179  do    do    248.   do        </p>

<p>Art. 180  do    do    249.   do        </p>

<p>Art. 181  do    do    250.   do        </p>
	
<p>Art. 182  do    do    254.   do     </p>

<p>Art. 183  do    do    255.   do    </p>

<p>Art. 184  do    do    257.   do        </p>

<p>Art. 185  do    do    258.   do        </p>

<p>Art. 186  do    do    280    </p>

<p>Art. 187  do    do    281</p>


<p>ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE IN CRIMINAL CASES</p>

<p>Additional article In criminal prosecutions the tryal of the facts
in the vicinity where they happen is so essential to the secure of
life, liberty, and property, that no offence or crime shall be tryed in
any other province than that in which it is committed, except in cases
subject to military-courts martial, and cases in which the public
safety, or evident and just reason of necessity, policy, or equity,
should require a tryal elsewhere</p>

<p>Take the whole of chapter 3d title 5th of the Spanish Constitution
<hi rend="italic">23 Articles</hi></p>

<p>Chapter X</p>

<p>OF THE INTERIOR GOVERNMENT OF THE <placeName>PROVINCES </placeName>AND <placeName>PUEBLOS</placeName></p>

<p>Art. 211 The political government of the <placeName>Provinces </placeName>shall be vested
in a Governor or Political chief to be appointed in each province for
four years; and in the Provincial Deputations.<pb n="625"/></p>

<p>Art. 212 The <persName>governors of <placeName>Provinces</placeName></persName> shall be commanders in <persName>chief
of the Militia</persName> conservers of the public peace and intendents in their
respective <placeName>Provinces </placeName>and their duties and powers shall be 
particularly specified by law &#8212;they shall be obliged to render an account to
the Provincial Deputations relative to every matter connected with
the Government or affairs of the <placeName>Province </placeName>whenever called on by said
Deputation therefor, and shall in all things obey and publish the
orders and decrees of the said Deputations when not repugnant to the
Constitution or laws of the nation, but they shall not be members
of the Provincial Deputations.&#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 213 There shall be a Provincial Deputation in each Province
composed of one member for every 5000 <persName>inhabitants</persName>, provided that
the number of <persName>Members </persName>shall never exceed fifty one whatever may
be the population of the <placeName>Province</placeName></p>

<p>Art. 214 The Members of the Provincial deputations shall be elected
every two years by the <persName>People </persName>at the same time and manner with
deputies to <persName>Congress </persName>provided that the records of the votes in this
case shall be taken by one of the <persName>assistant judges</persName> at each <placeName>Parish </placeName>
election to the <persName>Juez de letras</persName> of the Partido who in conjunction with said
assistants shall form the electoral <persName>Junta de Partido</persName>, in which the
votes for members to the Provincial Deputations shall be opened and
the same formalities observed in every respect as herein directed for
the <persName>electoral Juntas</persName> of districts&#8212;except that in this case one of the
certificates of the election shall be sent to the secretary of the 
Provincial Deputation, one to the person elected, and the third deposited
in the archives of the church in the place where the <persName>Junta de partido
</persName>meets &#8212;</p>

<p>Art. 215 The <persName>electoral Juntas de partido</persName> mentioned in the last
article shall be held at the principal town or Cabeza del partido -
and should there be no <persName>jeuz de letras</persName> to assist at the <persName>Junta </persName>the
<persName>Curate </persName>or <persName>alcalde </persName>of the place or any other person designated by the
Provincial Deputation shall supply the deficiency.</p>

<p>Art. 216 The limits and bounds of the <placeName>electoral Partidos</placeName> shall be
designated by the Provincial Deputations in the same manner 
prescribed relative to the electoral districts, so as to contain as nearly
as practicable 5000 <persName>inhabitants </persName>in each partido -</p>

<p>Art. 217 Should a <placeName>Province </placeName>be entitled by its population to more
than 51 <persName>members</persName>, the <persName>Provincial Deputations</persName> shall divide it into
fifty one electoral partidos, as equally as may be practicable and
each partido shall elect one member to the Deputation</p>

<p>Art. 218 To be a member of the Provincial Deputations it is 
necessary to be a <persName>Citizen </persName>in the exercise of his rights as such, more than
twenty five years of age, possessed of sufficient real property for
a decent support and a resident of the <placeName>Province </placeName>for which elected -<pb n="626"/></p>

<p>Art. 219 No person holding any office under the Government 
(except in the <persName>Militia</persName>) shall be, a <persName>Member of the Provincial 
Deputations</persName> - and not more than one tenth part of the members can be
<persName>eclesiastics</persName></p>

<p>Art. 220 The one half and one more of all the <persName>members </persName>must be
present to render the Provincial deputation competent to vote for
<persName>P.</persName> and <persName>V. P. of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>, to elect senators, to pass petitions for the
removal or impeachment of officers, to exercise legislative powers,
and for all other business of an important nature but Congress may
by law authorise a less number to dispatch affairs of minor 
consequence -</p>

<p>Art. 221 In addition to the powers and duties assigned them by
this Constitution, and by the Spanish Constitution and laws now in
force, or which may hereafter be assigned them by <persName>Congress </persName>the
<persName>Provincial Deputation</persName>s shall have power.</p>

<p>1 - To make representations to the chamber of Deputies against
the <persName>Governor </persName>or <persName>Supreme Provincial Judge of the Province</persName> for
misdemeanor in office on which representation the said chamber
may found an impeachment; or recommend the <persName>President </persName>to remove
the person or persons complained of from office according to the
nature of the offence, which recommendation shall be executed by
the <persName>President </persName>without delay -</p>

<p>2d To impeach the <persName>Jueces de letras</persName> for misdemeanor in office or
neglect of duty, which shall be tryed by the <persName>high tribunal of 
justice</persName> -</p>

<p>3 - To petition the <persName>President of Mexico</persName> to remove from office
any <persName>Juez de letras</persName> for misdemeanor in office, neglect of duty, 
incapacity or any other cause which may not be deemed of sufficient
magnitude to found an impeachment on&#8212;and the President on 
receipt of such petition shall immediately present it to the senate, and
if deemed well founded by a majority of that body, it shall take 
immediate effect and a new appointment shall be made to fill the
vacancy -</p>

<p>4&#8212;To exercise legislative powers relative to the internal affairs
police, and civil government of the <placeName>Provinces </placeName>to the extent and in
the manner which <persName>Congress </persName>may by law prescribe</p>

<p>Art.   The Provincial Deputations shall elect their own 
<persName>President</persName>, <persName>Secretary</persName>, and other <persName>officers</persName>; <persName>judge of the election</persName> and 
qualifications of their members and regulate the rules of their proceedings</p>

<p>Art. 222 The <persName>members of the deputations</persName> shall previous to 
entering on their duties take an oath to defend observe and support the
Constitution of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and faithfully to discharge the duties of
their station to the best of their ability -<pb n="627"/></p>

<p>Art. 223 The <persName>members of the Provincial Deputations</persName>, <persName>secretaries</persName>
and other <persName>officers </persName>shall receive a compensation to be fixed by law of
<persName>Congress </persName>which shall be paid by the <placeName>Provinces </placeName>-</p>

<p>Art. 224 every <placeName>Province </placeName>which has 20,000 <persName>inhabitants </persName>shall be
entitled to a <persName>Provincial Deputation</persName> and on the petition of the
Majority of the <persName>Ayuntamientos </persName>[to] the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> to that
effect orders shall be immediately issued through the <persName>Political chief
of the <placeName>Province</placeName></persName> for the election of the <persName>members </persName>and all other 
necessary measures shall be adopted to establish the Deputation without
delay -</p>

<p>Art-225 <persName>Congress </persName>may by law establish Special deputations in
provinces which have less than 20,000 <persName>inhabitants</persName>, or may establish
one Deputation for two or more <placeName>provinces</placeName>.</p>

<p>CHAPTER XI</p>
<p><persName>MILITIA</persName></p>

<p>take the whole of capitulo 2d titulo 8. S. C. [Spanish 
Constitution]</p>

<p>Chapter XII</p>

<p>PUBLIC INSTRUCTION</p>

<p>take the whole of titulo 9.    S. C.</p>

<p>Chapter XIII</p>

<p>OF AMENDMENTS TO THE CONSTITUTION</p>

<p>The State of <placeName>Texas</placeName></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Washington County</hi></p>
<p>Before me <persName>J. D. Campbell, a Notary Public in and for 
<placeName>Washington County Texas</placeName></persName> on this day personally appeared <persName>Major Moses
Austin Bryan</persName>, and <persName>Colonel Guy M. Bryan</persName> - who are well known to
me, and being by me duly sworn they state (and each of them) that
they are well acquainted with the handwriting of <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName> -
that the handwriting from the beginning to the ending of the 
foregoing instrument, "A Project of a Constitution for the <placeName>Republic of
Mexico</placeName> formed by <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName> of <placeName>Texas </placeName>- <persName>City of Mexico</persName>
<date when="1823-03-29">March 29 1823</date>" is the handwriting of <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName></p>

<p>(Signed)           <persName>Moses Austin Bryan</persName></p>

<p><persName>Guy M Bryan</persName></p>
<p>Sworn to and subscribed before me this <date when="1896-03-17">17th day of March 1896</date></p>

<p><persName>J D Campbell</persName></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><placeName>N. P. W. Co. Texas.</placeName></hi></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
