<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0635">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Samuel Williams to Unknown, 10-18-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Samuel Williams</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brazos, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 699-700
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Deposition</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-10-18">10-18-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Samuel M. Williams's deposition concerning loss of horses and responsibility therefore. Judicial procedure.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>In the month of <date n="08-xx-1822">August 1822</date> I was employed by <persName>Mr Jn° Hanna</persName>
and <persName>Israel Massey</persName> in <placeName>La Bahia</placeName> as an <persName>interpreter </persName>to assist them in
their business during the time of my being with them <persName>Mr Freeman
Pettus</persName> came there on business with <persName>Mr. Hanna</persName>, and previous to his
departure <persName>Mr. Hanna</persName> requested him to call (on his way home) at
<persName>Judge Cummins</persName>'s and take possession of a number of Horses and
Mules that were there belonging to sd <persName>Hanna</persName>, employ a person to
assist him and drive them from there to <persName>Mr. Pettus's Brother</persName> on the
<placeName>San Jasinto</placeName> w[h]ere they were to be taken care of until <persName>Mr. Hanna</persName>
would call for them on his way to the <placeName>United States</placeName>: I never heard
<persName>Mr Hanna</persName> say to the contrary and believed of course the Horses and
mules were considered at his risk <persName>Mr Pettus</persName> acting only as the
<persName>friend of Mr Hanna</persName> and<persName> Mr H</persName> paying all expenses, on the way as
I was afterwards informed the Cavellada Stampeded and a part of
the horses and mules were not recovered, still I heard nothing said
of <persName>Mr Pettus</persName> being considered liable for the accident until I was
informed by <persName>Mr Hanna</persName> that he had received a letter from <persName>Mr Pettus</persName>
informing him of the accident and that <persName>Mr H</persName>. should loose nothing
by it, (or words to that amount) Of the number of those Horses
and Mules their were ten that had been allotted by <persName>Mr Hanna</persName> for
the payment of some Coffee sugar and rice that belonged to <persName>Mr
Manifee of <placeName>Alabama</placeName></persName> which property <persName>Hanna </persName>and <persName>Massey </persName>had in
their possession and sold for their benefit previous to the departure
of <persName>Mr Hanna</persName> for <placeName>United States</placeName> he requested me as I was 
knowing to the circumstances of the stampede etc. to give him a certificate
that to the best of my knowledge the mules allotted for <persName>Mr Manifee</persName>
were in the Cavellada that stampeded and that the whole of the
Cavellada had never been recovered and that <persName>Mr Manifee</persName> as part
<persName>owner </persName>must bear part of the loss. <persName>Mr Pettus</persName> while in <placeName>Labahia </placeName>was
at some expense for board provisions for his return and I believe some<pb n="700"/>
little money <persName>Mr Hanna</persName> let him have the amt of the whole was to the
best of my recollection between forty and forty five Dollars which
sum was considered as to appear against <persName>Mr Pettus</persName>'s charge for
attending to the transportation of the Cavellada. The 
aforementioned Horses and Mules I know were considered by <persName>Mr Hanna</persName>
(with the exception of three or four mules) of an indifferent
quality. <persName>Mr Hanna</persName> having told me that the person with whom he
traded <persName>Mr David Price of <placeName>Labahia</placeName></persName> had cheated him in the quality
of the animals having delivered those of an indifferent quality: I
was afterwards informed by <persName>Mr Price</persName> that he had not given Horses
and Mules of good quality owing to <persName>Mr Hanna</persName>'s taking him in, in
the price of the goods given in payment for them.</p>

<p>In the month of <date n="02-xx-1823">February </date>I was at <placeName><persName>Mr Groces</persName>' place on the Brasos</placeName>
when <persName>Mr Massey</persName> came there and informed <persName>Mr G</persName>. he was in possession
of a note given by <persName>Mr William Pettus</persName> which he wished him to buy or
he <persName>Massey </persName>would attach a <persName>Negro </persName>and sell it to <persName>Mr Groce</persName>, <persName>Mr G.</persName>
informed <persName>Mr Massey</persName> that he had once had a <persName>Brother </persName>of <persName>Mr Pettus</persName>'s
living with him and that there had been a difference between them
and he was fearful that <persName>Mr William Pettus</persName> would think that <persName>Mr
Groce</persName> in purchasing the note or <persName>negro </persName>acted from feelings of
private animosity and declined having anything to do with it. <persName>Mr
Massey</persName> staid at <placeName><persName>Mr Groce</persName>'s</placeName> two days and nights endeavoring to 
induce <persName>Mr G.</persName> to trade with him. <persName>Mr Groce </persName>declined and <persName>Massey </persName>then
said he would go to the <persName>alcalde </persName>and get out an attachment. <persName>Mr
Groce</persName> advised him not and told [him] he believed he would be able to
arrange it without sueing.</p>

<p><placeName>Province of Texas Brasos</placeName> <date when="1823-10-18">18 Oct. 1823</date>.</p>

<p><persName>Saml. Williams</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Endorsed:] <persName>S. M. Williams </persName>    Deposition</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
