<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0682">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John P. Coles to Stephen F. Austin, 01-31-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John P. Coles</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 733-735
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-01-31">01-31-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Judicial procedure. Jury. Character of settlers.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Sir I send you a Transcript of the proceedings in the case of <persName>Peter
Whitaker</persName> on the <date when="1824-01-24">24th day of January</date> now past <persName>James Alexander
</persName>came before me and made oath that <persName>William F. Gibbon</persName> <persName>Peter
Whitaker</persName> and <persName>William Whitaker</persName> had stolen Hogs from <persName>John Mitchel</persName>
<persName>John Milican</persName> and <persName>Mr. Roberts</persName> sometime in the <date n="Summer-1822">summer of 1822</date> and
that they also had stolen three Horses from a <persName>Spaniard </persName>about the <date when="1823-08-30">last
of August 1823</date> upon which Information I found a warrant against
the said <persName>W. F. Gibbon</persName> <persName>Peter Whitaker</persName> and <persName>William Whitaker</persName> <persName>Peter
Whitaker</persName> was taken on the <date when="1824-01-26">26th day of January</date> and brought to a
Trial on the <date when="1823-01-31">last day of said month</date><persName> W. F. Gibbons</persName> and <persName>William
Whitaker</persName> not to be found said to have ran of to the <placeName>United States</placeName></p>

<p>On the day above mentioned the<date when="1824-01-31"> last day of January</date> the above
named <persName>Peter Whitaker</persName> was Tried for the above offences he being first
ask[ed] whether he was guilty or not declared that he was not
guilty and was Ready for Trial <persName>Mrs Alexander</persName> was introduced as an
Evidence against Sd <persName>Whitaker </persName>who first being sworn to make true
statements as the Law directs&#8212;stated as follows that sometime in
the <date n="Summer-1822">summer of eighteen hundred and twenty-two</date> she saw <persName>Peter
Whitaker</persName> the <persName>defendant </persName>in company with <persName>W. F Gibbons</persName> and 
<persName>William Whitaker</persName> at one time kill 2 Hogs the property of <persName>John Mitchel</persName>
and at different times Killed one other Hog belonging to <persName>John 
Mitchel</persName> and one belonging to <persName>John Milican</persName> and further states that she
lived at the <placeName>House of <persName>William F. Gibbons</persName></placeName> at the time and place
where those Hogs were Killed and has an Entire Knowledge of the
whole of the sircumstances</p>

<p>the Evidence being herd the case were submitted to a Jury of six
men who were duly qualified to Try the case the <persName>Jury </persName>found the<pb n="734"/>
<persName>defendant </persName>Guilty and returned a verdict as you will see 
accompanying this</p>

<p>Given under my hand this <date when="1824-01-31">31st day of January 1824</date></p>

<p><persName>Jno P. Coles</persName></p>

<p><date when="1824-01-31">January 31st 1824</date></p>
<p>Sir</p>

<p>as Respects this affair of <persName>Peter Whitaker</persName> the Evidence against him
is very positive and I am fearfull that they are altogether a bad set
my oppinion of the Matter is that <persName>Gibbons </persName>is very much of a <persName>thief</persName>
and has perhaps been the cause of those young men getting into
these bad habits he is their <persName>Step Father</persName> and has partly Raised them
this young man <persName>Peter Whitaker</persName> has the appearance of an Innocent
young man and appears much mortified&#8212;for my own part I feel
much disposed to pity the young man tho I believe he has done Rong
an order for the whole of them to leave the country Immediately
perhaps would be the shortest way of Ending the Trouble he the
sd <persName>Whitaker </persName>first paying all cost and charges before he should be
Released</p>

<p><persName>Jno. P. Coles</persName></p>

<p>There is also three Spanish Horses left in my possession the
Horses that were said to have been stolen tho the theft of the
Horses were not proven I have not found out the <persName>Spaniard </persName>name
that owns the Horses nor neither do I Know where he lives as also
there is an old Rifle Gun left Here that was taken from a <persName>duchman</persName>
by <persName>Gibbons </persName>the <persName>duchman</persName>s name not Known you will direct me what
to do with this property the Horses and Gun</p>

<p>as also State to me wheather <persName>Gibbons </persName>property can be taken to pay
for three Hogs that were stolen.</p>

<p><persName>Jno. P. Coles</persName></p>

<p>[Enclosure.]</p>

<p>Verdict of the <persName>Jury</persName></p>

<p><persName>District of Brasos Austins Colony Province of Texes</persName> Vs. <persName>William
F Gibbon</persName> <persName>Peter Whitaker</persName> <persName>William Whitaker</persName></p>

<p>the charges exhibited against the above Named Persons were
steeling of Hogs som time in the <date n="Summer-1822">summer of 1822</date> as also steeling of
three Horses about the <date when="1823-08-01">first of August 1823</date> we find the <persName>Defendants</persName>
<persName>Peter Whitaker</persName> to be Guilty of Steeling fore Hogs supposed to be
worth 10$ Dollars a peace and agreeable to Law in that Case we
assess three times the value which is One Hundred and Twenty
dollars<pb n="735"/></p>

<p>The theft of the Horses were not proven the <persName>defendant </persName>paying
all cost and Expence for Guarding at the rates of $2.00 for each
thirty fore Hours allowing Two men to be sufficient <persName>Guard </persName>Cost
as Respects his on Trial.</p>

<p><persName>James Whiteside</persName></p>
<p><persName>James Lynch</persName></p>
<p><persName>Micajah Byrd</persName></p>
<p><persName>R. C. Millican</persName>.</p>
<p><persName>Orlando Hopkins</persName></p>
<p><persName>Simon Miller</persName></p>

<p><persName>Jurors</persName></p>
<p><date when="1824-01-31">January 31st 1824</date></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
