<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0449">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James T. Dunbar and Others to Stephen F. Austin, 12-13-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James T. Dunbar and Others</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Baltimore, MD</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">New Orleans, LA</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 447-448
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-12-13">12-13-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Want information particularly about government and religious toleration in Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Baltimore </placeName><date when="1821-12-13">Dec 13.th 1821</date></p>
<p>Sir,</p>

<p>Having seen an extract of your letter on grants of land in the
<placeName>Morning Chronicle</placeName> of the city, and view the subject of great 
importance we are induced to obtrude on your notice, by addressing
you a few lines.</p>

<p>The liberal proffers of land in the <placeName>Province of the Texas</placeName> which
you are authorized to hold out to <persName>adventurers </persName>have attracted our
attention and raised an earnest solicitude to become more 
particularly acquainted than we have yet been or perhaps can expect to be,
through the medium of the public prints, on that subject. It is our
confident expectation, if the expense of getting to that country with
a <persName>family </persName>could be pretty nearly estimated, and if the character of
the <persName>government </persName>which shall immediately on our arrival direct us,
and of that which may at some short time subsequent be therein
established [should be satisfactory], that a large <persName>company </persName>might
soon be made up, provided that information on these points should
be such as to authorize our transition thither. No feature in any
government could be more abhorrent to men born in the land of
liberty,&#8212;and matured in the arms of universal toleration, than
religious restraint. The idea of an established <placeName>church </placeName>of any 
particular creed would forever banish from our minds the design of
leaving our natal soil. The consideration of toleration in Religion,
and the assurance that this will form one of the prominent and
auspicious features of the constitution will remove a thousand 
obstacles from the execution of our designs. The prospect of 
undisputed and permanent titles to land, and of quiet and peaceful 
regulations in the <placeName>Province </placeName>must also be powerful incitements to 
emigrants. The <persName>writers </persName>are aware that many difficulties and 
embarrassments must attend undertakings of this nature, and therefore it will
occur to you, Sir, that it must be greatly desirable to the <persName>emigrant</persName>
to obtain all the information possible on the subject, that he may
be the better prepared to encounter impediments, and to overcome<pb n="448"/>
opposition; and as there can be no source from which we can expect
so full, accurate, and satisfactory information as from him whom
makes these liberal proffers, we hope you will find in this our apology
for troubling you, and that you will assent to give us a clear and
candid statement in reply to this our humble letter.</p>
<p>Respectfully yours,</p>

<p><persName>Jas. T. Dunbar</persName></p>
<p><persName>George Keck</persName></p>
<p><persName>Peter Forder</persName></p>
<p><persName>Nathan W Peregoy</persName></p>
<p>N. B. Address to <persName>George Keck Inn Keeper <placeName>high St. Baltimore</placeName>.</persName></p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr. Stephen Austin,</persName> <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>.    To the care of
<persName>Jos. H. Hawkins Esqr</persName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
