<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0596">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Hewitson to James E. B. Austin, 05-26-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Hewitson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monclova, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Bexar, TX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 650-651
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-05-26">05-26-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker"> Commerce. Trespalacios declared a traitor.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mva [Monclova]</placeName> <date when="1823-05-26">May 26, 1823</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Bobby</persName>-</p>

<p>I have just had the pleasure of receiving a copious shower of
your communications, in one of which was inclosed a receipt of <persName>Dn
Jose Angel Rodgz</persName> <placeName>Pro of Durango</placeName> for collection - I am sorry to
state that this recpt can not be sold, or collected first because the
military Gent, is not well known and secondly because the great 
distance does not permit the recovery, the amount of writing and
answering letters to <placeName>Durango </placeName>would more than ballance the acct.
<persName>Dn Victor</persName> tells me there is no prospect of recovering this money -</p>

<p>I regret that I cannot forward you at present the Galappago.
as they are not made here I have sent on [to] <placeName>St Louis [San Luis
Potosi]</placeName> for one for myself sometime back and were I apprised of
your wishes timely, I would have sent on for one for you - I have
recd. two letters from your <persName>Brother </persName>one from <placeName>Satillo</placeName>, the other from
<placeName>Monterey </placeName>from which I have learned that his business has eventuated
happily for him and the <persName>settlers </persName>- Your obligation is here inclosed -
I wrote to <persName>Stephen </persName>at <placeName>Mt. Rey</placeName> and have not as yet recd an answer<pb n="651"/>
this <date when="1823-05-26">morning </date>I have seen the decree of the executive passed against
<persName>Trespelacios </persName>declaring him a <hi rend="italic"><persName>Traitor </persName></hi>and <hi rend="italic"><persName>Rebel </persName></hi>- you may judge
the result - he has lost all his employments, and I fear those 
<persName>Gentlemen </persName>in your place holding offices will have to bear the brunt of the
curse - <persName>Stephen </persName>can tell you the whole affair.</p>

<p><persName>Madero </persName>says he forward the money on to the <persName>Gov </persName>to pay 
<persName>Hawkins</persName>, and also had written and enclosed a draft on the <persName>Govr</persName>. for the
whole amt. of the obligation - that <persName>Mr. Hawkins</persName> had not answered
the letter inclosing the order, or any of the other letters on that
subject, that therefore his silence had manifested his conformity
with the <persName>Govr</persName>s. responsibility, and exonerates <persName>Madero </persName>entirely -
<persName>Madero </persName>has shewn me in his books that he has paid the amt. of the
note to the <persName>Govr</persName>. and that the last remittance was made through the
medium of <persName>Dn J Beremendi</persName> which was 150 Dolls, whom you can
ask I know <persName>Madero </persName>has sent on the money to pay this through the
hands of the <persName>Govt</persName>. and I believe the <persName>Govr </persName>to be the defalter <persName>Mr.
Hawkins</persName> ought to have informed <persName>Madero</persName>, when he recd. his order on
the <persName>Govr</persName>. last <date n="01-xx-1822">Novr</date>. that it was not paid and consequently have it
protested, but instead of this he holds over the order without 
acquainting <persName>Madero </persName>that it was not paid whereas at the same [time]
the <persName>Govr </persName>had been furnished with funds from here to meet the 
payment of the draft - now the <persName>Govr</persName>. is gone to <persName>H.</persName> and <persName>Madero </persName>will
not consider himself bound to take up the matter saying that <persName>Govr</persName>.
is <persName>Hawkins </persName>[ob]ject I have seen the acct. between <persName>Madero </persName>and
<persName>Trespalacios</persName>, and know <persName>Madero </persName>has not failed to send on to the
former the means of liquidating the obligation - tell your <persName>Brother</persName>
that there is no other feeling here at present other than purely
republican - I shall write him particularly on the subject by the
next post, and communicate to him the project, already spoken of -</p>
<p>And untill then I am</p>

<p><persName>James Hewitson</persName></p>
<p>Much hurry and no time for compts. -</p>
<p>[Addressed:] Al <persName>Ciudadano Santiago B. Austin</persName> <placeName>Bexar</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
