<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0087">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Unknown, Unknown</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-24">06-24-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 95-96
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date>Unknown</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-24" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Letter to Stephen F. Austin's tutor.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p>Your favour was handed me by <persName>Mr Penneman</persName> on his arrival at
this place. I am fully sattisfied with the arrangement <persName>Mr Penneman</persName>
has made respecting my <persName>son Stephen</persName>, the great distance <placeName>Colchester</placeName>
is from this <placeName>Country </placeName>rendered it impossible for me to give any 
absolute opinion to <persName>Mr. Penneman</persName> as to the propriety of his choice of
<placeName>Colchester </placeName>but such is my confidence in my <persName>friend </persName>that I am sattisfied with the disposition he has made. It cannot but be pleasing to
me to here my Boy so well spoken of and I have a hope under your
tuition he will give me no reason to repent the confidence I have
placed in those to whome I have commited him in charge&#8212; I have
a dispossition that <persName>Stephen </persName>should go through the Classicks in short
I wish to make him a scholar yet I must confess I have for many
years disapproved of spending month[s] and year[s] on the Greek
and Hebrew. I never have thought either of those languages of
much advantage to a man of business, and as I do not wish my <persName>son</persName>
to make devinity his study, [I should like] as little time spent in
Greek and Hebrew as is consistent with the regulations of the <placeName>Acady</placeName>-
If his talents will justify I wish him for the Barr but I have so many
times in my life blamed Fathers for pressing on their sons a 
profession nature never intended them for that I shall make of him
what Nature has best calculated him to be I want him to enter <placeName>Yale</placeName>
as soon as he is prepared but I have a Request to make which I
hope will not interrupt his regular studies and that is: that he may
be constantly reminded of the necessity of improving his hand 
writing&#8212; I have a great desire he should write well both as to the hand
write and composition&#8212; practice will bring writing both easy and
pleasing, a Correct mode of thinking both Religious and Political
is of consequence and aught to be early implanted in the mind of
man I do not wish my <persName>son </persName>a Bigot in Either, but correct Moral
principles is of the first consequence such I trust you will impress on
his mind.<pb n="96"/></p>

<p>I am also disposed to furnish my <persName>son </persName>money necessary for such
expenses as is proper for a young Gentlm in his situation both for
clothing and the Pockett Yet I wish my Boy to know that improper
uses may be made with money and that any Degree of profligateness
will not be tolerated by me you will suffer him to clothe himself
sutable for the first circles in Society he will perfect himself in
Musick If he has a turn that way</p>

<p>I have transmited to <persName>Mr Nath. Bran</persName> (?) a Draft for 160$ which
I trust has been forwarded to you <persName>Majr Hunt</persName> I expect will also
pay for me 100$ more and I shall take care to forward in Money in
Due time for his use In you my D Fr I have full confidence you
will act the father and Tuteror and transmitt to me infermation
how he progresses in his studies.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
