<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0604">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Colonel Charles Caldwell, 07-17-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-15">07-15-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Colonel Charles Caldwell
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Bexar, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 673-674
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-07-17">07-17-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Advantages of settling in Austin's colony. Federal system. Good crops. Character of settlers.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Bexar </placeName><date when="1823-07-17">July 17 1823</date></p>
<p>Dr. Sir,</p>

<p>I regret very much I was absent when you visited the <placeName>Province</placeName>,
but anticipate the pleasure of seeing you here this <date n="Fall-1823">fall</date>&#8212; My 
business is all happily terminated and I shall immediately commence
distributing the land&#8212; Owing to the difficulty of making a 
beginning when I first embarked in this enterprise, I was compeled to
admit some who would have been rejected under different 
circumstances&#8212;but that difficulty no longer exists&#8212;large crops will be
made this year on both the <placeName>Colorado </placeName>and <placeName>Brazos</placeName>-&#8212; My <placeName>grant </placeName>is
approved by the <persName>Sovereign Congress</persName> and <persName>Supreme Executive power</persName>
since the fall of <persName>Iturbide</persName>&#8212;The smallest quantity of land which a
<persName>family </persName>that <hi rend="italic">farms </hi>and <hi rend="italic">raises stock</hi>, both, will receive is one league
square or five thousands yards square&#8212;the cost will be 12 1/2 cents pr-
acre&#8212;</p>

<p>You have seen the country, and know whether it will suit you or
not you also know whether it would be for your interest, in case
you remove, to settle under my <placeName>grant</placeName>, or apply for a seperate one
from the <persName>Government</persName>&#8212; All I have to say therefore is that if you
join me, you may rely on the greatest privileges in my power to
grant. In conjunction with the <persName>commissioner</persName>, I have full power to
increase the quantity of land to more than a league for a family, in
case it should be necessary to accommodate a large <persName>family</persName>&#8212; You
will perceive by the enclosed that the number for <placeName>Brazos </placeName>and 
<placeName>Colorado </placeName>settlement is limited, the balance must settle on the <placeName>Guadalupe</placeName>
and <placeName>St. Marcos</placeName> and near this place etc. etc.&#8212;so say the Govt-</p>

<p>When I left <placeName>Mexico </placeName>no other grants had been made, nor could be
for some time to come, for the Colonization law was repealed in toto
on the <date when="1823-04-10">10 of April</date> except as refers to me, and when a new law will
pass is uncertain&#8212; the present <persName>congress </persName>have called a new one, the
election is to be on the <date when="1823-08-02">2d of August</date> and <persName>Congress </persName>is to meet the
middle of <date when="1823-10-15">October </date>next&#8212;   The majority of the <placeName>Provinces </placeName>have pro-<pb n="674"/>
claimed the Federal Republic System, and there is now no longer
a doubt that this <persName>govt</persName>. will be moddled after that of the <placeName>United
States</placeName>&#8212; This <placeName>Province </placeName>under the Federal System presents the most
brilliant prospects for the future. I repeat, that anything in my
power to do, to induce you and your <persName>friends </persName>to form a part of the
<placeName>Colorado or Brazos settlement</placeName> shall be done with pleasure.</p>

<p>[Autograph letter by Austin.   Signature clipped off.]</p>

<p>P. S. The regulations relative to the Govt. of the settlement are
provisional untill it is established and organized, the same system
will then be established that governs all other parts of the country&#8212;.
Should you and your <persName>friend </persName>wish to form a seperate settlement you
could easily do so on the Guadalupe under the grant made to me,
for no specified limits are designated.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Col Charles Caldwell</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
