<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0375">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Governor Martinez, 01-26-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Governor Martinez
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 377-378
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-01-26">01-26-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Disclaims any connection with his companion Kirkham and five Spaniards engaged in illegal horse and mule trading.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>His <persName>Excellency</persName></p>

<p>The <persName>Governor of the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName></persName></p>

<p>May it please your <persName>Excellency </persName>Since leaving your <placeName>City </placeName>some 
circumstances of a very unpleasant nature have come to my knowledge
which I consider it, my duty to communicate to your <persName>Excellency </persName>in
Exoneration of any blame or suspicion of blame that might be
attached to <hi rend="italic">me </hi>in consequence of my being in company With a man
that may have conducted unwisely and thereby drawn disgrace on
himself and endangerd my reputation</p>

<p>The day before I left <placeName>St Antonio</placeName> for the <placeName>United States</placeName>, <persName>Kirkham</persName>
the man in whose company, I visited your <placeName>Capital </placeName>mentioned to me
that five <persName>Spaniards </persName>would leave your city with us for <placeName>Nachitoches</placeName>,
but did not say that they had any intention to leave the City in a
Clandestin manner or to committ any act in violation of your orders
or that of Society. <hi rend="italic">Nor </hi>was there intentions made known to me
untill after I had arrived at the <placeName>River St Marks</placeName>, when I learned from
<persName>Kirkham </persName>that the <persName>Spaniards </persName>would come up with us at the <placeName>River
Colorado</placeName> at which place he <persName>Kirkham </persName>had agreed to delay for them
and that they was to bring with them a Number of Mules which he
<persName>Kirkham </persName>had told them he would purchase and give them a safe
conduct to the <placeName>United States</placeName>. I objected to have anything to do
with them or detain for them unless they brought with them a<pb n="378"/>
pasport, and expostulated with him for having given them any 
encouragement to bring out mules in as much as it Was expressly against
Orders of the <hi rend="italic"><persName>Governor </persName></hi>he then said that he had not given them any
other encouragement or words that would induce them to bring out
Mules except that If they should do so, he should purchase them, he
then said that the <persName>Spaniards </persName>had made a brake on the <persName>King</persName>s Yard of
Mules and Horses and taken ten or twelve and Escaped, that before
they left <placeName>St Antonio</placeName> they had stated to some of there <persName>friends</persName>, that he
<persName>Kirkham </persName>was to detain at the <hi rend="italic">River Colorado</hi> with the Other 
<persName>American </persName>and Conduct them with in, the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>United States</placeName></hi>, it was with real
regret that I Found myself implicated in this transaction and placed
in a situation to create doubts&#8212;as to my true intentions in visiting
your City, the object of this letter is therefore to remove from the
mind of your <persName>Excellency</persName>&#8212;any Suspicion if any exists or may have
been <hi rend="italic">created</hi>, from the conduct either of <persName>Kirkham </persName>or the <persName>Spaniards</persName>,
that <hi rend="italic">Stole </hi>the Mules and also to request them to be examined as to the
fact, whether I had an interview with either of them or Whether they
communicated to me there&#8212;intentions.&#8212;I do not pretend to say that
<persName>Kirkham </persName>made any agreement with them touching the theft, of the
Mules&#8212; if he did it is unknown to me he most positively <hi rend="italic">denies</hi>
any communication with them except what I have before stated, that
he would purchase the Mules. It is therefore to be clearly 
understood, that I do not accuse <persName>Kirkham </persName>of any, <hi rend="italic">Crime </hi>but it is that I
write this letter in consequence of being told that my Name had
been called in question and touching the theft of some mules and
which might lessen the confidence of your <persName>Excellency </persName>in the 
Declarations, I made when at your <placeName>City </placeName>of my real intention and motive in
Visiting the <placeName>Capital </placeName>and to assure your <persName>Excellency </persName>by our most Holy
Religion that, I had nothing to do with or any knowledge of&#8212;the
intentions of the <persName>Spaniards </persName>who <persName>Kirkham </persName>told me was to make a
Journey to <placeName>Nachitoches </placeName>in our Company, it is to do myself Justice
that I make this communication to you at this time, and for no other
object. I again <hi rend="italic">Repeat </hi>to your <persName>Excellency </persName>that If I am admitted to
reside With in the <placeName>province of Texas</placeName> it will be my Study to regulate
my conduct in such a manner as will strengthen the Confidence of
Your Excellency in my good intentions, and Respectfull attachment
to the Government under which <hi rend="italic">I live</hi></p>

<p>praying your <persName>Excellency </persName>to accept of my profound Respect,</p>

<p><persName>M Austin</persName></p>
<p><placeName>Nachitoches </placeName><date when="1821-01-26">Jany 26 1821</date></p>

<p>To His <persName>Excellency A Mons Martines
Governor Civil and Military over the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName></persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
