<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0870">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Martha Marple to Stephen F. Austin, 09-29-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Martha Marple</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Zainesville, Ohio</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 906-907
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-09-29">09-29-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Administration of estate of David J. Marple.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Zaines Ville</placeName> <date when="1824-09-29">Septemr 29 1824</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr. Stephen, F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dear Sir my <persName>late Beloved Husband</persName> <persName>David J Marple</persName> who 
accompanied you through the <placeName>Gother Country</placeName> in year <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821 </date>and who
died <date n="06-xx-1822">june 1822</date> at the <placeName>house of <persName>Judge James Cummings</persName></placeName>, has left me
as [illegible word] property or the means of obtaining a living for<pb n="907"/>
my self and three <persName>Children </persName>intirely destitute I have an article of
agreement between yourself and my <persName>husband </persName>agreeing to give him
cirtain parcels of land in consideration of his accompanying you
on the journey mentioned above and of settling or raising a crop
within one year which it appears he has done as by the 
<persName>administrators </persName>account, there was Considerable corn among other things sold
after his desease, and would ere this have removed his <persName>family </persName>there
had he lived, my eldest <persName>child </persName>is a son 12 years old named <persName>John J
Marple</persName> <persName>Mary P Marple</persName> third <persName>David J Marple</persName> the are too
young for me to go to a new <placeName>Country </placeName>with at this time my wish is
to secure the land in proportion amongst us giving me that part
<persName>David </persName>had settled on as is most likely will produce some income I
have appointed <persName>Martain F. Maker of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></persName> <persName>Agent </persName>for me,
to settle with the <persName>Administrator </persName>and to arrange my business with
yourself, also to procure <persName>families </persName>to settle on the land or pay taxas
if any and finely to act for me in avery res[p]ect I have directed
him to advise with you, if any further evidence, is wanting, to
convince you I am the <persName>wife </persName>of <persName>David J. Marple</persName> or that the three
Children are his by me I can produce it, <persName>Judge Cumming</persName> has a
letter of mine to my late <persName>Husband </persName>you can Compare writing to 
Satisfy yourself,</p>

<p>I feel the need of a <persName>friend </persName>to act for me I throw myself on your
goodness to act the part of a friend, to see that I have Justice done
by the <persName>administrator</persName>, it appears by accounts received from 
<persName>Commings</persName>, and <persName>James Tumlinson</persName>, that there must be over three 
Hundred dollars due for sales of corn and other property, <persName>tumlinson</persName>
acknowledges the sale of corn in 10 lots to be 265.60 and the 11 lots
sold at 175 cents per. Bus. but not delivered, afterward burnt in the
crib the corn was left at the risk of the <persName>purchaser</persName>, of Corse after
Public sale, I understood the man that Bought requested it might
remain till he could go across the Contry, to sell it, as it would loose
by removing twice, as you must have a good deal of influence in
the <placeName>settlement </placeName>your friendly advise may be of service to me I am
very poor and need the Money, I. have always lived comfortable
while my <persName>husband </persName>lived, now I am intirely destitute of anything to
live on or educate my <persName>Children </persName>have to be dependent on my relatives
whis is very unpleasant your attention to my intrust will be 
greatfully acknowledged by yours</p>

<p><persName>Martha Marple</persName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
