<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0231">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to John Scott, 05-28-1813</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-30">06-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        John Scott
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Durham Hall, Burton Mine, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">St Genevieve, MO</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 224-226
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1813-05-28">05-28-1813</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning the Renaut claim, and complications with Scott and John Rice Jones.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p>Sr</p>

<p>I should not trouble you with any observations on the <persName>Renaut</persName>
business, Was I not disposed to have the affair a justed, with out
difficulty, could such a thing take place or be effected, With <persName>Jones</persName>
I can say nothing more, I have recvd a most <persName>Billingsgate</persName>, letter,
with denunciations against the <placeName>Claim</placeName>, and what, he will do, he says 
"it is in my power to prevent your realising those Golden dreams
and, believe, me, the, <hi rend="italic">Inclination, to, do, so,</hi> is not nor shall not
be wanting.["] <hi rend="italic">the Soul, of the man, is, spoken, in, this line, it, is, in,</hi>
fact saying purchase me or I will act&#8212;the, Villing!!! <persName>Jones </persName>has
never paid a Dollar in money or in time spent, from the commence-<pb n="225"/>
ment of this transaction, and from his letter I soon gather that he is
determined not to pay a Dollar, and yet expects to hold 1/4 under an
Original contract between <persName>Maj. Hunt </persName>and himself, which he knowes
was never carried into execution by him, I also find that he 
disbelieves that I am called on to pay 2647 1/2 Dollares, the purchase
money for my 1/8 of the last half of said <placeName>Claim</placeName>, and that he intends
paying nothing, You know that I have advanced all the money that
has been paid and from mony Drawn from the funds of <persName>Moses
Austin and Co</persName> and now because I call on him to say&#8212;Whether he
intends to consider himself interested Equal with myself in the
purchase of the last half and provide for the same say thirteen
hundred and Twenty three Dollars and fifty Cents&#8212;I am answered
in a most <persName>Billingsgate </persName>Style. If <persName>Jones </persName>has a Claim on <persName>Maj Hunt</persName>,
for a 1/4 so be it, I&#8212; have nothing to do with that contract I&#8212;
only, speak of, my contract with <persName>Maj Hunt</persName> in which I have offered,
<persName>Jones</persName>, an equal part with myself, Conditioned as above, I have
made no stipulations with <persName>Hunt </persName>for any disposal of either, <hi rend="italic">Jones</hi>,
or, <hi rend="italic">his Contract,</hi> how can any man of common understanding say
that I have acted in any way improper with, <hi rend="italic"><persName>Jones</persName></hi>, when I gave
him an oppertunity to injoy with myself an equal participation if
he thought proper to come forward and make the proper advance
If, he, will, not, accept, <hi rend="italic">I cannot, make, him</hi></p>

<p>I have said thus much to you that hereafter I may have it in my
power to face, <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, or, any, Other, man, in Vindication of my 
Conduct, should it be called in question&#8212;</p>

<p>I have one other observation to make as respect <persName>Jones </persName>and I have
don, If <persName>Jones </persName>considers his Contract with <persName>Hunt </persName>valid, Why accuse
me of not Securing his interests in the <placeName>Claim </placeName>any act of mine could
not have changed his Standing with <persName>Maj Hunt</persName> unless he thought
proper to approve the same, and that he would not have don, so, is,
<hi rend="italic">clear</hi>, in as much as he objects paying or making his advance, on the
purchace, and I alone am bound to <persName>Maj Hunt</persName> for the consequences,
Such conduct is With out a parallel</p>
<p>I am Sr Yours</p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>again If <persName>Jones</persName>, had no expectations of being called on to pay, his
share on the last purchase money of the last half how came it to pass
that he made a provision in the contract With you that you should
pay all further and Other expenses that should Arrise on said <placeName>Claims</placeName>
from the day of making said Contracts in writing to me on this sub-
ject he say&#8212;" I have sold a part of my Share in the <placeName>Renaut Claim</placeName> to
<persName>Mr Wm Scott</persName> the conditions of which I will explain to you when
We meet" this explanatun has never taken place and I have only
agreed to Said Sale conditionally.   Now Sr forward to me <persName>John Rice</persName><pb n="226"/>
<persName>Jones </persName>acknowledgment&#8212;that he has sold to you a part of his share in
said <placeName>Claim</placeName>, expressing what part, and at the same time provide the
Money, to, meet, the expences on what ever part he may so express,
taking for your standard two thousand Six Hundred and forty Seven
Dollars as the expences and purchace money on Eight of shares of the
last half, and I will immediately agree and secure to you the same
title I may receive&#8212;from <persName>Mr Baldwin</persName></p>

<p>Provided always, that such Certificate of sale to you from <persName>Jones</persName>
doth not exceed or equal share I hold in Said <placeName>Claim </placeName>under my 
Contract with <persName>Maj Seth Hunt</persName> and that I am in no wise bound either to
you or <hi rend="italic"><persName>Jones </persName></hi>jointly or Separately, Verbally, or, Written either as
<persName>M Austin and Co</persName> or as <persName>Moses Austin</persName> for any more than a share to be
claimed by you both inclusive Equal to that I myself can and may
receive from <persName>Maj Seth Hunt</persName> <persName>Henry Baldwin</persName> or any Other person
authorised to make to me deeds for said property.</p>

<p>Such are the Conditions on which an adjustment may take place
respecting the <placeName>Renaut Claim</placeName>&#8212;Provided that with in eight [days?]
from the recept of this letter the conditions herein stipulated are 
ratified and also that the propositions herein contained are carr[i]ed with
good faith into real Execution Canceling all other pretentions from
either you or, <persName>Jones</persName>, on me, leaving the <persName>said John </persName><persName>Rice </persName><persName>Jones </persName>and <persName>Maj
Seth Hunt</persName> to settle any contract They may have between each Other
to be adjustd as they may think proper hereafter.</p>

<p>I have thus again givn both <persName>Jones </persName>and yourself an Oppertunety to
come forward and make a final finish of this business on termes equal
with myself&#8212;If you do not accept remember I hold myself exonerated
both in Honour and Justice</p>
<p>I am Sr Yours</p>

<p><persName>M Austin</persName></p>

<p><placeName>Durham Hall</placeName>,</p>

<p><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Mine a Burton</placeName>, <date when="1813-05-28">May, 28th 1813</date></hi></p>

<p>[Endorsed:] Copy letter to <persName>John Scott</persName> <placeName>Saint Geneveve on the
Renaut Claim</placeName> <date when="1813-05-28">May 28th 1813</date></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
