<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0751">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Unknown, 05-24-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 800-803
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Forms and Writs</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-05-24">05-24-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Judiciary.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>A list of Forms for the undermentioned writts to be used 
according to circumstances&#8212;<pb n="801"/></p>

<p><placeName>Austin's Colony</placeName>-</p>
<p>District of</p>

<p>The <persName>Constable </persName>of said District is hereby commanded to attach the property
of A. B found in sd district or so much thereof as may be necessary to satisfy
C. D. on a plea of debt grounded on the oath of Sd C. D. on file in my office and
in default thereof to take the person of said A B if found within his <placeName>District</placeName>,
and have it or him forthwith before me or whenever suit is to be tried to
answer sd C D in said plea in the sum of $--------</p>

<p>Given under my hand and seal this day of             1824</p>

<p><persName>Alcalde </persName>of sd District   seal</p>

<p>FORM OF ATTACHMENT WHERE THE PARTY HAS ABSCONDED OUT OF THE COLONY</p>

<p><persName>Austins Colony</persName></p>

<p>District of</p>
<p>The <persName>Constable </persName>of said District is hereby commanded to pursue and seize the
person and property of A B and have them or him before me forthwith to
answer C D: in a plea of debt in the sum of $            grounded on the Oath of
sd C D: on file in my office&#8212;given etc.&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Alcalde </persName>of sd District</p>

<p>FORM  OF  WARRANT  TO  APPREHEND  A  CRIMINAL</p>

<p><persName>Austin's Colony</persName></p>

<p>District of</p>
<p>The <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName> to the <persName>Constable </persName>of sd District Greeting   You are hereby
Commanded to take the Body of A B whereever to be found and . . . [torn]
to answer to a charge of . . . [torn]</p>

<p>FORM OF  SUBPOENA IN CRIML. CASE</p>

<p><placeName>Austins Colony</placeName></p>

<p>District of</p>
<p>The <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName> to AB. CD: and E F Greeting   You and each of you
are hereby Commanded personally to be and appear before the undersigned at
his office   (or wherever trial is to be held)  in the District afd on the day
of          between the hours of 9 A M and 3PM and not depart with leave then
and there to testify your knowledge in a certain suit at the prosecution of the
<placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName> agt W X on the part of the prosecution (or Deft as the case
may be) and therein fail not under the penalty of $200   Given etc.</p>

<p><persName>Alcalde </persName>of said District</p>

<p>FORM OF SUBPOENA IN CIVIL SUIT</p>

<p><placeName>Austin's Colony</placeName></p>

<p>District of</p>

<p>To A B CD and E F Greeting You and each of you are hereby commanded
personally to be and appear before the undersigned at his Office in the District
(or wherever suit is to be tried) on the            day of          between the hours
of 9 A M and 3 P. M and not to depart without leave then and there to testify
your knowledge in a certain suit depends before the undersigned wherein G M
is <persName>plff </persName>and I K is <persName>Deft</persName>, on the part of (plff or Deft. as the case may be) and
therein fail not under the penalty oi $100</p>

<p>Given etc.</p>

<p><persName>Alcalde </persName>of said District<pb n="802"/></p>


<p>FORM OF SUBPOENA TO GIVE DEP.Ns UNDER A COMMISSION TO EXAMINE</p>

<p><placeName>Austin's Colony</placeName></p>

<p>District of</p>

<p>To A B C D and E F Greeting Yon and each of you are hereby commanded
personally to be and appear before the undersigned at his office (or wherever
depns are to be taken) in the District aforesd on the day          of between the
hours of 9 A M and 3 P M and not depart without leave then and there to
testify your knowledge in a certain suit pending before</p>

<p><persName>Alcalde </persName>of the District of          wherein G M is pltff and I K is Deft on the
part of (Plff or Deft as the case may be) therein fail not under the penalty
of $100 . . .</p>

<p>FORM OF A  COMMISSION  OB REQUISITION  FROM  ONE ALCALDE  TO ANOTHER  TO  TAKE
THE DEPOSITIONS OF WITNESSES LIVING IN  ANOTHER DISTRICT</p>

<p><persName>Austin's Colony</persName></p>

<p>District of</p>

<p>A B vs C D</p>

<p>You are hereby requested to cause such persons as the <persName>plaintiff </persName>or <persName>Defendt</persName>
(as the case may be) in the above suit may name to appear before you if to
be found in your District at the time and place designated by said <persName>Plaintiff</persName>
(or Deft as the case may be) in his notice to the adverse party and then and
there between the hours of 9 oClock A M and 3 oClock P M take their 
depositions on Oath in writing of such thing, as they may testify touching the 
controverse between said A B and C D now pending before me to be tryed on
the          day of          together with such Interrogations as either party may
put and their answers thereto, And the same duly attested by you and 
subscribed by sd witnesses you will return to me in a sealed packet</p>

<p>Given etc.</p>

<p>To the <persName>Alcalde </persName>of the District of</p>

<p>FORM OF BAIL BOND FOR APPEAEANCE OF DEFENDT IN A CIVIL SUIT</p>

<p><persName>Austin's Colony</persName></p>

<p>District of</p>

<p>Know all men by these presents that we G M of          and I K of          are
held and firmly bound unto E F Constable of the District or to P Q Alguazil of
sd Colony in the sum of          Dollars, good and lawful money of the <placeName>Mexican
Nation</placeName> to be paid to the sd Constable or to his successor in office or Alguazil as
the case may be to which payt well and truly to be made We bind ourselves and
heirs Ex. and ad. firmly by these presents&#8212;Given under our hands and seal
this          day of</p>

<p>The condition of the above obligation is such that if the above bound G M
do appear before X Y: Alcalde of the District afd on the          day of          at
his office (or whenever suit to be tried as the case may be) to answer R S of
a Plea of debt in the sum of $          then this objection to be void otherwise lo
be in full force.</p>

<p>FORM OF A BAIL BOND IN A CRIMINAL CASE PRO. OF TEXAS</p>

<p><placeName>Austin's Colony</placeName></p>

<p>District of</p>
<p>Know all men by these presents that We G M of          and I K of          are
held and firmly bound to the <persName>Political chief</persName> of the Pro of Texas&#8212;(or P Q the
Algnazil of sd as the case may be) of the District aforesd in the sum of $<pb n="803"/>
lawful money of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName> to be pd to him and his successor in office
to which payt we bind ourselves our heirs Exrs and adrs firmly by these presents,
Given etc.</p>

<p>The condition of the above objection is such that if the above bound G M
do appear before R S Alcalde of the District afd or before (the <persName>superior Judge</persName>
of sd Colony as the case may be)  on the          day of            to answer to a
certain prosecuts (here insert for what offence) at the suit of the <placeName>Mexican
Nation</placeName> agt the sd G M then this objection to be void otherwise to be in full
force&#8212;</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
