<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0891">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James E. B. Austin to Stephen F. Austin, George Huff, and Joseph Servison, 10-26-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James E. B. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         George Huff
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Joseph Servison
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 927-928
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Contract</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-10-26">10-26-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Contract to build sawmill, gristmill, and cotton gin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>This agreement made and entered into at the Town of <placeName>San Felipe
de Austin</placeName> in the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName> this <date when="1824-10-26">26 day of October 1824
</date>between <persName>James B Austin</persName> of the one part and <persName>George Huff</persName> and
<persName>Joseph Servison</persName> of the other part witnesseth that whereas the
said <persName>James George</persName> and <persName>Joseph </persName>have obtained a grant from the
<persName>Mexican Government</persName> for Eight Leagues and a half of land Situated
on the <placeName>San Bernard Creek</placeName> in the <placeName>Coloney </placeName>formed by the <persName>Empresario
Stephen F. Austin</persName> in said <placeName>Province </placeName>on condition that they build
<placeName>Mills </placeName>on said tract within two years from the date of said 
Concession&#8212;now the said <persName>George Huff</persName> and <persName>Joseph Servison</persName> agree
on their part to build at their owne expence a good saw and <placeName>grist
mill</placeName> at the <placeName>Mill seat</placeName> on said tract of land to be completely 
finished in a good and workmanlike manner within the time specified
in said Concession&#8212;The <placeName>saw mill</placeName> to be of one saw with a good
and Sufficient House and the Machenery necessary for a <placeName>Saw
Mill</placeName>&#8212;The <placeName>Grist Mill</placeName> to be constructed either single or double
geared as may best suit the Stream with one pair of four feet
mill Stones of good quality and a good and Sufficient frame <placeName>mill
House</placeName> sufficiently large to Admit of the addition of a <placeName>Cotton Gin</placeName>.</p>

<p>The mill dam to be built in the Manner which may be deemed best
calculated for Strength and durability so as to suit the seat and the
size of the Stream.   The whole to be executed in a good and work-<pb n="928"/>
manlike manner and to be put in complete operation, which saw and
<placeName>Grist Mill</placeName> thus completed, shall be the joint property of said <persName>James</persName>,
<persName>George</persName>, and <persName>Joseph </persName>each one owning one third and each to receive one
third of the nett proceeds&#8212; And the said <persName>James B. Austin</persName> agrees
on his part to pay the Surveying and other fees on the said Concesion
of land in full out of his own individual funds&#8212; Also it is agreed
by the said <persName>parties </persName>that all further improvements besides the above
mentioned <placeName>saw and Grist Mill</placeName> which may be made on said tract of
land with the consent of each one of them shall be at the joint and
equal expence of all three each one paying one third &#8212; Also it is
agreed that a Copartnership shall exist between the said <persName>James</persName>,
<persName>George </persName>and <persName>Joseph </persName>for the purpose of working said <placeName>saw and grist
mill</placeName> which shall continue for the term of ten years unless sooner
dissolved by Mutual consent and the business of tending said Mills
shall be conducted in the name of <persName>George Huff and Company</persName>&#8212;
provided that neither of said parties shall contract any debts or make
any contracts whatever in the name of the <persName>Company </persName>with out the
consent of all three first obtained, and it is specially understood that
neither of them have any authority whatever to bind either of the
others for the payment of any Money or the execution of any 
contract whatever unless their consent is first given to that effect-&#8212; also
it is agreed that should either of said <persName>parties </persName>wish to improve a <placeName>farm</placeName>
on said tract of land as his own individual property a sufficiency
of land for that purpose shall be laid off with the consent of the
other two and deeds of relinquishment mutually executed therefor,
but no other <placeName>farms </placeName>or <placeName>Settlements </placeName>shall be made on said tract without
the consent of all three&#8212;</p>

<p>In witness of all which the said <persName>parties </persName>have hereto signed their
Hands the day and date first above mentioned</p>

<p><persName>James B Austin</persName>
by his <persName>agent</persName>
<persName>S. F. Austin </persName>   [Rubric]
<persName>Geo Huff</persName>
for him Self and <persName>Joseph Servison</persName>
<persName>Witness </persName>Present</p>

<p><persName>Samuel M Williams</persName>    [Rubric]</p>
<p>The above Agreement between <persName>George Huff</persName>, <persName>Joseph Severson</persName> and
<persName>James E. B. Austin</persName> is this day cancelled by mutual consent and 
declared to be null and void</p>

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1825-05-21">May 21, 1825</date>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Geo Huff</persName>
<persName>Joseph Seveson</persName>
<persName>James B Austin</persName>
by <persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
