<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0615">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Baron de Bastrop to Colonists, 08-09-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Baron de Bastrop</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-15">07-15-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Colonists
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 683-684
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-08-09">08-09-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Austin's authority. Procedure in Issuing titles.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[Copy by Austin]</p>

<p>To the <persName>Inhabitants of the <placeName>Colorado 
District in Austin's Colony, Province of
Texas</placeName></persName> convened at the <placeName>house of 
<persName>Sylvester Castlemans</persName></placeName> at a public meeting&#8212;</p>

<p>By order of the <persName>Governor of this Province</persName> I have convened you
together to inform you of the powers and faculties which the
<persName>Superior Government</persName> have conferred on <persName>Citizen Stephen F. Austin</persName>&#8212;
what those powers and faculties are you will see by the following
translation of the said <persName>Governor</persName>s Official letter to me dated at
<placeName>Bexar </placeName>the <date when="1823-07-16">16 of last month</date> (here read the letter).</p>

<p>I therefore, the <persName>Baron de Bastrop Commissioner</persName> duly appointed
by the <persName>Government </persName>for that purpose, now, in this public manner
invest him the said <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName> with the before mentioned
offices and powers, and I charge the <persName>inhabitants </persName>to respect and obey
him in every thing relative to the good Government and prosperity
of the <placeName>Colony</placeName>, and the defence of the <placeName>Nation </placeName>to which he belongs
under the penalty incurred by those who disrespect or disobey an
<persName>officer or magistrate of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName></persName>.</p>

<p>The number of <persName>families </persName>is limited to three hundred for this
<placeName>Colony</placeName>, those therefore who are not received by <persName>Mr Austin</persName> into it,
must move further into the <placeName>interior of the Province</placeName> or if they are
of bad character <persName>Mr Austin</persName> is ordered by the <persName>Supr Govt</persName> to remove
them out of the <placeName>Colony</placeName>, for which purpose he is authorized to use
military force should it be necessary.</p>

<p>In registering the <persName>Families </persName>all those who are connected either
by blood or marriage must be registered as one <persName>family</persName>, and the
land for the whole must be taken in the name of the <persName>head of the
family</persName>&#8212;<persName>Single men</persName> must either be included in some <persName>family</persName>, or a
sufficient number of them must unite to form a <persName>family </persName>and draw
land for all in the name of one.</p>

<p>The Colonization law agreeably to which the land for this <placeName>Colony</placeName>
will be distributed, was repealed on the <date when="1823-04-10">10 of April last</date>, as regards<pb n="684"/>
every other person except <persName>Mr Austin</persName> and the <persName>Families </persName>which he
is authorized to introduce. As respects the titles to your land, the
<persName>settlers </persName>may rest satisfied that they are indisputable and must
always be good under any circumstances, or any change of 
Government&#8212; The original Concession for this <placeName>Colony </placeName>was granted by
the <persName>Spanish Government</persName> before the revolution, it was then 
confirmed and the quantity of land designated by the <persName>Emperor 
Augustin</persName>, by his Imperial Decree dated <date when="1823-02-18">February 18th 1823</date>, and the
whole was reconfirmed by the <persName>Sovereign Congress of the <placeName>Mexican
Nation</placeName></persName> by their Decree dated the <date when="1823-04-10">10 of April 1823</date> which was
approved, published, and ordered to be executed by the <persName>Supreme
Executive Power</persName> on the <date when="1823-04-14">14 of the same month</date>&#8212;The Grant and
all the Decrees and papers relative to it are regularly recorded in
the office of the <persName>Secretary of State for <placeName>Interior</placeName></persName> and exterior relations
in the <placeName>City of Mexico</placeName>, and also in the <placeName>office of the <persName>Commandant
General</persName> of these Provinces</placeName> in the <placeName>City of Monterrey</placeName>, and also in
the <placeName>archives of this Province</placeName> in the <placeName>city of Bexar</placeName>, and <persName>Mr Austin
</persName>has a certified copy in his possession</p>

<p>Agreeable to the grant, the title Deeds for each tract of land will
be made in the name of the <persName>Mexican Government</persName> and signed by
<persName>Mr Austin</persName> as the <persName>founder of the <placeName>Colony</placeName></persName>, and by me as the 
<persName>Governmental Commissioner</persName> appointed for that purpose by the <persName>Governor
of this <placeName>Province</placeName></persName>, and records will then be made of them in the 
<placeName>archives of this Province</placeName> in <placeName>Bexar</placeName>&#8212;<persName>Mr. Austin</persName> is also authorized to
establish a <placeName><persName>Recorder</persName>s office</placeName> at the <placeName>Capital of the Colony</placeName> in which the
titles will also be recorded.</p>

<p>I cannot too strongly recommend to you the necessity of good
order, industry, and obediance to the <persName>Constitutional authorities</persName>, and
that you should be governed in all things connected with public 
matters by the <persName>founder of this <placeName>Colony </placeName>Mr. Stephen F. Austin</persName>, a man
whose former character in the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and prudent and 
correct conduct in this country has acquired him the full confidence of
the highest authorities of the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName>.</p>

<p><placeName>Castlemans </placeName>on the <placeName>Rio Colorado</placeName></p>
<p><date when="1823-08-09">August 9, 1823</date>&#8212;3d year of Independence
and 2 year of Liberty.</p>

<p>El <persName>Baron de Bastrop </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
