<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0819">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Nathaniel Cox  to Stephen F. Austin, 08-08-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Nathaniel Cox </persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, LA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 872-873
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-08-08">08-08-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Report in New Orleans of rebellion in Austin's colony.  Mexican character&#8212;unfit for self-government.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date when="1824-08-08">8 Aug 1824</date></p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>A report has been in circulation here for some days, brought I 
believe by a Steam Boat from <placeName>Natchitoches </placeName>that <hi rend="italic">all </hi>your <persName>settlers</persName>, have
raised the standard of Rebellion; and refuse obedience to law or any
authority whatever&#8212;As the <placeName>province </placeName>must now be the only resort
to which <persName>Mrs Hawkins</persName> can look for support for herself and helpless
<persName>family </persName>the report of course excites considerable Interest and I hope
it is not true&#8212;If you should receive this in any reasonable time after
its date you would greatly oblige me by forwarding such 
information as would put the subject beyond doubt, one way or the other&#8212;I
am the more anxious on this subject from a paragraph which on
reperusing your last letter strikes, me with much force, since 
hearing the foregoing report&#8212;you say "I have many things to explain
relative to events recently transpired here but have not time now" I
much fear these events are the rebellion of your <persName>settlers</persName>, and that
it will be a scene of confusion and disaster, retarding your final 
opperations for years to come.<pb n="873"/></p>

<p>I shall not make any communication on this all import Subject to
<persName>Mrs Hawkins</persName> or <persName>Mr Sanders</persName> until I am better informed myself,
but be assured I shall feel great anxiety until I know more on the
subject.</p>

<p>I have no doubt but your late <persName>Emperor Iterbide</persName> is by this time
relanded at <placeName>Vera Cruse</placeName>&#8212;he sailed from <placeName>London </placeName>in <date n="05-xx-1824">May </date>with the
declared intention of his again assuming Kingly Authority in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>,
and he further states that his voyage is undertaken at the Instance
of a large number of the <persName>first characters of the <placeName>Province</placeName></persName>&#8212;it is to be
hoped however that his views will not be reallized but that on his
landing he may be caught and hung&#8212;there is little doubt but <persName>Saint
Anna</persName> is no better than <persName>Iterbide </persName>and while such <persName>Arch Traitors</persName> hold
offices of trust and honour in the country there can be no guarantee
for the lives or property of the <persName>Citizens</persName>&#8212;In short I fear there is
not yet sufficient learning and virtue in the people of that country
to make a staple form of Government and then suppert it. They may
make and adopt constitutions every year and still find persons to
violate them, and when the penalty is called for, the criminal 
concentrates his party and puts down the whole System&#8212;This has been
the case for fifteen years, and still there is no fixed and solid 
foundation for them to sustain&#8212;and I fear wont be until the present 
generation passes away and another organized on different principals raises
up, who from more Experience will be able to frame a constitution
suitable to the manners and customs of the people it is intended for&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Nath: Cox</persName></p>

<p>I intended to send you the letter of <persName>Iterbide </persName>which he addresses
to a friend in <placeName>London </placeName>before sailing, but cant lay my hand on it at
present&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>N C</persName></p>

<p><persName>Col. Stephen F. Austin</persName> <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
