<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0693">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Charles Douglas to Stephen F. Austin, 02-26-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Charles Douglas</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Murfresborough, TN</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 743-746
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-02-26">02-26-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Monroe doctrine. England and the United States. Wants Austin's influence in helping Leftwich obtain colonial grant for Tennessee company. Depression in the United States. Banks.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Murfresborough </placeName><date when="1824-02-26">Feb 26th 1824</date></p>
<p><placeName>Rutherford County St[ate] Tennessee</placeName></p>
<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p>Much time has passed and many important political changes have
been effected since we parted. I hope they are all for the best and
will eventuate  in the establishment of  rational  liberty  in your<pb n="744"/>
country. It is difficult to say how the late unhappy change in <placeName>old
Spain</placeName> will effect you; but we have hope for the best and are anxiously
looking to the <persName>british Govt.</persName> for her final decision upon this important
question. Judging from the bold and energetic language used by
our <persName>President </persName>in his late Message to <persName>Congress </persName>upon the subject of the
presumed future conduct of the <persName>allied sovereigns</persName>, relative to the
subjugation of the <placeName>South American States</placeName>, and from the tone of the
english ministerial prints, we belive their is an understanding 
between us not only in opinion, but also as respects our future conduct.</p>

<p>Is it rational to suppose that <persName>England</persName>, possessing such decided
commercial advantages over every other nation will consent to
sacrifice all her fair prospects of a permanent and profitable market
for her commodities, merely for the sake of maintaining a good
understanding with those govts whose principles and policy she so
much dislikes ? We think not, and therefore conclude she will from
interest as well as principle not only agree with us in opinion, but
if necessary maintain her decision by a resort to arms. If this
opinion is correct you have nothing to fear from the consequences
of foreign invasion, for I am certain that the naval power of the
two govts united, can effectually prevent them from ever disturbing
your repose. I believe if <persName>England </persName>protests against the allied powers
interfering in the political affairs of your country and declares her
determination to oppose every such plan that this together with our
declaration will be sufficient to prevent them from attempting to
make any serious efforts.</p>

<p>Situated as you are it is a great misfortune that the people are
not more united. That there is not more disinterested patriotism
among them; and that your leading men are not more feelingly alive
to the real wants and prosperity of the nation. Action, virtue and
decision of character are now very necessary requisites in the 
conduct of your rulers and none ought to be elevated to stations of
power or honor without they possess them. If there is a <persName>bourbon
party</persName> among you it ought at all events to be destroyed such a party
united with the <persName>church </persName>might do you a great deal of injury. I hope
your <persName>congress </persName>will soon frame a good constitution and that the
<placeName>provinces </placeName>will not be backwards in adopting it then and not till
then will you be able to effectually suppress insurrection or repel
invasion. I want you to be united in your councils and actions to
cultivate friendship among yourselves and with other nations 
especially with those whose forms of govt most resemble your own. I
sincerely wish you well, and consequently take the liberty of giving
a little advice, I hope you will receive it as coming from a <persName>friend</persName>
who sincerely loves you individually and is warmly interested in
the prosperity of the <placeName>Nation </placeName>to which you, at present belong.<pb n="745"/></p>

<p>I have been in this country ever since <date n="04-xx-1823">April last</date> during which
I have not heard a solitary word from my <persName>friends in <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>! 
<persName>Loftwich </persName>has not yet returned and nobody has heard anything from him
for several months past we are afraid he is dead. If you should
happen to hear anything about him let me know. I am very anxious
that the <persName>government </persName>should make us a grant because I think it would
be a benifit to us here, and to them, and to yourself individually.
If a grant was made, there are so many of us interested that we
could procure a great number of <persName>settlers </persName>who would immediately
remove to the country and commence active operations, this would
undoubtedly enhance the value of your own, as well as our lands.
If you think with me (and no doubt you do) I want you to do all
you can with the govt for us. Your influence with it is very 
considerable, and if you will exert it for us I have no doubt but you
can do us a great deal of good. I want you to write to our friend
<persName>Don Ignacio de Cubas</persName> upon the subject of my land business and
urge him to exert himself to procure a grant as soon as possible, and
to send it directed to this place. I believe that 3 or 4 hundred 
respectable <persName>families </persName>might be procured here, without any difficulty
who would immediately remove to the country.</p>

<p>I have not heard a word from you since my arrival in the <placeName>United
States</placeName> only through the medium of <placeName>newspapers</placeName>, although I have
written you several letters directed to your <persName>friend </persName>in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
in which I particularly requested you to write to me and to direct
your letters to this place. I hope upon the reception of this you
will promptly answer it and let me know all about your present
situation and the prospects of your <persName>settlers</persName>. Do give me a 
particular description of your country as respects its soil, climate, health
etc. It is said by some that there is a great scarcity of timber, that
it is badly watered, that the banks of the rivers and small streams
are low and at particular times subject to inundation; and that 
during the croping season you suffer much for the want of rain. These
are important items of information for an agriculturist and as you
know all about it I want you to be particular in your statements
respecting the truth or falsehood of these reports. I want you also
to inform me which is the cheapest and best way for <persName>families </persName>to
remove from this to your country. I know you will correctly toll
me all about it, I therefore boldly make the request. Everything
here remains in Statu quo. Business of every kind is dull and the
people are heels over head in debt. Our banking institutions are
still playing their old games and the people are such wretched fools
as to quietly submit to their abominable impositions</p>

<p>Every species of property is verry low, and although our 
legislature has from time to time been trying to relieve the people, yet<pb n="746"/>
all their plans have the effect of plunging them still deeper into
difficulties. So much for legislative relief systems in time of 
pecuniary embarrisment.</p>

<p>Feb 5th [sic] I have just read in a <placeName>northern paper</placeName> accounts from
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>up to <date when="1823-11-24">Nov 24th</date> which state that the <persName>Congress </persName>have just 
reported the plan of a constitution in many respects similar to ours
here. I hope in God that the <placeName>provinces </placeName>will adopt it; and 
immediately proceed to organize a regular govt in compliance with its 
provisions. I was sorry to see that the roman catholic is the 
established religion and none other tolerated. This will have a bad effect
upon the minds of many good but weak people in the <placeName>U.S.</placeName> and (I
am afraid) will verry much discourage emigation to your country.
But a poor is better than no constitution and I only hope that the
good sense of your congress will so amend that clause as to at least
allow other sects freedom of conscience even if they make the catholic
the established religion.</p>

<p>Do write to me immediately upon the receipt of this and give me
all the information I have requested and as much more as you
please; it will all be more than acceptable.</p>

<p><persName>Chas. Douglas</persName></p>

<p><persName>Stephen Austin Esqr</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
