<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0684">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to John P. Coles, 02-02-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        John P. Coles
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 736-737
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-02-02">02-02-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Judicial procedure. Confirmation of verdict.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I received your official letter dated the <date when="1824-01-31">31 ultimo</date> together with
the charges against <persName>William Fitz Gibbons</persName>, <persName>Peter Whitiker</persName> and
<persName>William Whitiker</persName> for stealing, and enclosing a transcript of the
proceedings and verdict of the <persName>jury </persName>at the tryal of <persName>Peter Whitiker</persName>,
the other two having escaped, and also the defence of the said <persName>Peter
Whitiker</persName></p>

<p>The verdict of the <persName>Jury </persName>in this case finds the <persName>prisoner Peter 
Whitiker</persName> guilty of stealing four hogs worth ten Dollars each and assess
a fine against him of one hundred and twenty Dollars and costs of
Suit&#8212;</p>

<p>The 15th article of the Ordinance for the punishment of crimes
within this <placeName>Colony </placeName>declares that "any person who shall be 
convicted of stealing any Money horse or other property shall pay
trebel the amount of the property stolen and be condemned to hard
labor on public works untill the <persName>Superior Government</persName> decides on the
case" After attentively examing the transcript of the evidence and
proceedings in this case and the verdict of the <persName>jury </persName>and also the
defence of the <persName>prisoner Peter Whitiker</persName>, I have thought proper to
approve and do hereby approve the said verdict and order that it be
immediately executed with the following modifications</p>

<p>An execution shall immediately issue from the office of the <persName>Alcalde
of the <placeName>District of the Brazos</placeName></persName> against the property of <persName>Peter Whitiker</persName>
and his <persName>accomplices </persName><persName>William Fitz Gibbons</persName> and <persName>William Whitiker</persName>
for the sum of forty Dollars or the value thereof in property of
the kind stolen or any other property if none of that kind can be<pb n="737"/>
found, being the value of the hogs stolen which when collected shall
be delivered to the <persName>Alcalde </persName>of said district to be paid over when 
properly demanded to the rightfull owners of said stolen hogs also said
Execution shall issue for the whole amount of the costs of suit and
expence of the <persName>guard </persName>and any other legal charges to be collected
from the property of either or all of said <persName>parties </persName>concerned in said
theft&#8212;Also the <persName>Alcalde </persName>of sd District will cause a written notice to be
served by the <persName>constable </persName>on said <persName>Peter Whitiker</persName> <persName>William Fitz Gibbons</persName>
and <persName>William Whitiker</persName> that unless they remove and depart with
their <persName>families </persName>and effects from off the waters of the <placeName>Brazos </placeName>or
<placeName>Colorado River</placeName>s within three months from the date of said 
notice the full penalty of the 15 section of the ordinance before recited
will be enforced against them, that is that trebel the amount of the
property stolen will be collected from the property of the said <persName>Peter
Whitiker</persName> and his <persName>accomplices </persName><persName>William Fitz Gibbons</persName> and <persName>William
Whitiker</persName> and that they will also be condemned to hard labor on
public works as said section provides&#8212;The cost of serving which
notice shall also be paid by said prisoner and his said accomplices</p>

<p>The <persName>Alcalde </persName>of the said <placeName>district of the Brazos</placeName> is particularly
charged with the full execution of this order in all its parts and will
render an account to me when it is finally executed&#8212;</p>

<p>Given under my hand at the town of <placeName>St Felipe de Austin</placeName> this <date when="1824-02-02">2d
day of February 1824&#8212;4th 3d</date></p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>

<p><persName>Judge</persName></p>

<p>To the <persName>Alcalde of the <placeName>District of the Brazos</placeName></persName> [John P Coles]</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
