<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0053">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Antoine Soulard to Moses Austin, 02-17-1801</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Antoine Soulard</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-23">06-23-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Moses Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">St Louis, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 66-67
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1801-02-17">02-17-1801</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Inclosing certificate of survey. Advice about procedure in New Orleans to obtain title.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>St Louis</placeName> <date when="1801-02-17">February 17th- 1801</date></p>
<p>Sr</p>

<p>Herein Included you will find your Certificate of Survey, together
with the three petitions Granted by the Lieuts. Governors <persName>Don Zenon
Trudeau</persName> and <persName>De Lassus</persName> I Would recommend to you not to alter
the folds and to take the best Care not to Spoil it any way untill
you arrive at <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> for as the Deed of Grant which Shall be
Delivered to you is to be written underneath if it was not in a Good
order there might arise Some difficultys</p>

<p>I have requested <persName>Mr. Pascal D'etchemendy</persName> to Call upon you for
the payment of the Fifty Dollars which you are now owing me.
Which Sum with that of twenty five Dollars for which I have placed
myself upon you in favor of <persName>Mr. Thomas Maddin</persName> make up the Sum
of Seventy five Dollars full Ballance of the two hundred and twenty
five which you had agreed to pay me for the Compleat Survay of
your <placeName>Land</placeName></p>

<p>If for your own Satisfaction you would wish to have a Separate
map of Your <placeName>Land </placeName>upon a Scale Double of that of your Certificate
and upon which I Could write every word in english with the help
of <persName>Mr. Bellier</persName> I Could do and Send it to you for the time you might
want it and in the time of it's being delivered to you I Could tell
you what I Should think Just for you to pay me which I Cannot
tell but [by] the time that I may be Doing of it</p>

<p>If as I have been told you go down to <placeName>New-Orleans</placeName> I have no 
letter to give to you Since you are very well acquainted with <persName>Mr.
Zenon Trudeau </persName>who will Suport your rights try to get a letter from
<persName>Mr. Maxwell</persName> to his friend <persName>Mr. Leonard Gilbert the King's treasurer
</persName>and Doing now the Duty of <persName>Contador </persName>which Gives him the 
preponderency and the second office of the Intendency he is a very amiable
man and speaks very good english loves Joy and is the friend of
mankind ask him also [mutilated] for <persName>Don Walche</persName> his friend who
is a <persName>Minister </persName>Very amiable and an [mutilated] <persName>Irishman</persName>. Do not
go also without asking from Mr. [mutilated] letter from him to his
Son in Law <persName>Mr Derbigny</persName> my particular <persName>friend </persName>you will also find at
<placeName>New Orleans</placeName> a very handsome and Very well regulated <placeName><persName>mason</persName>'s
Loge</placeName>.</p>

<p>If your Intention is to return through the <placeName>United States</placeName> I wish
you would be So good as to let me know of it that I might Send to
you Letters for my friend <persName>Mr Chevalier</persName>.</p>

<p>After having told you what I think more convenient to your 
Interests I have only to assure you of my Sincere wish for your Success
in all your undertakings   I have not the least doubt but the Sheet<pb n="67"/>
Lead and Shot will be a Very Good article and In every thing which
you may have to Do with the <persName>Government </persName>I have not the least Doubt
but you know what Steps you are to take In order to Succeed</p>

<p><persName>Anto Soulard</persName></p>
<p>P. S.   be So good as to present my Best respects to <persName>Mrs. Austin</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
