<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0529">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Josiah H. Bell et al, 07-26-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Josiah H. Bell et al
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico City, MX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 533-535
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-07-26">07-26-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Introducing Col. Andrew Erwin. Prospect of liberal constitutional government. "Success of the settlement depends on the harmony and morality and industry of the settlers."</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>City of Mexico</placeName> <date when="1822-07-26">July 26 1822</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr J. H. Bell</persName><persName> A. Robinson</persName> and other <persName>settlers on the <placeName>Rivers Brazos
and Colorado</placeName></persName> Province of Texas</p>
<p>Gentlemen&#8212;</p>

<p>This will be handed you by my friend <persName>Col. Andrew Erwin of
<placeName>Tennessee</placeName></persName>, who you will find an intelligent and agreeable Gentleman,
he has a desire of procuring information relative to the country in<pb n="534"/>
which you live, and you will confer a particular favour on me by any
attentions in your power to afford&#8212;I refer you to him for every
particular relative to the political events which have transpired here,
and present state of the government etc., etc. On the <date when="1822-07-21">21 instant</date> the
<persName>Emperor </persName>and <persName>Empress </persName>were crowned with all the pomp and splendor
usual on such occations, and the <persName>Government </persName>is I think now 
established on a much more solid basis than it heretofore has been, the
legislative powers are all vested in the <persName>congress</persName>, and the <persName>Emperor </persName>has
sworn to support the Constitution which that body may form, so
that there is every reason to believe that the Govnt. will be as free
and liberal as any man could wish. As <persName>citizens </persName>of this, our <placeName>adopted
nation</placeName>, it is our duty to be obedient to the laws and to unite in 
support of the <persName>Government</persName>, I therefore hope that the <persName>Citizens of the
<placeName>Colorado </placeName>and <placeName>Brazos</placeName></persName> will present an example of good order worthy
of being followed&#8212;</p>

<p>I fear some of the <persName>Settlers </persName>may have become a little discouraged
at my long absence, and at the uncertainty in which they have 
remained, but I assure you that I have been labouring hard the whole
time for your Good, on my arrival here I found the <persName>Government</persName>
very much unsettled, Shortly after the <persName>Emperor Agustín</persName>, was 
proclaimed, and <persName>Congress </persName>have been so continually occupied with that,
and other important national concerns, that individual applications
could not be attended to, I now have a prospect of finishing every
thing in a short time, and hope to be with you once more shortly, I
wish you to assure the <persName>Settlers </persName>that all things will be arranged to
their full satisfaction, and that there is no cause for uneasiness at
my delay The <persName>Government </persName>are disposed to treat all good <persName>Citizens</persName>
with the greatest liberality&#8212;all bad one must expect the severest
rigor, I have been very uneasy at a report that the <persName>Indians </persName>have been
troublesome, I hope however that it is unfounded, this <date n="Fall-1822">fall </date>we must
try and force them to a peace, the <persName>Government </persName>will send on a body of
<persName>troops </persName>with whose aid I think the <persName>Comanches </persName>may be humbled, The
Constitution of this <placeName>Nation </placeName>is not yet formed, and there is no 
prospect that it will be finished short of five or six months, it is a work
of great magnitude and requires the most mature deliberation, I
have no doubt that it will secure all the personal rights and 
liberties of the people as effectually as we could wish&#8212;</p>

<p>I informed the <persName>Captain Genl.</persName> that I had appointed <persName>Mr. J. H. Bell</persName>
to act as <persName>Sindex </persName>in the <placeName>Settlement </placeName>which he approved&#8212;I hope there
has been no necessity for a <persName>civil officer</persName> and that every man has been
too much occupied with his <placeName>farm </placeName>to think of anything else The
whole success of the <placeName>Settlement </placeName>depends on the harmony and 
morality, and industry, of the <persName>settlers</persName>, if you establish your characters foi
these virtues, you have everything to hope which a generous and lib-<pb n="535"/>
eral Government can give you, but if unfortunately the reverse
should be the case, how great will be my mortification, and how 
different will be the state of the <placeName>Settlement </placeName>from what I hoped.</p>

<p>I think I shall be with you sometime in <date n="09-xx-1822">September</date>, when I flatter
myself with the pleasing hope of finding you all in peace and 
happiness, with Bread in abundance, and contentment in every breast&#8212;
I assure you that I feel the same interest for you all, which I could
do for a <persName>Brother</persName>, and I will labor for your happiness with every 
effort in my power. Remember me particularly to your <persName>family </persName>and
to every <persName>Settler </persName>you see&#8212;I wish you all health and happiness&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F Austin</persName></p>
<p>tell them (the <persName>settlers</persName>) not to be discouraged at the gloomy prospect
which wild woods present to them on their first arrival, a short time
will change the scene, and we shall enjoy many a merry dance and
wedding frolick together.</p>

<p><persName>S F A</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
