<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0488">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to James E. B. Austin, 03-23-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Loredo, Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Bexar, TX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 487-488
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-03-23">03-23-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Adventure with Comanches. Desolation of the country from Bexar to Laredo. How to study Spanish.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Loredo </placeName><date when="1822-03-23">March 23 1822</date></p>
<p>Dr <persName>Brother</persName>,</p>

<p>We arrived here on the <date when="1822-03-21">21 </date>and finding that a considerable 
<persName>Company </persName>were going on to <placeName>La Punta</placeName>, on Sunday afternoon I thought
it most prudent to wait for them, on acount of the <persName>Indians</persName>, who
are very numerous on all these roads,&#8212;about <placeName>six miles this side of
the river Nuesis</placeName> 50 <persName>Camanches </persName>charged upon us a little before sun
rise, the <persName>Doctor </persName>and <persName>Waters </persName>were out after the Horses and I was
alone at <placeName>Camp</placeName>, they surrounded me in an instant and took possession
of every article we had&#8212;resistance was useless for against so many
it would have been ineffectual the <persName>Doctor </persName>and <persName>Waters </persName>and the Horses
were soon brought up by the <persName>Indians </persName>and I then expostulated with
them for treating their <persName>Friends </persName>the <persName>Americans </persName>in such a manner,&#8212;
when they found there was no <persName>Spaniards </persName>with me, they gave us back
our Saddle bags, saddles, and everything else except 4 blankets, a
bridle, my Grammar and Several other little things and all our 
provisons, nothing saved our lives but being <persName>Americans</persName>, and as the next
party might not be so polite I have waited for the <persName>company </persName>that is
going on <date when="1822-03-14">to morrow</date>. Two men were taken <persName>prisoners</persName>, the day <date when="1822-03-11">before
yesterday</date> within a few miles of this place, one of whom escaped and
got in this <date when="1822-03-13">morning </date>he says the <persName>Indians </persName>are waylaying the road 
between this and <placeName>Punta</placeName>, (the road I am going)&#8212;about 3 miles this
side of where the <persName>Indians </persName>charged upon us, we met another <persName>party</persName>
of 34 who were encamped behind a hill watching the road, only two
of them came to us, they said their <persName>captain </persName>knew us to be 
<persName>Americans </persName>and ordered his men to let us alone.</p>

<p>The Country from the <placeName>River Madina</placeName> to this place is the poorest
I ever saw in my life, it is generally nothing but Sand, entirely void
of Timber, covered with scrubby thorn bushes and Prickly Pear&#8212;
this place is on the<placeName> bank of the Rio Grande</placeName>&#8212;and is as poor as sand
banks, and drought, and indolence can make it&#8212;The <placeName>river </placeName>is about
the size of the <placeName>Arkansas</placeName>, if anything a little larger&#8212;</p>

<p>I hope you are applying yourself closely to Study&#8212;get the first
volume of Dufiefs (?) Grammar from the <persName>Doctor </persName>and Study the
familiar phrases and lessons, and write them, also after commiting
a verb write it from memory and then compare it with the book to
see that the spelling is correct&#8212;also repeat your verbs as you learn
them to <persName>Francisco </persName>or some other who can correct your 
pronunciation, a bad pronunciation at the start will be difficult to correct,
therefore take no lessions [sic] from any but those who are capable
of giving them&#8212;Remember that it is all important to learn to write
the language&#8212;<pb n="488"/></p>

<p>Pray be particular in taking care of your things&#8212;The tent, 
Blankets, Kittle, Pack Saddle, the two bridles, and every other article
however trifling it may seem to be.</p>
<p>Write me directed to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>,</p>
<p>Your affc <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr James B. Austin</persName> <placeName>Bexar   </placeName><persName>Mr. Higginbotham</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
