<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0793">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John P. Coles to Stephen F. Austin, 07-07-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John P. Coles</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-17">07-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 845-846
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-07-07">07-07-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Austin's right to collect 12 1/2 cents an acre for land. This based on contracts with immigrants and can not be affected by interference of political chief.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1824-07-07">July 7th 1824</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>From the friendship I feel for you I venture to submit the 
following ideas for your reflection relative to the situation of this <placeName>colony</placeName>
and you as the <persName>founder </persName>etc.&#8212;you [know?] that the <persName>governor </persName>of this
<placeName>Province </placeName>has by his tory arrangements violated the contract made
between you and the People I can not conceive that the <persName>Governor
of the <placeName>Province</placeName></persName> has any thing to doo with the arrangement made by<pb n="846"/>
you with the <persName>settlers </persName>this I judge from the Authority Given you
by the <persName>Supreme Government of the <placeName>Nation</placeName></persName> I see that the <persName>Governor
of the <placeName>Province</placeName></persName> is Commissioned to assign the Titles to the Lands
and to put the <persName>settlers </persName>in possession or a <persName>commissioner </persName>by him 
appointed for that purpose. I see no Authority given him by the
<persName>Supreme Govt.</persName> to doo away the arrangement that you had made
with the <persName>settlers </persName>and Establish a list of Taxes to be paid by the 
<persName>Settler </persName>Contrary to the Laws of the <placeName>Nation </placeName>you say in a letter of a late
date to <persName>McNeel </persName>and to others that you are Ruined that the <persName>Governor</persName>
had Reduced the price of Land to fore cents pr acre why you should
have sujested such Ideas to <persName>McNeel </persName>or any one Else unless such as
you aught to have had more interest in I am at a loss to know it is
now Confirmed and believed by men who never believed before that
you have no authority from the <persName>Government </persName>and are only Imposing
on the people as has always been said. The fact is you are entitled
to 12 1/2 cents per acre for Lands from the <persName>settlers </persName>and there is no
candid man who would not agree that they are justly Indebted that
amount for all the lands he acquires through you and were I in your
situation I never would make any man a Deed to Land until I had
from him an assurance for the payment at 12 1/2 cents per Acre those
are the Grounds on which you have a Right unquestionably to ask
for pay and no other and it is on those grounds you should ask it
you can not say that the <persName>Government </persName>gives you the Right to ask
pay nor neither can you say that the <persName>Governor of the <placeName>Province</placeName></persName> has
a right to Establish a Bill of Taxes to be paid by the <persName>settlers </persName>to be
applied to his own use or to your Benefit. An attempt to collect pay
off of the <persName>people </persName>in any other way than on a Contract made by you
with the settlrs would be danger [ous] and it would have its day
of Persecution and <hi rend="italic">Trouble</hi>. I hope Sir that you will doo me the
Justice to believe that the foregoing observations are intended for
your good as well as for the Benefit of us all As respects those 
letters Referred to you must on Reflection concur with me in saying
that they are only calculated to Injure your standing and establish
more permanently the doubts of your Authority for such use is made
of them And further to intimidate the Respectable and prudent
<persName>Emigrant </persName>who would always prefer keeping himself and <persName>family </persName>out
of difficulty that might be Expected from such Reports. I received
an Official Order from the <persName>Governor </persName>which you will see by <persName>Mr. 
Williams</persName> the purposes of said order is vary contrary to my feelings
I shall not pay any respects to it until I see you.</p>

<p><persName>Jno. P. Coles</persName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
