<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0551">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to James E. B. Austin, 12-25-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico City, MX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 560-562
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-12-25">12-25-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Waiting for Emperor to approve the colonization law. Celebrations in Mexico City.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>City of Mexico</placeName> <date when="1822-12-25">Decr 25. 1822</date></p>
<p>A Merry and happy Christmas to my ever dear and beloved
<persName>Brother</persName>&#8212;You are no doubt much astonished to see my letter dated
at this place, the last I wrote which was about two weeks since I
expected to have started in 6 days, the Colonization law passed the
<persName>Junta </persName> near a month since and I then thought my business finished,<pb n="561"/>
but the <persName>Emperor </persName>has not yet approved it, and it will not be finished
for at least three weeks more, So that you need not look for me short
of two months from this day&#8212;<persName>Govr. Martinez </persName>and family arrived
here in good health three days ago, they give a favourable account
of your progress in the Spanish&#8212;pray do not my dear <persName>brother </persName>
disappoint me in this particular, it is of all importance that you learn
the language correctly, and particularly to <hi rend="italic">write it grammatically,</hi>
this can only be acquired by close attention and constant practice&#8212;
<persName>Govr. Martinez</persName> informs me that a part of the things sent in the
schooner Lively have arrived, you must do the best you can with them
and live as frugal as possible I have sent you two drafts on <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName> since I have been here for $50 each and you will make use
of such clothes and other articles which came in the schooner as you
may want.</p>

<p>I wrote you some time ago relative to taking a trip to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
with <persName>Don Salvador Carrasco</persName> &#8212;he probably will not be able to go
much before I arrive, as I am informed he has to wate for a quantity
of hides from <placeName>Chihuahua</placeName>&#8212;on this subject you must act your 
discretion but if you go, write me fully to <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>care of <persName>Andrews</persName>,
write every mail for 3 mails after you receive this directed to <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>
and let one of the letters be in <hi rend="italic">Spanish </hi>to give me a specimen of your
improvement&#8212;do not be discouraged at my long delay and inform
the <persName>settlers </persName>that I will not leave here until <hi rend="italic">all </hi>is well arranged&#8212;
"Blessed is he that holdeth out to the end" and I am determined to
persevere.</p>

<p>The last letter I recd from you was dated some time in <date n="08-xx-1822">August</date>, I
excuse this silence as you must have thought I was on the road write
to <persName>Mother </persName>every opportunity I wrote her this day by way of
<placeName>Tampico</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>There has been and still is much difficulty in the <placeName>Province of Vera
Cruz</placeName> a <persName>Genl Santana</persName> has proclaimed a <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Republic</placeName></hi>, but he met with
a defeat on the <date when="1822-12-20">night of 20</date> and <date when="1822-12-21">morning of the 21</date> at <placeName>Xalapa </placeName>which
it is expected will soon force him to leave the Country or yield
Everything is quiet here and this City appears pritty unanimous in
favour of the <persName>Emperor</persName>&#8212;You have nothing to do or say about the
Govt mind your studies&#8212;remember me most particularly to my
<persName>Friend </persName><persName>Don Erasmo</persName> and <persName>family </persName>and to the <persName>Baron de Bastrop</persName> and
<persName>Berrimandi </persName>and <persName>Musquis</persName>, also present my respects to <persName>Govr. 
Trespalacios</persName>, you must cultivate a good and friendly understanding with
him, visit him often&#8212;you have had a fine opportunity to study and
I shall really be <hi rend="italic">sorely </hi>disappointed if you have not made good use of
it&#8212;War was this day proclaimed by the <persName>Emperor </persName>against <placeName>Spain</placeName>&#8212;<pb n="562"/></p>

<p>This <placeName>City </placeName>has been and now is a constant scene of rejoicing 
illuminations etc. etc for three weeks past, on account of the birth of
another <persName>prince </persName>and the return of the <persName>Emperor </persName>from <placeName>Xalapa</placeName>&#8212;fare-
well, study hard, keep steady habits&#8212;live frugal&#8212;and keep up your
spirits all will be right in the end&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>ESTEVAN</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
