<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0586">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Robert Andrews to Stephen F. Austin, 05-15-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Robert Andrews</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Parras, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Monterrey, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 640-642
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-05-15">05-15-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Surveying. The people and country from Monterey to Parras.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Parras </placeName><date when="1823-05-15">May 15th/23</date></p>
<p>Nothing could have given me more satisfaction than an interview
with you, but I recollect the story of <hi rend="italic"><persName>Telemachus </persName></hi>who traveled
thro all grades of <placeName>Hell </placeName>and did not meet his <persName>father </persName>and at last they
met on <placeName>earth</placeName>, therefore as we did not meet in this infernal region I
most seriously hope we will meet on <placeName>earth</placeName>. I suppose we may be
allowed to compare ourselves to the Heathen Gods in this country,
where the people are more supersticious than they were when these
imaginary Deities existed.</p>

<p>I am really glad to hear that your wishes are compleatly fulfilled
in the business on which so much depends, but I do not recollect
the act of the <persName>Empl Govt</persName> on the subject, therefore do not know of
what magnitude your personal prospects may be, of this you will be
good enough to give me a scetch in your next, and whether the mode
of naturalisation will be as before&#8212;you say nothing of the 
surveying of which I am anxious to hear in as much as I have made 
application to the <persName>Govt </persName>for the appointment of <persName>surveyor </persName>in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, 
supposing that I might dislodge the <persName>Baron De Bastrop</persName> at this change
of <persName>Govt</persName>, by several good reasons some of which are the following,
that he is too old to give personal attention, that [he] probably
knows nothing of the new mode of calculation by Lat. and depart
which is the only mode to do it correctly - do not know, perhaps
my ineligibility alone may be sufficient to prevent me from obtaining
it, you who was at the fountain head can give me some information
on the subject, and if you think it possible,- write to some of your
<persName>acquaintances </persName>in <persName>congress</persName>, at least let me know what you think
on the subject - if I should obtain that office, I will land in <placeName>Texas</placeName>
in <date n="01-xx-1824">Jany</date>. with 20 odd labouring hands, 50 mules and horses, stores
and tools appropriate to open a <placeName>farm </placeName>and in all probability shall
be accompanied by the heads of several <persName>families </persName>who will go on in
order to settle, I have disclosed the plan of planting a <placeName>Town </placeName>on the
<placeName>collorado </placeName>or <placeName>Brazos </placeName>to the people here and they seem to be much
stimulated but as yet I cannot say what I can do. I believe I can
exercise about 2000 dollars on credit in that way, but the people
here are so da&#8212;d afraid of <persName>Indians </persName>that if they move in that 
direction they must have an <persName>American </persName>between them and the <persName>Comanches</persName>&#8212;
Therefore if a collony of these <hi rend="italic"><persName>sodomites </persName></hi>go on I shall have to be
their <persName>Joshua</persName>&#8212;I have written to your <persName>Brother </persName>and Alley to advise
me of the present circumstances and prospects in that quarter, and
shall depend much on your opinion, which you will remit me from
<placeName>Bexar </placeName>or <placeName>Colorado</placeName>, after seeing how things are, I shall leave this
place in a week or ten days for <placeName>Durango</placeName>, to which place I wish<pb n="641"/>
you to direct all letters here after except the answer to this from
<placeName>Monterey</placeName>, which if it startes soon may arive before I set out, and
if not I shall spend 3 weeks in the <placeName>Hacienda de los Hornos</placeName> with
the best <persName>family </persName>in the Govt, during which time I can send for it&#8212;</p>

<p>I am yet poor but owe nothing and shall perhaps be able to arive
at <placeName>Durango </placeName>with 25 or 30 dollars, where I have hope of doing better.</p>

<p>According to your request I am bound to say something of the
<placeName>country </placeName>over which I have passed, in this place it can be but short,
but when a work which I now have on hand comes to light a true
picture of many curious things persons and circumstances, 
accompanied by several drawings will be seen&#8212;The country from <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>to
this place has a nigh resemblance to that between <placeName>Monterrey </placeName>and
<placeName>La Punta</placeName>, there are 4 or 5 <placeName>farms </placeName>on the way, but one of which is of
any consideration this place is situated in rather a handsome and
very fertile <placeName>valley </placeName>about 3 or 4 miles wide, and about 6 miles south
and near 100 <placeName>west of Saltillo</placeName>, and contains upwards of 15,000 souls
the <placeName>Town </placeName>is closely joined to the mountain on the <placeName>south side of the
vally</placeName>, from which gush a vast number of <placeName>springs </placeName>one of which is so
large that it moves a very clumsy <placeName>grist mill</placeName>, the whole extent of
country over which this water extends is one continued <placeName>vinyard </placeName>with
the exception of a few fields of small grain and corn all of which is
in a fine state of cultivation, it also produces many other exquisit
fruits exclusive of the grape, but as to any spontaneous growth of
timber it is here like all other parts of the country that I have seen,
quite out of scrape&#8212;God d&#8212;n the luck! excuse me, my dear sir,
for breaking off so abruptly from my soft rural strane, I have just
recd a note informing me of more of my D&#8212;d bad fortunes which
would hunt me up in order to make things a little worse, if I were in
<persName>Pluto</persName>'s regions, enjoying all the comforts of <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Hell </placeName></hi>a <persName>friend </persName>writes
me that a few days after I left the <placeName>Hornos </placeName>for this place a message
arived for me to visit a rich patient in another village, which would
have been a greasor of 200 dollars, says my friend "he may send
for you yet"&#8212;God grant! if I thought it would do any good I would
send for the <persName>curate </persName>and have a mass said this moment 
notwithstanding it is near 3 oclock in the evening&#8212;The description of the 
country on to the <placeName>Hornos</placeName>, which is the furtherest I have been into the
country and which is about 50 miles west of this is near the same as
before&#8212;you told me nothing of our country man <persName>Fields </persName>for whom I
feel interested&#8212;<persName>Don Ignacio Peres</persName> and <persName>Mosieur Pier of <placeName>Bexar</placeName></persName> are
near this place on their way home and will fall in with you at 
<placeName>Monterrey </placeName>if they do not go by <placeName>Monclova</placeName>.</p>

<p>If my health, which now hangs on a more tender thread than
before should not be very good in the <date n="Fall-1823">fall</date>, the above mentioned plan
may be changed for a tour on sea, this will depend on circumstances<pb n="642"/>
If you should go to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, perhaps it might be well to leave
my address with <persName>Mr Hawkins</persName>, as I may fall in there some evening
and not be able to find any old acquaintance be sure to remember
me most affectionately to all old <persName>acquaintances </persName>in <placeName>Texas </placeName>and tell
them I hope to see them all again in the <date n="xx-xx-1824">year 24</date> give my respects
to <persName>Hickman</persName>. <persName>Philips </persName>and <persName>Doctr. Purnell</persName> in <placeName>Monterrey</placeName>&#8212;hoping that
the day will come when we may sit toe to toe under our own vine and
fig tree, retired from the bustle of the world, and reherse the toils
of our youth, over a can of domistic wine, I present you the best
wishes of</p>

<p>Your true friend</p>

<p><persName>Andrews</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] A <persName>Sr. Dn Estevan Austin</persName> <persName>Anglo Americano </persName>
<placeName>Monterrey</placeName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
