<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="AP0015">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas Norvell to Moses Austin, 11-09-1795</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Thomas Norvell</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-11">06-11-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Mr. Joseph Burr 
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Moses Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Richmond, VA</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 23-24
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1795-11-09">11-09-1795</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning slaves which Austin wishes to purchase. Connections with Blanchard and Lauman.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Richmond </placeName><date when="1795-11-09">November, 9th. 95</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr. Moses Austin</persName></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I am favord with yours of the <date when="1795-10-25">25th Ulto</date> and had 
sufficiently ( I hope) explaind every thing that was necessary, that is
to say with respect to <persName>Harry</persName>s stay here, as also to that of the
<persName>negroes</persName>. <persName>Mr. Randolph</persName> (who I twice went to see) would not sell his
<persName>negroes </persName>without his <placeName>land</placeName>, he mentiond to me that he had once offerd,
you a bargain and wish you to have purchased but Says now he has
declind selling without he could sell his Lands also I have been 
endeavoring to purchase two or three of <persName>Saml McCraw</persName>, for you, but
there appears to be little dependance in what he says. I have not yet
brought suit vs him because he has given me the fairest promises that
ever a man did however I shall not confide in him any longer altho
I think it will be as well for you to let him keep her as he does and
make him pay her hire every year, without her being at any risk of
yours, than to receive her. It is pretty interest on a mans money
without the smallest risk, however Sir I shall use my exertions to get
her as soon as possible agreable to your instructions etc.</p>

<p>This will be handed you by <persName>Mr. Joseph Burr</persName> who arrived here two
days since on business for <persName>John D Blanchard</persName> and <persName>George Lauman</persName>
and himself I suppose, he is a man I have a good oppinion of and
would very fondly oblige him but I could not comply with his 
requests, which was to let the 150,000 Acres survey be return into the
<placeName>Land office</placeName> he was extreemly anxious indeed but I could not oblige
him. he says it is for his own Sake, being interested, now I do
actually believe him to be a much better man than <persName>Blanchard </persName>and
think him a man of honor, but you very well know my reason for not
returning the survey. I conceive that some damages are to be paid
for the bills being protested which is by law 15 pr Cent but something
less I suppose will do; and at any rate I shall expect a commission
from <persName>Blanchard </persName>and <persName>Lauman </persName>of 5 pr Cent for my attention etc which
I hope you have no objection to, and also hope that you will endeavor
to secure that much for me, in receiving your Money from <persName>Mr. Burr</persName>,
before you instruct me to let the survey be enter4, this I conceive to
be just.   <persName>Mr. Burr</persName> himself acknowledges that I ought to have it   in<pb n="24"/>
fact I have it in my power to make them pay more etc. I only wish
justice to take place, you will without doubt have all the business
settled, to your satisfaction, before you instruct me to enter or return
the survey to the <placeName>Land office</placeName>. I shall expect you to give me full 
instructions how to proceed <persName>Shott</persName> is in great demand and I really
want money for Sundry purposes for the benefit of the <persName>company</persName>.
Shffs Demands are the principal</p>

<p><persName>Thom Norvell</persName></p>
<p>My respects to <persName>Mrs Austen</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
