<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0668">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Philip T. Dimmitt to Stephen F. Austin, 01-04-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Philip T. Dimmitt</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">St. Antonio, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 720-721
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-01-04">01-04-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reports large thefts of horses and mules at Bexar. Commerce.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>St. Antonia</placeName> <date when="1824-01-04">4th Janua 1824</date></p>
<p>My friend.</p>

<p>I am here still but I have Good and bad news to write you on
the first of this month I lost a Eleven mules and 3 head of Horses
with this brand. [He inserts the brand.] all except one Large Horse
Mule with this [Brand inserted.] brand. The Horses Has the
Same brand that the 10 Mules has The money that I recd frome
<persName>Varron </persName>I bought 5 mules and I recd from <persName>Treveño </persName>2 mules and fore
others I traded for with a few Goods. I bought of a <persName>frenchman </persName>the
five head of Horses I traded my wach for <persName>Little </persName>and a <persName>Spanyard</persName>
was taking ceare [care] of them with <persName>Smith </persName><persName>Cooks </persName>and <persName>Mr. T[r]evino
</persName>thar ware about 50 Head of Horses and mules lost. 8 Days pass I
recd. a letter from my <persName>brother </persName>at <placeName>Monclover </placeName>requesting me to come
and recd a few Goods he has brought for me my <persName>farther </persName>sent out
about 800 or 900 Hundred Dollars worth of Goods for me so States
my <persName>brother </persName>in his letter and they are at <placeName>refuria [Refugio]</placeName>. I shall
I hope be able to pay you for my land on my return but I shall not be
able to start until I here from you</p>

<p>I must requst it as a favor and one which I am a fraid I never
will be able to return but my prospects are some what flattern at
presant from a copie of letters I recd. with the letter of my <persName>brother</persName>
I am here Sr. without a cent. of money or Horse or mules and to
procure aney Sr. If you can Lend me Two mules it shall be Doble
paid nothing but my Death at present Can Prevent it as my
prospects are favorible and you may Rest assured that If you are
able to lend me this assistance I shall feel myself bound to you as
your servent and Under your command and the reward is within my
power at presant for to pay those favors you have Done me and
the maney benefits you have wish to doo for me and the Good hart<pb n="721"/>
and Disposition you have so opinley shown me. I want 2 mules to
Gow to my <persName>brother </persName>and from thence to my Goods and If I doo not
rece 2 mules from you I shall be unable to Gow untill my <persName>brother</persName>
Can send me mules or horses but If it is in your power to comply
with my request I shall not forget the assistance you will be so Good
if in you power to send them by <persName>Capt. Rooker</persName> the marks of them</p>

<p>I am without news at this moment. <persName>Capt. R.</persName> will Give you all.
<persName>Mr Little</persName> will [be] at you house in a few Days&#8212;a foot he wishes to
Get work at the <persName>Carpenter </persName>busness he will give you a scetch of my
lost</p>

<p><persName>P.  T.   DIMMITT</persName></p>

<p>NB Sr. If you cannot lend me 2 two mules send me one one [is]
sufficent to carry me to my <persName>brother</persName></p>

<p><persName>DIMMITT</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr. S. F. Austin</persName> in los <placeName>Brassos </placeName><persName>Capt. Rooker</persName>
NB    Give my best respects to <persName>J Austin</persName> and <persName>brother</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
