<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0700">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Randall Jones to Stephen F. Austin, 03-05-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Randall Jones</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-16">07-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Fort Settlement, TX</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 749-750
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-03-05">03-05-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning Mrs. Long. Judicial system. Economics.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Fort Settlement</placeName></p>

<p><date when="1824-03-05">5th March 1824</date></p>
<p><persName>Col Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>
<p>Sir</p>

<p>I received your note including the copy of an account of <persName>Mrs.
Jane H. Long widow</persName> of <persName>Genl James Long</persName> and having a tolerable
long story to communicate have thought proper to do it in this way
that you might think over it at your lesiure I became acquainted
with the relations of <persName>Mrs. Long</persName> in the year <date n="xx-xx-1820">1820</date> near 
<placeName>Ale[x]andria Louisiana</placeName> and in the <date n="Fall-1820">fall of that year</date> I traveled with her to her
<persName>husband </persName>then in <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>I received the thanks of <persName>Genl Long</persName>
for my attention to his <persName>Lady </persName>on the road. On my return from the
trip in exploring the <placeName>Colerado </placeName>I understood that <persName>Long </persName>had gone
on to <placeName>Labahia </placeName>and had left his <persName>wife </persName>at <placeName>Galveston </placeName>without provision
or <persName>friends </persName>to suffer. Some time in the <date n="05-xx-1820">month of May</date> <persName>Mrs Long
</persName>arrived near the mouth of the <placeName>river Hyacinth</placeName> and was living with
a family by the name of <persName>Smith </persName>the <persName>old man</persName> was taken in a short
time with the fever and died. <persName>Mrs. Long</persName> about that time had a
difference with some of the female part of the family and left the
house and hired a <persName>negro </persName>to build her a <placeName>palmetto camp</placeName> where she
was exposed to the sun and rain and without any provision except
a small quantity of milk and some times a little venison. I calld
on her and she very frankly told me her situation stated that she
had written to her <persName>friends </persName>but had received no answers that she and
her <persName>family </persName>must certainly suffer that she had no provission but a
very scanty supply that she drew from the <persName>family </persName>she livd near. I
told her that if she would move up to the <placeName>Tuscoseto crossing of the
river</placeName> I would do every thing in my power to prevent her and <persName>family</persName>
from suffering to which she agreed. About the same time I purchasd
goods from her to the amount of fifty Dollars not to be paid in
money but a horse. Before I movd her I built her a vary comfortable
<placeName>cabin </placeName>I then went down carried a <persName>negro </persName>with me and hired two
others and movd her up to the house I had built for her some time
previous I had purchased some corn meal pork, and salt my <persName>Brother</persName>
and myself hunted and found her and <persName>family </persName>in plenty of moat
I movd her up early in the <date n="07-xx-1820">month of July</date>. During the time she
was there she wishd very much to go on to <placeName>St. Antonia</placeName> I persuaided
her to go first to her <persName>friends </persName>and then if she found it necessary she
could be better prepard to go on to the <placeName>Spanish country</placeName>. About the
<date n="08-xx-1820">middle of August</date> a <persName>negro </persName>arrivd from <placeName>Alexandria </placeName>with a horse and
mule for her service he also brought letters leaving it entirely with
herself whether she should return to her <persName>friends </persName>or go on to see the<pb n="750"/>
<persName>Governor </persName>but rather recommended her to go on if she thought the
prospect of getting anything from the government was flattering.
She immediately consulted my <persName>Brother </persName>and myself on the subject
we persuiaded her not to think of setting out on so long a Journey
with her small <persName>children </persName>but she was determind to go. She proposd
that we should go with her she told us that she would make us ample
satisfaction when she should arrive at <placeName>San Antonia</placeName> for all our
services We finally agreed to go with her if she would bear our
expenses and pay us when we arrived at <placeName>San Antonia </placeName>there was
no price namd but her word was complete satisfaction for our services
We also furnishd her horses to carry part of her Baggage and
<persName>family </persName>and walked ourselves the greatest part of the way. We left
the <placeName>Hyacinth </placeName>the <date when="1820-08-31">last of August</date> and arrivd in <placeName>San Antonia</placeName> some time
in <date n="10-xx-1820">October </date>some of the <persName>Party </persName>being <persName>footmen</persName></p>

<p>When we arrived in <placeName>San Antonia</placeName> I waited on the <persName>Baron de
Bastrop</persName> to whom I had a letter of introduction and stated to him
the arrival of<persName> Mrs. Long</persName> and <persName>family </persName>in town he walkd with 
myself and <persName>Brother </persName>to the <placeName>government hous</placeName>e and introduced us to
the <persName>Governor </persName>who treated us with attention. After being in Town
four or five days I informed <persName>Mrs. Long</persName> our wish to return she
then told me for the first time that it was impossible for her to
settle with us at that time that she had been so short a time there
that she disliked asking the <persName>governor </persName>for any thing. I then told
her I was in want of a horse to return on that I had walkd nearly
all the way there and could not think of walking back she then
told me to take a grey horse which she rode out which I expected
to return to her when she settled with me for my services I had
also carried her Rifle I told her if I left the <placeName>Province </placeName>I would
leave the gun at <persName>Mr. Rankins</persName> with other property she had there but
if I remaind I would keep it until she calld for it. She stated that
the gun was not hers and wishd me not to part with it. The gun
I never contracted for in no way and am ready to deliver it and
when she settles with me for my services will deliver the horse and
pay her for the bridle. I consider that <persName>Mrs. Long</persName> is considerably in
my debt and wish the thing settled immediately my treatment to
<persName>Mrs. Long</persName> and <persName>family </persName>is well known and I can prove the most of
what I have here related</p>

<p><persName>R[andall] Jones</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
