<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0099">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William Morrison to Nathan Pusey, 04-04-1806</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William Morrison</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-24">06-24-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Nathan Pusey
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Kaskaskia, IL</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 103-105
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1806-04-04">04-04-1806</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-24" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker"> Purchase of goods in New Orleans.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Sir You will please to embark on Board the flat boat under the
Care of <persName>Mr Alexis Panna</persName> bound to<placeName> New Orleans</placeName> laden with Nine
hundred bars of lead and some . . . Pieces makeing together
46000 lb. the Batteau that [I inte]nd to send after you under the
Care of <persName>Mr Francois Menard</persName> a young man who can be of Great
Service to you in <placeName>Orleans </placeName>from his being acquainted with nearly all
the <persName>Merchants </persName>that you may wish to call on for the Articles you want
to send up in the Batteau.<persName> Mr Menard</persName> is a Careful Sober man
and Possesses a high sence of Honor, will never neglect any Charge
committted to him. Can assist you in Settling with the men and
in engaging any that you may want at <placeName>Orleans</placeName>&#8212;As well make some
enquiry for the Persons you will be in search of in <placeName>Orleans</placeName>, <persName>Viz
Arequoitte</persName>, <persName>La Doucour</persName> and others, I wish you to make sale of all
the lead should it bring 7 Cents per lb and employ the Proceeds
to the Purchase of the Return Cargo, if the Blocading Decrees
should be in force you must make the best sale or Barter of the
load in your Power Contract with some person for your lead and
let them supply you with the articles you want If nothing else
will do Deposit a quantity of lead as Security for anything you
bring up and fix the Price of lead if not sold we will hold ourselves<pb n="104"/>
responsible for the money next <date n="Winter-1806">Winter</date>. The Peltry if I should
Send any ought to bring at least 30 Cents if no more can be had
and if that price Cannot be obtained Ship it to <persName>Guy Bryan Esqr</persName>
<placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>and Should no vessel appear Ready to Sail for 
<placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>Ship to either <placeName>New York</placeName> or <placeName>Baltimore </placeName>to Some house that
you either know or that you Get Recommended to by your <persName>friends</persName>
of <placeName>Orleans</placeName>. I think <persName>Jacob Aster of <placeName>New York</placeName></persName> would be the house
I would Recommend, In <placeName>Baltimore </placeName><persName>John Comerges</persName>&#8212;Perhaps&#8212;It
will be necessary [to] observe I wish that you may be able to Procure
freight from <placeName>Orleans </placeName>to <placeName>St Louis</placeName> or to the <placeName>mouth of Ohio</placeName>. I would
Rather Carry on freight this year than bring a quantity of the
Articles herein mentioned the common Price for freight is from 5
to 7 Dollars per 100 lb to this Place. <persName>St Louis</persName> or to the <placeName>mouth of the
Ohio</placeName>, and it is also a Custom to Receive the Payment at <placeName>Orleans </placeName>or
at least half the Amot.</p>

<p>After the Batteau loaded Say about 50,000 weight on board, you
Return by the Shortest Route by land and bring with you the Invoice
of the Cargo and a Statement of all the Transactions Since you Set
out</p>

<p>Keep an Exact account of all the Expenses etc. Should you find
it necessary to Remain longer in <placeName>Orleans </placeName>so as to Effect the 
Settlement with those persons on your list and you see a prospect of doing
it [I shall?] be Very Glad&#8212; Return by the way of <placeName>Nashville </placeName>Call
on <persName>J B Demonbrun</persName> for the . . . note as also Settle the amount of
feathers left in the hands of <persName>George Poyner</persName> by <persName>Archibald McNabb
</persName>agreeable to the receipt you are in Possession of&#8212;</p>

<p>I  shall Give you a letter to <persName>Mr Morgan</persName> by <persName>Mr Menard</persName> pr Batteau</p>

<p><persName>Wm Morrison</persName>.</p>
<p><persName>Nathan Pusey</persName>&#8212;</p>
<p>[Kaskaskia] <date when="1806-04-04">April 4th 1806</date>.</p>

<p>Articles Wanted from <placeName>Orleans</placeName></p>

<p>2  Pipes french Brandy</p>
<p>10 hhds red Wine if cheap say not more than 40 Dols</p>
<p>10,000 lb <placeName>Orlean </placeName>Sugar</p>
<p>16  Crates earthen  ware,  Plates,  dishes,  Bowls,  cups.  Saucers,
tureens, Tea Potts, Sugar Dishes, Cream Jugs etc&#8212;</p>
<p>100 Doz 1/2 pint tumblers Glass in Crates etc</p>
<p>1  hhd red wine in Bottles to be drawn off after the wine is Purchased&#8212;</p>
<p>2  Bags Corks&#8212;</p>
<p>3  Boxes Cigars large size&#8212;</p>
<p>1 Barrel Salted Mackrell<pb n="105"/></p>
<p>Some keggs Cut Nails for Joint Shingles and others for lathing
of the Smallest kind they ought not to exceed 15 Cents per lb&#8212;</p>
<p>2 Demy Johns lime Juice&#8212;</p>
<p>100 lb Allspice&#8212;</p>
<p>100 lb peper&#8212;</p>
<p>500 lb Steel</p>
<p>1 Barrel Rice besides the Provision for boats</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
