<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0107">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Will C. Carr to Moses Austin, 08-12-1806</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Will C. Carr</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-27">06-27-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Moses Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">St Louis, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Burton Mine, MO</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 112-114
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1806-08-12">08-12-1806</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-27" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Opinion of Austin's procedure with John Smith T. Rufus Easton's attack on Donaldson, one of the Land Commissioners.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>St Louis</placeName> <date when="1806-08-12">12th. August 1806</date></p>
<p>Sir,</p>

<p>Your several favors have been duly received: in answer to the first
I have to inform you that the reports of the <persName>indians</persName>, being embodied
to do any damage either at this place or any where else within the
<placeName>territory </placeName>is the mere idle suggestion of timid minds or designing
knaves. It is the shallow pretext of those who wish, the residence
of the <persName>military </persName>amongst us. and as in the reality there is not the
existance of even the semblance of danger to warrant the report so
I trust, the wish of those who wish the encampment of a great many
<persName>troops </persName>in our agitated <placeName>territory </placeName>may be entirely blasted&#8212;</p>

<p>Your conduct towards <persName>Smith </persName>so far as I have any knowledge of
it, meets my entire approbation. But You certainly are disposed to
compliment me, by the submission of your conduct to my judgment&#8212;
Your age as well as your talents and experience doubtless warrant
me in saying the reverse of this would certainly be the most proper&#8212;
But if the suggestion of my ideas in any case or in any situation can
be of any service to you, they shall always flow free as air, and warm
from the dictates of friendship&#8212;</p>

<p>I approbate your answer to <persName>Smith </persName>and hope you will continue to
pursue towards him a line of conduct, firm yet moderate&#8212; If I may
once be permitted to mention to you one trait in your character that
may be amended; it is your temper, I do not mention this as being
a prominent feature in any part of your late conduct either towards
<persName>Smith </persName>or others&#8212;far from it&#8212; Your conduct has been cool, 
dispassionate and Prudent. But I only mention it to you as your weak
side and on which it is so necessary to arm yourself in your 
treatment to <persName>John Smith</persName>. <hi rend="italic">Beware of that man! He is the spirit of
faction and exists only in the element of discord!</hi> Give such men
tether enough and they will hang themselves. Endeavour to act
only on the defensive, and suffer the Law to deal with him&#8212; For
with this you will find men of this discription often enough coming
into contact.&#8212; At the same time it will not be necessary for me
to mention to you, those lengths to which a man of character ought
to proceed, (overleaping the line of defensive conduct) to maintain<pb n="113"/>
unsullied his reputation. On this subject you need no prompter,
and I shall not presume even to hazzard the suggestion of a single
idea.</p>

<p>In regard to your having commenced actions against <persName>S[mith]</persName> and
<persName>M[adden?]</persName> you have probably done well: and I can only observe
further, that the report by <persName>M.</persName> was certainly very improper and
doubtless actionable&#8212;</p>

<p>I cannot see as far as the probable consequences of your notification
to <persName>Mr. Oliver</persName>, concerning your removal from office: and more 
especially of an attempt, should you make one, to resume your seat on the
bench. This is certainly an affair pregnant with important 
consequences both of a public and private nature&#8212;and deserves well to be
weighed, before you proceed to carry it into execution. Will it not
produce a riot? Can <persName>Smith </persName>yield to it peaceably? I fear not? I
fear he would proceed to some outrage ? If so it might tend to very
pernicious effects. Besides I should not desire to see you for a 
moment subject to the mortification of disappointment. I should not
wish you to make an attempt without being certain of success&#8212; 
Under these circumstances would it not be best, to have the question
decided in the general Court? This might be very easily effected by
pleading in abatement, to some one writ <hi rend="italic">that <persName>John Smith T.</persName> is not
<persName>first justice of the court</persName></hi> I am aware that This method is subject to
several inconveniences, such as delay etc. But the question is, is it
not the best method that can be adopted at this moment ?&#8212; If you
and <persName>S</persName>. were friends so that you could assume the seat again without
breeding any disturbance, it would then rest, for the <persName>governors
friends</persName> to prove you were legally dismissed&#8212; But I suppose the
terms between you will not warrant you in writing to him to know
what would be his conduct if you were to do so&#8212; But I do not see,
wherein, this measure would be dishonorable on your part. For you
might inform him of the letter received from <persName>governor Harrison</persName> and
your intention to resume your seat if he were not determined to 
oppose it with force: and that as you abhored every thing that had a
tendency to irritate the public mind and disturb the administration
of justice&#8212; You wished that the law might decide the question.
However in this I submit entirely to yourself act as you may deem
most prudent for yourself and beneficial to the public interest-</p>

<p>As the <placeName>Western World</placeName> says&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Look here! read this!</hi> To day&#8212;
whilst the <persName>board </persName>was sitting <persName>Easton </persName>marched into the room and
gave <persName>Donaldson </persName>the cane whilst sitting on the bench. This was
the first time (I believe) that <persName>E</persName> had seen <persName>D </persName>after his return&#8212; The
room was very full of people and we were just commencing the ex-<pb n="114"/>
animation of <persName>old Matte</persName>s case&#8212; <persName>E </persName>gave him four or five [a]ssaults
with the cudgel and then stepped back a few paces. <persName>D.</persName> then jumped
off the bench and seized a sword cane which he always carries with
him and which was standing at the end of the bench&#8212; But did
not attempt to do any thing with it&#8212; However I forgot to tell
you&#8212; Whilst <persName>E.</persName> was plying him with his cudgel he commanded him
all the time to <hi rend="italic">march you damned little rogue March you damned
rascal</hi>&#8212; and when retired at the distance of a few paces as above,
he abused <persName>D. </persName>very much all in the room and in presence of a full
<persName>board</persName>&#8212;<persName> D.</persName> not saying a single word, and Doubtless seized with a
double portion of that suspense which held every body for some
time in utter astonishment&#8212; At last <persName>Judge Lucas</persName> (as of course he
was obliged to do) ordered <persName>E.</persName> out of the <persName>house</persName>, and, cleared the room
to deliberate on what should be done to revenge the insult offered to
the board. The result was; they issued some kind of process against
him but of what nature I am not able to tell you. The effect of it is
not yet known and how they will punish him otherwise than for assault
and battery&#8212;I cannot tell&#8212; Surely there never was a more 
ridiculous act committed by any man-&#8212; For in the first place the time was
beyond all calculation improper&#8212;and insulting every member of the
board&#8212; in the second place after he began it, he did not half finish
it&#8212; He gave him only a few strokes with the cane and they not put
on hard enough to hurt him&#8212; I am very sorry it was done: be-
cause it will not only operate against him but all the party&#8212; On
the contrary&#8212; if he had given it to him in the streets&#8212; or on some fit
occasion he would have been supported, by every body and ultimately
sustained no damage&#8212; But now even the passions of the 
government abroad must be enlisted on their side; for the sake of 
protecting their officers from similar outrages&#8212; It was done without the
knowledge or approbation of any of his friends&#8212; However much
I deprecate the circumstance at present: yet I believe it is better
done any way than no way at all&#8212; I do not wish any thing I have
said to operate against <persName>Easton </persName>but candour has obliged me to give
you this full statement&#8212; Therefore do not let the world know we
censure him&#8212;</p>

<p>One word more and I have done&#8212; Do you not owe <persName>Perigrine
Falconer</persName> something&#8212; If so let me advise you even at the expence of
a sacrifice, be punctual to a day to pay him at <placeName>Orleans</placeName>&#8212; Trust me
in this, it will be for your benefit&#8212;- More I cannot say&#8212; But be
certain to pay him to the hour there, if within the compass of 
possibility&#8212;   More I will probably tell you of this hereafter.</p>

<p><persName>Will C Carr</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Moses Austin esq </persName>  <persName>Mr. E. Bates</persName>.    <placeName>Mine a Breton</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
