<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0583">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>J. H. Bell to Jose Felix Trespalacios, 05-04-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>J. H. Bell</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Jose Felix Trespalacios
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 636-637
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-05-04">05-04-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Describes administration of justice against horse thief; asks approval or instructions.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>To his <persName>Excellency Dn Jose Felix Trespalacios
Govr of the <placeName>province of Texas</placeName></persName></p>

<p>Sir.</p>

<p>On the <date when="1823-03-23">twenty first of March last</date> there was a <persName>Frenchman </persName>who
called his name <persName>Bt. Rashall</persName> a <persName>citizen of the <placeName>United States of America</placeName></persName>
pased through this <placeName>Neighborhood</placeName>, he had in company with him a
man he said was an <persName>Indian</persName>. <persName>Rashall </persName>had a small cavallard sixteen
in number of horses and mules of different brands, as they passed
through the <placeName>neighborhood of the Colorado</placeName> they stole thirteen head
of horses from <persName>Mr Buckner</persName> and <persName>Parker</persName>, came on to <persName>Martin Varner</persName>
living on the road in the <placeName>neighborhood of the Brazos</placeName> and stole four
head from him, and passed on across the <placeName>Brazos </placeName>entending to make
their escape for the <placeName>United States</placeName> we raised a party of men and
followed them near the <placeName>Trinity river</placeName> and overtook them, and they
having no pasport we brought them back, and on examination found
them Guilty of Theft I detained the cavallyard and started the
men on to <placeName>St Antonio</placeName> under a guard for your instruction at the
<placeName>Colorado</placeName>, the <persName>Alcalde </persName>and <persName>Comandant </persName>stopt them, and directed the
guard to return, saying they had instructions from your <persName>excellency</persName>
not to send any guilty of such crimes on but to decide on the case
ourselves, their doing so put it out of my power to send them on
after they returned as we have not horses for that purpose and men<pb n="637"/>
could not leave their crops having lost so much time already being
convinced of the guilt of <persName>Rashall </persName>I took the property I found to be
his, to pay the expence of appehending them and also to pay for the
property they stole and did not return thir was one hundred and
fifty dollars of the stolen property we could get nothing for, which
was lost to the <persName>owners</persName>, that was the property of <persName>Mr Parker</persName> which he
will lose as <persName>Rashall </persName>had not property sufficient to satisfy the 
demand, and the property they stole was lost and not returned&#8212; the
<persName>hands </persName>that were with <persName>Rashall </persName>were <persName>Spaniards </persName>who claimed part of
the property which we gave them and directed them to return home
the property I let <persName>Parker </persName>have to pay part of his loss, I had it valued
and bound him in a bond to return the property or the value thereof
in case you disaproved of the proceedings and anyone came forward
to claim it, the manner in which I acted appeared from every
evidence I could get on the subject to be as near justice as was in my
power to come at and I wish your <persName>Excellency </persName>so soon as convenient
to say whether the part I acted was right or not, we are much at
a loss for Instructions from that place, as we have never received
one official line since the <persName>officers </persName>were elected be so good as to give
us instructions when you can with convenience.</p>

<p><persName>J. H. Bell. </persName>   [Rubric]</p>
<p><date when="1823-05-04">May the 4th 1823</date></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
