<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0850">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James E. B. Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 09-06-1824</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James E. B. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-18">07-18-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Mr Hale
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Hazel Run, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, TX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 890-892
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type=" Private"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1824-09-06">09-06-1824</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Marriage of sister to James F. Perry. Will return to Texas alone. Note by Emily at bottom.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Hazel Run</placeName> <date when="1821-09-06">Sept. 6th 1821</date></p>
<p>My dear <persName>Brother</persName>/</p>

<p>I improve the present opportunity of writing you by <persName>Mr Hale</persName>,
lest my letters to you previous to this Should miscarry as I wrote
by mail, directed to the care of <persName>Cable </persName>in <placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>.</p>

<p>I presume ere this you have heard of our irreparable loss in the
death of dearly beloved <persName>Mother</persName>, and also of <persName>Aunt Austin</persName>. So many
unhappy changes, have taken place in <placeName>Missouri </placeName>since I left it that
I long to be with you once more in <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>Another change tho not of so unpleasant a nature is Shortly to
transpire in our <persName>family</persName>, which is, the marriage of our <persName>Sister Emily</persName>,
with <persName>Mr James F. Perry of <placeName>Mine A Burton</placeName></persName>!! I confess that I was
as much Surprized as you will be, when she informed me of it, a few
days ago:&#8212;<persName>Emily </persName>asked my advice on the Subject:&#8212;my reply to
her was, that <hi rend="italic">She </hi>knew whether her marriage with <persName>Mr P.</persName> would be
conducive to her happiness or not if She considered it would, I
acquiesed with cheerfulness and made no doubt you would do the
Same&#8212; I only regret that it will be impossible for us to collect the
remains of our unfortunate <persName>family </persName>together for some years; <hi rend="italic">if ever.</hi>
As to <persName>Mr. P</persName> you are acquainted with him and best know w[h]ether
her choice is a judicious one or not, his Standing is high and morals
unexceptionable&#8212;</p>

<p>I intend to leave here some time next month So as to be in <placeName>Ns.
[Natchitoches]</placeName> by the <date when="1824-11-01">1st of Novr</date>. I should like to hear from you
before I start but the dread of spending a <date n="Winter-1824">winter </date>in this <hi rend="italic">"cursed
land"</hi> determines me to leave it, my expences will be light returning,
as I Shall be alone, I have nearly all the money by me still; and
will not spend one cent more than I possibly can help untill I hear
from you which I hope to on my arrival at <placeName>Natchs</placeName>. I shall take on
with me a great many articles that we <hi rend="italic">shall want</hi> and <hi rend="italic">may </hi>have
enough to load the waggon light&#8212;any thing you may want write me
to <placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>, you had better send a <hi rend="italic">list </hi>and such things as I have
not I can procure there&#8212;or if you think I can lay out the money to
any advantage let me know. If I receive no instructions from you
when I arrive at <placeName>N.</placeName> I shall take the money with me&#8212; <persName>Saml. Perry</persName>
has returned from <placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>with an extensive assortment of
goods, his business is so situated in this country at present that it
is impossible for him to leave it. So there is no hopes of his moving
to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">at present</hi>. <persName>Rob. Bruffe[y]</persName> is anxious to remove but his
affairs are so arranged that he cant leave this country either&#8212; and
<persName>Jas. Bruffe[y</persName>] is in the Same Situation.   So you need not calculate<pb n="891"/>
on them. I wrote to <persName>Ashley </persName>immidiately on my arrival in this 
country but have received no answer as yet&#8212; I am induced to believe
he intends to act <hi rend="italic">Shabbily </hi>in this Business I should have proceeded
to the <placeName>Lttle Rock</placeName> but <persName>Emily </persName>opposed it and wished nothing done
in the business untill you came up yourself. All the papers of
<persName>Father</persName>s I shall lock up [and] leave with <persName>Emily</persName>&#8212; <placeName>Durham Hall</placeName> can
be recovered&#8212;when our <hi rend="italic">purses </hi>are long enough to <hi rend="italic">Stand </hi>a 7 years law
Suit. <persName>Price </persName>the present owner is making his fortune&#8212;</p>

<p>Your <persName>friends </persName>are all well at the <placeName>Mines </placeName>and enquire particularly
after you&#8212; <persName>John S Bricky</persName> <persName>Stephenson</persName>, and <hi rend="italic"><persName>Cole </persName></hi>were elected to
the <persName>General Assembly</persName>&#8212;<persName>Fred&#8212;Bates Govr</persName> and <persName>Reeves Lt. Govr</persName> &#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Maj. Andrew Henry</persName> returned a few days ago from the <placeName>Stony
Mountains</placeName>&#8212;  he has suffered much and met with many misfortunes&#8212;</p>

<p>A Deputation from <placeName>Santa Fe</placeName> arrived a few weeks ago at the 
<placeName>council Bluffs</placeName>&#8212;the object of their visit was to acertain the most eligable
Situation for a road to be cut from <placeName>Santa Fe</placeName>&#8212;to that place&#8212;and
also to enter into some arrangement to Secure <persName>traders </persName>(to and from
the <placeName>Province of New Mexico</placeName>)&#8212;from attacks of the <persName>indians</persName>&#8212;and to
appoint <persName>agents </persName>for the purpose of facilitating an intercourse and
commerce to the <placeName>United States</placeName>&#8212; <persName>Beards Father</persName> attended the 
deputation as <persName>interpreter </persName>tell <persName>Beard </persName>his <persName>father </persName>is in good health&#8212; <persName>Elias
Bates</persName> and <persName>family </persName>are well he is doing an imense business at
present&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Emily </persName>is well desires her love to you her little <persName>girl </persName>is a smart
little creature</p>

<p>Give my respects to all my <persName>Friends </persName>in <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; I long to be with
you and them&#8212; <hi rend="italic">take good care of my Poney and my poor Cano</hi> [his
pointer dog]</p>

<p><persName>Jas E. B. Austin</persName></p>
<p>P. S.   <persName>Mr. Andrews</persName> and the <persName>Alleys</persName> arrived Safe&#8212; the <persName>Alleys </persName>will
hardly return before <date n="Spring-1825">Spring</date>&#8212;   I could say much more but I refer
you to <persName>Mr Hale</persName>&#8212;   Not one word <hi rend="italic">from <persName>Varner </persName>as yet</hi></p>

<p>(Note by <persName>Emily </persName>at bottom)</p>

<p>Time will not admit of my writing My Dear <persName>Stephen </persName>a lengthy
letter I shall incert a few lines in <persName>Brother Brown</persName>s, to assure you
that you are still remember'd with the greatest affection by your 
<persName>Sister </persName>altho I am fearfull you will accuse me of ingratitude, for not
going on with <persName>Brother </persName>and shareing with you and him the hardships
of settling a <placeName>New Country</placeName>; I have not giving up (nor never will)
the idea of moving to <placeName>Texas</placeName>: I flatter myself that when you visit
<placeName>Missouri </placeName>that you will prevail on <persName>Mr Perry</persName> to join you in <placeName>Texas</placeName>
I can assure you that I shall make use of every means to perswaid<pb n="892"/>
him to go on; by <persName>Brown </persName>I will write you a long letter; you must
<hi rend="italic">not forget</hi> my <persName>Children </persName>but <hi rend="italic">consider </hi>them as <hi rend="italic">yours</hi>, for as soon as
<persName>William </persName>and <persName>Austin </persName>are old enough to be of any service to you I
wish you to have them I will most cheerfully give them up to one
that I know will be their best friend and protector&#8212; Adieu and
think of me some <hi rend="italic">times </hi>and always as your affectionate Sister</p>

<p><persName>E. M. B</persName>&#8212;</p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Col Stephen F. Austin</persName> <placeName>San Felipe de Austin Rio
Brazos Texas</placeName>&#8212;<persName>E. M.</persName> pr <persName>Mr Hale</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
