<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0151">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to John G. Bond, 05-03-1809</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-30">06-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        John G. Bond
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">St Genevieve, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 155-156
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1809-05-03">05-03-1809</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning credits and shipments to New York and Boston. Banking conditions.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><persName>Mr John G Bond</persName></p>

<p>a few days past I rec'd. letters from my friend <persName>Seth Hunt</persName>. 
Stateing the substance of an arrangement he had made with you for the
shipment of Lead from this&#8212;Country to either <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>&#8212;<placeName>New
York</placeName> or <placeName>Boston </placeName>as the market shall from time to time answer. It
was my Expectation to have rec'd authority to draw on <placeName>N York</placeName>
however I trust I can so arrange the business that Drafts on <placeName>Boston</placeName>
will answer but with this deference that I must Suffer a Delay untill
information of the Acceptanc of the Drafts are Known in <placeName>lexington</placeName>
the disadvantages resulting from the Bills being drawn on <placeName>Boston</placeName>
I trust will only be felt in the commencement of this business&#8212; Its
a great object to have Cash on hand to make the purchase but as I
have it in my Power to make a Shipment from my own funds I
shall do so rather than sell our Draft at a Discount, the <placeName>Bank in
Lexington</placeName> will not take Drafts at 120 Days except at 2 1/2 of 3 p'c
this loss I shall prevent by forwarding my Drafts on to <persName>Mess. Hart
Barton and Hart <placeName>Lexington</placeName></persName> and by them to be forwarded to <persName>frends<pb n="156"/>
in <placeName>New York</placeName></persName> for Acceptance. When the Credit of my Drafts are
established I shall Never hereafter meet with difficulty&#8212;from my
friend <persName>Hunt</persName>s letters I had good reason to expect letters from you
respecting this business, giving directions to whom the Lead should
be ship.d whether to <placeName>New York</placeName> or <placeName>Boston</placeName></p>

<p>I shall make the first shipment to the Care of <persName>Mess Hart Barton
and Cox <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></persName>&#8212; Subject to be forward'd either to <placeName>New
York</placeName> or <placeName>Boston </placeName>as you shall order with information in time to have
Insurance made in either place as the case may be&#8212;but the risque
from this to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> can not be cover'd as an <placeName>office of 
Insuran[ce]</placeName> doth not Exist in this Country&#8212;</p>

<p>I trust you have a full understanding of this buseness in as much
as my friend <persName>Hunt </persName>States in his letters to me, that it is to be don on
the same conditions I stated to him in my letter from <placeName>Lexington</placeName>
<placeName>Shelbyvill </placeName>and <placeName>Lewisvill </placeName>that is the shipments are to be made on
joint account and risque both as it respects Profit and Loss&#8212;</p>

<p>Its my Wish that this transaction may be so managed that you
will finde it Your Interest to continue Shipments from this 
<placeName>country</placeName>. It will be my Interest to conduct the business in such a way
as to confirm not destroy the good opinion and confidenc my friend
<persName>Hunt </persName>has in me, with expectations of information from you on this
Subject and your directions to whom the Shipment will be made
either in <placeName>N York</placeName> or <placeName>Boston </placeName>I shall prepare and make a Shipment
to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></p>

<p>You will be so good as to Write <persName>Mess Hart Barton and Cox <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName></persName> ordering to whom the shipment from that place will be
made I shall always make my shipments to <persName>Mess Hart Barton and
Cox</persName> in the name and for the account of <persName>John G Bond <placeName>Boston</placeName></persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>John G Bond esq</persName> <placeName>Keen N Hampshire</placeName></p>
<p><placeName>Saint Genevve</placeName> <date when="1809-05-03">May 3 1809</date></p>

<p>[Moses Austin.]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
