<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0585">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to James E. B. Austin, 05-10-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Saltillo, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 638-639
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-05-10">05-10-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Settlers must keep out of politics. Prospect of federal republic. His colony safely approved.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Saltillo </placeName><date when="1823-05-10">May 10, 1823</date></p>
<p>Dr. <persName>Brother</persName>,</p>

<p>I arrived here on the <date when="1823-05-08">8th</date> and shall proceed <date when="1823-05-11">tomorrow </date>on to 
<placeName>Monterey </placeName>where I probably may be detained ten days untill the new
<persName>Comdte Genl</persName> arrives, <persName>Don Felipe de la Garza</persName>, who is a particular
<persName>friend </persName>of mine - At this place I heard that <placeName>Texas </placeName>had renewed the
oath to the <persName>Emperor </persName>and had refused to adopt the new system - this
is bad - the whole nation without exception have adopted the plan
of <placeName>Casa Mata</placeName> and acknowledged the <persName>Sovereign Congress</persName> - <persName>Iturbide</persName>
has embarked for <placeName>Italy</placeName>, and when I left <placeName>Mexico </placeName>on the <date when="1823-04-18">18</date> all was
quiet - <persName>Doctor Miguel Ramos Arispe</persName> now in this place informs
me that <placeName>Texas </placeName>only refused the new system because it was supposed
the majority of the nation still adhere to the <persName>Emperor</persName>, but that on
receiving a full confirmation of the unanimity of the <placeName>Provinces </placeName>in
favour of the plan of <placeName>Casa Mata</placeName>, it immediately adopted it also and
that at this time all is well&#8212;I wrote to the <persName>settlers on the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>
and <placeName>Brazos</placeName></persName> that they ought not to meddle with politics, and to have
nothing to do with any revolutionary schemes, I hope they have 
followed my advise&#8212;they are as yet too recently established in the
country to take an active part in its political affairs&#8212;if any 
questions are asked them as to their opinion of the Govt etc. they ought
to answer that they moved here to live under the government which
the <placeName>nation </placeName>may establish they can do themselves no good by 
meddling in politics and at such a time as this when the Govt is not yet
settled and the nation in a state of political fermentation it is
embarking on a doubtfull voyage to embrace any <persName>party</persName>&#8212;as 
<persName>foreigners </persName>we have a good excuse for remaining neutral without being lyable
to suspicions and this is the safe course&#8212;The <persName>Emperor </persName>has deceived
us all&#8212;I thought he would have adhered to his oath, and governd
according to law&#8212;but on the contrary he has violated the one, and<pb n="639"/>
trampled on the other&#8212;nothing therefore is more just, and more
magnanimous than the spirit of indignation and resentment which
the nation have manifested and the result I hope and confidently
believe will be a <placeName>Confederated Republic</placeName> very similar to that of the
<placeName>United States</placeName>&#8212;Some of the principal <placeName>provinces </placeName>of the nation have
declared in favour of this system, such as <placeName>Oaxaca</placeName>, <placeName>Guadalaxara</placeName>,
<placeName>Guatamala</placeName>, <placeName>Guanaxuato</placeName>, and these <placeName>Provinces </placeName>and I think a 
majority of the <persName>members of Congress</persName> are in favour of it.</p>

<p>I wrote you from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>that my business was completely finished
as I wished, and when I arrive I will try and revive the spirits of the
<persName>settlers</persName>, they have nothing to fear as to the titles to their lands, their
own industry and good conduct is all that is wanting to make them
live plentifully&#8212;I am in hopes we shall be able to take the <persName>Indians</persName>
in hand and teach them to let us alone&#8212;I recd your letters at this
place informing me of the disasters on the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>&#8212;the day of
vengeance I hope is not far off&#8212;I am very glad <persName>Littleberry Hawkins
</persName>took charge of the things from the Lively, I approve fully of 
everything he has done in the business if he still has the suit of blue
request him to keep it untill I arrive. I am destitute of clothes and
want it&#8212;remember me to him in a very particular manner and tell
him that I anticipate with pleasure a renewal of our former 
acquaintance in <placeName>Lexington</placeName>, and hope that we shall spend many happy years
as <persName>neighbours </persName>in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and receive an ample reward for the 
difficulties, hardships and disgusts of the first year or two&#8212;your Spanish
letter does very well. I am happy at your advancement in the 
language. It probably will be about the <date when="1823-06-10">10 of June</date> before I can reach
<placeName>Bexar </placeName>as I shall pass through <placeName>Monclova </placeName>if <persName>Dn Matias Ximenes</persName> is in
<placeName>Bexar </placeName>give my respects to him, I am anxious to see him&#8212;when I
arrive I will try and see what can be done with the tobacco, when I
purchased it in <placeName>Orleans </placeName>the law prohibiting the introduction had not
passed so that I am an innocent sufferer. Speak to <persName>Berrimendi </persName>and
request him not to do anything in the business until I arrive that is,
unless he will release the tobacco and deliver it to <persName>L. Hawkins</persName> if he
will do this it will be the same as delivering it to me&#8212;I am very glad
you did not go with <persName>Carrasco </persName>apply yourself to hard study, let your
whole time be devoted to emprove your mind, the only divertion,
except that necessary to preserve your health, which you ought to
take is a change of study from the Spanish to the French, and 
reading the <persName>Baron</persName>'s English books&#8212;<hi rend="italic">the mind makes the man</hi>. In 
writing Spanish be careful not to confound the b and the V as is 
customary in this country, when in doubt refer to the dictionary, this is
important tho totally disregarded here</p>

<p>[Stephen F. Austin.]</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
