<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0110">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Unknown to Unknown, xx-xx-1806</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-27">06-27-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 123-124
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Memorandum</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1806">xx-xx-1806</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-27" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Memorandum of agreement to sell land [1806?].</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p>Memorandum of an Agreement, this Day executed and agreed
upon Between <persName>Jaduther Kendle</persName> of the first part and <persName>Saml Hammond</persName>
and <persName>Moses Austin</persName> of the second part. Witnesseth. That whereas
the said <persName>Jaduther </persName>is now posses'd of a Concession of <placeName>Land granted to
<persName>Trams Widerman</persName></placeName> and by him settl'd and cultivat'd situated at the
<placeName>mouth of the Joachim</placeName> so Called containing four Hundred Acres
more or less, which said tract of Land the said <persName>Jaduther </persName>hath agreed
and do by these presents agree to dispose of to the said <persName>Saml 
Hammond</persName> and <persName>Moses Austin</persName> with all and singular the improvement
<placeName>ferrys </placeName>and <placeName>Landings </placeName>both on the <placeName>Mississippi </placeName>and <hi rend="italic">Joachim </hi>bound'd
agreeable to the Concession and Survey granted to the said <persName>Trams<pb n="124"/>
Widerman</persName> It is also understood and agreed that where as the said
Concession has not recd the approbation and confirmation of the
<persName>Board of commissioner</persName> agreeable to the Laws of the <placeName>U States</placeName> made
and provided for the adjusting of Land Claims in <placeName>Louisiana </placeName>It
shall be the Duty of the said <persName>Judather Kendle</persName> to obtain Decree of
said <hi rend="italic"><persName>Board </persName></hi>and when such determination <hi rend="italic">shall </hi>be had, and the said
concession of Land confirmed to the said <persName>Trams Widerman</persName> or his
assigns that he the said <persName>Kendle </persName>shall make or cause to be made to
them the said <persName>Saml Hammond and Moses Austin</persName> a good and 
sufficient <hi rend="italic">Warrant </hi>in fee simple for said <hi rend="italic">Land </hi>on Condition always that
the said <persName>Saml Hammond</persName> and <persName>Moses Austin</persName> shall pay or cause to be
paid and Deliverd to him the said <persName>Judather Kendle</persName> in nine months
two <persName>Negro Men</persName> in full Helth not to exceed Twenty five years of age
and Got under fifteen and to be good <persName><placeName>Plantation </placeName>negros</persName> and aquainted
with common <placeName>plantation </placeName>Labours and not new import'd <persName>negroes </persName>that
after the said <persName>Judather </persName>shall have made the Title within mention'd
It is also clearly understood that the said <persName>Kendle </persName>shall not be
bound to make good to the within nam'd <persName>Saml Hammond</persName> and <persName>Moses
Austin</persName> any Damages that may <hi rend="italic">Arise </hi>under this agreement should
the said Concession of Land be rejected by the <persName>board of 
Commissioners</persName> and under such circumstances the said <persName>Kendle </persName>shall not
Demand the consideration herein mention'd of Two <persName>negroes </persName>nor is
he to by any authority that he may hold by virtue of the Concession
of said <persName>Widerman </persName>on any other Claim he may have to said Land
attempt to molest or disturb the said <hi rend="italic"><persName>S H and M A</persName></hi> in the enjoyment
of said Land untill a final Determination can be had&#8212;at the same
time It is fully understood that whereas the said <persName>Kendle </persName>has made
Sale to <persName>Mr. John Conner</persName> of the same Tract of <hi rend="italic">Land </hi>which contract
altho nul and void by consent of <persName>parties </persName>yet as the objection given
by the said <persName>Conner </persName>is now in the hands of <persName>Jos Spinner</persName> that It shall
always be in the power of the said <persName>Kendle </persName>to make an arrangement
of said Contract in such a way as shall best answer his convenience
but with this restriction that the said Land shall always remain in
the • • •</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
