<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0451">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Bryan to Stephen F. Austin, 12-15-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Bryan</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-12">07-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Hazel Run, MO</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Colorado, TX</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 449-450
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-12-15">12-15-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Much interest aroused in Kentucky, Ohio, Illinois, and Missouri.    Commerce.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Hazel Run [Missouri] </placeName><date when="1821-12-15">Decr 15th 1821</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>I send this letter by <persName>Brother </persName><persName>J. E. B. [Austin]</persName> and hope he will have
a safe and expeditious journey he will have very good Company
<persName>Mr Henry [Elliott]</persName> and four very fine young men, two I have given
certificates, both <persName>mechanics </persName>and <persName>Bartholomew </persName>is an exception, we
recd your letters from <placeName>Orleans </placeName>with pleasure to find you in good health
and spirits and Prospects favourable I can assure you that a great
number will move from this State as also from other States and the
<placeName>Arkansas Territory</placeName>&#8212;I recd at <placeName>Hercm [Herculaneum]</placeName> a number of
letters addressed to you and have answered the most of them, from
<placeName>Kentucky </placeName><placeName>Ohio </placeName><placeName>Illenois </placeName>and <placeName>Missouri</placeName>, I will be particular as to
granting Certificates, and <persName>brother Brown </persName>will give you the News of
this State our <persName>Legislature </persName>is now in session tho have done very little
business, I shall be engaged making ready to move as soon as 
Possible should everything appear flattering and your letters give me
encouragement on the return of <persName>Mr Henry Elliott</persName> which he says
will be by the <date when="1822-05-01">first of May</date>, I will expect you and <persName>Brown </persName>to make my
selections and will flatter myself with the expectation of a judicious
and valuable selection and the more I get the more valuable, I am in
hopes <persName>Brown </persName>will be able to get me some Stock by the Barter and
Sale of some goods, and I trust <persName>Mr Henry Elliott</persName> will raise me some
Cash to have improvements commenced for me I shall be glad to
have a Crop raised the insueing season if Possible&#8212;I will try and send
on some Whisky and Flour and <persName>Elliott </persName>will send on some Goods, I left
the <placeName>Mines </placeName>a few days since and <persName>Majr Hawkins</persName> requested me to say to
you that he would be with you this <date n="Winter-1821">winter   </date>he expects to start in 15<pb n="450"/>
days and requests that you will select a spot for him, their will be
<persName>emigrants </persName>a plenty, and I truly hope and trust that nothing may
happen to mar the <placeName>Settlement </placeName>do not neglect to write by every 
oppertunity and give me all the important News relative to the Country
-Prospects etc&#8212;I will do all I can for its wellfare and with the hope
that we all will be rewarded I am like many others who want Land
near the <placeName>Town </placeName>and as much as I can get I am anxious to get a 
quantity of sheep while they can be had low and if <persName>Mr Elliott</persName> leaves
money for me I wish a part appropriated in that way I expect in a
few days to receive a letter from you wrote at <placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>&#8212;I shall
be anxious to hear from you and also <persName>Mother </persName>and your <persName>Sister</persName>. <persName>Mother</persName>
has been in very ill health for the last three Months if she lives [to]
reach the <placeName>Colorado </placeName>I have no doubt she will enjoy much better health
than she does here&#8212;I hope to God you may enjoy good health and
succeed in the Grand object&#8212;if <persName>Bartholomew </persName>and <persName>Powell </persName>are not
employed all the time in surveying you can get them to help in making
improvements and you will find them good hands&#8212;may God protect
us all and that we may yet live in his mercies&#8212;Adieu</p>
<p>Your <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p><persName>J. Bryan</persName></p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Stephen F. Austin Esqr</persName> <placeName>Colorado Texas</placeName> Attention
<persName>J. E. B. Austin</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
