<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0145">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to Seth Hunt, 07-25-1808</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-28">06-28-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Seth Hunt
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 150-151
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1808-07-25">07-25-1808</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-28" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Contract for purchase of goods in England for Austin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1808-07-25">July 25 [1808]</date></p>
<p>Dear Sr</p>

<p>Your favour under date <date when="1808-06-06">June 6</date> from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> came to hand
two days sence and I loose no time in Answering it I have examined
the contract in my hands for the Shipment of Merchandise from
<placeName>England </placeName>and find it thus expressed "the following premiums and
commissions as a compensation for his time trouble risque of losses
and personal Expences that may be hazard'd or incured in making
such purchases and guaranteeing the payment thereof, that is to say
he the said <persName>Austin </persName>will allow and pay to the said Hunt&#8212;Two and
half pr Cent Commission on all goods Wares etc that may be 
purchased and shiped by him on account of the said <persName>Austin </persName>with five
pr cent for his guaranteing the payment therefor and five pr. Cent.
more thereon in lieu of any interest or concern whatever in the
business in <placeName>america</placeName>"&#8212;</p>

<p>Notwithstanding the defects in the contract spoken of by you do
not exist in the one in my hands yet to remove all doubt I have
annexed an Article to this letter Which will I trust satisfy you and
such is the situation of our <placeName>Post Office</placeName>&#8212;Arrangement that I shall
send Duplicates in due time to meet you in <placeName>New York</placeName>&#8212;directed to
the care of your friend <persName>Gen Baily</persName>&#8212;I have nothing of moment to
relate at this time things stand as When you left us&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>M. Austin</persName></p>
<p>[Enclosure.]</p>

<p>Know $11 men by these presents that where as <persName>Seth Hunt Esqr</persName>
lately of the <placeName>district of Saint Genevieve</placeName> and <persName>Moses Austin</persName> of the
<placeName>Township of Breton</placeName> did enter into an agreement under date of
[undecipherable] day of <date n="02-xx-1808">Feby 1808</date> respecting shipment of goods
Wares and Merchandize from <placeName>Europe </placeName>to <placeName>Louisiana </placeName>for the account
and risque of the said <persName>Austin </persName>as therein stipulated and Where as
said Agreement is intended to secure to him the said <persName>Hunt </persName>
compensation&#8212;in all equal to Twelve and half pr cent on all Purchases
he shall make and ship to him the said <persName>Austin </persName>conformable to said
Agreement</p>

<p>Now should the agreement in the hands of the said <persName>Hunt</persName>, be so
expressed as not to secure to him Two and half per Cent on 
purchases mad and five pr cent for garentee of said purchase also five pr
cent more on said purchase in leu of any Interest in the business&#8212;in
<placeName>America </placeName>in all Twelve and half pr cent Be it known and 
remembered in such case that I do&#8212; agree and delair that I will allow to
him the, said <persName>Seth Hunt</persName> Twelve and half pr cent on all the purchais
and shipments he shall make under said agreement of the <date when="1808-02-17">17 day<pb n="151"/>
of Feby&#8212;1808</date>&#8212;and I do by these presents acknowledge this 
memorandum to be a part of the original agreement&#8212;</p>

<p>In witness to which I have hereunto sett my hand and Seal this
<date when="1808-07-25">twenty fift day of July 1808</date>&#8212;</p>

<p>[Endorsed:]   Copy Letter and agreement to <persName>Seth Hunt</persName> <date when="1808-07-25">July 25.
1808</date> <placeName>N. York</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
