<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0188">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John Bowman to Stephen F. Austin, 04-28-1811</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John Bowman</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-30">06-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mercer County, KY</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Burton Mine, St Genevieve, LA</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 188-190
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter </channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1811-04-28">04-28-1811</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">College mate's letter.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Mercer County Kentucky</placeName> <date when="1811-04-28">April 28th 1811</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Stepen</persName>,</p>

<p>It has been a considerable time since we parted and I have not had
the pleasure of hearing one single word from you since <date n="01-xx-1811">January</date>
although this is the third time I have written, you have not thought
it worth while to answer me, and I had concluded not to have
troubled you again with a letter but meeting with this opportunity,
th° at a late hour of the night; the very high regard I always had for
you from our first acquaintance and the very friendly maner in
which I was treated by you and the <persName>family </persName>while in <placeName>Louisianna </placeName>almost
destitute of <persName>friends </persName>or <persName>acquaintances </persName>impell me once more to address
you&#8212;but should I not receive an answer to this in a convenient time<pb n="189"/>
after it may have come to hand, I shall take it for granted that my
letters have not met with a favourable reception, and that I have only
been intruding on your patience; if this should be the case which I
should be extremely sorry to hear, I must beg the favour of 
forgiveness for the past, and will not intrude for the future&#8212;</p>

<p>When I left <placeName>Louisianna </placeName>I had fully determined upon returning in
a short time to that <placeName>country </placeName>and permanently fixing myself there, but
after arriving at home after a tedious and disagreeable journey of
Six weeks from the time of our parting; and enjoying the company of
my <persName>friends </persName>and <persName>relatives</persName>, who to me are most dear and affectionate;
through their Solicitations, and the violent objections of a most 
passionate and fond <persName>mother</persName>, I could not but at the expence of her
hapiness persist in the Idea; of course I d[e]clined the notion and
have now settled on a farm in <placeName>Mercer County</placeName> <placeName>near Danville</placeName>, where
I have turned my attention entirely to farming; a life which to me has
always appeared most agreeable, and that which is best calculated to
render a person most happy particularly if comfortably situated,
with an agree[able]&#8212;companion&#8212;in this last respect I am 
unfortunate for instead of having any person on whom I might gaze with
pleasure, when retired from the fateigues of the day; and the Silent
shades of the night come on; I have to pass My hours in lonely 
meditation, enveying the hapy lot of those in the connubial State, who have
inlisted under Cupids banner and are engaged in the wars of Venus&#8212;
how long I shall thus continue almost in sight of battle without the
liberty of entering into the contest I am at a loss to know but my
Services are volenteered and I am only waiting for Some one to say
she is willing to engage in the conflict and enter into a scene of 
pleasures too delicate for my pen to describe&#8212;</p>

<p>I am sorry that I cannot give you some account of your <persName>Amaretto</persName>
near <placeName>Lexington</placeName>, but my having been absent from that place about
three months and confined closely to business prevent my having
that information which perhaps to you would be most desirable,
however I beleive she is not yet maried and have no doubt but she
anticipates with pleasure the happy hour when you are to meet
again&#8212;This however may not continue to be the case long for I can
hear of Mariages being celebrated almost every day&#8212;</p>

<p>I am told that your <persName>Sister </persName>has been maried since I left that 
<placeName>Coutry </placeName>to <persName>Mr B&#8212;n [James Bryan]</persName> if so I think she has made a very
Judicious choice for there is no man in my opnion more worthy,
and for whom I have a greater regard</p>

<p>I cannot with justice to my own feeling close this letter, (although
I fear I have spun it out to lengthy on subjects not perhaps to you
emportant without expressing the obligations I am under to the
young <persName>Gentlemen </persName>about the <placeName>mines </placeName>for the friendship manifested to<pb n="190"/>
me during my stay at that place, particularly to <persName>Mr Bowling</persName>; to
whom, with the rest of my acquaintances you will do me the favour
of presenting my best compliments and warmest respects&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>John Bowman </persName>   [Rubric]</p>
<p>N B If you shoud favour me with a letter please to direct to 
<placeName>Danville, Mercer County</placeName></p>

<p><persName>J.B.</persName></p>
<p>[Address:] <persName>Mr Stephen F. Austin</persName><placeName> Mine A. Burton District St
Geneveeve U. Louisianna</placeName> favd by <persName>Mrs Rector</persName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
