<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0398">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Joseph H. Hawkins, 07-20-1821</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-10">07-10-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Joseph H. Hawkins
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nacogdoches</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 402-404
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1821-07-20">07-20-1821</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reporting progress. Outlining plans for exploring grant and announcing conditions of settlement.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Republic of Texas</placeName>,</p>
<p><placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName><date when="1821-07-20">July 20, 1821.</date></p>

<p>Dear Sir&#8212;I wrote you fully from <placeName>Nachitoches</placeName>, relative to the
confirmation of my <placeName>father's grant</placeName> by the <placeName>governor general</placeName>, and
<persName>council of the four internal province</persName>, enclosing you copies of the
documents delivered me by <persName>Don Erasmo, the agent on the part of
the Spanish government</persName>, and who is authorized to conduct myself
and <persName>settlers </persName>to the <placeName>lands granted</placeName>.</p>

<p>We are thus far on our way to explore the country, and select the
most judicious sites for our <placeName>settlement</placeName>.</p>

<p>We found several <persName>families </persName>at this place, who held a council upon
our arrival, and resolved to remove within the limits of the lands
granted my father; the inducements to their removal being the
advantages of a situation nigher to the sea, and consequently to the
<placeName>seat of trade</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have not the boundaries of the grant before me, but understand
it will include the <placeName>harbor of Mata Gorda</placeName>, and the <placeName>mouth of the
Colorado river</placeName>.</p>

<p>I met here a gentleman who travelled through the grant, and who
assures me it is the richest and best watered part of the province.
All <persName>travellers </persName>unite with our much lamented <persName>Gen. Pike</persName>, in alleging
the climate to be one of the most delightful in this, or any other
country.</p>

<p>I had both verbal and written correspondence with a number of
gentlemen who proposed to migrate to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and become <placeName>settlers</placeName><pb n="403"/>
within the <placeName>grant</placeName>.   As I have not leisure to write them all, be pleased
to make known through the public prints:</p>

<p>1st. That I shall comply with the condition of the <placeName>grant</placeName>, and
effect the settlement to the full extent, and in the same manner
contemplated by my late <persName>father</persName>.</p>

<p>2d. That I shall explore the country, and then select the most
judicious points for our <placeName>settlement</placeName>.</p>

<p>3d. That a port has been established by the proper authority, in
the <placeName>Bay of St. Bernard</placeName>, which will at once secure great facilities
to commerce.</p>

<p>4th. That I am authorized to introduce and settle on the <placeName>grant</placeName>,
<persName>three hundred families</persName>; and they are permitted to carry with them
all the property, effects and supplies they think proper.</p>

<p>5th. That every facility will be given calculated to aid the <persName>settlers</persName>,
and they will be secured in grants of land proportionate to the
numbers of each <persName>family</persName>, and the force or means they possess of 
carrying on useful and agricultural pursuits.</p>

<p>Liberal grants of land will also be made to mechanics of all 
descriptions who will become <persName>settlers</persName>; but no settler will be received,
or grant made to any individual, who does not produce satisfactory
evidence of good character and industrious habits; and the <persName>settlers</persName>
will supply themselves with certificates to this effect from some court,
<persName>magistrate</persName>, <persName>mayor</persName>, <persName>justice</persName>, <persName>notary</persName>, or other <persName>public officer</persName>.</p>

<p>The objects of this settlement are entirely agricultural. The 
richness of the soil, healthfulness of the climate, contiguity to the sea,
and other natural advantages, promising a reward to our labors,
which few spots on the globe could furnish to an equal extent.</p>

<p>I shall return to <placeName>Natchitoches </placeName>in <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>, by the <date when="1821-09-25">25th Sept</date>. and
after a visit to <placeName>Herculaneum</placeName>, in the state of <placeName>Missouri</placeName>, shall proceed
with the <persName>settlers </persName>to the points of location.</p>

<p>All persons desiring information, will address me at " 
<placeName>Herculaneum, Missouri</placeName>," and their letters shall be answered immediately
on my reaching that place.&#8212;As the communications will be numerous,
it is expected that the <persName>applicants </persName>for information will pay the 
postage on their letters.</p>

<p>I will publish on my return, the point at which the <persName>settlers </persName>had
best convene, and in the mean time, those who may come on should
not descend the <placeName>Mississippi river</placeName> below the<placeName> mouth of Red river</placeName>, nor
go farther into the <placeName>interior </placeName>than <placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>.</p>

<p>Persons wishing to become <persName>settlers </persName>will forward me to 
<placeName>Herculaneum</placeName>, their names, occupation, number and description of their
<placeName>families </placeName>and the number of <persName>work hands</persName> they would employ.</p>

<p><persName>Mechanics </persName>will be particular in describing their trades, and the
number of persons, including <persName>apprentices</persName>, attached to their <persName>families</persName>.<pb n="404"/></p>

<p>A <placeName>port </placeName>having been legally established in the <placeName>Bay of St. Bernard</placeName>,
the <placeName>settlement </placeName>will at once be secured in a direct communication
with <placeName>New-Orleans</placeName> and other places, from which supplies can be
obtained.</p>

<p>You have already been informed that the Spanish constitution is
in full force in the <placeName>internal provinces</placeName>. And <persName>Don Erasmo, the 
commissioner appointed to conduct us to the lands</persName>, brought to <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>
proclamations, promising security and protection to all persons who
have left the country during former troubles, and who would not
return.</p>

<p>I understand a number have already embraced the offer.</p>

<p>Such parts of my letters as you cause to be published calculated
to give information to the <persName>settlers</persName>, I hope the <placeName>newspapers </placeName>in 
<placeName>Mississippi</placeName>, <placeName>Tennessee</placeName>, <placeName>Kentucky </placeName>and <placeName>Missouri </placeName>will republish.</p>
<p>Very respectfully,</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>,</p>

<p>P. S. All persons who were <persName>citizens of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName></persName> at any time
prior to its cession to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, will find great facilities in
obtaining grants for land in this <placeName>province</placeName>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
