<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0051">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen Austin to Unknown, 01-10-1801</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-23">06-23-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 63-64
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Statement</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1801-01-10">01-10-1801</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning the business of Stephen and Moses Austin in Virginia.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Account in the Settlement at 3666 D 66 C with the expressed 
conditions if <persName>M A</persName> did not repay that sum in twelve months then I was
at Liberty to sell them for cash for what they would bring which if
had been done would have sacrafisd full half the sum the lands was
charged me at I am therefore willing to allow the price the 
Gentlemen aprised them at I therefore request <persName>Mr. James and Charles
Austin</persName> to Credit <persName>M Austin</persName>'s private acct with the Value of the 
remaing Lands as apprised but first deducting the overcharge on 
<placeName><persName>Bengham</persName>s bottom</placeName> and <placeName><persName>Newfield </persName>place</placeName> I have requested <persName>Jas and Charles
Austn</persName> to state the Acct of all the particulars taken by <persName>M A</persName> as well
Cash as what was taken by <persName>Kendal </persName>on his first trip west and other
things and if there is any over or short charge to add or deduct such
sum from this Acct which when all this is done will no doubt Leave
due me about the sum of 12000 Dollars a sum every Dollar of which
I have actually paid out of my private Pocket and it is a sum justly
due me from <persName>M A</persName> for the statement I have made is in Equity and
Good Conscience and as God is my Judge I have made it as if under
the most Solem Oath to do justice between <persName>M A </persName>and myself and 
although he may think it hard to be charged with the Loss on the
<persName>Estate </persName>of <persName>Merril </persName>and <persName>Austin </persName>still it is much harder that I had all the
trouble of doing all the business after <persName>Mr. Merril</persName>s Death which took
me sum years to close nor on the Money advanced for the <persName>Estate </persName>am
I allowd one Dollar Expence nor Interest on the Money besides all
which I was arested in <placeName>England </placeName>for their debt only and thrown into
<placeName>prison </placeName>and at last holden on bale 2 years and 4 months besides all the
costs of the suit at least one hundred guinas&#8212;<persName>M A</persName> may also think
hard to pay part of my Expence during this time but it is just he
should be charged with the half though I have charged but one third
because he advised and Consented to my going to <placeName>England </placeName>to make
sale of the <placeName>Lead Mines </placeName>and which I actually did sufficiently Effect to
the Amt of £8400 sterling if he had effected the incorporation of the
<persName>Company </persName>besides this Acct there is still and ought to do me Justice be
settled and for which I now hold his obligation at the expiration of
the partnership in 1800 to be adjusted the following Acct (Viz)<persName> M A
and C°</persName> Acct due <persName>S A</persName> 12647 Dollars 65 Cents due him more than 10
years the Interest of which for this time was to be left to arbitration
to three men Chosen by us both the Opinion of any two to be binding
on in besides this Acct there is <persName>M A</persName>s private Acct while at <placeName>Richmond</placeName>
his family Expences for Seven years to defray which by an 
agreement in the partnership he was to be Allowd 5 pet on all actual
Sales to support his <persName>family </persName>but the money and Goods charged his
Acct by himself in his own books Amts to double the commission<pb n="64"/>
and leaves him in debt to the <persName>Company </persName>as appears by his books now
in my Possetion more than 2000 Dolls which belongs to his private
Acct and to be charged as such besides this his private Acct in the
books at the <placeName>L Mines</placeName> more than 2000 Dollars also to be Acct for
to me besides this there is small Accts in the book to be charged
him Acct of Cash pd his <persName>Brother </persName>and <persName>Sisters in law</persName> but which now
stands charged to them (Viz) <persName>Joseph Rebecca and Peggy Brown</persName>
in a just settlement of all these things still a Large sum would
be due me for against them there is no charge <persName>M A </persName>can possibly
bring Except sum Small private Acct in the <placeName>L Mine</placeName> Books as in the
<placeName>Richmond </placeName>Books Everything was charged <persName>S A and C0</persName>, and in those
Accts was settled who ever will take the trouble to Look at these Accts
with these observations will be able to Judge with what Justice or
propriety <persName>M A</persName> should object to the whole of the property at the <placeName>L
Mines</placeName> being applyd to the discharge of so Large a debt due me and
which although I have credited at the Apprisment can by no means
be turned into Money these Objections it must by All who are made
acquainted with the Circumstances be Considered as improper and
unjust when it is to be considered that every shilling that can now be
Scraped up from the wreck of the affairs which <persName>M A</persName> left behind will
not pay me ten shilling on the pound of the just balance due me from
him I have made this remark not only for the perusal of <persName>M A</persName> and
<persName>J A </persName>but as far as it may be Necessary to be made publick in case <persName>M A</persName>
or <persName>J A</persName> or any other person for him should persist in objecting to the
Sale of <persName>Negroes </persName>and all other of the properties formerly belonging
to the Company of <persName>M A and Co</persName> but now the property of <persName>Charles
Austin</persName> by Legal Sale made to him by me whose Sole legal Right to
the property no power can anul or dispute as to <persName>M A</persName> holding the bill
of Sales of the <persName>Negroes </persName>which was purchaced of <persName>Mr. Epps of 
<placeName>Petersburgh</placeName></persName> I need only observe that I now hold the Bond given <persName>Mr. Epps</persName>
for the <persName>Negroes </persName>every dollar of which I paid my self and have 
always been in possfession of all of them untill I sold them for which
<persName>M A</persName> has full Credit for his proportion of them in the Acct of <persName>M A
and C°</persName> within stated as Pr Apprisement.</p>

<p><persName>S Austin</persName></p>
<p>A copy of the Original</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
