<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0481">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John J. Clarke to Stephen F. Austin, 02-25-1822</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John J. Clarke</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-14">07-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Pinckneyville, MS</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 480
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1822-02-25">02-25-1822</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Many wish to go from Mississippi to your colony. Asks for information about conditions and terms.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Pinckneyville Misse</placeName> <date when="1822-02-25">25th Feby 1822</date>.</p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I avail myself of a favorable opportunity to address you a few
lines of enquiry respecting the tract of Country you have made
choice of in the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>I presume that no apology for my thus troubling you, may be
necessary, as I beg to refer you to a limited acquantance some short
time since at <placeName>Mount Prairie in the Arkansas Territory</placeName>, the renewal
of which I trust may prove duly reciprocal.</p>

<p>I have some idea of becoming an inhabitant of your <placeName>settlement </placeName>by
the ensuing fall, and would calculate on taking with me a few
articles of Merchandise that might answer the <persName>inhabitants </persName>of that
vicinity. Your advice as to what would be the most proper and the
best method of transportation will be highly acceptable.</p>

<p>In case of shipment from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, to what point ought I to
make a landing nearest your <placeName>neighborhood</placeName>? etc. There are many
in this <placeName>Country </placeName>who wish to remove to your <persName>Settlement</persName>, but are 
detered from not having any correct information respecting its local
situation, the prospects that are held out to emigrants, and the dread
of having a savage foe, committing depredations on their property
either before or after their arrival.</p>

<p>If you will give me every information in your power on these
or any other subjects touching your Country, it may perhaps prove
beneficial to your interest in encouraging the migration of those,
who are prevented from these causes. Have the goodness to address
me at this place as soon as practable. Be pleased to note what 
number of <persName>families </persName>have already arrived, and what are your prospects
of laying off a Town on the <placeName>sea bord</placeName>. This latter has been much
the subject of confab among the <persName>Mercantilest </persName>and I believe 
generally wished to take place.</p>

<p>I shall at any time feel gratified in acknowledging the favor of
your attention to this letter, and hope I may soon have the pleasure
of seeing you at your immediate residence.</p>

<p><persName>Jn° J Clarke </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F Austin Esqr</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
