<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0229">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin to James Bryan, 01-04-1813</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-30">06-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James Bryan
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Durham Hall, MO.</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 222-224
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1813-01-04">01-04-1813</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Effects of war of 1812 in Missouri. Indians. Project for trade with Mexico.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Durham Hall</placeName> <date when="1813-01-04">Jany 4th 1813</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr. James Bryan</persName>,</p>

<p>Dear Sr I reeved you[r] last favour under-date of <date when="1812-10-06">Octbr 6th
</date><date when="1812-01-02">day before Yesterday</date> only. My last letters from my son <persName>Stephen</persName>
from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> was under date of <date when="1812-11-02">2 Novr</date>&#8212;he then contemplated
to leave that <placeName>City </placeName>in a day or two and as I have nothing from him
since I hope he has closed his business and left the Country, sence
I wrote you last, little business has been don in the mineing or
Smelting of Lead in consequence of the extreme badness of the
weather <placeName>Shebboleth </placeName>is nearly abandoned, and such as remain are
doing nothing. I have been raising mineral to Some advantage my
<placeName>Shaft </placeName>is dry and produces as Well as I have don in times past, last
month gave me 20 Thousand, I hope to raise as much this month,
Collections are bad and I see little prospect of the <persName>Miners </persName>beeing
in a Situation of makeing payment this Year, if they had a 
disposition which is generally wanting.</p>

<p>I do not think your <persName>brother </persName>or <persName>Mr Bates</persName> has collected 200 Dollars
the last six months <persName>Thompson </persName>has not yet paid, in short no man
pays a dollar, lead Never was so difficult to collect, and I am
clearly of the Opinion that Ten thousand Dollars would,&#8212;
Command Every Pound of Lead for sale this <date n="Spring-1813">spring </date>and <date n="WInter-1813">Winter </date>Would
to god I could command that Sum a Speculation of moment could
be made but I have not the means, I think I shall make up 60
thousand by <date n="04-xx-1813">April</date>. If my prospects continue and <persName>Indians </persName>do not
disturb us</p>

<p>I could not advise many goods being brought to the <placeName>Country</placeName>.
Not but they would sell readely&#8212;but the pay is the question&#8212;the
situation of the People is such that they cannot pay.   You would<pb n="223"/>
be astonished to see the change in all Orders of <persName>Citizens </persName>in the
Article of dress <persName>Indian </persName>dressed Buckskin for Overhalls and frocks
are now as universal as broadcloth used to be, notwithstanding
goods of a proper kind will sell Such as I have heretofore stated
to you but I am clearly of Opinion that 5 thousand Dollars in
Cash would produce double the neet produce in a Year than
10 Thousand Dollars in goods, because No man would calculate
on asking Credit on Money, but goods at the prices they must sell
at, purchased at War Marketts cannot be sold in this Country for
ready, pay, to, much advantage, Lead is now 375 in <placeName>St Genevieve</placeName>
part goods and 400 in <placeName>Herculaneum</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">Cash</hi>, a Cargo purchased at
even 450 and sent up the Ohio would do better than goods as I
cannot suppose the expence of transportation to <placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>over
6 Dollars pr Hundred which would Make the cost 950 in 
<placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>and If <hi rend="italic">14 or 15</hi> can be obtained the Neet proceeds would
out do any advance on goods, and all in hand, nothing on Credit.
As to <persName>Indians </persName>I have a hope we shall not be troubled with them I
think the <placeName>mine a Burton</placeName> a safe place much more so than any other
place in the <placeName>Territory </placeName>because no body of hostile <persName>Indians </persName>are in
our <placeName>quarter </placeName>and cannot get to us untill they pass the <placeName>Settlements
of Saint Charles</placeName>&#8212;Yet I am inclined to Suppose that the <persName>Militia</persName>
will be called on in the <date n="Spring-1813">spring </date>unless the <persName><hi rend="italic">U S</hi> government</persName> sends us
<persName>troops</persName>.</p>

<p>I have seen an account of a machine said to be const[r]ucted by a
man by the name of <persName>Readhefer </persName>about <placeName>10 miles from Philadelphia</placeName>
Which gives, <hi rend="italic">perpetual, motion,</hi> I have a desire to know more of
this machine and If you could find time to Visit the [place] and 
examine the machine you your self and if to [be obtained?] git a 
Drawing of the machine I wish you to, <hi rend="italic">do </hi>so. the advantages to be derived
from the use of such an invention in the <placeName>Western Country</placeName> passeth all
the Ideas and imagination of man, I am only doubtful it is <hi rend="italic">not true.</hi> I
wrote you some time since respecting a <placeName>Mine of Antimony</placeName> which had
been discovered near the <placeName>River Illinois</placeName> <persName>Mr Elias Bates</persName> has information
how to find the <placeName>Mine</placeName>. If a lead can be obtained; he also say[s] he
has not any Doubts as to the goodness and quantity&#8212;this is also an
object of great magnitude and worthy of attention, on both of these
subjects I wish you to be attentive&#8212;If you can find time</p>

<p>I also wrote you my opinion on the opening towards <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, I
have had Nothing to change a belief that an adventure to that 
<placeName>Country </placeName>would be both safe and advantageous As to a general assortment
of <persName>English </persName>goods in this <placeName>Country </placeName>I do not think payment could be
obtained so as to make the thing profitable except in the Articles I
have mentioned. I am fully of the Opinion that many goods may be
Sold but a life of labour could not collect the payment.<pb n="224"/></p>

<p>I have so long contemplated the Arrival of my son <persName>Stephen </persName>to 
attend my <persName>family </persName>to this <placeName>Country</placeName>, that I am truly distressed at this 
delay, and must depend on you to make with <persName>Mrs Austin</persName> the 
arrangements Should my Dear <persName>Son </persName>Not arrive in time Which god grant
May Not be the case all I can say is that .... [mutilated]
Could leave <placeName>Orleans </placeName>.... which I have recvd Nothing . . .
I cannot Express my mortification at his Misfortunes and detention,
but, <hi rend="italic">gods</hi>, will be don little did I expect to be thus long deprived of
the Company of my Dear <persName>family</persName></p>

<p>I am D Sr With esteem Yours</p>

<p><persName>Moses Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>
<p>N B the appointment of the <persName>Counsel for this <placeName>Territory </placeName></persName>Was 
nomi-nated by the <persName>Assembly </persName>and the following Gentlemen were named&#8212;</p>

<p><placeName>St Louis</placeName>
<persName>Aug Choutau</persName>
<persName>Saml Hammond</persName></p>

<p><placeName>St Genevieve</placeName>
<persName>Colo Cook</persName>
<persName>M Austin</persName>
<persName>John Scott Lawyer</persName>
<persName>James Maxwell</persName>
<persName>John Smyth</persName>
<persName>John McArthur</persName>
The other members I can not Name</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
