<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB0614">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Josiah H. Bell, 08-06-1823</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-15">07-15-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Josiah H. Bell
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 1, pp. 681-683
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1823-08-06">08-06-1823</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">His expenses in surveying land and issuing titles. Colonists must repay. Wants a secretary, blank books or writing paper, ink powder. Waco Indians.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName><persName>Castleman</persName>s on the Colorado</placeName></p>

<p><date when="1823-08-06">Augt. 6 1823</date>.</p>
<p>Dr <persName>Friend</persName></p>

<p>Enclosed I send you sundry papers to be communicated to the
<persName>Settlers</persName>&#8212; I rely greatly on your prudence and judgment in 
preserving harmony and content amongst the <persName>settlers </persName>it now depends
altogether on my will to admit or reject who I please, and if there
are any who are not worthy I must be informed of it that they may
be ordered off, and if the order is not obeyed it will be enforced with
rig[or] I think the enclosed letter ought to satisfy them all as 
regards the payments&#8212; I give up the right of axacting all the pay
in hand and will receive any kind of property, that I shall not loose
on&#8212; Surely there ought to be no difficulty on this subject&#8212; can
any man doubt that in less than three or even two years he cannot
sell a part of his land far cash at 50 cents or one dollar pr. acre?
There are but few men in the world who would undergo what I have,
and exact so little in proportion to the benefit conferred&#8212; I shall
make the fortunes of all my <persName>followers </persName>for which I ask them to pay
me but a very little more than the money this business will actually
cost me the Govt. do not pay one cent of any kind of expense, I
pay it all, besides this I have risked my life, my health, my property,
<hi rend="italic">my all</hi> in this enterprise&#8212; If there is any discontent as to the 
payments I think I shall have a right to complain after what I have
done&#8212; And those who complain without reason may have cause to
regret it&#8212; I shall treat the <persName>settlers </persName>as my <persName>children </persName>and <persName>Brothers</persName><pb n="682"/>
but at the same time I shall exercise that firmness and energy which
my duty to the <persName>Government </persName>of my adoption, to the common good of
the <placeName>Colony</placeName>, and to my own <persName>family </persName>require.</p>

<p>I am told there is a man near you by the name of <persName>Eccleston</persName>, a
<persName>schoolmaster</persName>, who is a good <persName>clerk </persName>and understands Spanish and
French&#8212; if so and he is a man of confidence I wish to employ him
to make out and record titles and do such other writing as may
be necessary&#8212; inform yourself on this subject by the time I arrive,
also if there are any good <persName>surveyors </persName>amongst you, let them come
and see me at your <placeName>house </placeName>on my arrival&#8212; Also if any of the
<persName>settlers </persName>have <hi rend="italic">blank books</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">writing paper</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ink powder</hi>, I wish
to get some of all those articles&#8212; A party of <persName>Indians </persName>supposed to
be <persName>Wacos </persName>are now in this <placeName>neighborhood </placeName>and their conduct is rather
suspicious. I wish <persName>Capt Robinson</persName> and you to collect all the 
information in your power relative to that nation, and if any person
is going to their <placeName>village </placeName>charge them to try and sound the <persName>chiefs </persName>as
to their disposition towards us&#8212; I hope the <persName>nation </persName>are not hostile,
this party is a war party I expect, who were defeated a few days
since by the <persName>Toncaways </persName>[on the] <placeName>San Marcos</placeName> We must be 
vigilent&#8212; I [wish] if possible to avoid an open rupture with them
for six months longer at least, by that time we shall have more
strength, but if they commit any more depradations the only 
alternative will be an expedition to distroy their village, but this I
wish to avoid until next year if possible&#8212; If they appear amongst
you and you can see them treat them friendly but tell them firmly
the consequences of a war&#8212; I wish for peace, but am ready for
war if it cannot be avoided. On this subject use all the prudence
possible, my object is to keep them quiet for 6 or 8 months more.</p>

<p>I regret to hear that there is some sickness on the <placeName>Brazos </placeName>and
that your <persName>family </persName>have suffered. We must not be discouraged at
this, all new countries are sickly at first&#8212; <hi rend="italic">we must let nothing
discourage us</hi>.</p>

<p>I have an order from <persName>Hawkins' agent</persName> to receive any property
notes, etc which may be on this <placeName>river </placeName>or the <placeName>Brazos</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I leave here on the <date when="1823-08-11">11th.</date> for the <placeName>mouth of the river </placeName>expect to [be
there] 12 days and shall then go direct to the [Brazos?]</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>N. B. Decide before my arrival on the way you wish your land
run, you may take it all in one tract the smallest quantity allowed
is 1000 yards square which may be increased without limit by 
myself and the <persName>commissioner</persName>. I presume you will want at least one
League Square agree on the division lines between your <persName>neighbors</persName>
I hope none of them will have difficulty on this subject I wish
them to agree on their division lines themselves.    I want a first<pb n="683"/>
rate horse suitable for an <persName>Indian </persName>expedition or a first rate riding
mule. Am told <persName>Abner Keykendall</persName> has such a horse See if he will
suit and his price to go towards his land&#8212; let me know when I
arrive all the objections made by the <persName>settlers </persName>and what fault they
find or what they want.</p>
<p><persName>J. H. Bell</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
