<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1946">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Archibald Austin to Stephen F Austin, 05-31-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Archibald Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-21">08-21-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 401-403
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-05-31">05-31-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Discussing Swiss emigration to Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New York</placeName> <date when="1830-05-31">31 May 1830</date>,</p>
<p>My Dear Sir,</p>

<p>Your very interesting letter of <date when="1830-02-25">24 feby,</date> elucidating with so
friendly a spirit, so much relative to your <placeName>Colony</placeName>, that I was 
desirous to hear about, came safe to hand, and I assure you, I value it
much, as harassed as you must be with a multiplicity of avocations,
causes me to feel sensibly your kindness in gratifying my intrusive
questions, I however hope to reciprocate the same, in some measure
by promoting your views in regard to <persName>Swiss emigrants</persName>, that I shall
prevail on any to join you is yet doubtful, but I have had 
conversations with Several <persName>Swiss Gentlemen</persName> on the subject, and I shall be
on the look out to find some of them that will take more interest, or
rather a more active interest, than those I have yet met with, <persName>Mr.
Richard</persName> a <persName>Swiss Gentleman</persName> who has resided many years in this<pb n="402"/>
<placeName>Country </placeName>approved very much of the project, told me he had often
thought of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, as being a <placeName>country </placeName>well calculated for his 
<persName>Countrymen</persName>, and thought it would be fortunate for them if they would
Emigrate to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, instead of coming here, that many of them, were
disappointed on their arrival here and were at times so much at a
loss to know which way to go on there arrival here, that he had
purchased a <placeName>Tract of Land in this State</placeName>, from no other cause, than
to find them a Speedy location, that his land was not however, or
rather the climate calculated for them, for it is in the <placeName>northern part
of this State</placeName> and too cold for them but they were in the habit of
going to <placeName>Ohio</placeName>, and<placeName> other Western States</placeName>, which was attended with
too much expence for many of them I told him, as I think would be
the best plan (if such a person could be found that would feel
Sufficient interest, to take the trouble to communicate the 
information to his<persName> Country men</persName>) to send your <placeName>pamphlet</placeName>, and such other
information as I could give to some <persName>Swiss Genl [gentlemen]</persName> going
to <placeName>Switserland</placeName>, and for him to recommend them taking passage to
<placeName>New Orleans</placeName> so as to arive there in a healthy season, and proceed
from thence to your <placeName>Colony</placeName>, he was of my opinion but did not know
of any one going at present, and he was not acquainted with any one
that would be of use to send it to, out of the <placeName>Canton </placeName>he came from
(<placeName>Geneva</placeName>) where they were all, or principally mechanics,&#8212; at
present there do not appear to be many or any <persName>Swiss Emigrants</persName> in
the <placeName>City </placeName>about a month since another<persName> Swiss Genl [gentleman]</persName> told
me there would probaly be a good many here&#8212;</p>

<p>I called on<persName> Mr. Theoder Meyer a German</persName> many years a <persName>merchant</persName>
here, and <persName>consol for <placeName>Hanover</placeName>,</persName> who I have been long acquainted with,
he thought it would be difficult to prevail on his <persName>country men</persName> to go
there, under the impression that the climate would be to warm for
them, that they were generally pretty well of, and if three or four
of the most respectable <persName>familys </persName>that were disposed to Emigrate
could be prevailed on to go direct <placeName>from their Country to Texas</placeName>,
and should be pleased, you would have no difficulty in prevailing
on as many to follow, as you could wish, he thought it would be
best for you to send over some person to <placeName>Germany</placeName>, and prevail on
three or four <persName>Familys </persName>to come over, and pay the expences, but
this I presume would not be convenient for you at present&#8212;as I
said before I shall be on the alert&#8212;-in hopes that the information
you gave interesting to <persName>Swiss Emigrants</persName>, Might reach the Eyes
of some of them, that were on the look out for a favorable place to
locate, I thought best, and ventured to put an extract from your
letter in the <placeName>Journal of Commerce</placeName>, I found <persName>Mr. Meyer</persName> has seen it,
and was pleased with it, it paid his <persName>Countrymen </persName>a Compliment,
which had a good effect&#8212;   you will on the receipt of this have<pb n="403"/>
observed it, in that <placeName>paper</placeName>, as <persName>Mr. Halock the Editor</persName>, told me, he
forwarded them to you, he <persName>Mr. H </persName>expressed the high opinion he
entertained in regard to the <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and thinks it will become of
very great importance, ere long,&#8212; It is astonishing how you have
surmounted so many difficulties, as you have had to contend with
in such a variety of ways, and placed your <placeName>Colony </placeName>in a flourishing,
and prosperous Condition, there are but few men, if any that would
have had nerve, patience and perserverance to have acomplished
what you have done, I am glad to hear that it is now plain sailing
with you, and hope that you will now be able to resuscitate&#8212; Since
the last Revolution in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>took place we have heard no more
of the purchase of <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; The <persName>Fabius </persName>that left <placeName>Cadiz </placeName>with <persName>Troops</persName>
in company with the <persName>squadron </persName>for <placeName>Havana</placeName>, arrived at the latter
place in 49 days passage, and I presume the other Ships with her,
it appears the <persName>Troops </persName>were only intended to replenish the <placeName>Garison</placeName>
of that place&#8212;They talked, and I presume were desirous in <placeName>Spain</placeName>
of sending another Expedition against <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, but the difficulty
appears to be the want of means, a letter from a <persName>Genl [gentleman]
</persName>dated in <placeName>Cadiz </placeName>who I think must have a good oppy of obtaining
information writes that he does not beleive that they will, or can
send <persName>Troops </persName>for want of means&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Henry </persName>writes under date of <date when="1830-04-04">4 April </date>that he has had sickness, and
various difficulties to incounter but that his prospects were then
pretty favorable, I have not seen his <persName>wife </persName>since you wrote, she 
resides with her <persName>Family </persName>in <placeName>New Haven</placeName>, I shall probably see her ere
long, when I will communicate what you wrote about her coming
to your <placeName>land of promise</placeName> it would be very difficult I presume for her
to make up her mind to go&#8212; I am very glad to hear that your
<persName>Sister </persName>was well, and that it was probable she and her <persName>Husband</persName>
would join you<date n="Fall - 1831"> next fall</date>, it will be a great acquisition and 
gratification to you to have them so near&#8212; You intimate that you may
some day make us a visit, we should all be delighted to see you, but
I suppose we might almost as soon expect the<persName> Emperor of Russia</persName>
here, If you can so organise your <placeName>colony </placeName>as to be able to leave it
with safety, you will do wonders, but after what you have done,
we aught not to be surprised at your acomplishing any thing you
undertake&#8212; I only saw<persName> Mr. Treat</persName> a few minutes as he passed
through this <placeName>City</placeName>, but I hope on his return here, to have an oppy of
learning many particulars about your <placeName>settlement</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I shall send some <placeName>English and French newspapers</placeName> by this 
conveyance&#8212;   I remain very affectionately</p>

<p><persName>Arch Austin</persName></p>
<p><persName>Colo. Stephen F. Austin</persName>  <placeName> San Felepe de Austin   Texas</placeName>,</p>

<p>I observe the arrival of some<persName> Swiss passengers</persName> within a few days
past from <placeName>Havre</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
