<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1824">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 01-01-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-17">08-17-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 311-312
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-01-01">01-01-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Urging him to move to Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Austin</placeName>,<date when="1830-01-01"> Jany. 1, 1830</date>.</p>
<p>My dear <persName>brother </persName>and <persName>sister</persName>,</p>

<p>I have taken a few moments of Leisure to present to you my
sincere wishes that the <date n="xx-xx-1830">new year </date>which has just entered may be<pb n="312"/>
a happy and prosperous one to you and that before its close we may
all be united once more in this <placeName>country</placeName>.</p>

<p>I wrote you <date n="12-xx-1829">last month</date> advising and urging you to remove here
as soon as possible. I again repeat the same, I wrote you that
I had petitioned for <placeName>land </placeName>for you I have asked of the Govt <placeName>eleven
Leagues of land</placeName> for you on the condition that you remove here.
My <persName>friends </persName>are of the opinion the whole Eleven Leagues will be
granted which will be near 50,000 acres. The land I have selected for
you <placeName>lies on Galveston Bay and within six miles of Galveston harbor</placeName>.
if land is ever worth anything,<hi rend="italic"> one single</hi> league at that <placeName>place </placeName>will
be worth a fortune. I cannot say positively that the whole <placeName>Eleven
Leagues</placeName> will be granted, but I have no doubt that at least five will
be.   I shall know the final result in <date n="03-xx-1830">two months</date> and inform you.</p>

<p>There is an opening here now for <persName>merchandising</persName>. Goods can be
brought in free of duty until <date n="11-xx-1830">November next</date>, and if you have an
idea of removing here you ought to come immediately so as to bring
in a large assortment of goods before the time expires for free
importations.</p>

<p>I am very desirous for you to remove and there now cannot be
a doubt remaining [as] to the rapid rise of this <placeName>country</placeName>. [I can] do
something for you <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, and you must come in time. If the <persName>Govr</persName>
grants the land I have asked, the title will be void unless you remove
at least within 18 months from this time but if you delay untill after
<date n="11-xx-1830">Novr </date>you will have to pay heavy duties on every thing you bring.</p>

<p>You may be sure that I would not urge your removal in so 
positive a manner if I was not convinced that you will be greatly 
benifited. <hi rend="italic">There is no time for hesitation or delay</hi>. You will find us a
plain set of <persName>people</persName>, and you need not be at much expense to bring
furniture.</p>

<p>Farewell and let me hear from you as quick as possible.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin.</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>Direct your letter post paid to the care of <persName>James W. Breedlove
</persName><placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, and if you wish for any information relative to vessels
coming to this <placeName>colony </placeName>write to <persName>Breedlove</persName>, also if you wish to send
anything here, consign it to him with instructions to ship it to the
care of <persName>John Austin </persName><placeName>Brazoria</placeName>. <persName>Breedlove </persName>does most of the business
of this <placeName>colony </placeName>and I wish you to give him yours if you come here,
<hi rend="italic">and you must come</hi> and that immediately.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName>.</p>
<p>Bring all kinds of fruit seed and a quantity of it</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
