<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1999">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William W Morris to Stephen F Austin, 07-21-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William W Morris</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-23">08-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        >Mexican Consul New Orleans
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 458-460
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-07-21">07-21-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">His son Lewis wishes to settle in Texas and wants to buy at least 10,000 acres.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New York </placeName><date when="1830-07-21">July 21st&#8212;1830</date></p>
<p>Sir</p>

<p>In the year <date n="xx-xx-1829">1829 </date>towards the latter end I wrote a <placeName>Pamphlet </placeName>on
the subject of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, shewing the propriety and the necessity of
annexing that <placeName>Province </placeName>to the<placeName> United States</placeName>, a copy of which I
forwarded to you by<persName> Captain Thompson </persName>late of the <persName>Mexican Navy</persName>,
which I hope came safely to hand&#8212;- Never having had the 
opportunity of travelling in that <placeName>country</placeName>, I wrote from data collected<pb n="459"/>
from a variety of persons <persName>strangers</persName>, and <persName>acquaintances</persName>, who had
visited the<placeName> Province of Texas</placeName>, and more particularly your <placeName>Colony</placeName>.
It is not improbable that [in] a hasty publication embracing points
of general policy some of the Ideas thrown on paper and statements
with regard to it were incorrect: In speaking of the characters and
descriptions of <persName>persons </persName>who have located and settled themselves
within the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>, if my information had been as minute
as subsequent opportunities had afforded means of Judging, I should
have made a marked discrimination in favor of those people who
have located and settled themselves in <placeName>St Philipe De Austin</placeName>&#8212; Upon
further investigation and enquiring into the plan of your <placeName>settlement
on the Rio Brassos</placeName>, I was much gratified to learn, that you had
wisely taken a stand in favor of moral rectitude, deeming those the
best <persName>settlers </persName>who had the highest pretensions to character on that
score&#8212;and that in all instances where persons of suspicious 
character presented themselves for the facilities and liberal patronage
which you extend to <persName>settlers</persName>, you instituted the most rigid inquiries
and scrutiny into their private character. In every instance where
it was discovered the <persName>applicant </persName>had taken refuge in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, to escape
the Just punishment of crime committed within the <placeName>United States</placeName>
whose laws he had violated. That such persons have never met
your countenance, and have been prohibited a domicile<placeName> in the 
boundaries your Territories </placeName>circumscribe. Being very lately impressed
with this Idea connected with the favorable light with which
I look upon the <placeName>Country</placeName>, its capacities to give to enterprize new
and reiterated energies, by offering to the early <persName>settler</persName>, a reasonable
prospect of gain where disease is rare, and the soil exuberant (a
location at once commercial and agricultural.) With these strongly
impressed considerations I have come to the determination of 
locating my<persName> eldest Son </persName><persName>Lewis </persName>some where in the <placeName>province</placeName>, and altogether
more than probable within your <placeName>grant</placeName>&#8212; To facilitate this enquiry
you will please address a letter to me as soon as circumstances will
permit, stating your terms to actual <persName>Settlers</persName>&#8212; The price of your
<placeName>first rate Sugar Lands</placeName>, in relation to all governing circumstances,
the proximity of Navigation direct, or as the case may be more 
remote from Navigation. And as a preliminary of great consequence
to me, what term of credit if any is allowed ?</p>

<p>The object of my <persName>Son </persName>is to take up at least the quantity of Ten
thousand Acres, and unless facilities are given to [make] payments
he may not be able to bring round his engagements with punctuality.
My <persName>Son </persName>contemplates writing you on the subject whose letter will
reach you not long after this. I am informed that a <placeName>Newspaper</placeName>
is published weekly at <placeName>St Philipe De Austin </placeName>  if it would be com-<pb n="460"/>
patible with your convenience and not impose upon your politeness
too much trouble I should be much pleased to receive one or two
numbers of so interesting a Journal&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Wm. W. Morris </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Colo. Stephen Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed] <persName>Col. Stephen Austin  </persName><placeName> St Filepe De Austin   Texas
</placeName>Care of the <placeName>Mexican Consul New Orleans</placeName></p>

<p>[Indorsed by Austin:] From the author of the "revolutionary
officer??</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
