<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1082">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Dr. John Sibey to Stephen F. Austin, 04-20-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Dr. John Sibey</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-07">06-07-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nachitoches, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1077-1079
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-04-20">04-20-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-07" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Congress taking steps to open a road from St. Louis to Santa Fé. Attention also to improvements of navigation of Red River, which will divert Santa Fe trade to this route. Cotton trade. Egyptian crop has failed England and created strong demand. Great South American trade from United States. Political news.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Nachitosh </placeName><date when="1825-04-20">April 20&#8212;1825</date></p>
<p>Dr. Sir.</p>

<p><persName>Mr. Sherboneir</persName> has just called at my <placeName>House</placeName> to inform me he was
about setting off for your <placeName>Country</placeName>. I was from home, and have but
a few minutes to write. If I had have had a longer notice should
have written you a longer letter. Should you see<persName> Mr. Sherbonier</persName>
you will find him well informed and intelligent, an Amiable 
Discréete man Esteemed here by all who know him, you will collect
from him very correctly whatever has come within his knowledge,
I am sorry I cannot send you a list of the Acts passed the last session
of Congress, you will have understood for some time past a 
considerable trade has been carried on from <placeName>[St.] Louis</placeName> to <placeName>New Mexico</placeName>,
this has Attracted the Attention of Government and a <placeName>Road</placeName> is to
be opened from<placeName> St. Louis</placeName> to <placeName>Sta Fee</placeName>. A council is appointed to
Reside at <placeName>Chehuawa</placeName> and another at <placeName>Sta fee</placeName>. this has opened the
Eyes of Govt. Relative to the <placeName>Raft in Red River</placeName> and Measures are
about to be taken to open it, when I believe Steam boats will be
able to assend within a day or two's Journey from <placeName>Sta Fee</placeName>, if this
is done the whole current of the Intercourse with <placeName>New Mexico</placeName> will
be by way of <placeName>Red River</placeName> and the whole <placeName>valley</placeName> of it will Soon be
settled, and the time may come when more cotton may go out of
<placeName>Red River</placeName> than now goes out of the <placeName>mississippi</placeName>. Cotton was sold
in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> as high as 24 cents pr. lb last week the demand in<pb n="1078"/>
creasing, in <placeName>England</placeName> they will fall more than 50,000 Bales short
of the ordinary supply, they depended on <placeName>Egypt</placeName> for a supply
which has failed. Such as they have Received is so full of sand
it cannot be Worked and the danger of its bringing the Plague is a
stronger objection to it, the demand in the <placeName>United States</placeName> for our
own <placeName>manufactories </placeName>increases beyond all calculations, two million
Dollars worth of Articles of cotton manufacture of the <placeName>U. S</placeName>., were
exported to <placeName>South America</placeName> in a part of last year :&#8212;
</p>

<p><persName>Mr. Adams is President</persName>. <persName>Mr. Clay Secretary of State</persName> <persName>Mr. Rush
Secty of the Treasury</persName>. <persName>James Barbour of <placeName>Virginia </placeName>Secty of War</persName>.
<persName>Mr. Southard of <placeName>N. Jersey</placeName> of the Navy</persName>. <persName>Mr. Wert Atty. Genl</persName>- <persName>Mr.
McLean of <placeName>Ohio</placeName> Post master Genl</persName> so that there is no doubt but <persName>Mr.
Adams</persName> has an able Cabinet. <persName>Mr. Clinton</persName> of <placeName>N. York</placeName> was nominated
<persName>Minister to London</persName> but being lately appointed <persName>Governor</persName> declined
accepting the appointment. I do not know who is Nominated in his
place. <persName>Mr. Everett</persName> of <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName> is <persName>Minister to Spain</persName> in place
of place of <persName>Genl Nelson</persName> who wants to come home. <persName>Mr. Poinsette</persName> of
<placeName>S° Carolina</placeName> is <persName>Minister to Mexico</persName>. <persName>Col Forbs Charge of Affairs</persName> at
<placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>. <persName>Mr. Allen</persName> continues at <placeName>Chili</placeName> and <persName>Mr. Anderson</persName> at
<placeName>Columbia</placeName>, none appointed to <placeName>Peru</placeName>. <persName>Consuls </persName>are appointed for
several places.&#8212;</p>

<p><placeName>Red River</placeName> is now higher than it has been since <date n="xx-xx-1803">1803</date> and rising.
it Must overflow <placeName>Alexandria</placeName> and it will injure the crops in many
places <placeName>Bridges </placeName>and <placeName>Roads </placeName>suffer much <placeName>Bluclworths great Bridge</placeName> Over
<placeName>Red River</placeName> is gone&#8212;<persName>Genl Lafayette</persName> is now in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> in no
place has greater preparation been made to Receive him; he goes up
the <placeName>Mississippi</placeName> and <placeName>Ohio</placeName> and is to be at <placeName>Boston</placeName> the <date when="1825-06-17">17th of June</date> the
Anniversary of the Battle of <placeName>Bunker Hill</placeName>. Our <persName>Congress</persName> have given
him 200,000 dollars and a Township of Land I believe not yet 
located.&#8212;Congress has under consideration a Bill Reported by the
committee on Foreign Relations for the suppression of Pi [racy]
which did not pass with all the provisions. If it had it was thought
it would have Resulted in a War with <placeName>Spain</placeName>, the sections stricken
out were the Blockading the <placeName>Island of Cuba</placeName> Landing and persuing
the <persName>pirots</persName>. and Reprisals the Bill as it has passed augments our
<persName>Navy</persName> and Leaves some discretion with the <persName>President</persName> relative to the
employing of it.<placeName> England</placeName> has Recognized the Independence of all
<placeName>Spanish America</placeName>.    <placeName>France</placeName> and <placeName>Holland</placeName> will do it.</p>

<p>You will oblige me if you will give me as Early information as
you can Relative to <persName>Mrs. Robinsons</persName> affairs. I want to write to her,
her eldest <persName>son</persName> is a Midshipman in the Navy and with <persName>Commodore
Porter</persName> and of high promise.&#8212;</p>

<p>Please to present my compliments to your <persName>Brother</persName> and to <persName>Mr.
Cook</persName>.&#8212;I shall be glad to Receive a letter from you  <persName> Mr. Poinsette</persName><pb n="1079"/>
will as soon as he arrives in <placeName>Mexico</placeName> move the Subject of the setling
our <placeName>Boundary Line</placeName>&#8212;I had a severe Pleuretic Attack in 03-xx-1825<date n="">march
</date> but
have got well.&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>John Sibley</persName>    [Rubric]</p>
<p><persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
