<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1990">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Secretary of Relations, 07-13-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-23">08-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Secretary of Relations
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 449-451
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-07-13">07-13-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Colonists of Texas are loyal to Mexico. Excited by alarming rumors, but are now quieted, "Poinsett has no adherents here."</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin,</placeName> <date when="1830-07-13">July 13, 1830</date>.</p>
<p>Dear Sir:</p>

<p>I have learned from the <placeName>public prints</placeName> that various rumors have
upset public opinion concerning the <placeName>colonies of Texas</placeName>; rumors 
without the least foundation in fact, although not without a specious
basis. Much injustice may sometimes proceed from a mistaken
opinion concerning an individual or a <placeName>community</placeName>, and I believe it
is the duty of every man to contribute in so far as he is able to the
correction of errors. In this opinion, and in obedience to the truth,
I have believed it to be my duty to explain to you (what I have 
constantly manifested to the<persName> authorities of the state</persName>) that there has
never been the least disturbance of good order in this <placeName>colony</placeName>, and that
the <persName>inhabitants </persName>have always been obedient to the <persName>authorities</persName>.</p>

<p>The idea that the <persName>colonists </persName>of <placeName>Texas </placeName>wish to separate from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>
is entirely mistaken; there is not, and never has been, such an idea
in the sensible part of the <persName>colonists</persName>, because it is very evident that
it is not to the interest of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to be separated from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, even
if such a thing were possible. These <persName>colonists</persName>. Dear Sir, are not
discontented nor dissatisfied; nor have they shown [any] discontent
until after the circulation here of a thousand alarming rumors con-<pb n="450"/>
cerning the excitement which was said to have been manifested
against them in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and until it was said that a large <persName>expedition</persName>
was coming here to destroy them. The injurious effect of such
rumors has been entirely removed by the letters of his <persName>Excellency the
Vice President</persName> and of <persName>General Teran</persName> and by the observations 
published in the <placeName>Gazette </placeName>of this day, some numbers of which I send you.
The discussion in the <placeName>Gazette </placeName>of the <date when="1830-07-10">10th of this month </date>has had a
decisive effect because it gives a clear explanation of the origin of
all of the evil.   <persName>Señor Poinsett</persName> has no <persName>adherents </persName>here.</p>

<p>I for my part declare to you that I have had no other rule but that
of <hi rend="italic">fidelity and gratitude to <placeName>Mexico</placeName></hi>: I have passed nine years in the
most trying labors in the effort to reclaim this <placeName>country </placeName>from the
<placeName>wilderness</placeName>; I have fulfilled my duty to the extent of my ability; I
have worked in good faith; and I can refer with confidence to all the
<persName>authorities </persName>of <placeName>Texas </placeName>and of the state to prove my conduct from the
time I first entered this <placeName>wilderness </placeName>in <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date>.</p>

<p>I can do no less than feel much interest in the fate of the <persName>colonists
of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>. I was the cause of the emigration of most of them and
we have borne years of labor together. I could do no less than feel
much interest in the advancement and prosperity of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, because
it has been the object of my efforts and the sole aim of my ambition
to contribute to the redemption of this <placeName>country </placeName>from the unpopulated
condition in which I found it in <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821 </date>and make it a useful and 
productive part of the great <placeName>Mexican republic</placeName>. I protest to your 
<persName>Excellency </persName>that I came to <placeName>Texas </placeName>with sound intentions and I have never
had others. All my interest and all my <persName>family </persName>are here, and never
have I spared labor in the service of this, my <placeName>adopted country</placeName>.</p>

<p>With great cost and labor I have made a map of all <placeName>Texas</placeName>, which
I sent to the <persName>Political Chief</persName> in <date n="06-xx-1829">June of last year</date> to be forwarded to
the <persName>President</persName>, accompanying it with some notes in order to add to
the geographical knowledge of the <placeName>Mexican territory</placeName>. In <date n="03-xx-1830">March of
this year </date>I sent to your <persName>Excellency </persName>a copy of the translations which
I made of the colonization laws; accompanying them with an 
historical sketch of my <placeName>colony</placeName>. From this your <persName>Excellency </persName>can form an
idea of the labors that have passed.</p>

<p>I have entire confidence in the justice and in the talent of the 
present <persName>administration</persName>; I consider it the Savior of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>from anarchy,
and can assure your <persName>Excellency </persName>that the hope of seeing this <placeName>country</placeName>
happy, after the convulsions of the last two years had almost 
suffocated it is again revived among these <persName>colonists</persName>. We have confidence
in our old<persName> Commandant General</persName>, our present <persName>Vice President,</persName> and in
his <persName>cabinet</persName>; and I beg your <persName>Excellency </persName>to permit me to commend
to the high consideration of the government the worthy <persName>inhabitants
of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, new as well as old.   If suffering years of hardships in the<pb n="451"/>
<placeName>desert </placeName>and being exposed to danger from <persName>Indian </persName>bravos offer any
ground for claiming the attention of the Government, surely the
<persName>inhabitants </persName>of <placeName>Texas </placeName>deserve to be effectively protected and not to be
sacrificed to rumor or to suspicions fed by party feeling or by the
intrigues of a <persName>foreigner [Poinsett?]</persName></p>
<p>With the highest consideration I am your<persName> Excellency</persName>'s servant,</p>

<p><persName>Estevan F Austin</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
