<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1291">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John Iiams to Stephen F. Austin, 09-30-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John Iiams</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-13">07-13-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1463-1464
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-09-30">09-30-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Misunderstanding concerning survey. Austin's reply.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Philip</placeName> <date when="1826-09-30">September 30th 1826</date></p>
<p>Dier Sir</p>

<p>I am informed that <persName>Mr Hirams</persName> has orders for Resurveying my
<placeName>Land </placeName>and I am of the opinion that it is not necessary&#8212;I have left
in your <placeName>office </placeName>a correct Return of the survey and understood you to be
satisfied as <persName>Mr Hunter</persName> had acknowledged his Error, and as he has
never made any Resurvey of any part of my <placeName>Land </placeName>and there is
writen agreements between myself and him that will cover all the
surveying that he has done about my <placeName>land</placeName>&#8212;The last writen 
agreement between him and me is to this effect, he agrees to Correct all
his field notes on the lines miandering on the <placeName>waters </placeName>and Change
the variation on the other side of the needle so as to make them
agree with a true meridian and to Return the same with the other
lines as I had surveyed them, to your <placeName>office</placeName>, all which should be
done before the filling of my Deed that it might not be damaged
by his Errors and I agreed to pay him $37.50 in trade.&#8212;Now
I hope the writen contracts between <persName>Mr Hunter</persName> and myself will
be respected</p>

<p>But as other <persName>surveyors </persName>has been allowed to survey their own and
by your directions I have surveyed mine and hope it will be 
Respected I am not willing to pay <persName>Mr Hirams</persName> for surveying it again.
I hope you will not put me to any more cost or give <persName>Mr Hunter</persName>
any unjust advantage over in consequence of my having detected
his Error Dier Sir I have not been able to comply with my 
obligation to you as to time, but I would be willing to spare you some
cattle at presint if you are ready to Receive them and the 
remainder as fast as I am able untill my <placeName>land </placeName>is paid for&#8212;</p>

<p>But if I am compelld to pay <persName>Mr Hunter</persName> Contrary to my writen
Contract or to pay <persName>Mr Hirams</persName> to survey on his account I shall not
be satisfied and shall personally lay my Complaint before the <persName>heads
of the department</persName> and if I cannot obtain justice I will Publicly
Relinquish all pretensions to Citizenship and leave the <placeName>State </placeName>altho
I have the best Improvement that I have seen in the <placeName>Colony</placeName><pb n="1464"/>
<persName>Mr Hunter</persName> has not spoken with me since our last agreement
and I know not why he wishes a Resurvey</p>

<p>Dier sir It is my wish to remain at home and by Honest 
Industry to maintain my little <persName>family </persName>without those vexatious disputes
and I hope you will Condiscend to write me a fiew lines informing
me what I shall do in the above case</p>

<p>I am Sir with Respect your friend and humble Servant</p>

<p><persName>John Iams</persName></p>

<p><persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p><date when="1826-09-30">Sept 30</date> I have this moment returned <placeName>home </placeName>unwell and tired and recd
the above letter which I return to you because the last page contains
very improper reflections&#8212;All I have to say on the subject is that
you and many others in this <placeName>colony </placeName>would save themselves much
unnecessary trouble and much useless vexation by ascertaining facts
from me in person instead of picking them up from common report
which as a general rule in this <placeName>country </placeName>is always wrong&#8212;<persName>Mr Hirams</persName>
never recd any instructions from me to resurvey your land&#8212;neither
did I ever say that it [would be neces]sary to resurvey it&#8212;neither
have [I ever thou]ght that such resurvey was necessary, for <persName>Hunter</persName>
told me that the lines were all corrected to your full satisfaction&#8212;-
as to relinquishing your citizenship you can do so and abandon the
<placeName>country </placeName>whenever you please&#8212;I know of nothing to prevent&#8212;but
common good breeding ought to have taught you to have reserved
your threats against the <persName>Government </persName>until injustice had been done
you and you had something to complain of&#8212;</p>

<p>I have nothing to do with the appointment of <persName>surveyors </persName>it belongs
to the <persName>commissioner </persName>and I had it in contemplation to recommend
you to the <persName>commissioner of the <placeName>Trinity country</</placeName>person_mentioned> when one was 
appointed for the appointment of <persName>surveyor </persName>for that <placeName>River</placeName>, for I had
been requested to do so by some of the <persName>inhabitants </persName>of that <placeName>river</placeName>&#8212;
but the disposition you seem to manifest to complain without cause
is a rather bad recommendation, tho I can make great allowances,
the slow motions of the Govt sometimes put me out of patience and
it is not to be wondered that the patience of the <persName>Settlers </persName>are 
sometimes exhausted&#8212;all you have to do is pay no regard to common
report if you wish to know any fact write to me in person and
you shall be informed correctly if in my power to inform you&#8212;</p>

<p>I am very hard pressed for the fees, but you and all others know
my unwillingness to press the <persName>settlers</persName>&#8212;you must do the best you can</p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr. John Iiams</persName> <placeName>San Jacinto</placeName></p>

<p>[Stephen F. Austin]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
