<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1202">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Jose Antonio Saucedo, 07-17-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-23">06-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Jose Antonio Saucedo
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1375
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-07-17">07-17-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asks instructions concerning procedure for legal separation of husband and wife.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>I am under the necessity of consulting Your <persName>Lordship </persName>in relation
to a legal case which arose in this jurisdiction, and to request you to
give me your instructions as to the mode of proceeding which will
be in conformity to the laws of the <placeName>Country</placeName>.</p>

<p>One of the <persName>colonists </persName>behaves so badly toward his <persName>wife </persName>and <persName>family</persName>,
that she can not bear his ill usage any longer. He is a <persName>drunkard</persName>
and if there are no means of preventing him, will soon squander all
the property they have. The <persName>family </persName>is composed of his <persName>wife </persName>and
three <persName>daughters</persName>; the property consists principally of <persName>slaves</persName>, furniture and cattle, to the amount of 7 or 8,000 dollars, all of which
belongs to the <persName>wife</persName>, as is shown by legal titles of possession. He
received <placeName>land </placeName>here as a <persName>colonist</persName>, but having neglected to cultivate
it as is required by law, he forfeits his right. Now, <persName>she </persName>wishes to
be separated from him and to take possession of <placeName>her property</placeName> for
her own and her <persName>children</persName>'s support. He refuses to permit her to do
so, and threatens to take the <persName>negroes </persName>to the <placeName>United States of the
North</placeName>; she is even apprehensive of her personal security. I have
neither <placeName>jail </placeName>nor guard, nor the means of securing men of his 
character and disposition. In his intoxication he treats me and the
other <persName>public officers</persName> of this jurisdiction with contempt.</p>

<p>As I am unacquainted with the law in such cases, and the form
of proceeding therein, I request your <persName>Lordship </persName>to instruct me on
the subject; and, also, to tell me what I have to do with those who,
when intoxicated, abuse, and speak contemptuously of the 
<persName>authorities</persName>. If such conduct is tolerated all respect will be lost and good
order can not be enforced. The actual cause of these offences is,
that these <persName>men </persName>are aware that we have no means of confining them,
and, they say, the laws do not allow the punishment of flogging,
and they have no money to pay a fine. What am I to do with such
bad <persName>characters</persName>, who ought to be punished for disturbing the peace,
and appearing, publicly, in a state of drunkenness?</p>
<p>God and Liberty.</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName>, <date when="1826-07-17">July 17th 1826</date>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
