<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1675">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas White to Stephen F Austin, 01-31-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Thomas White</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-10">08-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Franklin, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas, via Natchitoches, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 164-165
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-01-31">01-31-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asking information especially about social conditions and character of the colonists. Has heard disturbing reports about conditions on the Sabine border.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Franklin Louisiana</placeName> <date when="1829-01-31">31st Jan 1829</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>As I contemplate becoming a <persName>resident of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, I feel great
solicitude about the nature of the population which will inhabit the
country I have been informed that you permit no one to settle
<placeName>within the limits of your colony </placeName>unless they produce vochers 
sufficient to convince you that they possess a good moral character 
indeed I beleive such is the law and I was truly glad to hear that
you were disposed to rigidly inforce it&#8212; But I am fearful you
may be imposed on for I do no of some very bad <persName>men </persName>who I have
been told are going there. There are a number of <persName>criminals </persName>who
after serveing in the <placeName>state prisons</placeName> who it is said when they are turned
out look towards <placeName>Texas</placeName>. The <persName>planters </persName>here have a most desperate
oppinion of the <persName>population </persName>there orriginating I presume from such
<persName>vilains </persName>as has been driven from among them and who have taken
shelter in that <placeName>province </placeName>There are others of my acquaintance whom
I got acquainted with before I came to this <placeName>state </placeName>who I have 
understood are now on their way there. I beleive they are from <placeName>Tennassee</placeName>
and <placeName>Alabama </placeName>and I can assure you that I know no good of them
I do not wish to make specific charges but be strict in your enquiries
about character&#8212; I do not wish to mention names because I may see
them when I arrive there-™ A Gentleman expects to leave <placeName>Attakapas</placeName>
shortly for the purpose of exploreing your <placeName>country </placeName>If he gives a
favourable report I shall certainly remove there and endeavour to
carry along with me a numerous train of <persName>friends </persName>who I am sure
you will find to be honest and industerous <persName>citizens </persName>and who will
bring with them considerable <persName>property</persName>&#8212; The <persName>Gentleman </persName>above 
alluded to feels some apprehension of danger of robery by <persName>persons
liveing on the opposite side of the <placeName>Sabine river</placeName> </persName>from this and is
waiting to get company to go with him a <persName>planter </persName>told me not long
since that persons who stole his horses fled to the <placeName>Spanish country</placeName>
meaning <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I mention these things to you to apprise you of
the objections which the most respectable class of <persName>citizens </persName>have to
comeing to your <placeName>county </placeName>thinking it probable that you would adopt
some means to have those lawles <persName>fugatives </persName>from the laws of their
<placeName>country </placeName>driven away from this <placeName>province </placeName>As it regards your <placeName>Colony</placeName>
I have confidence in what I have heard that your intention is only
to admit respectable <persName>persons </persName>But I am fearful that some persons
haveing the appearance of gentlemen will impose themselves&#8212; I
heard the other day of a<persName> man from <placeName>New York</placeName></persName> who says that he is
an <persName>intimate friend of Bur </persName>going to <placeName>Texas </placeName>from what expressions
which I heard he dropt I fear you will find him a restless sperit
and perhaps a troublesome fellow&#8212;   Will you be so good as to write<pb n="165"/>
me and let me know whether it is dangerous traveling on the <placeName>other
side of the sabine</placeName> in consequence of <persName>Robbers</persName>&#8212; I have heard also that
you have obtained an extension of your <placeName>colony </placeName>pray let me know
at what time I could obtain land in it as I was informed that it
was probable it would be ready for settlement this winter if that
be the fact do let me know and the terms on which I could obtain
lands for my self and five or six other <persName>families</persName>&#8212; I removed to this
<placeName>state </placeName><date n="xx-xx-1828">last year</date> and have not purchased land yet&#8212; nor shall I 
purchase largely untill I see your <placeName>country </placeName>or Know more about it from
the <persName>Gentleman </persName>who is about to visit it</p>
<p><persName>Thomas White</persName></p>
<p>Ps</p>

<p>I shall leave here in a few days for <placeName>St Martinsville</placeName> where I would
thank you to write me</p>

<p>Since writeing the within I have been told by a <persName>gentleman </persName>that
there is liveing <placeName>near the sabine</placeName> a man by the name of <persName>William
Knight</persName> who brok geoil here and frequently crosses the <placeName>river </placeName>and
commits depredations on the <placeName>state of Louisiana</placeName> would it not be
wise to send a <persName>force </persName>and detect him and his <persName>bandits </persName>I presume that
the <persName>commander of the Mexican Troops at <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName></persName>would order
him and his <persName>gang </persName>arrested if information was given of the character
of <persName>Knight and his associates</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Colo S. F Austin </persName><placeName>Natchitoches Louisiana</placeName> The
<persName>post master</persName> will be so good as to foward this to <placeName>San Felipe de
Austin Texas</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
