<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1812">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>H H League to Stephen F Austin, 12-19-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>H H League</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-16">08-16-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 301-302
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-12-19">12-19-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asking Austin to obtain for him leave of absence from service in the ayuntamiento. His unpopularity makes it inconvenient to serve.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Town of Austin</placeName> <date when="1829-12-19">Decr 19. 1829.</date></p>
<p><persName>Col Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dear Sir My Extreem bad health precludes the possibilitys of
my Visiting your <placeName>office </placeName>as often as my business would require it
after weighing the Subject maturely I find it all important for the
interest of the <placeName>Community </placeName>to quiet the outrageous Clammer that
actually threatens at this moment the Over throw of every thing
and as a Step of Self preservation that I should by all means be
Released from serveing any longer as a <persName>Rigedore</persName>, it is impossible
that my health can ever be restored under my present State of
Depressed and mortified feelings, my hopes and prospects are all
blasted; and my oppression is beyond the Controll of all the
philosiph[y] and fortitude I can Call to my aid my health has
actually Sunk, and unless I can produce a Change, the 
Conseiquences will be fatal to me and that Very Shortly, thare is no laber
or fatigue I would not willingly under go for the advancement of
the <placeName>Country </placeName>if my Exertions Could avail, but Such is the Violence
of feeling Existing against me at this moment, that any 
interfearance with the <persName>publick </persName>business by me or Even an Idea that I will
interfear infuriates them to madness&#8212;it is resolved that the next
<persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>shall not be contaminated with my (Rascally
intrigues) as they Say-&#8212;, be the conseiquences what they may&#8212;, my
own Idea is this, the <persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>will dispence with my meeting
them on account of my bad health and if it is possible for me to
obtain Two month leave of Absence from the <persName>Chief of Department</persName>,<pb n="302"/>
I wish to take a Trip to <placeName>N. Orleans </placeName>to See if it will not facilitate my
recovery, and if the <persName>Commissioner </persName>can be prevailed upon to represent
my Case to the Government at the Same time it is possible I may
obtain a total Exemption, and should I recover my health which I
have much reason to doubt I may be useful to the <persName>publick </persName>in 
someother way&#8212;, will you have the goodness to lay the case before the
<persName>comissioner </persName>and do all in your power for me, which I Shall always
acknowledge as the gratest of favours.</p>

<p><persName>H. H. League </persName>   [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
