<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1483">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to J. H. Bell, 01-21-1828</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-29">07-29-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J. H. Bell
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 7-8
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1828-01-21">01-21-1828</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-29" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Difficulty in getting capable men to serve as officers of the ayuntamiento.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1828-01-21">Jany. 21. 1828</date></p>
<p>Dr sir,</p>

<p>I recd, your letter stating that you wish to decline serving as one
of the <persName>Ayuntamiento</persName>, and feel somewhat discouraged at your 
determination&#8212;As you personal <persName>friend</persName>, I should say you did right, but
as a friend of this <placeName>colony</placeName>, I must say you are doing wrong&#8212;It is
very important to get good <placeName>men</placeName>, and men of business in the 
<persName>Ayúntamto</persName>. I feel no individual interest on the subject and as a mere
individual I am indifferent who are elected&#8212;but in all matters 
connected with the welfare of this <placeName>colony </placeName>I cannot feel or think 
indifferently&#8212;As for myself I shall devote my whole time and attention
to the land business and have some idea of taking a trip into the
<placeName>United States</placeName> in order to try and bring out a large number of
<persName>families </persName>in a body, but I do not wish to leave the <placeName>colony </placeName>again, even
for a moment, untill I see the local government well organised, and
this cannot be done without putting good <persName>men </persName>in office</p>

<p>I am getting very tired and worn down with the business and
were it not my duty to the <persName>settlers </persName>who are here never to abandon<pb n="8"/>
them, I should give up my last contract with the Govt for the 
settling of the <placeName>new Colony</placeName>, and either settle myself down on a <placeName>Stock
farm</placeName>, or seek some other <placeName>country </placeName>where I might hope to find 
harmony but it is my duty to persevere and for that reason, and that
alone, I will go on&#8212;</p>

<p>you are wrong to decline serving for I think you can do an
important service to the <placeName>colony </placeName>as a member of the <persName>Ayuntamto </persName>but
you have a right to do as you please, tho if you are elected the law
compels you to serve&#8212;</p>

<p>I have heard of no opposition to <persName>Ingram </persName>and I think he will
be unanimously elected I am sorry to say that <persName>Kinny </persName>has also
declined serving, tho, he is excusable for his business I expect will
compell him to devote all his time to his private affairs&#8212;I have not
thoroughly known <persName>Kinny </persName>untill <date n="Winter - 1827 [?]">last winter</date> he is a usefull and
valuable man and I wish it was in my power to aid him in his
pecuniary difficulties&#8212;</p>

<p>My <persName>friend </persName>we must all be united and harmonious&#8212;without this
the <placeName>colony </placeName>never can flourish&#8212;-poor <persName>Pettus </persName>is broken up&#8212;he has been
imprudent in the highest degree&#8212;and has abused me and every
one else&#8212;if I had the means of aiding him I would freely do so&#8212;
he is in misfortune&#8212;-let that alone be remembered and all his abuses
forgotten&#8212;I send you a valuable <persName>neighbor </persName>(I hope) in <persName>Mr. Robison</persName>,
I have nearly given him a small place merely because I think him
a good man</p>

<p>Think better of the matter and say you will serve- My respects
to <persName>Mrs Bell</persName> I can let you have some fig roots next year if the slips
I brought from <placeName>Bexar </placeName>grow</p>

<p><persName>S F Austin</persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Mr J. H Bell</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
