<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1045">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Charles Douglas to Stephen F. Austin, 02-15-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Charles Douglas</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-05-30">05-30-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Tuscumbia, Franklin County, North Alabama</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1046-1049
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-02-15">02-15-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-05-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Great interest in Texas, but emigration checked by uncertainty on several points: (1) Will freedom of worship be winked at? (2) Are slaves safe? Can they be held as "working servants"? (3) Character of the soil? Climate? Navigation? etc., etc.   Political news of United States and of Europe.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Tuscumbia Franklin County
North Alabama</placeName> <date when="1825-02-15">Feb 15th 1825</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p>I wrote you a long letter several, months ago and have been anxiously
expecting an answer for a considerable time past, but thus far my
wishes have not been gratified. I am inclined to think from your
silence that the letter miscarried and as a good opportunity offers
by a <persName>Mr Royal</persName> who is about starting for your <placeName>settlement</placeName> I embrace
it to make a second communication. It would afford me much
 pleasure to receive from you as an old and highly esteemed acquaintance
a long letter filled with information relative to yourself and the
<placeName>country</placeName> in which you reside. Much interest is excited about your
<placeName>settlement</placeName> and respectable people here are verry anxious to obtain
satisfactory information upon the subject. In order to satisfy this
laudable curiosity and to gratify my own private wishes I venture
to ask you several questions which will be the easiest and best way
of satisfying both, them and myself. I wish to know what the 
feelings of the Govt are at this time upon the subject of religion. Will
it wink at liberty of conscience and permit good and worthy 
<persName>inhabitants</persName> to peaceably assemble and worship their God in the way most
agreeable to their feelings without evincing any disposition to make
<persName>proselytes</persName> or to interfere with the prevailing religion of the country.
This is a subject of vast importance to the people of these <placeName>U States</placeName>
and has a most powerful effect in preventing respectable <persName>families</persName><pb n="1047"/>
from removing from this to your <placeName>country</placeName>. To those who think 
liberally an exclusive religion presents no formidable difficulties but you
are well apprised of the wonderful influence of education upon a
subject involving the present and future happiness of <persName>Mankind</persName>,
particularly in a <placeName>country </placeName>like this where religious liberty exists in
all its purity. The operation of your system [will be alarming?] to
our <persName>Females</persName> whose influence we must submit to in every thing 
relating to social and domestic happiness. We will not say they renounce
the religion of our <persName>Fathers</persName> or be deprived of the pleasures derived
from its doctrines and ceremonies for all other earthly enjoyments.
If deprived of these every other object would cease to please and all
around would appear dark and dreary. An elysium under such 
circumstances would be more intolerable than <placeName>Siberian desserts</placeName>. You
may depend upon it that your exclusive system has a most 
discouraging effect upon imigration particularly among the more respectable
classes of the community. If that first and most obnoxious article
could be blotted from your constitution, my word for it, <persName>families</persName> of
respectability and influence would flock to your <placeName>country </placeName>from every
part of the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

<p>Our most valuable <persName>inhabitants</persName> here own <persName>negroes</persName>. I am therefore
anxious to know what the laws are upon that subject. Can they be
introduced as the labouring <persName>servants</persName> of <persName>emigrants</persName>? and, when are
they free ? They are an important species of property here and our
<persName>planters</persName> are not willing to remove without they can first be assured
of their being secured to them by the laws of your Govt.</p>

<p>Inform me about the general appearance of your <placeName>country</placeName>, its
soil, and climate, particularly in that part of it immediately on
or near the <placeName>sea coast</placeName>. Is it high and dry or is it low and swampy ?
Do springs abound and is it difficult to produce water by digging
<placeName>wells</placeName>? and is the <placeName>country</placeName> as well adapted to sugar cane as to cotton?
Are you subject to severe droughts during the summer? What
is the size of the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>, will it admit of schooner navigation up
to your <placeName>town</placeName>: and is the land immediately on the <placeName>river</placeName> high or
low and subject to inundation? How far is your <placeName>town</placeName> from the
<placeName>sea coast</placeName> and would a store of goods to well in it ? What are your
most common diseases; are bilious fevers frequent and severe and
would a <persName>Doctor</persName> do well among you? In what way do you dispose
of your lands; do you give long credit to <placeName>purchasers</placeName>, and how
much is the extent that each <persName>family </persName>can posses? Must they settle
it themselves or will you allow them to settle their purchases in the
first instance with good and industrious <persName>families</persName>? My reason for
asking this question is that many of our first rate men might be
induced to purchase if they were certain that it was not necessary
for them to remove untill after their places were well improved and<pb n="1048"/>
comfortably fixed with houses etc etc&#8212;Is your <placeName>country </placeName>well 
timbered, and what is your most common growth ? Please answer these
questions and give as much other information as you conveniently
can, all which will be very pleasing to me and may probably prove
beneficial in its consequences to yourself, as I think, I can be of
service to you in procuring <persName>settlers</persName> that would do honour to any
<placeName>country</placeName>. A letter coming from you would be considered as official
and people would act accordingly. I take the liberty of suggesting
the propriety of your having a<placeName> mail rout</placeName> immediately established
between your <placeName>Town</placeName> and <placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>, it would verry much facilitate
the intercourse and prove advantageous to your <placeName>settlement</placeName>. I am
anxious to procure a good tract of <placeName>land</placeName> immediately on the <placeName>sea
coast</placeName>, if I could do so I would remove to it with a number of
good <persName>families</persName>. If you know of such a situation where the land is
good and where it will be healthy write me all about it. The only
national news of importance is the Presidential election. The 
prominent <persName>candidates </persName>are <persName>General Jackson</persName> and <persName>Mr. Adams</persName>. The tug of
war commenced at <placeName>Washington city</placeName> on the <date when="1825-02-09">9th of this month</date> and
how it will end is uncertain. The prevailing opinion in this 
<placeName>western country</placeName> is that <placeName>Genl Jackson</placeName> will be elected. This present
congress have voted <persName>Genl La Fayette</persName> $200000 and given him a
township of land to be selected by the <persName>President</persName> of the <placeName>u States</placeName>.
This is as it should be and has proved to the world that republics
are not ungrateful. It is now engaged in perfecting a law for the
more effectual suppression of piracy. The law as reported provides
for the building of 10 additional sloops of war of 20 guns each
to be employed on the <placeName>West India</placeName> station. To permit merchantmen
vessels to arm in their own defence and allows a provision to such
as are wounded whilst defending their vessels, and to make prizes
of piratical vessels if they can. It also allows the <persName>officers</persName> and <persName>crews</persName>
of our National Vessels to pursue and if necessary to land in 
pursuit of <persName>pirates</persName> and if the <persName>authorities</persName> of the <placeName>Towns</placeName> in which they
secrete themselves attempt to protect them or refuse to give them
up after a proper demand has been made to blockade such<placeName> port</placeName> or
place untill compliance is obtained. This law, I hope, will satisfy
<persName>Mr. Vives</persName> of <placeName>Cuba</placeName> and the rascally <persName>governor of <placeName>Po[r]to Rico</placeName> </persName>that
we will no longer submit to their infamous conduct. The affairs
of <placeName>Europe</placeName> are in Statu Quo. Poor degraded <placeName>Spain</placeName> is yet 
convulsed with intestine broils . and groaning under the iron arm of
her cruel Monster of a <persName>King</persName>. The <persName>French army</persName> is about leaving
that unfortunate <placeName>country</placeName> and what the consequences will be God
only knows. I sincerely hope the <placeName>nation</placeName> will react, and if it does
I hope all those cursed fanatical <persName>monks</persName> and tyranical <persName>villains</persName> who
have so long oppressed that people will be quickly made to bite
the dust.    As to <placeName>Greece</placeName> every thing appears encouraging.    Her<pb n="1049"/>
<persName>army </persName>and <persName>Navy </persName>have done wonders. The classical ground of 
<placeName>Thermopolse</placeName> has been lately again and again crimsoned by the valor
of her modern <persName>heroes</persName> with the blood of her infidel <persName>oppressors</persName> and
her <persName>navy </persName>has covered itself with glory under the direction of her
Gallant <persName> Canaris</persName> and other valient <persName>Chieftains</persName> and has driven, and
is now blockading within the <placeName>dardanells</placeName> the few remaining ships
of the great<persName> Turkish fleet</persName>. Do answer this by the very first 
opportunity and give me all the news. As I have nothing more at present
to communicate I close by subscribing myself your sincere Friend
and Obt Servt</p>

<p><persName>Charles Douglas</persName></p>

<p><persName>Hon Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>The <persName>bearer </persName>can tell you all about me and what I am doing I
received a letter not long since from <persName>Doctor Parrot</persName> he is still living
in <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and is doing well&#8212;</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
