<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1413">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Robert D. Dawson to Stephen F. Austin, 06-16-827</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Robert D. Dawson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-25">07-25-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Postmaster at Nachitoches
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                         Louisiana
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Madrid, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Austin's Colony, Province of Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1658-1659
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1827-06-16">06-16-1827</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-25" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning collection of a note.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Madrid. Mri</placeName> <date when="1827-06-16">June 16th 1827</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>You would no doubt pardon an old <persName>acquaintance </persName>under any 
circumstances for presuming to write to you without prefacing his
communication with " Your Excellency &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c but really and in
truth I am not so Democratical in my feelings as to omit to give
you your just and proper title from any repugnance of feeling but
simply because I am ignorant of the title you really bear and beg
you on this ground to excuse me</p>

<p>A friend of mine <persName>Mr. Alexander La forge</persName> in a settlement with
<persName>George Tennille</persName> some years ago obtain'd from him by assignment
a note drawn in his favour by you for $1500.00 given as is 
undestood by <persName>Mr Laforge</persName> in consideration of the purchace by you of some
<placeName>land </placeName>from said <persName>Tennille</persName>, <persName>Mr Laforge</persName> is anxious to know whether he
may justly entertain the expectation that you will ultimately redeem
this obligation, and if so when and how it is contemplated to be
done. He suffered greatly by <persName>Tennille</persName> whose obligation he now
holds for a considerable amount independent of the note assigned
him on you, and being in moderate circumstances only with a young
and increasing <persName>family </persName>would be greatly benefitted by the receipt of
the amount appearing to be due him by you.   On this subject he<pb n="1659"/>
has frequently conversed with me and I have constantly assured him
of my firm belief that if the debt was considered just by you&#8212;you
would make no difficulty whatever in the payment of it whenever
your means would enable you to do so. This cannot now be doubted
as from the best information we are able to obtain the success of
your <placeName>colony </placeName>is beyond a doubt, and if rightly judged of here must
long ere this have secured you wealth in as great abundance as you
have honors in your New Government</p>

<p>You will confer a particular favor on me and render <persName>Mr Laforge</persName>
a great kindness if you will write me fully on this subject as early
as your convenience will permit and in addition my obligation will
be heightened by the receipt of any information of the condition of
your <placeName>colony</placeName>&#8212;province and Government which you may deem worthy
of communication to an old acquaintance and friend</p>

<p><persName>Robt D Dawson</persName></p>

<p>The <placeName>Postmaster at Natchetoches</placeName> will confer a favour on the writer
of this if he will forward this to its place of Destination by mail if
there is any, if not by any safe private conveyance as early as 
possible.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <placeName>New Madrid</placeName> <date when="1827-06-17">June 17th </date><persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> <placeName>Austin's
Colony Province of Texas</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
