<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1649">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Emily M Perry to J E B Austin, 11-29-1828</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Emily M Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-08">08-08-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J E B Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Herculaneum, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 149-150
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1828-11-29">11-29-1828</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Record of Austin's business with Butler burned. Conditions in Missouri.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Herculaneum</placeName> <date when="1828-11-29">November 29.th 1828</date>&#8212;</p>

<p>I received a few days since Mr Dear <persName>Brothers</persName>, letter of <date when="1828-09-28">Sepr 28,</date>
which gave me the most sincear pleasure, as I have not had any letter
from eather of you since<persName> M.r J. Austin</persName> was up; I was very much
disapointed in not seeing him as I had a great many inquires to
make, respectting you and my <persName>Sister </persName>I have not words to express
to you the pleasure, that I felt when I heard that you were Married;
I have no doubt but what you will enjoy life much more than you
ever did; you now have some inducement to exert yourself to acquire
an independence, which I have no doubt you will do, If it only
pleases the <persName>Almighty </persName>to spare your lives;&#8212;</p>

<p>I am on a Visit to this place, and shall see all your numerous
<persName>Cousins</persName>; <persName>Adeline Lewis</persName>, is living with her <persName>Father</persName>; and the <persName>Sisters</persName>
of her <persName>deceas'd Husband</persName> are living with her, one of the <persName>Young
Laydes</persName>, is to be Married<date when="1828-11-30"> to Morrow night</date>, which is the reason of my
being hear, I expect to see the most of our <persName>relations </persName>that live in this
<placeName>County</placeName>&#8212;their is very little alteration with them, since you left here
excepting in Deaths, the Town of <placeName>Herculaneum</placeName> is all going to
Naught; I do not know when I shall visit it again, for when I look
at our old <hi rend="italic"><placeName>habitation </placeName></hi>it brings to mind <persName>Friends </persName>and seans that have
long gone by, it casts such a gloom on my feelings, that it is with
difficulty that I can appear chearfull, in the Midst of our <persName>Friends</persName>,
<persName>Mary Honey</persName> has four <persName>Children </persName>one <persName>Daughter, Maria W.</persName> three, 
<persName>Adeline</persName> one, Old <persName>Aggy </persName>call to see me today, she looks very like old times,
she inquired very particularly after you, and<persName> Master Stephen</persName>, and
express'd a great wish to see you boath, poor old <persName>Jack </persName>is number'd
with the Dead&#8212;&amp;c.</p>

<p>Tell <persName>Stephen </persName>that <persName>M.r Woodson</persName> had his <placeName>house </placeName><hi rend="italic">burnt </hi>to the Ground,
when he was <persName>Clerk of the Court</persName>, and that <hi rend="italic">all the <placeName>Papers</placeName></hi> relating to
the <persName>Butler </persName>business where burnt, not <hi rend="italic">one </hi>to be <hi rend="italic">found</hi>, so he may give
himself no uneasiness on that business; <persName>Judge Carr</persName> intends writing
to him very fully respecting the business&#8212;</p>

<p>I shall look for you and <persName>Sister </persName><date n="Spring - 1829">Next Spring</date>, you must not wait
to make a <hi rend="italic">fortune</hi>, for if you do, I shall think that you do not want<pb n="150"/>
to see <hi rend="italic">me</hi>; but wish only to make a show and <hi rend="italic">parade</hi>, for <persName>James</persName>, I
know that you inherit all our Dear <persName>Father</persName>s Pride, and ambition, I
once possess'd my share of it, but misfortune and trouble has 
compleatly humbled me; I want you to come and see how <hi rend="italic">happy </hi>I live
with my Dear good Man, and to see what a handsome <persName>Family </persName>of
<persName>Children</persName>, I have, it is very old fashion for one to write about ones
<persName>Husband </persName>and <persName>Children</persName>, I trust I may always be so far out of Fashion
as to praise merit where it is deserving, you could visit <placeName>Missouri</placeName>, and
return in 6 weeks, <persName>Sister </persName>would only have to stop at <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>-
procure a Fashionable Bonnet and two or three Fashionable Dresses,
and she would Eclips us all Fashionables at <placeName>Potosi</placeName>; but indeed My
Dear <persName>Brother </persName>you must visit us in the <date n="Spring - 1829">Spring</date>; we shall know by that
time wheather there can be any thing recover'd in <persName>Jersey</persName>, the last
accounts were very flattering&#8212;</p>

<p>I send you by <persName>Mrs Lockhart</persName> a box of Roots and more gardin seed;
I hope long ere this the box of seed that I send in <date n="10-xx-1828">October </date>has yet 
arrived safe, I wrote to <persName>Sister </persName>and inclosed the letter, and a little bundle
in the Box; I must bid you Adieu for the <placeName>house </placeName>is full of <hi rend="italic"><persName>Girls </persName></hi>and
they keep such a fuss and chattering around me that I hardly know
what I am doing&#8212;tell <persName>Stephen </persName>that I have a most <hi rend="italic">amiable </hi>and 
<hi rend="italic">beautifull <persName>Girl</persName></hi> picked out for him the <persName>Daughter </persName>of an old <persName>Friend </persName>and
favourit of his&#8212;she very much resembles a Laydy that he once was
very <hi rend="italic">partial </hi>too-&#8212;</p>

<p>Present my most affectionate love to <persName>Sister</persName>, and <persName>Brother</persName>, you must
all of you write to me often, and believe me always your truly
attached Sister</p>

<p><persName>E, M, Perry</persName></p>

<p>[Address:] <persName>James E. B, Austin Esqr.</persName> <placeName>St Filippi de Austin&#8212;
Provence of Texas</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
