<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1691">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Josiah H Bell to Stephen F Austin, 03-13-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Josiah H Bell</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-10">08-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 182-183
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-03-13">03-13-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">People of his section disgusted with disturbances at San Felipe. He thinks the lawyers are to blame. All have confidence in Austin and depend on him to set things right. People will support an academy but don't want it located at San Felipe.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>it is with much regret that we hear that the<persName> p[e]ople of <placeName>st Philepe</placeName>
</persName>is still keeping up a difficulty among themselves and is 
concequinteally Calculated to give uneasiness to the p[e]ople genarly&#8212;-I fear
there is some who do not think as they should do of the necessity of
harmony and Good feelings among the people Gennorly but suifer
their inflamatry feelings to leed them to far it may be they suifer
their veiws of Interest to over-ride their duty to the publick Good
and I fear the <persName>Gentlemen of the bar</persName> has no small shear in the affair
I am of opinion that if the <persName>lawers </persName>do not Change their manner of
doing business or there is not a stop put to their management in
some way that it will be productive of more sereous Injury to the
<placeName>Collony </placeName>than they are aware of or prehaps to themselves in short
there is more Clamour among the p[e]ople against the proceeding
at that place than I have heard on any subject and they all agree
that the <persName>lawers </persName>is intitled to the principal blame&#8212;I have paid all
attention to what is passing in my power and am Convinced that
the people have little hope but in you for a reformation&#8212;they all
have Confidence that you will as you have done do all in your power
for the publick Good. I am Convinced that you have much in your
power and that you have the intire confidence of the people and
that any measure you [approved] would meet their seport and 
apprebation what have you not done for us and what may you not
yet do&#8212;    I received your letter on the subject of establishing a<pb n="183"/>
<placeName>school </placeName>and have spoken to the p[e]ople Genarly the[y] are all
willing to Give it liberal support but object intirely to sending
their <persName>children </persName>to <placeName>San Philipe</placeName> in fact they are so disgusted with
the precedings at that place that there is nothing that Centers there
that they will have any thing to do with&#8212;as to my own part I
would do any way that a <persName>mejority </persName>might think best&#8212;</p>

<p>My opinion is that if the <persName>lawers </persName>ware placed in a situation to go
to work and Could be converted into good <persName>farmers </persName>that all things
would go on well and quietly and I think I risk nothing whin I say
that this is the opinion of the p[e]ople Genarly&#8212;and also that any
measure you may perpose would meet their aprobation, and also
that they look to you alone as having it in your power to remady
the Evils they now Complain of&#8212;and their whole hope is that you
will be with them in using your Influince and means for the Good
of the <placeName>Collany </placeName>and they beleave that while the <persName>lawers </persName>Continue as
they are that they have nothing but Confusion to hope for.&#8212;</p>

<p>it is rumored that our <persName>Ayuntimiento </persName>is preparing a petition to
the <persName>Legislature </persName>of the state to pass a law to levy a tax on the <placeName>Collany</placeName>
I think it a subject that ought to be well reflected on the people is
pore and a tax should be as little resorted to as possable</p>

<p><persName>J. H. Bell</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
