<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1125">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Militiamen, 05-01-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-11">06-11-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Militiamen
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1317-1319
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Address urging discipline</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-05-01">05-01-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Address urging discipline and obedience during campaign against Waco and Tahuacano Indians.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            
<p>[about May 1, 1826.]</p>
<p>F[ellow] S[itizens]</p>

<p>You are therefore now called upon to protect your own <placeName>homes</placeName>,
your own <placeName>property</placeName>, to shield your <persName>wives </persName>and <persName>children </persName>from the 
arrows of a savage and merciless <persName>enemy</persName>&#8212;your adopted <placeName>country </placeName>now
also called upon you to rally around the national flag and fight its
enemies the <persName>Wacos </persName>and <persName>Tahuacanies</persName>&#8212;every honorable and ardent
impulse Therefore that can animate the bosoms of <persName>free men</persName> burns
in yours and urges you forward to meet the <persName>enemy</persName>&#8212;the defence of
your <placeName>firesides</placeName>&#8212;of your <persName>wives </persName>and <persName>childen</persName>, your <persName>friends</persName>&#8212;<persName>yourselves</persName>&#8212;
your <placeName>property </placeName>and your <placeName>country</placeName>, fellow S. the motives which have
caused you to take up arms is a sufficient guarantee that you will use
those arms as becomes brave <persName>men </persName>fighting in a just cause. You are
<persName>decendants of freemen</persName>&#8212;the <persName>decendants of brave soldiers </persName>also 
<persName>Americans</persName>&#8212;the blood that fills your viens has warmed the hearts of <persName>those
who fought in the American Revolution</persName> fought and conquered the
<persName>oppressors </persName>of American Liberty. Perhaps the spirits of your <persName>Fathers</persName>
watch over the conduct of their <persName>decendants</persName>, perhaps their eyes as
well as those of your <persName>friends</persName>, your <persName>countrymen </persName>and your adopted
Govt are upon you They see the great importance of the duties, 
before you, that the prosperity the safety of an infant and flourishing
new <placeName>colony </placeName>depends in a great degree on your bravery and good 
conduct in this first effort to humble and punish our <persName>enemies</persName>. Shall their
hopes, their prairs be disappointed&#8212;No. Your conduct since the first
commencement of this <placeName>colony</placeName>, the union and determined spirit that
now animates you are guarantees that the only obstacle to your 
complete tryumph will be the flight of your <persName>enemies </persName>before you can find
them.</p>
<p>The depradations of your <persName>enemies </persName>the <persName>W. and T. indians</persName> and there
hostile preparations, has driven us to the necessity of taking up arms
in self defence. The <placeName>frontier </placeName>is menaced&#8212;The whole <placeName>colony </placeName>is
threatened&#8212;under these circumstances it became my duty to call the<pb n="1318"/>
<persName>militia </persName>to the <placeName>frontier </placeName>to repel the threatened attacks and to teach
our <persName>enemies </persName>to fear and respect us.&#8212;It is with feelings of the deepest
regret that I have yielded to a sense of duty in agreeing not to go out
in person on this expedition, not because I think there is any 
necessity for my presence, or that the <persName>officers </persName>who command you will need
my aid, but because I wish to share equally with you in all your
labors, and all your fatigues in defending this <placeName>colony</placeName>&#8212;but my duty
to the <persName>settlers </persName>in attending to the unfinished business of the <placeName>Co</placeName>. and
completing the genl system for our defence which is in contemplation
to adopt and the wishes of the <persName>people </persName>strongly urged upon me 
requires that I should remain at <placeName>home</placeName>. I shall not be idle in your
absence. The command therefore of the expedition agreebly to the
militia law devolves upon <persName>Capt A. C. B [Aylett C. Buckner]</persName> and
the most prompt and attentive obedience to his orders is expected
from all the <persName>officers </persName>and <persName>men </persName>composing the expedition.</p>

<p><persName>Mr. John C. Quick</persName> has been appointed <persName>Adjutant </persName>during the 
expedition and it will be a part of his duty to drill the <persName>officers </persName>and <persName>men</persName>
and instruct them in their duty under the orders of the <persName>Commander</persName>
whenever it may be deemd necessary to do so&#8212;The utmost attention
is necessary to this part of your duties&#8212;A body of armed <persName>men </persName>
acting in union and with system are formidable, frequently irresistable
and always prepared to act on the defensive, whilst the same body
without discipline or system are incapable of acting efficiently on the
offensive and fall an easy prey to an attacking force.</p>

<p>Your own security, your own strength and your own interests
therefore requires that you should patiently and attentively attend
to drilling, and apply all your leisure moments on the march to this
highly important and essential branch of your duty&#8212;I present the
<persName>Adjutant </persName>to you recommended by a long course of practice in
 military duties both as an <persName>officer </persName>of the <placeName>U. S</placeName>. <persName>regular army</persName> and of <placeName>U. S.</placeName>
<persName>militia </persName>in active service, and also recommended as a man of honor
and confidence and I feel no hesitation in believing that you will find
him a valuable <persName>officer</persName>&#8212;and that you will strictly attend to his 
instructions&#8212;a rigid obedience to orders is the basis of all military
discipline and organization&#8212;The <persName>officers </persName>who command you are 
responsible for their conduct to their <persName>superior </persName>and their duty as well as
their honor imperiously requires strictest obedience to the orders 
issued to them so also with the <persName>privates</persName>, their duty as <persName>soldiers</persName>, and their
honor as such, as good <persName>citizens</persName>, requires the most rigid attention and
obedience or their part to the order they may receive from their
<persName>officers</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>This is the commencement of hostile movements on our part in the
only war of any consequence we have had since our settlement in this
<placeName>country</placeName>, and I feel confident that your decisive conduct on this first
expedition will so harrass our <persName>enemies </persName>that they will seek safety by<pb n="1319"/>
humbling themselves and sue for peace&#8212;Much however very much
depends on our first efforts&#8212;If we strike a decissive blow our future
peace and security will probably be the result</p>

<p><persName>friends </persName>and f&#8212;s I close by saying that your <persName>friends</persName>, your <persName>officers</persName>,
and your <placeName>country </placeName>are confident that you will do your duty as <persName>soldiers</persName>
fighting in a just cause, their prairs and blessings therefore go with
you&#8212;their welcome and thanks will hail your tryumphant return.</p>

<p><persName>[Stephen F. Austin.]</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
