<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1722">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>J E B Austin to Emily Perry, 05-26-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>J E B Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-12">08-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Emily Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brasoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Potosi, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 05-26-1829
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-05-26">05-26-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Rapid settlement of Texas. Cotton and sugar exports</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Brasoria Texas.</placeName> <date when="1829-05-26">May 26th 1829</date></p>
<p>Dr <persName>Sister</persName></p>

<p>I improve the opportunity which offers pr Schooner Eclipse, <persName>Cap.
J. Austin</persName> which Sails <date when="1829-05-27">to Morrow </date>for <placeName>N. Orleans </placeName>of Acknowledging
the recpt of Your letter dated the the <date when="1829-04-16">16 of April last</date>, the dispach<pb n="218"/>
with which it came (only 15 days from <placeName>Potosi</placeName>) has Made the 
immense distance between us Seem Shorter than ever before. So much
so Indeed that I have not wholly abandoned the anticipacion of Yet
embracing you under the roof of my own <placeName>Cabbin </placeName>in this <placeName>country</placeName>, and
from hints in your last letter, I really flatter myself that I shall have
that pleasure <date n="Fall - 1829">this fall</date>&#8212;our <placeName>country </placeName>is beginning to call the attention
of <persName>capitalists </persName>not only in the<placeName> U. S.</placeName> but in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, and I am fully
sensible that the period cannot be far distant when our fullest 
anticipaclons will be realized. I have nothing very interesting to 
communicate to you, the <placeName>country </placeName>is improving and <persName>Emigrants </persName>are 
dropping in almost daily. Crops look fine and we have every prospect of
an abundant harvest, about 500 hundred Bales of Cotton was made
last year for exportation and about sixty or 80 hogsheads of Sugar,
this year the Sugar crop will treble and a much larger Cotton crop
than ever before</p>

<p><persName>Brother </persName>is now on a visit with us, he begins to look quite old and
the wrinkles are becomeing plainer daily, I think<date n="Fall - 1829"> this fall</date> he will
visit <placeName>Missouri </placeName>he intended doing so <date n="SPring - 1829">this Spring</date> but, being anxious
to close all his <placeName>Colony </placeName>business he declined going in until it was
accomplished entirely.</p>

<p><persName>Eliza </persName>wrote you Sometime Since acknowledging the recpt of your
letter accompanied by a box of garden Seeds which was very 
acceptable&#8212;she has promised to write you by the Vessel, and out brag you
if possible, on <persName>Young Stephen</persName>&#8212;tho I say to her that odds are against
her for she has but one to brag on and You have half a dozen-
Remember me to <persName>Mr. Perry</persName> and tell <persName>Joel </persName>and <persName>Austin </persName>to improve their
time, I shall want <persName>Austin </persName>in about <date n="05-xx-1830">a year from this</date>, and in the mean
time keep him at <placeName>School</placeName>, and let him attend closely to Arithmatic,
as I expect to Make a <persName>business Man </persName>of him.</p>

<p>Write us often my dear <persName>Sister</persName>, I shall expect that you and <persName>Eliza</persName>
will keep up a steady correspondence&#8212;<persName>females </persName>can always find
Matter to fill one sheet and sometimes&#8212;two, to one another and
therefore I intend in future to resign my letter writing (to you)
principally to <persName>Eliza</persName>.</p>

<p>Kiss <persName>Mary </persName>for me and her <persName>Aunt </persName>who has promised me to send her
some pieces of Embroydery and drawings of her own execution as
soon [as] materials can be procured from <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName>.
<persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p><persName>J. B. Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>P S. <persName>Eliza </persName>begs you to excuse her for not writing by this 
conveyance, as she has been so engaged that she has not had time, but she
has promised me to write by the next opportunity</p>

<p>[Addressed] <persName>Mrs. Emily M Perry</persName> <placeName>Potosi Missouri</placeName> [by] Schooner
Eclipse</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
