<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1694">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>J E B Austin to Stephen F Austin, 03-18-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>J E B Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-10">08-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brasoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 193-194
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-03-18">03-18-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Coasting trade. Popular discontent with local government. Popularity of Austin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Brasoria </placeName><date when="1829-03-18">March 18th. 1829</date>&#8212;</p>
<p>Dr <persName>Brother</persName>.</p>

<p>The Eclipse sailed <date when="1829-03-18">this morning</date><placeName> from the mouth of the river</placeName> and
you may expect her by the<date when="1829-04-20"> 20th of next</date>.</p>

<p>The Little Zoe arrived to-day from <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName> <persName>Dr Gibson </persName>came
out with the intention of becoming a permanent Settler in the
 <placeName>Colony </placeName><persName>John </persName>thinks <persName>Mr Williams</persName> is mistaken in regard to the Seal
necessary for a clearance, the Patente or register&#8212;may perhaps 
require a $6. Seal but the registro or clearance is obliged to be on
one&#8212;however as he tells me the <persName>Consul </persName>at <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>, informed
him that Seldom two clearances were given alike&#8212;I anticipate no
difficulty on that head&#8212;</p>

<p>I came by the <placeName>Fort Settlement</placeName> and used my influence to push the
<placeName>Academy </placeName>forward but I am sorry to say I did not find one <persName>advocate</persName>
for it&#8212;Not because they were opposed to [it] altogether but owing
to the hands the funds for that purpose will be deposited in. I find
the<persName> Members of the Ayuntamiento</persName> unpopular throughout the <placeName>Colony</placeName>.
They all appear willing to subscribe for a <placeName>Jail </placeName>and <placeName>Academy </placeName>
provided a committee of responsible men be appointed to receive the
subscriptions, but as the <persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>is a changeable body they
are opposed to their having anything to do with it. Again, I find
something must be done as regards the admission of <persName>Lawyers </persName>in the
<persName>Alcaldy Court</persName> the people to a man are opposed to them, they evince
no disposition to be violent, or resort to violent measures but they are
determined to have them dismissed from the practice, and the 
measure that they are about adopting is to mildly petition the <persName>Alcalde</persName>,
to dismiss them altogether from the practice of law&#8212;</p>

<p>the <persName>people </persName>think that justice is often very lamely administered by
the <persName>Alcalde </persName>owing to the perplexity he incurs by hearing lengthy
and contending arguments, that frequently have no bearing to the
case in discussion&#8212;Also another grievance they complain of is this&#8212;
frequently a suit for a small amt is brought before the <persName>Alcalde </persName>where
one or both of the <persName>parties </persName>reside in another district, the <persName>sheriff </persName>is
sent with a process&#8212;and costs are accumulated to an amt that 
thribble the principal, the question is asked what are the <persName>Commissaryos</persName><pb n="194"/>
appointed for in the different <placeName>districts</placeName>, if these things could be
remedied, I think the <persName>people </persName>would remain quiet for a while&#8212;at
least untill they had another hobby to stride&#8212;Yourself it seems, at
present, is the polar Star, and the <persName>people </persName>look to you, and confide in
you to a man, to put matters to rights&#8212;I may say with propriety
that you are at present the <persName>most popular man in the <placeName>country</placeName></persName>, and
Your opinion will have more weight with the people generally than
all the clamour that now goes abroad.</p>

<p><persName>John </persName>informs me that <persName>Mr Smith the consul at <placeName>Matamoros</placeName></persName>, 
intimated to him that he wished to appoint a <persName>Vice Consul</persName> for this-
<placeName>Colony </placeName>and he stated to <persName>Mr Smith</persName> that perhaps I would accept the
appointment&#8212;and took the liberty of proposing me to him&#8212;I
should be willing to accept the appointment, and You will please
write to him on the Subject by the first opportunity lest some one
else may procure it&#8212;as I am informed one or two applications have
been already made to him on the subject.</p>

<p><persName>Elisa </persName>and the <persName>Boy </persName>are well and wish to be rememberd</p>
<p>
<persName>J B Austin  </persName>  [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
