<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1393">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Unknown to Unknown, xx-xx-1827</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-23">07-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1648-1649
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Extract from remarks made by Austin</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1827">xx-xx-1827</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Austin's toast on promulgation of State constitution.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p>Extract from remarks delivered by <persName>Col Austin</persName> after reading the
constitution of the<placeName> state of Q. and T.</placeName> at the time of its promulgation in <placeName>Austin Colony</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>You have heard fellow <persName>citizens </persName>of the Constitution of <placeName>Quahuila
and Texas</placeName> which has just been read, and I think you must have 
discover'd in it abundant manifestations of the liberal and enlightend
principles on which our adopted <persName>Government </persName>is founded. The
rights of the people are guarded with the utmost precaution,&#8212;the
security of persons and property solemnly guaranteed&#8212;the different
branches of the Government divided&#8212;the responsibility of public
<persName>agents </persName>is direct&#8212;the tryal by <persName>jury</persName>&#8212;recognized and the foreign 
<persName>emigrants </persName>legally settled in the <placeName>State </placeName>are placed on an equal footing
with all others in the exercise of the elective franchise and admitted
to all the rights of citizenship with the exception of eligibility to
certain offices of the State. The constitution is liberal and 
Republican and its just and enlightened administration must insure the
rapid advancement and permanent prosperity of the <placeName>State</placeName>. Should
experiance discover evils or embarassments in its details or 
operations a competent remedy is provided. The power of Amendment
rests with the <persName>people </persName>and the mode is not more difficult than the
importance of the subject requires.&#8212; Indeed when we take into
view the state of bondage and intellectual night from which the
<persName>Mexicans </persName>have so recently emancipated themselves, the entire 
difference of the federal republican System which they have adoptd from
all their former experience and the variety and conflicting prejudices
and opinions that were to be reconciled, there is complete 
astonishment and admiration at the steadiness and rapidity of advancement
in political Science and the perfection of their Constitutional 
Organization&#8212;</p>

<p>Fellow <persName>Citizens </persName>we have great and abundant cause for thankfulness
and gratitude, first to the great <persName>Author </persName>of All good, and Secondly
to the Government that has so munificently received us.&#8212;-   We emi-<pb n="1649"/>
grated to this <placeName>country </placeName>when it was a <placeName>wilderness</placeName>, by our labors we
have Settled and improved it&#8212; plenty now rewards our industry&#8212;
the charms of refined society, like the budding rose, is beginning to
shed their genial influence around us and the wild characteristics
of nature are rapidly disappearing before the March of enterprise
and civilization&#8212; we inhabit a <placeName>country </placeName>unparalelled for the 
Salubrity of its climate, and the value and variety of its resources&#8212;,
harmony and union and content now universally reign, and this day
presents us in the State Constitution with a Sacred guarantee of the
blessings we enjoy,&#8212; let us duly appreciate them, duly prize the
bounty of our Government and sacredly observe the obligations we
have this day entered into Let us continue true to the honest 
motives which induced our emigration true to the pure principles of
patriotism and gratitude; and we shall live respected by the good
of all <placeName>nations </placeName>retain the confidence of our <persName>adopted Gvt</persName>. and Secure
our permanent prosperity and happiness.</p>

<p>[Endorsed:] copy of Toa[s]ts and remarks of <persName>Col. A</persName> at the 
publication of the State Constitution <date when="1827-07-27">July 27 <date when="1827-05-29">[May 29],</date> 1827</date>, at <placeName>S. F.
de A</placeName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
