<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1208">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>B. W. Edwards to Stephen F. Austin, 07-21-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>B. W. Edwards</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-23">06-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nacogdoches, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1380-1386
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-07-21">07-21-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Describing abuse of justice at Nacogdoches and persecution and misrepresentation of his brother, Haden
Edwards.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName><date when="1826-07-21">July 21st 1826</date></p>
<p><persName>Colo Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Sir, After an absence of several months from this <placeName>province </placeName>to
the <placeName>United States</placeName>, where I was detained much longer than I had
anticipated in consequence of continued and serious indisposition,
I returned to this place about the <date when="1826-04-01">1st of April last</date>; and, much to my
astonishment and mortification, found everything in disorder and
confusion in <placeName>this section of the Province</placeName>. I had it at first in 
contemplation to return back to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and to abandon this
<placeName>country </placeName>forever; believing it my <hi rend="italic">individual </hi>interest to do so; but in
consideration of the <hi rend="italic">motives </hi>that induced me here, which was the
happiness and prosperity of <persName>hundreds</persName>, more than myself, and the
consequent effect that my abandonment of the <placeName>Country</placeName>, and my 
return to <placeName>Mississippi </placeName>would have produced upon my numerous <persName>friends</persName>
not only there but elsewhere I determined to remain, for a time at
least, an idle spectator of passing events, that I might be the better
able to determine upon a course for myself, which was to be 
decisive of the fate of so many of my <persName>relatives </persName>and <persName>friends</persName>, whose
confidence in me, in this enterprise, imposes a responsibility, truly
awful indeed&#8212;I have now been here three months and upwards,
hoping that order and confidence would be restored to this distracted
<persName>community</persName>; believing that the <persName>Government </persName>would bestow that 
attention to it, which its present condition so promptly and so 
imperiously demands.&#8212;but alas!&#8212;every mail brings, as it is said (for
we have no publication of government documents here) additional
cause of confusion amongst the people, and consequent distrust of<pb n="1381"/>
the rights and security of <persName>Americans </persName><placeName>on this side of the Sabine river</placeName>;
and the events of every day seem productive of new excitements
against the <persName>civil authority</persName> here, in consequence of proceedings and
decisions, believed to be incompatible with a <persName>republican government</persName>,
and contrary to the fundamental principles of the constitution of
the <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;From those considerations, I came to the determination,
a few days since, after mature reflection, to return to my <placeName>native
country</placeName>, where I have a sure guarantee of my rights, and security
of my person and property. I was preparing to carry this 
determination into effect, when I recd a letter from <persName>Haden Edwards</persName> at
<placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>, whose return I was daily expecting, informing me of
his intended absence for two or three months to the <placeName>U. S. of the
North</placeName>, and requesting me to take charge of his <placeName>colony </placeName>until his
return, and to do the best I could for his interest and the benefit of
the <placeName>Grant</placeName>&#8212;This request, together with the wishes of my <persName>friends</persName>
here, have influenced me, for the present, to remain longer, hoping
that some change may take place in the present aspect of affairs.&#8212;</p>

<p>Thus you see, I have taken upon myself a charge of much 
responsibility, which is greatly augmented by the peculiar embarrassment
of the affairs of <hi rend="italic">this </hi><placeName>Colony</placeName>, and which is not a little increased by
my ignorance of the Castilian language, and my want of 
information in relation to complaints and charges against my <persName>brother</persName>, which
seems to be almost the sole cause of all the difficulties existing here-
Having always felt a deep interest in the success of the <persName>Americans</persName>
in the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>, and being personally interested myself in
its advancement, I should have opened a correspondence with you
immediately upon my arrival here but for the unfortunate 
misunderstanding that <hi rend="italic">appeared </hi>to exist, much to my regret and 
astonishment, between you and my <persName>brother</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Although I could not believe that any just cause of difference could
have been intended on either side; yet delicacy, under existing 
circumstances, forbid that I should write to you in relation to the affairs
of the <placeName>Colony</placeName>, so long as there was a possibility of an unfriendly
feeling on your part against him and his <placeName>Colony</placeName>. Having received
an assurance on the part of my <persName>brother</persName>, that there was no disposition
on his part to commence hostilities, and that he had on the contrary
desired nothing more than a friendly understanding with you, as
well as all the <persName>Empresarios</persName>, I was not a little gratified to learn from
<persName>Colo Leftwich</persName>, and more recently from our friend <persName>Colo Pettus</persName> your
declarations of amity and friendship, which does away [with] any
restraint, I may have heretofore laboured under, in consulting with
you upon the affairs of the <placeName>country </placeName>of our adoption&#8212;</p>

<p>In consequence of the confusion into which every thing is thrown,
relative to the affairs of his grant, my <persName>brother</persName>, I suppose, thought<pb n="1382"/>
it best to make a tour through some of the <placeName>states </placeName>with a view of 
obtaining <persName>settlers </persName>as soon as possible, by means of interesting <persName>men of
<hi rend="italic">influence </hi>and <hi rend="italic">capital </hi></persName>in his grant. This he will do even at a great
sacrifice of his interest, if necessary. I was opposed to this 
expedition to the <placeName>States </placeName><hi rend="italic">at this time</hi>, and exacted a promise from him before
he set out to <placeName>Natchitoches </placeName>that he would defer it until he could bring
things to some issue with the government, which I had hoped would
have been done by this time.</p>

<p>After my arrival at this place, finding things in their present
train, I urged him to open a correspondence with the different 
<persName>departments of the Government</persName>, and to ask an investigation into his
conduct without delay. This he accordingly did more than two
months since; but as yet no reply to any of his communications, 
except a letter from the <persName>Political chief</persName>, not regarding his request and
remonstrance against false accusations, and the <hi rend="italic"><persName>characters </persName></hi>that have
made them, whose infamy is established by certificates of the highest
character, transmitted to him. Order after order has been 
transmitted here, containing censure of <persName>Haden Edwards</persName>, without any 
inquiry into the truth or falsehood of the accusations, presumed to be
made against him; and no list of charges furnished him even, to
give him an opportunity of self defence&#8212;In the first place orders
have been recently reca here by the <persName>Alcalda </persName>(as it is said) that <persName>Haden
Edwards</persName> was not entitled to charge any thing for <placeName>lands</placeName>. A more
recent order says, that all contracts already made may stand; but
that none hereafter made will be good, and that any person here-
after contracting to pay said <persName>Edwards </persName>for <placeName>lands </placeName>shall forfeit them
and be ordered out of the <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;A later order still says, that
said <persName>Edwards </persName>shall refund whatever he may have recd for <placeName>lands</placeName>,
making it the duty of the <persName>Alcalda </persName>here to compel him, should he
refuse&#8212;Another order a few days ago says that <hi rend="italic">this <placeName>town</placeName></hi> shall have
its original jurisdiction, (which is said to <placeName>extend to the Sabine on
the East</placeName> and <placeName>nearly to the Trinity on the West</placeName> etc) and that the
<persName>Junto </persName>alone and not the <persName>Empresaria </persName>shall dispose of said lands
within <hi rend="italic">said district</hi>&#8212;The last order said to be recd by tuesday's mail
directs the <persName>Alcalda </persName>to inform <persName>H. Edwards</persName> that unless he changes
his conduct (without informing him what it is complained of) that
his grant will be <hi rend="italic">taken from him</hi> and that he will be held amenable
to the <persName>tribunals </persName>of the <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;These two last orders if directed by
the government&#8212;if not forged or misrepresented here, speak an
awful warning to <persName>Americans</persName>!!&#8212;" There must be something rotten
in the state of <placeName>Denmark</placeName>"&#8212;</p>

<p>Whether here or elsewhere prejudice against <persName>Haden Edwards</persName> has
preponderated over justice in some department&#8212;I am slow to 
believe that those orders have eminated from the government itself.<pb n="1383"/>
It cannot be, that the fundamental principles of a free constitution,
cemented by the blood of thousands is thus early trampled under
foot, and its most sacred principles violated in the persons of 
<persName>Americans</persName>, after being invited into this <placeName>country </placeName>with a guarantee of their
rights and liberties&#8212;I have strong reasons to believe that there have
been some forgeries of papers here, and there exists too much 
evidence of the fact, that letters have been broken open, directed to my
<persName>brother </persName>before he recd them&#8212;This is my only hope of the fate of
the <placeName>colony </placeName>and consequently of the <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;If the government can
divest <persName>Haden Edwards</persName> of <placeName><hi rend="italic">half </hi>his grant</placeName>, they can divest him of the
whole in the same manner; and if they can, in violation of the 
constitution, <hi rend="italic">confiscate </hi>or declare a <hi rend="italic">forfeiture </hi>of his property, they can
in like manner divest every other <persName>Empresario </persName>of his rights: and what
security can any <persName>American </persName>feel, should this be the case, in the tenure
he may hold under them, or even the government itself?&#8212;</p>

<p>This is a question of serious import, and one that seems to be
coming <placeName>home </placeName>to the bosom of every reflecting <persName>American </persName>in this 
section of the <placeName>country</placeName>, friend or foe, who is apprised of said orders,
said to have been recd here. The fact is my friend, I am becoming
alarmed at the present indications of distrust and excitement, that is
manifesting itself every day among the <persName>Americans </persName>in <placeName>this section
of the province&#8212;</placeName>I am too well acquainted with the character and
feelings of the <persName>Americans </persName>not to feel uneasy at the present state of
things. It is reported and believed that <persName>Been </persName>has a <placeName>grant </placeName>to the
<placeName>Nuteral lands</placeName>; and yet the <persName>Alcalda </persName>is letting out said <placeName>lands </placeName>to his
favourites, suffering them to take the improvements of others, while
some rely upon obtaining their titles through <persName>Been </persName>or his 
<persName>commissioner</persName>, and all doubtful of the security of their lands eventually&#8212;
What so much adds to this confusion, is the abuse of justice and the
continual outrage upon the rights and liberties of the <persName>Americans </persName>by
the <persName>civil authority</persName> of this place, aided and supported by the 
celebrated <hi rend="italic"><persName>James Gaines</persName></hi>, and his <persName>followers</persName>, who seem determined to put
down every man, who will not bow in adoration to him, and who has
independance to be a <persName>freeman</persName>. This man by much affectation of
patriotism for this government, and by inducing the people to believe
his influence very great with the <persName>governor </persName>etc obtained a standing
with them, that has made him truly formidable to his <persName>enemies</persName>-
Having been active with others in organizing two regulating 
<persName>companies</persName>, the object of which was no doubt laudable <hi rend="italic">at first</hi> and has
done good, he now makes use of this <persName>auxiliary aid</persName> to oppress and
bear down every man, who is obnoxious to him, or who does not
approve of his policy of throwing the whole <placeName>country </placeName>into 
commotion, which he has done, for no other purpose than for his groveling
political views and self-aggrandisement.<pb n="1384"/></p>

<p>This very man, aided by a <persName>Spaniard </persName>here named <hi rend="italic"><persName>Sepulver 
[Sepulveda]</persName></hi> of infamous character, as well as himself; as the <hi rend="italic">records of
<placeName>Louisana</placeName></hi> bear witness, after acting with the utmost duplicity
towards my <persName>brother</persName>, has been the chief cause of all the evils that now
exist here, so much to the detriment of the <placeName>country</placeName>, and the almost
entire loss of confidence by the moving population of the <placeName>United
States</placeName>, who have been preparing to emigrate to this <placeName>Province</placeName>. It
is he and this said <persName>Sepulver </persName>that set themselves to work, upon the
arrival here of <persName>Haden Edwards</persName>, to create the alarm and to arouse
the prejudices of the <persName>Spaniards </persName>and even the <persName>American</persName>, upon which
they have predicated a thousand falsehoods, and fabricated the
many unfounded charges, made to the government, which seems to
have been taken for granted without an examination into the truth
or falsehood of the accusations&#8212;Having established himself now as
he supposes in the affections and confidence of the <persName>Political Chief</persName>,
he assumes the character of <persName>dictator</persName>, and arrogates to himself the
privilege of sending every man into banishment, who will not kneel
to his majesty, and acquiesce in his corrupt and tyrannical 
proceedings. We have just heard that he has decreed the expulsion of <persName>Judge
Williams</persName>, and <persName>Mr. Elisha Roberts</persName>, two of the most wealthy, 
intelligent, industrious, and useful <persName>citizens </persName>in the whole <placeName>Province</placeName>; but this,
together with other transactions of late, have developed to the people
his real character and designs, and, if I am not mistaken, he is now
tottering upon his throne.&#8212;I have been thus particular in reciting
the conduct of this man, because, contemptible as he is in talents and
character, he has done more to produce confusion here by falsehood,
intrigue, the abuse of <persName>Empresarios</persName>, and of the <persName>Baron de Bastrop</persName>;
and by the necessary effect of the loss of confidence in the 
government itself than every other man in the <placeName>Province of Texas</placeName>&#8212;The fact
is, the <persName>Alcalda</persName>, his <persName>brother in law</persName>, in [is] guided by him in all his
proceedings, being very ignorant himself, and a <persName>stranger </persName>to any
national feelings towards his <placeName>native country</placeName>, as, I am told, is his
boast&#8212;Twice since I have been here have the <persName>Militia</persName>, from the <persName>Aish
Bayou</persName>, been ordered to this place, under false pretexts of its being
the request of the <persName>government</persName>, and of making treaties with <persName>Indians</persName>
etc., when the only object indeed, was, in reality, to increase and to
create anew excitements, and, if possible, violence against my <persName>brother</persName>
to favour the designs of this petty <persName>demagogue</persName>, who makes it his
boast, that he will be the first <persName>member to Congress</persName> from <placeName>this section
of the State</placeName>. It seems now that the different <persName>chiefs of the tribes
</persName>of <persName>Indians </persName>in this <placeName>section of the Province</placeName> are to be assembled at this
place in a few days (for what purpose God only knows), at the
request of the <persName>Alcalda </persName>and his mighty <persName>counselor</persName>!&#8212;I was informed
by <persName>Genl Wavell</persName> while here, that <persName><hi rend="italic">Capt. Hunter</hi> the Indian agent</persName>,<pb n="1385"/>
appointed by the government for that purpose would be here, about
this time, to form treaties with all those <persName>tribes </persName>for the security of
the <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;What then can be the policy of the <persName>Alcalda</persName>'s tampering
with them prematurely, I cannot conceive!&#8212;</p>

<p>As to the administration of justice here, I can, through such a
medium, give you but a faint idea&#8212;Suffice it to say, that it is such
however as is alone conducive to the <hi rend="italic">interest </hi>of the <hi rend="italic">officers</hi>, and 
subservient to their private feelings against those, who are obnoxious to
them. Twenty and twenty five dollars costs is not an unusual fee
bill, or rather a <hi rend="italic">charge</hi>, in a single suit.&#8212;In short the darkest period
of the reign of <persName>Ferdinand </persName>does not equal the despotism, that prevails
here now!&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Col. Austin</persName>, these abuses and outrages upon the <persName>Americans </persName>will
not be tolerated long!! The rumbling of the volcano has already
become audible around us, and if any accident should cause its 
explosion in any part of its surface, not all <hi rend="italic">our efforts</hi> could arrest its
progress.</p>

<p>It is upon you then, that I mostly rely in <hi rend="italic">preventing </hi>the storm that
seems to be now coming in. It is your <hi rend="italic">interest</hi>, it is mine, and that
of every <persName>Empresario </persName>in particular to prevent, if possible, such a
state of things&#8212;</p>

<p>You already know <hi rend="italic">my views</hi>, relative to this <placeName>country</placeName>, and how
much it has been my hope and wish that it would <hi rend="italic">peacibly fill up</hi>
with enterprising <persName>Americans</persName>, without any interruption to their 
enterprise, or premature collision with the <persName>authorities </persName>of the <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;
But sir, I confess I am alarmed at the present aspect of affairs in
this <placeName>quarter</placeName>&#8212;I know the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>American </placeName>character</hi> too well to feel 
indifferent to what is passing here&#8212;Once shaken in their confidence of
this government, an outrage upon the rights or person of one 
<hi rend="italic">influential </hi>American will produce a spark of ignited matter, that will
kindle into a conflagration, which, we cannot doubt, will immediately
extend itself to the sympathies of the <persName><hi rend="italic">people </hi>of another 
Government</persName>&#8212;It has been from these considerations, that I have been inclined
to abandon the <placeName>country</placeName>, because I could see no advantage that was
to result from an event so probable&#8212;so inevitable&#8212;without a change
in affairs&#8212;</p>

<p>I have been thus free in my communication to you in consequence
of our former confidential conversations in relation to the affairs of
this <placeName>Province</placeName>, and in consideration of the mutual interest, we must
both feel in every thing relative to it, and conducive to its 
advancement and prosperity. I have already told you the <hi rend="italic">motives</hi>, that have
influenced me to continue any longer in this <placeName>country</placeName>, and I have
opened this correspondence with you in the most friendly confidence,
hoping to receive from you every <hi rend="italic">information </hi>and <hi rend="italic">advice </hi>as to what<pb n="1386"/>
steps had best be taken on my part, in the present attitude of
affairs&#8212;</p>

<p>I am pleased to learn that matters are progressing better with
you at present; but rely upon it my friend, that their continuance
there, and indeed the fate of the whole <placeName>country </placeName>depends upon the
<hi rend="italic">speedy </hi>adjustment of the affairs of this <placeName>colony</placeName>&#8212;I am sensible of
the importance of a personal interview with you; but this at present
is impossible&#8212;I hope to hear from you as <hi rend="italic">soon as possible</hi>&#8212;I should
deem a private conveyance much safer then by mail&#8212;Accept my best
wishes for your success, and believe me</p>

<p><persName>B. W. Edwards</persName></p>

<p>P. S. The <persName>Americans </persName>have been under the impression, that they
were exemp, under the colonization law, from taxation for ten years;
yet they are told now, that Orders have come on, requesting them to
pay <hi rend="italic"><persName>Sepulver </persName></hi>the most exorbitant prices for stamp-paper, which
seems necessary to give validity to <hi rend="italic">any </hi>instrument of writing 
between individuals, for money or what not&#8212;An <persName>acquaintance </persName>of mine
a few days since was compeled to pay $6 in making a transfer of a
<persName>negro</persName>, estimated at $400. Pray write me your views upon this
subject&#8212;                                                                               </p>
<p><persName>B W E_</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
