<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1769">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>R C Nicholas to Stephen F Austin, 10-11-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>R C Nicholas</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-15">08-15-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nashville, Tennessee</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 263-264
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-10-11">10-11-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Intention to settle in Texas, uncertain status of labor deters many, but great interest aroused in Tennessee and Kentucky. Prospect of purchase of Texas by the United States.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Nashville </placeName><date when="1829-10-11">Oct 11th 1829</date></p>
<p><persName>Col. Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Sir. I was much concerned in leaving your <placeName>country </placeName>without seeing
you, and having farther conversation; I left it with a fixed 
determination of returning as soon as possible and my health was not
restored until the <date n="07-xx-1829">July </date>or <date n="08-xx-1829">august </date>thereafter,&#8212; I descended the <placeName>river</placeName>
<date n="Winter - 1828">last winter</date> for the purpose, but hearing of the extreme indisposition
of my brother <persName>Maj. Carey Nicholas</persName>, I was obliged to go to 
<placeName>Tallahassee</placeName>, where I arrived in time to see him die, and was compelled
to administer upon his <persName>estate</persName>.</p>

<p>In the mean time I have constituted myself a sort of <persName>recruiting
sergeant </persName>for your <placeName>Colony</placeName>, I have said and done every thing in my
power to aid in its prosperity&#8212;it has now become a leading topic
in conversation, and one of the most interesting subjects of 
discussion in the <placeName>political papers</placeName>.&#8212;</p>

<p>A strong and simultaneous effort is at this moment making <placeName>from
the one end of the country to the other</placeName>, to induce this <persName>Govt </persName>to 
purchase it&#8212; I incline to the belief, that if the<persName> Mexican Govt</persName> will <hi rend="italic">sell</hi>
this <persName>Govt </persName>will <hi rend="italic">buy</hi>. I think that the prospects are so strong, as should
forbid a disposition to sell&#8212; The <placeName>Sugar lands</placeName> on the <placeName>Mississippi</placeName>
are selling for <hi rend="italic">seventy </hi>dollars the superficial acre&#8212;let the change
take place what will they be worth on the <placeName>Brassos</placeName>?&#8212;</p>

<p>Under all and every circumstance it is my fixed purpose to make
it my <placeName>future residence</placeName>, and I doubt not that one or two years 
experience will enable me to induce the greater portion of my <persName><placeName>Kentucky</placeName>
relatives </persName>to do the same.&#8212; Their doubts as to the health, the 
difficulty that presents itself to them as to <hi rend="italic">labor</hi>, the abandonment of
their <placeName>native Country</placeName> and <persName>government</persName>, are the stumbling blocks of
the present hour, Could these be removed the <placeName>Country </placeName>would be
filled immediately,&#8212;the unproductiveness of the Capital heretofore
engaged in the culture of Cotton, would fly there in Crowds beyond
your most sanguine hopes and calculations, I expect to be with
you the latter end of <date n="11-xx-1829">November </date>or first of <date when="1829-12-01">December</date>&#8212; I will come
in the double character of <persName>Uncle </persName>and <persName>guardian to the Hawkinses</persName>-&#8212;
and will be ready to take Such steps as you may suggest for the
division of the <placeName>property</placeName>,   I shall come prepared to sit down upon <placeName>one<pb n="264"/>
of the Leagues on the Oyster Bayou</placeName>,&#8212; My wish is to get the one
<placeName>nearest the Sea beach</placeName>&#8212; Should it be more valuable than any of
the others, I will be willing to pay the difference&#8212;that difference
being estimated by the intelligent and disinterested. As I shall come
prepared with men, tools provisions, seeds, and every description of
thing that the new <persName>settler </persName>would require&#8212;</p>

<p>The prime object of this letter is to induce you to point out and
designate the <placeName>league </placeName>that you may be willing or wish me to settle
on. For instance, I wish you to procure some <persName>surveyors</persName>, to go on
the ground, and remark and designate the league&#8212;leaving the 
istructions at <placeName><persName>Mitchell</persName>s</placeName>, or should there be no <persName>inhabitants </persName>at 
<placeName><persName>Mitchell</persName>'s former residence</placeName>, at <placeName><persName>Clark</persName>s</placeName> or some intermediate place, where
I may be sure to fall in with them, and thus save the time and trouble
of calling at your <placeName>residence </placeName>to obtain the information&#8212; If there
is no insurmountable objection to getting the <placeName>league next the ocean</placeName>,
I rely most confidently on your acquiesance,</p>

<p>I shall come prepared to become a loyal useful <persName>citizen</persName>&#8212;it is my
expectation and intention to be able to put up immediately a small
<placeName>steam Saw mill</placeName>, and to build immedeately a schooner for the 
<placeName>Coasting</placeName> trade&#8212;tho' so long neglected, I feel confident this is the most
valuable part of your <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212; with moderate luck, I think I shall
be able to exemplify this beyond a doubt, and in consequence, 
enhance the value of the lands-&#8212; I shall bring with me some choice
seed wheat, I wish you to select some <persName>planter </persName>to whom I will give it,
and thus have at once a satisfactory experiment made upon this
valuable grain.</p>

<p><persName>Ro. C. NICHOLAS</persName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
