<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1765">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Henry Austin to Stephen F Austin, 11-24-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Henry Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-15">08-15-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Comargo,Chihuahua</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 259-260
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-11-24">11-24-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Difficulties of navigating the Rio Grande.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Comargo  </placeName><date when="1829-09-24">Sept 24th  1829</date></p>
<p><persName>Col. S F Austin</persName></p>

<p>My deae Sir I wrote you from <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>, advising you of my
arrival there with a steamboat to commence the navigation of this
<placeName>river</placeName>. <placeName>Bravo del Norte</placeName> I have been up nearly to <placeName>Revilla</placeName>, where I
found the <placeName>river </placeName>so dangerous in low water that I did not think it
prudent to proceed up at <date n="Fall - 1829">this late season.</date>&#8212; At the 
commencement of the wet season the <placeName>river </placeName>May be Navigated quite to <placeName>presidio
del Norte,</placeName> but as that season is now nearly passed, I shall confine
My trips for the <date n="Winter-1829">winter </date>to this place</p>

<p><placeName>Between Matamoros and this</placeName>, the <placeName>river </placeName>is navigable and Safe
but I have great reason to apprehend there will not be business
enough to support the boat We have by law the privilege of taking
up lands but the <placeName>unoccupied lands on this River</placeName> are not worth
having.</p>

<p>I was induced to embark in this operation by the hope of 
retrieving my ruined fortune and of laying a foundation for an estate for
my <persName>family </persName>by Securing a large tract of land. Before leaving the
<placeName>US</placeName> I laid before <persName>Govt </persName>a Memoir on the <placeName>western boundary</placeName> pointing
out the advantages of exchanging the <placeName>land beyond the Rocky 
Mountains for those between this River and the U S</placeName> and suggesting the
Mode in which it might be effected had I a Sure conveyance I would
Send you a copy of it&#8212; I have reason to believe there is now a
negociation pending on the Subject-
Now I have reason to apprehend that my present effort will not
realize the expected advantages and some reason to fear it may result
in a failure&#8212;in which case, I should only be able to save my self
from ruin by taking the boat to some place where She could be
Sold or employed to advantage-</p>

<p>Can you inform Me whether the <placeName>laguna </placeName>which is laid down on the
<placeName>Map </placeName>as <placeName>extending from Brassas St lago to the Colorado River</placeName> is
Navigable with four feet water, if not by what rout could a 
Steamboat be transported <placeName>from the Mouth of this river to Galveston bay
or to New Iberia</placeName> Is there sufficient wealth produce and travel in
your <placeName>quarter </placeName>to employ a steamboat Could I obtain in your 
<placeName>neighbourhood </placeName><placeName>a tract of good land</placeName> in perpetuity either through you or by
application to the State</p>

<p>I wish extremely to have an interview with you but it is impossible
for me to leave the business I am engaged in even for three days&#8212;
I shall leave this in a week for <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>and return from there
with a cargo immediately&#8212;during the <date n="Winter - 1829">winter </date>I will be alternately<pb n="260"/>
<placeName>here </placeName>and at <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>as frequently as business May offer for the
boat and probably Make 2 or 8 trips pr month&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Henry Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
