<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1682">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Josiah H Bell, 02-24-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-10">08-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Josiah H Bell
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 172-174
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-02-24">02-24-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Political news from Mexico. Sees prospect of amending Federal constitution to permit religious toleration; thinks household worship will cause no trouble now, but wants no Methodist excitement. Plans for an academy at San Felipe.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1829-02-24">Feb 24 1829</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>The mail has this moment arrived&#8212;the subject of <placeName>foriegn </placeName>debts
is finally settled as you will see by the enclosed law which speaks<pb n="173"/>
for itself and needs no explanation&#8212;it is very full&#8212; The 
difficulties in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>are all settled. <persName>Guerrero is the President </persName>and 
<persName>Bustamante the vice President</persName>&#8212; <persName>Pedrasa</persName>'s election was set aside by
<persName>congress </persName>in the manner prescribed by the constitution on the ground
of fraud and corruption and <persName>congress </persName>then proceeded to elect from
the other persons who stood highest in the list, and at the first vote
<persName>Guerrero </persName>recd. 15 <placeName>States </placeName>and Bustamte <persName></persName>13&#8212;there are 19 <placeName>states </placeName>in
all so that this great question is now finally settled in a legal and
constitutional manner and tranquility is fully restored</p>

<p>The prospect of a change in the national constitution so as to
strike out the restriction on Religious toleration is so great and
brightening so rapidly that I have no longer any doubts that it
must and will take place, and under this belief I am of opinion
that no evils will arise from <persName>family </persName>or <persName>neighborhood </persName>worship, or
from the delivery of moral lectures, provided it is not done in a
way to make a noise about public preaching So as not to start
excited  <persName>methodist preachers</persName>, for I do say that in some instances
they are too, fanatic, too violent and too noisy,&#8212; Moral 
instruction delivered in that pure, chaste and dignified language and 
manner with which such instruction ought to be imparted to rational
beings, will certainly not be objected to by the Govt on the 
contrary it will be highly approved of.   I give this as my opinion</p>

<p><persName>Mr Pilgrim</persName> proposes to teach <placeName>school </placeName>I am pleased with him so
far as I have been able to judge&#8212; My opinion on this subject is
that we should all unite with a view of establishing a permanent
<placeName>Academy </placeName>at this place&#8212;</p>

<p>If we now commence on this basis, I have no doubt of succeeding,
and if the subject is pushed and properly laid before the Govt. I have
no doubt of obtaining a liberal endowment of funds&#8212; I fear that
a division in the minds of the people as to where the <placeName>Academy </placeName>ought
to be located would totally defeat the object, and for this reason I
am in favor of engaging <persName>Mr Pilgrim</persName> to establish a <placeName>School </placeName>here 
permanently and that measures be adopted without delay to raise funds
by subscription for a suitable <placeName>house</placeName>, large enough to accommodate
about 100 <persName>scholars</persName>&#8212;   I have drawn a plan which I send you</p>

<p>This subject is a very important one, it has always been a favorite
one with me, and I think an effort should be now made to get the
<placeName>school </placeName>under way, it can be added to afterwards&#8212;in fact it will
naturally increase as its reputation becomes known and I fear that
if the present opportunity passes of geting a permanent <persName>teacher </persName>
another may not o[ffer so] on.   I will however unite in support of any<pb n="174"/>
general plan to establish <placeName>Schools</placeName>, which will do the most public
good&#8212;</p>

<p>Please present my best respects to <persName>Mrs Bell</persName>. <persName>Mrs Powel</persName> <persName>Dr.
Wells</persName> and <persName>family </persName>etc</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>The subject of preaching must be managed with prudence, for I do
assure you that it will not do to have the <persName>Methodist </persName>excitement raised
in this <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;   All this is for your eye, and your confidential
<persName>friends</persName>, and not for the public indiscriminately</p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>J.H.Bell</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
