<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1264">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Jose Antonio Saucedo, 08-28-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-11">07-11-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Jose Antonio Saucedo
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1440-1443
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-08-28">08-28-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asking approval of a plan formulated by a local convention for maintaining a standing militia force on frontier.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Through my communication of the <date when="1826-08-14">14th Instant</date>, I informed your
<persName>Lordship </persName>that I had called a meeting of the <persName>people</persName>, to agree upon
some system of defence for this <placeName>section</placeName>, until the <persName>Government </persName>can
adopt measures for the protection of the whole <placeName>frontier of Texas</placeName>.
The <persName>board </persName>assembled on the <date when="1826-08-21">21st Instant</date>, and, after due deliberation,<pb n="1442"/>
we agreed upon the following articles, which are to receive the 
approbation of your <persName>Lordship </persName>before they are carried into effect.</p>

<p>Articles agreed upon by the <persName>Board</persName>.</p>

<p>First: All the <persName>militia </persName>of this <placeName>Jurisdiction </placeName>shall be organized into twelve <persName>sections</persName>; one section to be sent to the <placeName>frontier </placeName>every month, to do duty as <persName>spies</persName>, or <placeName>frontier </placeName><persName>guard</persName>.</p>

<p>Second: These <persName>sections </persName>shall include all the <persName>men </persName>living in this
<placeName>Jurisdiction</placeName>, whether resident in lawful possession of land, or not;
provided they are able to bear arms. All those who own <placeName>half a league
of land</placeName> shall be included in said <persName>section</persName>, even though he be exempted
from service in the <persName>National Militia</persName> Regulations, in consequence of
his age, physical impediment, or for other reasons; all those who
have <placeName>two leagues of land</placeName> shall be counted as two <persName>men </persName>in the 
organization of said <persName>classes</persName>; those who have <placeName>four leagues</placeName> shall be counted
as four <persName>men</persName>; and those who have more than <placeName>eight leagues</placeName> shall be
counted as five <persName>men</persName>.</p>

<p>Third: Those who have <placeName>half a league and upwards,</placeName> and are not
actual <persName>residents </persName>of this <placeName>Jurisdiction</placeName>, shall enter said <persName>classes </persName>and be
counted at the call of one man for each half league, up to two leagues;
above which quantity, they shall come within the provisions of the
following article. In case said <persName>persons </persName>should be absent and should
fail to supply a man in their place, they shall be considered as 
responsible for the ordinary rate of the hire of a <persName>substitute</persName>, which amount
shall be collected by the civil <persName>authorities </persName>and be paid into the 
Treasury of this Department.</p>

<p>Fourth: In case that any person should fail to serve at his time,
or to supply a <persName>substitute </persName>agreeably to these regulations, then the
<persName>Commanding Officer of the Militia</persName> of the <placeName>district </placeName>to which that
person may belong, shall hire a <persName>substitute </persName>to serve in his place, 
provided that such <persName>substitute </persName>shall not receive more than $40, a month,
to be paid in merchandize, or the productions of the <placeName>Country</placeName>;
and said <persName>Commanding Officer of the district</persName> shall forthwith make
his report to the <persName>Alcaldes of the <placeName>Jurisdiction</placeName></persName> in which the <persName>absentee</persName>
and the <persName>substitute </persName>hired in his place may reside; and the <persName>Alcalde </persName>shall
order the <persName>Sheriff </persName>to collect the amounts, due by said <persName>absentee</persName>, from
his property by a public sale of the same, the proceeds, when 
collected, to be paid to said <persName>substitute</persName>. In case of the sickness of any
of the <persName>men</persName>, the <persName>officers of the district</persName>, jointly with the <persName>Alcalde</persName>, may
relieve him from one tour of duty, but no more. <persName>Volunteers</persName>, shall,
in all cases, be received to supply the place of <persName>absentees</persName>.</p>

<p>Fifth: The <persName>Commanding Officer of the Jurisdiction</persName>, having a due
regard to the respective strength of the various <persName>parties</persName>, and in
conformity to the inventory of <placeName>lands </placeName>belonging to each person, shall<pb n="1442"/>
assess the number of the <persName>militia</persName>, that each <placeName>district </placeName>shall supply every
month, and he shall give corresponding orders to the respective 
<persName>commanding officers of the districts</persName>; and these <persName>officers</persName>, jointly with the
<persName>Alcalde</persName>, shall divide the <persName>men of their district</persName>, who are thus bound
to serve according to these regulations, into twelve <persName>sections</persName>, one for
each month, in a just and impartial manner.</p>

<p>Sixth. Said <persName>Commanding Officer of the Jurisdiction</persName>, shall, if 
possible, engage an <persName>officer </persName>to take the permanent command of the <persName>party</persName>
referred to in the first article of these regulations; and, if it be 
impracticable, from want of the necessary funds to pay the <persName>officer</persName>, the
said <persName>Commanding Officer</persName> shall detail from among the <persName>officers of
the Militia</persName>, one for every month, selecting those whom he deems
best qualified for that duty.</p>

<p>The object of the plan is to keep twenty or thirty mounted <persName>men</persName>
continually on the <placeName>frontier </placeName>as <persName>spies</persName>; as well for the preventing of
the incursions of small parties of <persName>Indians</persName>, as to give timely notice
should they come in force to make a formal attack.</p>

<p>The intention of the several articles is, to compel every one to 
contribute his share in the common defence in proportion to the interest
he has in the <placeName>Country</placeName>.</p>

<p>Some <persName>persons </persName>who have received and own lands here, have gone
to <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>in consequence of the <persName>Indian </persName>difficulties, thus hoping
to avoid being compelled to furnish their proportion towards the
defence of this <placeName>Jurisdiction</placeName>, alleging that the laws governing the
<persName>National Militia</persName> only require their personal service in the <placeName>district
in which they reside</placeName>, and that while they live at <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>they
are bound to do militia service there, and, that, therefore, they 
cannot be compelled to serve in this <placeName>Jurisdiction</placeName>, although all of their
property is here; adding, furthermore, the colonization law 
exempting the <persName>Colonists </persName>from taxes for some years, no taxes can be levied
on the property they leave here, and that to compel them to serve
in this manner amounts to a tax. Those who have <placeName>more than two
leagues of land</placeName> say also, that the law on <persName>Militia </persName>makes it obligatory
on them to be in readiness to serve personally, but that they cannot
be compelled to serve two, three or five terms more than any other
persons on account of the greater interest they may have in the
<placeName>country </placeName>alleging that it would be a tax imposed upon them in 
opposition to the colonization law.</p>

<p>I anticipate the most favorable results from this plan if there is
no impediment thrown in the way of its execution; and I pray your
<persName>Lordship </persName>to communicate to me such doubts as you may feel 
respecting its realization. If you approve it I wish you would send me
a formal approbation, with such corrections and additions as you<pb n="443"/>
may deem necessary, that I may publish and circulate it for the
information of all concerned.</p>

<p>God and Liberty.</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName>, <date when="1826-08-28">August 28th, 1826</date>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
