<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1924">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Emily Perry, 05-16-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-20">08-20-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Emily Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 375-376
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-05-16">05-16-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-20" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Glad that Perry is coming to Texas. Great field and future for men of education and talent. Removal of bodies of Mr. and Mrs. Moses Austin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>San Felipe</placeName><date when="1830-05-16"> May 16, 1830</date></p>
<p>Dr. <persName>Sister</persName>,</p>

<p>I was most agreeably surprised indeed by meeting <persName>Mr Perry</persName>
who hunted me up in the <placeName>Prairies </placeName>where I was engaged in surveying
the <placeName>land which has been granted to him by this Govt. </placeName>It appears
to be a singular coinsidence, that he found me on the very spot
where I presume we shall spend a large portion of the balance of
our lives&#8212; he is delighted with the situation and I think you also
will be it is on the <placeName>bay</placeName>, and is a very handsome and I think healthy
one&#8212; The <persName>boys </persName>can have their fill of fishing, and in the winter
wild fowl are numerous tho. he will tell you all about it</p>

<p>I have conversed with him relative to the removal of the bodies
of our dear <persName>parents </persName>and I highly approve of their removal to a
<placeName>church yard</placeName>&#8212; I think that the best place will be the <placeName>church yard
at St Genivieve&#8212;</placeName> They were recognized under the <persName>Spanish Govt</persName>,
as <persName>Catholics </persName>and there cannot be any objection to receiving them
there, or should the yard there be thrown open and uninclosed, I
should be in favor of taking them to <placeName>St Louis</placeName>, of this you and <persName>Mr
P.</persName> must be the judges but I am not in favor of taking them to
<persName>Potosi </persName>for the reason that the <placeName>burying grounds</placeName> there are all on
<placeName>private property</placeName> and may some day become <placeName>common Fields</placeName>&#8212; I
wish you would consult <persName>Mr Carr</persName> and <persName>Elias Bates</persName> on the subject and
speak to <persName>F. Valle</persName> relative to their admission into the <placeName>Catholic 
burying ground at St. Genivieve</placeName> If they are taken to <placeName>St Louis</placeName> I should
prefer the Catholic to any other, but will leave that solely to you
and <persName>Mr. Carr</persName>, to do as you think proper I do not know in
what <placeName>burying ground</placeName> <persName>Uncle and Aunt Elliott</persName> and <persName>Mrs Carr</persName> were
buried, and if they were taken tó <placeName>St Louis</placeName> I should wish if possible
that they be placed<placeName> by the side or near <persName>uncle and aunt Elliott</persName></placeName> and
<persName>Mrs Carr</persName> I wish that a plain decent tomb stone be procured, If I
should be in a situation to do it I will some day have a handsome
monument erected <placeName>over their graves&#8212;</placeName></p>

<p>I am really happy at the idea of your leaving that <placeName>cold region</placeName>,
I look forward to many days of peace and enjoyment in this 
<placeName>country</placeName>&#8212; I hope in a few years to free myself from all my debts and to
close my affairs here so that I may live a quiet and retired life in
the society of my <persName>sister </persName>and her <persName>family</persName>&#8212; we must provide a <persName>teacher</persName>
to live in the <persName>family </persName>and educate them well&#8212; by the time they will
be coming on to the <placeName>Stage</placeName>, <placeName>Texas </placeName>will present a fine field for <persName>men of
education and talents</persName>&#8212; <persName>Mr P</persName> will get Spanish bookes they all
ought to learn that language</p>

<p>I think that<persName> John Perry</persName> might pass his life more agreeably in this
<placeName>country </placeName>or in <placeName>Louisiana </placeName>than in that <placeName>cold region</placeName>.   I should be happy<pb n="376"/>
to see him here, tho I cannot take on myself the responsibility of
advising him to move for I presume he would wish to bring his
<persName>Slaves</persName>, and they could not be held as <persName>slaves </persName>by the laws now in
force here&#8212;</p>

<p>If <persName>Genl Hammond</persName> wishes to come I will befriend him all in my
power and assist him in getting <placeName>land </placeName>he would do very well here,
by proper industry and econemy and provide a foundation in <placeName>land</placeName>
for the future settlement of his <persName>children</persName></p>

<p>Bring all the papers and books of my <persName>Father </persName>and <persName>Bryan's</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Remember me to the <persName>children</persName>, tell them to be attentive to their
books and obedient to you and <persName>Mr Perry</persName> and I will give the <persName>boys</persName>
ponies and a little boat, and something pritty to the <persName>Girls</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I have seen your letter by <persName>Mr T. Browne </persName>and am glad that you
have learned not to attend to reports and rumors if you suffer
yourself to be made uneasy by them you will all the time be unhappy
after you start to this <placeName>country</placeName>, for you will hear a great variety of
them on the road and before you start</p>

<p>remember me to <persName>Mrs John Perry</persName> particularly and also to all my
old <persName>friends </persName>there&#8212;   I will visit that place some day</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName> [Rubric]</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
