<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1578">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Samuel Parkman to Stephen F Austin, 08-01-1828</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Samuel Parkman</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-07">08-07-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Petit Saw Bluff, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 85-86
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1828-08-01">08-01-1828</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-07" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Contemplates emigrating to Texas; asks Austin many questions about the country.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Petit Saw Bluff Missouri</placeName> <date when="1828-08-01">August 1st 1828</date></p>
<p><persName>Col Austin</persName></p>

<p>Sir A desire which I have for some time entertained to have a
knowledge of the distinguishing characteristics of the <placeName>Province of
Texas</placeName> has been of late much increased by the perusal of some of
your letters published in the <placeName>papers of this country</placeName>. I write at this
[time] to request a minut description of the <placeName>country </placeName>but the more
particularly of that part of the <placeName>country </placeName>in which you are established
I am under the impression that you have obtained of the <persName>Mexican
Government</persName> an extensive <placeName>Country </placeName>which you are now Colonizing,
For the sake of brevity I will condense the subjects of my enquiries
into the following questions. How far is your <placeName>Colony </placeName>from the
<placeName>Gulf Coast</placeName>? Is the country Mountainous or level. How Large are
the<placeName> Rivers Colorado</placeName> and <placeName>Brasos</placeName>? Do they in any considerable 
degree afford facilities for navigation? What proportion do the<placeName> rich
lands bear to the poor or barren lands</placeName>? I have taken the Idea that
<placeName>lands along the rivers</placeName> are extremely fertile but that the <placeName>intermediate
hills</placeName> were dry and barren. Am I right? Is it a <placeName>timbered Country</placeName>
What is the extent of your <placeName>grant</placeName>? Is it Surveyed? Is the <placeName>country</placeName>
in general explored and Surveyed? What enducements can you
hold out to a <persName>Surveror </persName>who is a complete master of the business in
all its branches? Are you in want of a person to assist you in 
making your map of the <placeName>Country</placeName>? Are the <placeName>unoccupied lands</placeName> in the
hands of the general Government of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>as in this <placeName>Country</placeName>?
What Route would you recommend to <persName>emigrants </persName>from the <placeName>States on
the Ohio River</placeName>. What time is required to Sail from your <placeName>Colony </placeName>to
the <placeName>port </placeName>nearest to the <placeName>City of Mexico</placeName>. I have now given you some
of the leading points uppon which I desire information. There
may be others which may occur to you if so I shall be grateful
for their insertion. I have an intention of visiting your <placeName>country </placeName>if
the prospects shall appear favorable. I am a <persName>Surveyor </persName>and in that
business would wish to be employed either in <placeName>Texas </placeName>or elsewhere in<pb n="86"/>
the <placeName>Mexican Provinces</placeName>. I am aware that the number of my enquiries
may intrude uppon your leisure but you may rest assured that in
giving me the desired information you will confer a verry 
particular favor and not only on myself but a verry considerable 
number of my <persName>acquaintances </persName>who have some Idea of emigrating I must
request that you will answer as early as convenient</p>

<p><persName>Samuel Parkman</persName></p>

<p><persName>Con Austin</persName></p>

<p><placeName>San Felippe de Austin Texas</placeName></p>

<p>P. S. If convenient I would be happy to see a small <placeName>map </placeName>of your
<placeName>colony </placeName>Direct to <placeName>Petit Saw Bluff La Fayette Co Missouri</placeName> via <placeName>St,
Louis Missouri</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
