<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1207">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John A. Williams to Stephen F. Austin, 07-19-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John A. Williams</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-23">06-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Ayish Bayou, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1379-1380
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-07-19">07-19-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Maladministration of government in east Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Texas Aysh Bayou</placeName> <date when="1826-07-19">19th July 1826</date>.</p>
<p><persName>Conl Austin</persName></p>

<p>Sir Although I have not the pleasure of your acquaintence, yet I
hope you will take no exceptions at my attempting to hold 
corrispondence with you, on a subject, which I deem important to every
<persName>emigrant </persName><placeName>in this section of country</placeName>.</p>

<p>The peculiar manner in which business has been transacted, for
some time, in this <placeName>settlement</placeName>, and also at <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>has, by no
means been satisfactory. Charges against <persName>individuals </persName>for 
immaginary crimes hitherto unheard of in a free <placeName>country</placeName>. Threats of 
banishment against several of the best and most worthy <persName>farmers </persName>in the
<placeName>District of Nacogdoches</placeName> who happen unfortunately to be, not of the
<persName>ruling party</persName>. These are the rewards we receive for leaving our 
<placeName>native country </placeName>and coming to participate in the liberties of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></p>

<p>The other day one <persName>James Williams</persName>, while in a state of intoxication,
made use of some ungarded expresions to the <persName>constable Johnson</persName>.
He, <persName>Williams </persName>was arrested, brought up before the <persName>Alcalde, Sprowl</persName>,
prosecuted, tried, and convicted, for speaking inflametory words
against the <persName>government</persName>, and has since, as I am informed, received
sentence of banishment.</p>

<p>I have good reasons to believe that depositions have lately been
taken against me for charges of simmiler nature. It is said by my
<persName>enemies </persName>that these depositions, has been, or shortly will be, forwarded
on [to] the <placeName>seat of government</placeName>, and that I am to have a secret trial.</p>

<p><persName>James Gaines</persName> is believed to be the prime mover of all these 
questionable measures. Who, if suffered to pursue with impunity, the
course which he has adopted, must ultimately, render the <persName>Americans</persName>
in this section of <placeName>country </placeName>odious to the <placeName>Mexican nation</placeName>, considerably
retard the progress of emigration and in the end produce consequences
the most dangerous to <persName>society </persName>The <persName>people </persName>are compleetly in a 
ferment, and what will be the consequences I am unable to say. But this
much I will venture to predict. Anull arbutary power, and 
tranquilety will be restored, It is said that <persName>James Gains</persName> has threatened
to emancipate all <persName>Elisha Roberts</persName>' <persName>negroes</persName>,  (about 30 in number)<pb n="1380"/>
These are only reports, I know not as to the truth of it. but it has its
effect in acting to the general confusion, and exciting the suspicions of
credulous man.</p>

<p>The people are willing and ancious to obey the law properly 
administered. But it is mortifying to the feeling of an <persName>American </persName>to stoop
to arbetary sway. I atribute none of our present difficulties to any
person but <persName>James Gaines</persName> and his <persName>understrapers</persName>.</p>

<p>I hope sir that you will have the goodness to inquire into our 
condition, minutely; and make such statements to the proper authority
or take such other measures as you may deem most expedient to 
restore tranquilety, and afford us that protection of person, property,
and civil rights, which the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName> has promised to the
<persName>strangers </persName>who come and settle in her <placeName>teritories</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Jno A Williams</persName>    [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
