<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1842">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Gideon Blackburn to Stephen F Austin, 01-19-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Gideon Blackburn</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-18">08-18-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Danville, Kentucky</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 322-323
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-01-19">01-19-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Wants to establish a settlement of 50 or 100 families and promote "literature and religion."  Inquiries concerning Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Danville</placeName> <date when="1830-01-19">Jany 19 1830</date></p>
<p><persName>Col. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Sir Though I have not the pleasure of a personal acquaintance,
yet perhaps my standing and character may not be entirely unknown
to you. I am now in the fifty eighth year of my age, have been a
<persName>minister of the Presbyterian denomination</persName> now more than 37 years
and for the last three years have held the <persName>Presidency of Centre
College at <placeName>Danville</placeName></persName>. I give you the information to prepare the
way for some inquiries I wish to make of you respecting the portions
of <placeName>country </placeName>held by you, and by some other <persName>Americans </persName>in the region
of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. My <persName>family </persName>are nearly grown and, including myself, we
have in the connection five <persName>ministers </persName>and I am disposed to make a
<placeName>settlement </placeName>some where that might bring together 40 or 50 or even 100
<persName>families </persName>and thus spend the evening of life amongst my <persName>friends </persName>in
promoting the cause of literature and religion; and leave them with
prospects of doing good in the <placeName>world</placeName>. I have thought of your
<placeName>country </placeName>but am not in possession of sufficient information to enable
me to make a fair conclusion and have therefore taken the liberty
of troubling you with the following enquiries. 1st Is your title
free from dispute. Also the other 2 or 3 <placeName><persName>American </persName>claims</placeName> in your
region;</p>

<p>2d Is there liberty of conscience and the free exercise of religion?</p>

<p>3d. Is the climate safe for constitutions formed in <placeName>Kentucky </placeName>and
<placeName>Tennessee</placeName>?</p>

<p>4th What is the quality of the soil generally, is it timbered
or naked. Will it admit a dense population or must the <placeName>settlements</placeName>
be sparse?<pb n="323"/></p>

<p>5th What is the quality of the water, are <placeName>springs </placeName>numerous and
wholesome&#8212; Are <placeName>streams </placeName>frequent and permanent, suited to 
manufacturing and commerce?</p>

<p>6th   Is yours a region of mosquitoes and full of fevers?</p>

<p>7th   Are you exposed to <persName>Indian </persName>ravages ?</p>

<p>8th   What proportion of your settlement is <persName>French </persName>or <persName>Spanish</persName>?</p>

<p>9    What is the state of improvement in your society, in 
agriculture, commerce, education, and religion ?</p>

<p>10    Will the <persName>Mexican government</persName> seriously oppose the <placeName>U. S.</placeName>
extending to the <placeName>Del Norte</placeName>?</p>

<p>11    Are the present <persName>settlers </persName>satisfied with the <persName>government </persName>which 
they are under.   Can they enjoy to a good degree the right of self
government?</p>

<p>12    What bounties would be granted to <persName>settlers </persName>especially to such
a settlement as stated above? It would contain many literary 
<persName>characters </persName>and perhaps from 20 to 30 young <persName>men </persName>who have nearly
finished a classical course. What is the usual price for land by
purchase?</p>

<p>13    What are the ordinary expenses of living? Can the 
necessary and absolute conveniences of life be easily obtained ?</p>

<p>14    What is the best mode of approaching your <placeName>settlement</placeName>,
whether by water by the<placeName> mouth of the Brazos</placeName> or by <placeName>Red River</placeName> if
by the latter the point of debarcation and the distance by land
from that point and also the practicability of the route?</p>

<p>15    What is the size of your <placeName>grant</placeName>? What of <persName>Milams</persName>, of 
<persName>Leftwich </persName>and do they lie contiguous ?</p>

<p>Should you be kind enough to favor me with information on
this subject please direct your communications to <persName>Gideon 
Blackburn President of <placeName>Centre College Danville Kenty</placeName> </persName>and I will be
happy to receive it as soon as you might find it convenient.</p>

                                                                  <p>   <persName>GiDn Blackburn</persName></p>

<p><persName>Col. Austin   Commandant of Texas.</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
