<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1506">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James F Perry to Stephen F Austin, 03-02-1828</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James F Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-30">07-30-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        James Cole
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Potosi, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Province of Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 20-22
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1828-03-02">03-02-1828</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Conditions in Missouri. Local political news.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Potosi Missouri March 2d 1828</p>
<p>Dear <persName>Friends</persName>.</p>

<p>We take the opportunity of writing to you by <persName>Mr James Cole</persName> who
says he is going directly to your <placeName>Country   </placeName>we feel anxious to hear<pb n="21"/>
from you as we have not heard from you for a long time, the last
letter we had was from <persName>James </persName>dated in <date n="07-xx-1827">July </date>or <date n="08-xx-1827">august </date>last in which
he said he expected to [be] a married man on the<date when="1828-10-03"> 3d of Oct</date>. We
have not heard neether by letter or otherwise since we wrote you
on the <date when="1828-07-22">22d of July</date> last respecting some Land in <persName>Wyth County 
Virginia</persName> also a Tract in <persName>Newjersay</persName> we also wrote you on the <date when="1828-08-12">12th of
august</date> on the same subject none of which we have had a reply to
on <date when="1828-07-22">22d of July</date> we enclose [d] to you a note on <persName>Bartlet Sims</persName> in favr of
<persName>Alfred Sougroun</persName> for $788.61. please say whether you recd it and
if so what prospect there is for collecting the money. In <persName>Stephen</persName>s
letter to us of the<date when="1827-05-26"> 26th of May last</date> he expresed a wish for me to
visit that <placeName>country </placeName>last fall I feel anxious to see the <placeName>Country </placeName>but
the situation of my business would not permit me to leave it nor is
my prospect any better at preasant. Now our <persName>Family </persName>is all well at
preasent but it has pleased divine providence to deprive us of our
little daughter <persName>Emely</persName>. she was taken sudenly and died in a few
hours without any previas sickness the shock was verry great the
loss of a near relation is surely felt but no one knows the feeling of
a <persName>parent </persName>but a parent. We have since had another added to our
famaly a <persName>daughter </persName>about 2 months old we call hir <persName>Eliza Margrett</persName>.
the boys <persName>Joel</persName> <persName>Austin </persName>and <persName>Guy </persName>are going to school and I think
progress as well as boys of there age could be expected. I know of
no material change among your old <persName>acquantences </persName><persName>W C. Carr</persName> is our
circuit <persName>Judge </persName>he was here two weeks since we have a great many
enquiries for you all your old <persName>acquantences </persName>and <persName>friends </persName>apear
anxious to hear how you are doing Business is very dul here at
present the great emigration within the last year to the <placeName>Fever
River Mines </placeName>togather with the low price of Lead has made business
verry dull Lead is only worth now at the <placeName>river </placeName>$4.50 and but $5.60
in <placeName>Phila Potosi</placeName> has been and is still improving some we are now
living on the lots formaly owned by <persName>Josiah Beardsley.</persName> I expect you
recollect where they are we have got a small but comfortable house
built and are making some other improvements and in a short time
will be tolarably conveniantly fixed for living our <placeName>country </placeName>has 
improved since you left this <placeName>country </placeName>but not near as much as might
be expected <placeName>St Louis</placeName> is improving rapidly. <persName>S Perry</persName> has 
purchased <persName>part of old Chouto lot opposit the market</persName> in that place and
is building a house in it that he has rented for $1828. pr annum,
the aproching presidentle Election creates a great interest: party
spirit runs very high the <persName>members of Congress</persName> in all there offitial acts
are verry much governed by party spirit, and it has a great 
influeance in all our state Elections and Legislational proceedings 
Administration and Anti administration <persName>Adams </persName>and <persName>Jackson </persName>Internal
improvements and state rights are the subjects of differance.   I<pb n="22"/>
think it will be a close contest   it is uncertain who will be the next
<persName>President </persName>the <persName>friends </persName>of each are verry sanguine. I know of 
nothing more interesting to write you excuse the scrawl as I have not
time to copy   <persName>Mr Cole</persName> is just starting   write to us offener</p>
<p><persName>J. F and Emily Perry</persName></p>

<p><persName>Mr. S. F. Austin</persName> &amp; <persName>J. B Austin</persName></p>

<p>Give our best respects to our new <persName>sisterinlaw</persName> if we have one
[Addressed:] <persName>Col, Stephen F Austin</persName> or <persName>Jas B Austin</persName> <placeName>San Felipe de Austin Provance of Texas</placeName>politeness of <persName>Mr James Cole</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
