<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1454">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William S. Parrott to Stephen F. Austin, 11-07-1827</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William S. Parrott</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-26">07-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Saltillo, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1707-1709
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1827-11-07">11-07-1827</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Masonic political organizations in Mexico&#8212;York and Scotch rites. Political conditions. Poinsett.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1827-11-07">Nov. 7th 1827</date></p>
<p><persName>Stephen F Austin Esqr</persName></p>

<p>My Dear Sir It is with heartfelt pleasure I now acknowledge
receipt of your much esteemed favour of the <date when="1827-10-22">22nd ulto</date> &#8212; As it is
presumable <persName>Mr Almy</persName> may have given you some of the most 
remarkable occurrences with me of late. I shall proceed without ceremony
to your many <hi rend="italic">preguntas </hi>Much excitement has and still exists
among more properly speaking the <persName>Patriots </persName>and <persName>anti republicans</persName>
than between the <persName>masonic brethren</persName> for what, we call <persName><hi rend="italic">Yorkoino </hi></persName>is
strictly speaking <persName>whig</persName>, with us and <hi rend="italic"><persName>escoseses </persName></hi><persName>Tory </persName>&#8212; Some name
of distinction was necessary and as the <persName>parties </persName>became better known
about the time we established the <persName>York </persName>writ &#8212; and as every true
<persName>american </persName>flocked to our standard we were in a short time able to
outweigh the <persName>anti-republicans</persName> or <persName>Scotch party</persName> and they began 
immediately to make a bug bar of <persName>yorkism </persName>and to charge <persName>Mr Poinsett</persName>
with the crime of introducing a system or machine by which he 
intended to carry on all his intrigues a thousand ugly things have
been said and his answer to the <persName>congress of <placeName>Veracruz</placeName></persName> which I now
hand you will give you some Idia of what they wished to make him
appear before the public    So much for the <persName>Scotch </persName>and <persName>yorkism</persName></p>

<p>If you have a wish to forward a petition to the <placeName>grand lodge</placeName>, I
will see that you have your <placeName>charter</placeName>, to this effect you will form
a <placeName>lodge </placeName>in your <placeName>settlement </placeName>and extend a petition to the <placeName>grand lodge
of Mexico</placeName> signed by all the <persName>members </persName>and <persName>provisional officers</persName>; The
<placeName>charter </placeName>will cost you perhaps 50$ though I recollect of having paid
30$ for the <placeName>charter </placeName>of a <placeName>lodge </placeName>in <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>. Please see <persName><hi rend="italic">Jesus </hi>Ma Ybarra</persName>
of that place from whom you can get all necessary information and
to whom please present my best respects &#8212; Fear not but the 
<persName>Yorkinos </persName>will gain the day. the poor <persName>Scotch </persName>are making their last
struggle I have no doubt but the true object of <persName>masonry </persName>has been
in some measure perverted with us; but at the time when the 
salvation of the <placeName>country </placeName>perhaps &#8212; depended, upon such a measure<pb n="1708"/>
and when it became necessary to try their strength which 
manifested itself in the last elections Much to the mortification of the
<persName>Scotch Gentry</persName> and fortunately about that time the plan of <persName>Padre
Arenas</persName> was discovered in which some of their <persName>Chieftains </persName>were 
complicated, I am so far from believing that the establishment of a
<placeName>lodge </placeName>by the <persName>americans in <placeName>Texas </placeName></persName>would prove injurious that I would
give my vote, and whole influence to carry into effect such a 
laudable purpose, and would prove to be another spoke in our wheel of
transcendent importance for your <persName>settlers </persName>are spoken of in the
highest terms and it has been made public and generally believed
that your settlers put a stop to <persName>Edwards Fields</persName> etc &#8212;</p>

<p>We have had for some time a state of things heretofore unknown
with us owing to the intrigue of the <persName>Scotch </persName>to get possession of the
reins of <persName>Government </persName>but they have so completely failed that I am
convinced they will have to give over their point, at least for the
moment and the great outcry seem to be in all parts, Expulsion of
the old <persName>Spaniard</persName>. In <placeName>Michoacan Durango</placeName> to the <placeName>south </placeName>and other
parts parties of considerable force have taken up arms against them
and have committed some excesses. The States of <placeName>Xalisco </placeName>and
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>have passed laws expelling certain <persName>classes </persName>from their 
<placeName>territories </placeName>and particularly <persName>Mexico </persName>for having published its decree on the
<date when="1827-10-27">16th ulto</date>. expelling all <persName>Spaniard friars</persName>&#8212;so far so good&#8212;I have
just had a private interview with the <persName>President</persName>. He assures me
all will go well he is a true <persName>Patriot </persName>but slack of energy&#8212;which by
the bye turn out with the mañana folks to be often preferable at
least in the present case I have no doubt of the fact We had formed
a <placeName>grand lodge</placeName> and 5 <placeName>symbolic lodges</placeName> when <persName>Mr Poinsett</persName> arrived in
the <placeName>country </placeName>he became a <persName>member </persName>and through his agency we 
received our <placeName>charters </placeName>from <placeName>New York.</placeName> We are somewhat in your
case respecting the abolition of slavery though not to the same
extent; they propose an indemnification to <persName>slave holders</persName> and in
cases where a <placeName>state </placeName>is not able to make indemnition; the right of
<persName>property </persName>is certainly attacked in the most flagrant manner. I hope
you will have it repealed or the same principle of indemnity adopted
by which we have been blessed-</p>
<p>It is difficult to guess who will be the next <persName>President </persName>I have no
doubt but he will be an <persName>american </persName>and <persName>Patriot </persName>some speak of 
<persName>Guerrero</persName>, <persName>Pedraza </persName>etc etc I admire the decided character of the former
but the latter possess[es] more qualifications than any other man
in the <placeName>Republic </placeName>this is my opinion, The <persName>Scotch </persName>will try to get
in <persName>Bravo</persName>&#8212;or some other <persName>Scotch brother</persName> The System of government
for the <placeName>territory </placeName>is something like ours&#8212;The <persName>President </persName>is their
executive, a representative or <persName>Delegate in the House of 
Representatives</persName>, a <persName>judiciary </persName>something like our <persName>territorial governments</persName> and
as respects <placeName>interior </placeName>economy,   they have a <persName>governor </persName>etc etc<pb n="1709"/></p>

<p>In short I am convinced that differences must arise from the union
of two <placeName>states </placeName>composed of different materials like <placeName>coahuila and
Texas</placeName>&#8212;and that a better plan might be to separate the practicability
of which you should better know than myself. The only material
inconvenience which strikes me at this time is the delay of the 
dispatch of affairs Subject to the executive, department for the rest
your situation might be bettered,</p>

<p>It was my intention to be more concise but have been led astray by
a [desire] to satisfy your many enquiries] [some] of which requires
a more expert [hand] than mine to do them justice I have always
avoided political correspondence from motives, which have in some
measure subsided, and will now with pleasure do all I can to Quench
your thirst&#8212;</p>

<p>I shall leave <placeName>Mexico </placeName>for the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> in the <date n="02-xx-1828">month of February next</date>,
it would have been sooner but for the unexpected delay of My 
copartner <persName>Willson </persName>in the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> he will be out in the packet for this
month. Hoping to hear from you often, I remain sincerely your
friend obt. and humb servt</p>

<p><persName>W. S. Parrott  </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p>I have a file of <placeName>New York papers</placeName> on the road and if they arrive
in time for the mail [will] hand you a few</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Sor Don. Estevan F. Austin</persName> <placeName>Saltillo</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
