<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1108">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William Pettus to R R Royall and Austin, 05-16-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William Pettus</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-09">06-09-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        R R Royall 
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1096-1098
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Deed of Trust</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-05-16">05-16-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Deed of trust to secure lien on slaves.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Sello 2° 12 rrs. Habilitado por la <placeName>Nación Mexicano</placeName> pa. el año de
<date n="xx-xx-1825">1825</date></p>

<p><persName>Austin</persName></p>

<p>Whereas <persName>William Pettus</persName> formerly of the county of <placeName>Lawrence </placeName>and
state of <placeName>Alabama </placeName>in the <placeName>United States of North America</placeName> and at
present a <persName>setler </persName>in <placeName>Austins Settlement</placeName> in the department of <placeName>Texas</placeName>
of the <placeName>State of Cuahuila and Texas</placeName> of the <placeName>United Mexican States</placeName>
Heretofore to wit on the <date when="1821-03-06">sixth day of March in the year 1821</date> 
executed to<persName> Thomas Bibb</persName> and <persName>Daniel Coleman</persName> a deed of Sale in Trust
to certain <persName>Negroes </persName>therein named to secure the payment of certain
monies which will also more fully appear on the face of said deed
of Trust and the said <persName>William Pettus</persName> being disposed to strengthen
the security of Said money to <persName>Richard R Royall Attorney</persName>  in fact
of the <persName>Trustee Daniel Coleman</persName> have agreed to convey to <persName>R R Royall</persName>
and <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> the <placeName>Lands </placeName>herein after described in Trust
and upon the conditions herein after expressed</p>

<p>This Indenture made and entered into this <date when="1825-05-16">16th day of may 1825</date>
by and between the said <persName>William Pettus</persName> of the first Part the said
<persName>Richard R Royall</persName> of the second Part and <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> of
the third part. Therefore witnesseth that the said <persName>William Pettus</persName>
for and in the consideration of the premices and for the further
consideration of one dollar to him in hand paid by the said <persName>Stephen
F Austin </persName>before the ensealing and delivering of these presents the
receipt whereof he doth hereby acknowledge hath Granted bargained
and sold and by these presents doth Grant Bargain and sell to the
said <persName>R R Royall</persName> and <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> the following <placeName>tracts of land</placeName><pb n="1097"/>
the <placeName>uper half of league of Land  </placeName>situated on the <placeName>eastern Bank of
the Brassos River</placeName>Bounded by <persName>William Hall</persName> on the <placeName>uper side</placeName> and
<persName>Francis Bigum</persName> on the <placeName>lower side</placeName> and also the <placeName>uper half </placeName>of a league
of land on the <placeName>Western Bank of the Colorado River</placeName> <placeName>Bounded on
the uper side by </placeName><persName>Thomas Westall</persName> Granted to said <persName>Pettus</persName> by the
<persName>Mexican Government</persName> by the concession dated the <date when="1824-07-10">10th of July 1824</date>&#8212;dividing each league so as the fronts on the river of each whole league
shall be equally divided and runing thence in a Straight direction
so as to divide the league equally to have and to hold the said Tracts
of land to the said<persName> R R Royall</persName> and the said <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> their
<persName>heirs </persName><persName>administrators </persName>and <persName>Executors </persName>in Trust nevertheless and upon
the conditions following that is to say if said <persName>William Pettus</persName> shall
pay to said<persName> R R Royall</persName> or in his absence to the <persName>Trustee Stephen
F Austin</persName> on or before the <date when="1825-11-15">15th day of September 1826</date> forty Good
merchantable mules of Reasonable age, of Good order for the Road
and of a suitable size for the Plough and it is also understood said
<persName>Royall</persName> is not to receive such wild mules as are caught wild out of
the <placeName>Range </placeName>and the said <persName>Royall </persName>agrees to accept said mules in 
discharge of fifteen Hundred dollars in discharge of part of said deed
of sale upon Trust executed to <persName>Bibb</persName> and <persName>Coleman </persName>and to give full
and faithful credit upon the same. But If the said <persName>Pettus </persName>shall fail
to make payment Punctually on or before the <date when="1825-11-15">15th day of September
1825 </date>delivering the said mules at <placeName>San Felippe de Austin</placeName> then the
said <placeName>Stephen F Austin</placeName> shall proceed to sell to the highest bidder in
the Town of <placeName>San Felippe de Austin</placeName> the said<placeName> half leagues of land
</placeName>giveing fifteen days notice of said sale and the sale shall be for cash
in hand which shall be immediately applyed to <persName>Pettus</persName> credit on said
Trust after deducting costs of sale and the said <persName>Pettus</persName> hereby 
empowers said Austin to sell Deed and Put the <persName>Purchaser </persName>in 
Possession of said <placeName>Lands </placeName>without consulting said <persName>Pettus</persName> thereon and said
<persName>Royall </persName>agrees provided said <persName>Pettus </persName>shall punctually Pay said forty
Mules of Quality etc as expressed to release from the Deed of Trust
executed to <persName>Thomas Bibb</persName> and <persName>Daniel Coleman</persName> <persName>Negroes Edmund</persName>,
<persName>Joe</persName>, <persName>Anacy </persName>and <persName>Mima </persName>but in no wise to lessen the effect and force
of said deed of trust till said delivery of mules is punctually 
complyed with and then only to the four <persName>negroes </persName>above expressed and
said deed to have full effect in all other relations expressed therein
and also the note of hand which accompanys it and was its origin
and all parties here present agree to accept of these presents in all
its forms and said <persName>Austin </persName>agrees to execute the Trust hereby 
reposed in him to the best of his ability, and faithfully to pay over
the money arising from the said sale of the Land should it be 
necessary after dediMing the expences of the sale in Testimony whereof<pb n="1098"/>
the parties have hereunto set their hands and affixed their seals this
,<date when="1825-05-16">16th day of may 1825</date> as above,</p>
<p>Witnesses Present</p>

<p><persName>Wm Pettus</persName>                  [seal]</p>

<p><persName>R R Royall  </persName>                [seal]</p>
<p>aty in fact of <persName>Daniel Coleman</persName></p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>    [seal]</p>

<p>Witness</p>
<p><persName>Samuel M Williams</persName></p>
<p><persName>Jno P Coles</persName></p>
<p>To prevent all misunderstanding in relation to the meaning of the
within deed of Trust it is clearly understood that the <placeName>land </placeName>deeded in
the Trust is to be totally released from all lien whatever and reverts
to said <persName>Pettus </persName>on the payment of the forty Mules punctually as 
stipulated and it is not the intent of this deed to give any other lien on
the land except for this payment of the fifteen hundred dollars in
case of a failure to pay the Mules as expressed but the <persName>negroes </persName>shall
not be released as If the payment of the mules had been punctually
made but both land and <persName>negroes </persName>be held subject, the land to this and
the <persName>negroes </persName>to the old Trust executed to <persName>Bibb </persName>and <persName>Coleman </persName>and all
parties here present agree to accept of this with all the force and
effect as If it had been incorporated in the body of the deed Given
under our hands and seals the same day <date when="1825-05-16">16th of May 1825</date></p>

<p><persName>Wm. Pettus </persName>               [seal]</p>
<p><persName>R R Royall</persName>                [seal]</p>
<p>Aty in fact of <persName>Daniel Coleman</persName></p>

<p><persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>    [seal]</p>
<p>Witnesses</p>

<p><persName>Samuel M Williams</persName></p>
<p><persName>Jno P. Coles</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
