<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1115">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Mateo Ahumada, 04-06-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-10">06-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mateo Ahumada
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1304-1305
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-04-06">04-06-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Quoting a report of April 4, by Capt. Ross of the destruction of a party of marauding Tahuacanos.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>The <persName>Captain of the Militia of the <placeName>Colorado District</placeName>, James J. Ross</persName>,
transmitted to me the following report bearing date of the <date when="1826-04-04">4th Instant</date>.</p>

<p>"In compliance with your orders of the <date when="1824-03-28">28th of last March</date>, in which
you inform me that a party of <persName>Tahuacanos </persName>had left their <placeName>villages</placeName>
on their way to the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>, under the pretext of looking for the
<persName>Tancahues</persName>, and order me to watch and attack them if they should be
seen in this <placeName>neighborhood</placeName>; I lost no time in sending <persName>spies </persName>to the
<placeName>frontier</placeName>, and <date when="1826-04-05">yesterday</date>, at noon, I received information that sixteen
<persName>Indians </persName>of said <placeName>nation </placeName>had arrived near the settler <placeName><persName>Asa Anderson</persName>'s
house</placeName>, about <placeName>five Leagues below the road to La Bahia</placeName> on this <placeName>river</placeName>.<pb n="1305"/>
I collected the <persName>militia</persName>, and by ten o'clock at night, I mustered 
thirty-one <persName>men</persName>, with whom I marched eight Leagues, and attacked the 
<persName>Indians </persName>at daybreak. It was not an easy matter to get at them in their
position; they were on a deep <placeName>creek</placeName>, the banks of which are covered
with a dense thicket and chaparal, which induced me to divide my
<persName>men </persName>into two parties. One <persName>party </persName>under the command of <persName>Lieutenant
Rawson Alley</persName>, commenced the attack in front, from the bank of the
<placeName>creek</placeName>, while I took position with the other <placeName>in the bottom of the little
run</placeName>, above the place where the <persName>Indians </persName>were so as to be able to fire
on them when they crossed the <placeName>creek</placeName>. This disposition had a good
effect. At the first fire of <persName>Alley's party,</persName> the <persName>Indians </persName>ran for the 
<placeName>bottom</placeName>, and there received a volley from my party. Eight <persName>Indians </persName>fell
<persName>dead</persName>, and five were <persName>wounded </persName>and escaped to the thicket. We took
five fire arms, seven bows, and a considerable number of arrows and
quantity of ammunition. The thickness of the <placeName>Chaparal </placeName>prevented
us from pursuing the <persName>fugitives</persName>, who scattered in various directions.
There is sufficient reason to conclude, from the signs of blood and
other indications on their trails, that only three of the sixteen 
<persName>Indians </persName>will ever reach their <placeName>villages</placeName>. Each <persName>Indian </persName>had a leather rope
and noose, and they were all on foot, having with them only one horse.
They were a portion of the <persName>party </persName>who, last fall, stole horses at the
<placeName>Atascosito crossing</placeName> on this <placeName>river</placeName>. I found among their property
some papers which show that one of their dead was the <persName>chief called
Cordero</persName>, and that two other <persName>chiefs </persName>named <persName>Lisaque </persName>and <persName>Guichupa </persName>were
killed. It affords me great satisfaction to be enabled to say that the
<persName>men </persName>obeyed my orders with alacrity, and behaved well during the 
attack.    I send you herewith the papers I found."</p>

<p>In consequence of this incident, I gave orders to the <persName>captains of
Militia</persName> in this <placeName>Colony</placeName>, to have their <persName>men </persName>ready at a moments notice;
and I would send spies to the<placeName> <persName>Indian </persName>villages </placeName>to watch their 
movements and ascertain their intentions. I apprehend no danger of an
attack on the <placeName>Colony </placeName>by these <persName>Indians</persName>, as, according to information
I have received, the <persName>party </persName>destroyed by <persName>Captain Ross</persName> was the only
one that visited this <placeName>neighborhood </placeName>for the purpose of stealing, and
the other <persName>chiefs </persName>disapproved their conduct. I will leave today for
the <placeName>upper road</placeName> from <placeName>Bexar </placeName>to <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>; I may there receive 
information that will compel me to open a campaign against the <persName>Waco</persName>
and <persName>Tahuacano </persName><placeName>villages</placeName>, in which case I shall report to you in due
season.</p>

<p>Which I have the honor to report to you, enclosing the papers and
documents found in the possession of the routed party.</p>

<p>God and Liberty</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Town of <placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName>, <date when="1826-04-06">April 6th, 1826</date>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
