<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1981">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Thomas Barnett, 07-06-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-23">08-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Thomas Barnett
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 442-444
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-07-06">07-06-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Order of court authorizing Austin to make a certain disposition of land belonging to his brother's estate,</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Department of<placeName> Bexar</placeName></p>
<p>Jurisdiction of <placeName>Austin</placeName></p>
<p>To the <persName>Citizen Thomas Barnett constitutional Alcalde of the 
jurisdiction of <placeName>Austin</placeName>.</persName></p>

<p>The petition of<persName> Stephen F Austin</persName> a Citizen of the Jurisdiction
aforesaid, With respect represents that <persName>James E. B. Austin</persName> late
of the Jurisdiction aforesaid died some time since leaving his 
surviving <persName>widow </persName>and an infant male <persName>Child </persName>now aged about nineteen
months. That at the time of the death of the said <persName>James</persName>, he held
in his name an undivided <placeName>fourth part in a league of land </placeName>granted
by the<persName> Mexican Government</persName> to <persName>Elias R. Wightman</persName>, lying at the
<placeName>mouth of the Colorado River</placeName> and being the same part of which has
been laid off by <persName>Elias R. Wightman,</persName> and <persName>persons </persName>interested into
squares and lots with a view of fixing upon this same as a <placeName>town site</placeName>,
Your <persName>petitioner </persName>further represents that the <placeName>fourth part of the said
League</placeName> which is in the name of the said <persName>James E. B. Austin</persName> is really
the property of your <persName>petitioner </persName>which he will make appear as soon as
circumstances will permit and that the other three fourths are owned
in unequal portions by<persName> H H League</persName>, <persName>Ira Ingram</persName> and the said <persName>Elias
R. Wightman</persName>. The said League of land lying immediately at the
<placeName>mouth of the Colorado River and partly on the Bay of Matagorda,</placeName>
is thought to be an eligible situation upon which to fix a <placeName>town site</placeName>.</p>

<p>That the persons now interested in the <placeName>said league of land</placeName> wish
to associate themselves together for the purpose of laying off a <placeName>town</placeName>
on said league by which it will be rendered more valuable and more
immediately productive.</p>

<p>That in order to effect this and enable him to act, he should be
vested with power and authority to act and bind himself in his 
<persName>representative capacity</persName> (so long as he acts in that capacity) as 
<persName>administrator of the said James E. B. Austin </persName>deceased to do and perform<pb n="443"/>
all and every act, Jointly with the other persons interested in the
said league or with such others as may hereafter become legally
interested therein with power and authority to sell lease or 
otherwise bind the said land or make donations thereof. Jointly with
the said other <persName>persons </persName>interested, and your <persName>petitioner </persName>prays such
other and further relief in the premises, as from Equity, justice and
law he may be entitled to and as in duty etc.</p>

<p>(Signed)           <persName>S. F. Austin.</persName></p>

<p><placeName>Austin </placeName><date when="1830-07-06">6th July 1830</date></p>

<p>Department of <placeName>Bexar</placeName></p>
<p> <placeName>Jurisdiction of Austin</placeName></p>

<p>Having read and maturely considered the facts stated in the
foregoing petition and the evidence advanced in support thereof
it is by reason thereof and of the law, and it having been made
clearly to appear to my satisfaction that the <placeName>land </placeName>mentioned in
the foregoing petition when laid off in part or in whole, into <placeName>town
lots</placeName> will greatly increase the value thereof and will besides render
it more immediately productive. It is therefore ordered, adjudged,
and decreed that <placeName>Stephen F Austin administrator of the estate
of James E B Austin </placeName>deceased be authorized and empowered and
he is hereby authorized and empowered to form and connect himself
into an association with the present <persName>owners </persName>of the league of land
refered to in <persName>Plff</persName>. petition or with any other <persName>persons </persName>who may
hereafter acquire an interest therein necessary to carry views of the
said association into full and compleat effect having for object the
establishment of a <placeName>town </placeName>on the said league of land&#8212;and in order
to vest the said <persName>Stephen F Austin </persName>with full and compleat powers
to do whatever may be necessary to the completion of the object
set forth in the foregoing petition. It is further ordered adjudged
and decreed that the said <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> is hereby clothed with
authority to sell transfer, lease, give or grant Jointly with the
<persName>persons </persName>interested or who may hereafter become interested in the
said league of <placeName>land</placeName>, any part or portion thereof, and it is further
ordered and decreed that in order to effect the said object, and with
a view to give regularity and permananey to said association of
present and future <persName>owners</persName>, the said <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> is hereby
authorized and empowered to sign a constitution or charter for
the government of the said <persName>association </persName>to make, agree to and consent
to any rules or by-laws entered into by the said association of the
present or <persName>future owners of the <placeName>said league of land </placeName></persName>which may
be deemed necessary for their government. Signed with assisting
<persName>witnesses </persName>as the law requires at my <placeName>offce </placeName>in the town of <placeName>San Felipe
de Austin</placeName> this <date when="1830-07-07">seventh day of July in the year of Our Lord, 1830</date>,<pb n="444"/></p>

<p>(Signed)   <persName>Thos.  Barnett</persName> assisting witness<persName> L.  Lesassier</persName> Assisting
witness <persName>Samuel M. Williams</persName>,</p>

<p>the words on first page "them" erased on second page the words
"more valuable and" inserted, the third page the word "said"
erased.</p>

<p>I hereby Certify that I have carefully compared the foregoing
copy with the original petition and decree in my possession and
declare it to be an exact Copy of the original document.</p>

<p><placeName>Houston </placeName><date when="1837-05-31">May 31, 1837</date></p>

<p><persName>I. R. Lewis</persName> [Rubric]</p>




        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
