<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1325">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Ayuntamiento of Bexar, 11-07-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="1826-07-17">07-17-1826</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Ayuntamiento of Bexar
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Bexar, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1495-1498
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-11-07">11-07-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="1826-07-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Interpretation of law exempting colonists from tariff duties.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>A letter I have just received from the <persName>Empresario Green De Witt</persName>,
dated from <placeName>La Vaca Bayou</placeName>, apprizes me of a disagreeable occurrence
which took place there relative to the seizure of a cargo of goods
consisting, principally of flour, corn, coffee, whiskey and dry goods.
by virtue of the decree of <date when="1824-05-20">May the 20th 1824</date>, in relation to 
contraband articles. I understand that this cargo was purchased at <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName> by its <persName>owners </persName>for the purpose of assisting the <persName>colonists</persName>
of that <persName>Empresario</persName>, at the commencement of his establishment, under
the impression that the law permitted the introduction of such goods
for the consumption of the <persName>people </persName>of <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>I candidly state, that, with the decree of the Sovereign Constituent
Congress, N° 141, of <date when="1823-09-29">September the 29th 1823</date>, and the Colonization
law in my hand, I should, without the least hesitation have 
introduced the same goods that have been seized; as well for my
own consumption as for the purpose of selling them to the <persName>people</persName>
of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. The above mentioned decree clearly declares, in the most
specific terms, the object and intention of <persName>Congress </persName>in passing it.</p>

<p>The text of the decree is as follows:</p>

<p>"The Sovereign Mexican Congress, taking into consideration the
deplorable situation to which the <placeName>Province of Texas </placeName>has been 
reduced by <persName>Indian </persName>hostilities, and in order to give partial relief to
the destitute condition of her <persName>civilized people</persName>, have determined upon
decreeing, and do hereby decree, that all goods of what class soever,
whether home products, or foreign, introduced in the <placeName>Province of
Texas</placeName>, for the consumption of her <persName>people</persName>, shall be free from taxes;
and the exemption shall continue in force for the term of seven
years, from the date of the publication of this decree in the <placeName>capital
of said province</placeName>."</p>

<p>Now the object of that decree, was "to give a partial relief to the
destitute condition of her <persName>people </persName>" by granting them certain definite
privileges, for a limited term; to which <persName>Congress </persName>considered them
entitled in consequence of their sufferings and "the deplorable 
situation to which they were reduced by <persName>Indian </persName>hostilities." It is
therefore obvious, that the object of <persName>Congress </persName>was to encourage the
<persName>people </persName>of <placeName>Texas </placeName>by granting a well determined and clearly defined
privilege, an absolute right, without restriction or reservation 
whatever, except limitation of the term to seven years, during which this
favor is to continue; and this very limitation to a specific term, is,
in my opinion, indisputable proof that the object of <persName>Congress </persName>was to
grant and guarantee to the <persName>people </persName>of <placeName>Texas </placeName>the full enjoyment and
benefit of the privileges of said decree during that term, without any
reservation of the power to rescind it by another decree, unless in<pb n="1496"/>
cases of abuse, or such criminality on the part of her people as would
place them without the pale of any law. For instance, if <persName>Congress</persName>
for sufficient reasons, had, by decree, granted to an <persName>individual</persName>, (let
us suppose a <persName>resident </persName>of <placeName>Bexar</placeName>) an exclusive right, or privilege to
manufacture powder, or paper, or to introduce, for a limited period,
certain goods free from taxes; and, subsequently by a general 
decree, should prohibit the concession of such privileges to any person;
can it be supposed that the local <persName>authorities </persName>of <placeName>Bexar</placeName>, would consider
as annulled, by this latter decree, the special favor granted to that
individual by the former, without any abuse of the privilege on his
part?</p>

<p>There cannot exist more general and at the same time more 
explicit terms, than those of the decree of <date when="1823-09-29">September the 29th 1823</date>, it
says: " all goods of what class soever, whether home products, or
<persName>foreign</persName>;" which includes anything whatever, any production of
every part of the <placeName>world </placeName>" that may be introduced in <placeName>Texas</placeName>." That
is to say, not only by her own <persName>inhabitants</persName>, but by any other person
having the right to trade with the <persName>Mexicans </persName>and to enter their 
<placeName>territory</placeName>. " For the consumption of her <persName>inhabitants</persName>," that is to say,
not only for the consumption of the <persName>individual </persName>who may introduce
them, but, also, for the <persName>purchaser</persName>, if he is a <persName>resident of <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</persName> To
pretend that the <persName>individual </persName>who goes personally to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, or
any other place, to buy flour, coffee, sugar, etc., for his own 
consumption, has the right to introduce these goods, but not to sell
them to his <persName>Texian neighbor</persName> appears to me to be unjust, and 
oppressive, repugnant to the system that rules us and to the Constitution
in every sense, because it amounts to a declaration that the <persName>rich</persName>
possess rights the <persName>poor </persName>are not to enjoy; that the <persName>rich man</persName>, who can
take his gold and silver to purchase his necessaries in <placeName>foreign 
countries</placeName>, can introduce whatever he pleases, and live in luxury; while
the <persName>poor man</persName> who earns four reals a day by his labor, or by that
of his mules, horses, or mares, with which he could each day parchase
from a <persName>merchant</persName>, the flour, sugar, etc., necessary for the subsistence
of his <persName>family</persName>, is deprived of the use of those indispensable articles
because he has not a sufficient capital to absent himself from the
<placeName>country </placeName>and to introduce them expressly for his own consumption.
If a broad construction of this measure is recognized, it appears to
me, that the fundamental principles solemnly acknowledged, and
guaranteed by the Constitution, that all free <persName>citizens </persName>are to enjoy
equal privileges and to be equal in the eyes of the law, is a nullity and
a mockery.</p>

<p>This is a very important matter, particularly to the <persName>older 
inhabitants </persName>of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, who have been so long exposed to the depredations
and hostilities of the <persName>Indians</persName>.   <placeName>Texas</placeName>, does not, at present, produce<pb n="1497"/>
in sufficient quantities for her own consumption, flour, sugar, rice and
many other articles; she has not a sufficient number of <persName>curriers</persName>, 
<persName>shoemakers</persName>, <persName>hatmakers</persName>, <persName>tailors </persName>and other <persName>tradesmen</persName>; she has no <placeName>cloth
factories</placeName>; and cannot expect to have any for some years to come, for
want of <persName>hands </persName>and capital. A communication with the other <placeName>States</placeName>
which might supply her with these articles, cannot be conducted
without an escort of <persName>troops </persName>for protection against the <persName>Indians</persName>. All
this was certainly well understood by the <persName>Sovereign General 
Congress</persName> when they passed the decree referred to, and their object was,
obviously, to admit from <placeName>foreign countries</placeName>, all the articles required
by the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas </placeName></persName>until she extricated herself from her 
unfortunate situation. <placeName>Texas </placeName>is now in the condition she was at the time
of the publication of the decree of <date when="1823-09-29">September the 29th 1823</date>, and all
the motives that urged <persName>Congress </persName>to grant the privileges contained in
said decree, still exist to the same extent. Therefore, taking into
consideration the text of the decree, and the evident intention of the
<persName>Sovereign authority</persName> that made it, it appears to me that justice and
the welfare of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, alike demand that the decree of <date when="1824-05-20">May the 20th
1824</date>, which prohibits the introduction of certain articles, should not
be so construed as to abrogate or in any wise impair, diminish, or
change the decree of <date when="1823-09-29">September the 29th 1823</date>; and, that, by virtue of
said last mentioned decree, any goods not coming from an <placeName><persName>enemy</persName>'s
country </placeName>may be lawfully introduced into <placeName>Texas </placeName>by the <persName>citizens of
any <placeName>nation </placeName></persName>at peace and in friendly relations with our <placeName>Republic</placeName>;
and be sold to the <persName>people </persName>for their own consumption, agreeably to the
letter and spirit of said law of <date when="1823-09-29">September the 29th 1823,</date> and the 
intention of the <persName>sovereign Constituent Congress</persName> which was evidently to
grant to the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas </placeName></persName>the liberty of introducing " all goods
of any class whatever, whether home products or <placeName>foreign</placeName>," free of
taxes for the term of seven years from the publication of the decree
at <placeName>Bexar</placeName>. Indeed, if we admit the principle that a subsequent law
may deprive the <persName>people </persName>of a portion of that favor we must also
admit that they can be deprived of the whole. The law of <date when="1824-05-20">May the
20th 1824</date>, on prohibited goods, and other laws published subsequently
to the decree of <date when="1823-09-29">September the 29th 1823</date>, establish the taxes to be paid
on goods introduced into the <placeName>Mexican Republic</placeName>. Now, why are these
laws not extended to <placeName>Texas</placeName>; and why is it not declared that the
goods introduced into <placeName>Texas </placeName>shall pay the same taxes as in other
<placeName>sections of the country</placeName>? Why is the law establishing the tariff of a
date posterior to that which exempts <placeName>Texas </placeName>from taxes? it occurs
to me that it is as natural to give this construction, as to hold that
goods are prohibited by a general law published subsequently to the
law which grants the particular privilege of introducing them into
<placeName>Texas </placeName>free from taxes "all goods, whether home products, or 
<placeName>foreign</placeName>."   Furthermore the law of <date when="1824-05-20">May the 20th 1824</date>, makes no mention<pb n="1498"/>
of that of <date when="1823-09-29">September the 29th 1823</date>, and does not declare that it is
annulled. It must also be observed that the law of <date when="1823-09-29">September the
29th 1823</date>, is a special law, concerning a <placeName>single province</placeName>, and not a
general law; consequently if the object of <persName>Congress </persName>at the time of
passing the law of<date n="05-0-1824"> May the 20th 1824</date>, had been to annul the prior
law, it would certainly have been expressly stated, and be 
accompanied by a declaration of the reason for its abrogation. Indeed, a
particular and special privilege is as sacred a right as that of 
property, which <persName>Congress </persName>would never withdraw without well grounded
motives, nor without stating their reasons for doing so in the 
preamble.</p>

<p>The seizure of the cargo at the<placeName> mouth of La Vaca Bayou</placeName> is a 
matter of great importance. As I understand, a part of this cargo was
intended for the new <persName>settlers</persName>, and was necessary for their 
subsistence ; and the other belonged to some <persName>merchants </persName>of the <placeName>United States
of the North</placeName>, who came to trade with the <persName>Mexicans </persName>in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, in the
belief that the law of <date when="1823-11-29">September the 29th 1823</date>, was still in force.
That seizure withholds from the <persName>settlers </persName>indispensable provisions;
and the <persName>citizen </persName>of a friendly and allied <placeName>nation </placeName>is deprived of his
property. He will, undoubtedly, make his complaint to his 
government, which will inevitably result in disagreeable demands on the
part of that government.</p>

<p>The <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, in their present condition, must possess the
full and unrestricted enjoyment of all the privileges that the 
<persName>Supreme Government</persName> has been pleased to grant them. The privilege
of introducing any goods is very necessary; therefore, and 
considering that they hold this right by virtue of the law of <date when="1823-09-29">September the
29th 1823</date>, and as I am personally interested in the subject as a 
<persName>resident of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, and in my capacity of <persName>Empresario </persName>of one of the <placeName>new
colonies</placeName>, I have made use of the freedom of a <persName>citizen </persName>in the 
expression of my opinion, hoping that your Honorable Body will be pleased
to forward it to the proper authority, in order to remove the doubt
that exists in the interpretation of the decree of <date when="1823-09-29">September the 29th
1823</date>.</p>

<p>God and Liberty.</p>

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName>, <date when="1826-11-07">November 7th 1826.</date></p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
