<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1729">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Martin Allen to Stephen F Austin, 07-05-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Martin Allen</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-12">08-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Harrisburg, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 225-226
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-07-05">07-05-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Report on militia muster for campaign against Waco Indians. Discussion of Indian population of Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Harisburg </placeName><date when="1829-07-05">5th July 1829</date></p>

<p><persName>Col Austin</persName></p>

<p>Sir Agreeable to your order dated <date when="1829-06-23">23rd June</date> for the purpose of
raising <persName>Volunteers</persName>; I Calld a muster of My <persName>Company </persName>on the <date when="1829-07-02">Second
of this instant</date> and red your order to the <persName>Company </persName>and told them I
was willing to go&#8212;but the Shortness of the notice and the want of
Horses being in order and the extream hotness of the weather renders
it all most imposable to fit out a Compaign at this time altho the
<persName>men </persName>in My <persName>Company </persName>Seam to Show the greatest marks of Patriotism
in defending ther <placeName>Country </placeName>but wish to be Commanded by <persName>american
officers</persName>&#8212;I advised the men in my <persName>Companey </persName>to hold them selves in
readiness to go as soon as horses Could be put in order. I gave it
as my opinion that a Campaign would be fitted out altogather from
this <placeName>Coloney</placeName>. and <persName>Capt Hiram</persName> informed me on his return from 
<placeName>San-felip</placeName> that it is your opinion Also&#8212;at the time Your order arived
here there was a large number of <persName>indians </persName>at this place and of different
<persName>tribes </persName>there was <persName>Caddoes </persName><persName>Anadarkoes </persName><persName>Ieshes </persName><persName>Inies </persName><persName>Beedies </persName><persName>Coshaties</persName>
and <persName>Delawares </persName>and <persName>Kickapooes </persName>they ware all friendley and Showed
every mark of to remain so except the <persName>Kickpooes </persName>they purchased
All the powder that was here and put off amediately&#8212;I was not at
home my self when the <persName>Kickapooes </persName>was here or they Should not
have goten any powder from this place I wish you to send me the
Law relitive to Selling amunition to <persName>Indians </persName>that a Stop may be
put to it in time, the <persName>Indians </persName>ware very inquisitive to know if the
<persName>whites </persName>were going against the <persName>WayCoes</persName>, there <persName>Chiefs </persName>all apply to me
for information as they had appointed me there <persName>white Chief</persName> as they
term it&#8212;in place of there <persName>Greate Chief Capt Toolin</persName> of<placeName> Red river</placeName>
I kept them as much in the dark as posable in order to Learn from
them how the Different <persName>tribes </persName>Stood affected to wardes our <persName>inimyes</persName>&#8212;
they seemed to All be against the <persName>waycoes </persName>except a part of the
<persName>Caddoes </persName>who told me that the <persName>waycoes </persName>and them ware <persName>Friends </persName>which
I believe to be the Case&#8212;I have Learnt a few days Since from a
very Smart intilagent <persName>Coshatty </persName>who Stayed at my <placeName>hose </placeName>All night
Directly from the <placeName>Villiege</placeName>&#8212;he informed me that a jenril <persName>Expedition</persName>
was to be fitted out against the <persName>waycoes</persName>, of All the different <persName>Tribes</persName>
<placeName>between the Brazors and Red river </placeName>nameley the <persName>Coshatties </persName>
<persName>Alabammoes </persName><persName>Baluckshes </persName><persName>Chocktoas </persName><persName>Cherokees </persName><persName>Kickapooes </persName><persName>Caddoes </persName>and
all the other Small <persName>tribes </persName>in ther vicinty he says they are to devide
them Selves in different bands and all march at one time by different
routs So that the enimy Can have no Chance of ascaping&#8212;he says
they intend to kill all <persName>men </persName><persName>wimmin </persName>and <persName>Children</persName>&#8212;he says also they
are to March in two moons&#8212;this <persName>Indian </persName>gave this information 
without being able to have heard any thing from the <persName>Whites</persName>, relitive to<pb n="226"/>
the expedition at preasant I think it would be good policy when
there is an expedition on foot against the <persName>Waycoes </persName>or aney of them
<persName>tribes </persName>to keepe it as much from the Knowledge of other <persName>indians </persName>as
posable&#8212;there being so much Communication from one <persName>tribe </persName>to 
another the <persName>waycoes </persName>and <persName>Caddoes </persName>ware friendly some years go to my
own Knowledge&#8212;I was at a <placeName>Council of the Chiefs</placeName> of both <persName>tribes</persName>
held with <persName>old Capt Toolin</persName> there greate <persName>Chief </persName>at Camp ty on <placeName>Red
river</placeName> <persName>Capt Samul C Hiram</persName> informed me you are comeing over soon
to go down on the <placeName>bay </placeName>I am going Down soon my self and would
be very glad of your Company&#8212; I have an exelent Skiff for the
purpose if she is sent home in time to repair her for the trip I lont
her to <persName>Captain Scott</persName> when he Came on to Convey <persName>Misstriss Williams
</persName>Down from this place as she was two weak to ride throng the hot
sun I Should be very glad to be furnished with the Militia law
as soon as is Convenient and also to know the cause of the 
<persName>Commission[er]s</persName> not comeing on&#8212;Your order never reached my hand untill
the <date when="1829-06-29">29th of June</date>&#8212;you will do me the favour to write to me as soon
as is Convenient&#8212; I am Allways ready and ever have been to Serve
My <placeName>Country </placeName>and My <persName>Friends </persName>and remains</p>

<p><persName>Martin Allen</persName>    [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
