<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1042">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Juan Martin de Beramendi to Stephen F. Austin et al, 02-15-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Juan Martin de Beramendi</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-05-30">-5-30-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin et al
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Bexar, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1044-1045
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Order for arrest</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-02-15">02-15-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-05-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Ordering the arrest of a Frenchman, Andrew Valentine, for horse stealing.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><persName>Juan Martin de Beramendi Sqse first judge Constitutional of San
Fernando de Bejar, and accidental Political Chief</persName> for fault of 
proprietor</p>
<p>Cordillera</p>
<p><placeName>Los Brazos</placeName></p>
<p><placeName>Trinidad</placeName>,</p>
<p><placeName>Neches</placeName></p>
<p><placeName>Nacodoches</</placeName>p>

<p>to</p>
<p>This <persName>Tribunal</persName></p>

<p>[Rubric]</p>

<p>To your's the <persName>juge's citizen's dependant's</persName> to the new <placeName>colony</placeName> and
town of<placeName> San Felipe de Austin</placeName>, Departments of <placeName>Coahuila and Tejas
Estate</placeName>.&#8212;I put in your knowledge in virtu of this my requerant 
Letter, that divers robbery made in this <placeName>City</placeName> of drove Horses, and Mules
Lately instant this <persName>citizen</persName>'s experiment checks mischief's; at the same
time I have had the verification before my <persName>Tribunal</persName>, that the principal author of this excess, was the ingrateful <persName>foreigner </persName>French,
<persName>Andrew Valentine</persName> with others perverses, they are stealing in 
differents parts the aforesaid Droves of Horses and Mules, with the 
indiftenseness to drive into <placeName>United States of America</placeName>, I am informed that
this desertion is for that <placeName>Country</placeName>, I desire for my part to accomplish
with the Laws and oughts of my employ, with what prevents the
Laws, and our <persName>Mexican </persName>Constitution, I order, require, and charge in
name of <placeName>Republica</placeName>, and for my part I prayer, and request with 
exaggeration, that immediately you see this requiring, to prepare for
reserved way, to all <persName>inHabitants </persName>of your's comprehension of this
<placeName>new Colony</placeName>, to take care of straitely and to be with vigilance in all
the passages of <placeName>Brazos River</placeName>, when thinking can cross the <placeName>river</placeName>,
the aforesaid thief <persName>Andrew Valentin</persName>, and his <persName>companions</persName>, as soon
can be see towards of this point, to take prisoner with all his 
company and put in embargo all what carry on, and to send to me 
immediately under a safe conduct, and so doing you accomplishing with
the will of <persName>Superior Governmt</persName>, to whom many times it is assures of
your honest process, and of your submission, and obedience to Laws.-&#8212;-
I trusty in this recommendable circumstances that caracterize you,
my heart it is tranquilized, and I believe that the wicked <persName>ingrateful</persName>.<pb n="1045"/>
<persName>Valentin</persName> will be prisoner in your hands.&#8212;And with the object of
the assurance, I order for last that be circulated this my aforesaid
Letter from juge in juge with the quickness possible until put this in
hands of the <persName>Colonel Estevan Austin Sqse- principal chief of this 
department,</persName> he can dispose the more convenient.</p>

<p><placeName>Government House of Bejar</placeName> <date when="1825-02-15">15th. Feby. 1825</date></p>

<p><persName>Juan Martin de Beramendi </persName>   [Rubric]
De Assist*-</p>

<p><persName>Josef Antonio Navarro</persName> [Rubric] De assa- <persName>Victoriano Zepeda</persName></p>
<p>[Rubric]</p>

<p>To the <persName>Juges </persName>of the <placeName>Towns </placeName>and Places noted in the margin</p>

<p>[On margin:]</p>

<p><date when="1825-02-15">Martes quince</date>, sale a las nueve y quarto del dia, este requerente.</p>

<p>[Rubric]</p>

<p>Recibido a la una de la tarde el dia <date when="1825-04-01">primero de Abril</date> en este
<placeName>Juzgado</placeName> en la <placeName>Villa de San Felipe de Austin</placeName>.</p>

<p>Austin    [Rubric]</p>

<p>a los dos de la misma tarde salieron extraordinarios pa dar el
correspondiente aviso en los diferentes pasos <persName>poblados</persName> del <placeName>Rio de
los Brazos</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
