<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1577">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John Sibley to Stephen F Austin, 07-30-1828</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John Sibley</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-07">08-07-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Natchitoches, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 81-85
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1828-07-30">07-30-1828</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-07" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Political news. Local gossip. Rage for railroad construction.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Natchitoches </placeName><date when="1828-07-30">July 30th 1828</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir.</p>

<p>I have Just Recd your friendly letter dated <placeName>Austin </placeName><date when="1828-06-17">17th June</date>,
which of us is in debt in our literary Accounts is a subject I am not
disposed to discuss at present, I will say that I am glad always to
Receive a letter from you and will with pleasure communicate 
anything to you I may possess of sufficient Interest to excite your 
attention&#8212; we were soon informed of the arrival of <persName>Genl Taran</persName> at
<placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>. <persName>Col Piedras</persName> commanding at that <placeName>post </placeName>lately made us
a visit and spent ten days here, through him I Recd some 
communications from the <persName>Genl </persName>particularly what he found the <placeName>latitude, 
longitude, Elevation and degree of heat</placeName> at <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>, and that he was<pb n="82"/>
waiting to meet us to designate the <placeName>Boundary line</placeName>? on that subject
I have only been informed officially that the treaty between our
Govt and <placeName>Mexico </placeName>relative to the <placeName>boundary </placeName>and some other matters
was Ratified by the <persName>Senate </persName>of the <placeName>U States</placeName> on the <date when="1828-05-01">first of May</date> and
Returned to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>to be Exchangd and might be expected back in
<date n="09-xx-1828">September </date>and that the treaty of <date n="xx-xx-1819">1819 
</date> was Recognised generally,,
the treaty has not been published and will not be untill it returns, i
have not been informed of the Particular Stipulations. I have no
Knowledge of the oppointment of a <persName>commissioner </persName>on Our part,
there is a Report that I shall be named, but I have receivd nothing
official about it, If I should I shall Serve and have great pleasure
in being associated with <persName>Genl Taran</persName> for whose Character I feel the
greatest respect.&#8212; I am happy to learn that the Intestine 
difficulties in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>have subsided, such might have been expected, 
experience will no doubt tranquilise such Ebilutions, all governments have
experienced the Same; <placeName>Primary schools</placeName> and enlightning the people
is the Surest Course.</p>

<p>The Subject of Our <persName>Presidential </persName>Election has produced, and keeps
up more excitement than any thing has ever done in the <placeName>United
States,</placeName> the Choice of <persName>Electors </persName>conies on in <date n="11-xx-1828">November </date>next, both
<persName>Parties </persName>affect to be sanguine of success, for my own part I believe
<persName>Mr. Adams</persName> will be Reelected, and the cause of the <persName>administration</persName>
seems to be gaining ground, the Printed paper Enclosed I think
is a fair Exhibition of the case as it now Stands.&#8212;</p>

<p>I am glad to hear that the Govt of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>have concluded to
settle those<placeName> Belts of Neutral territory</placeName>, it would have been impossible
to have kept those reserves free from <persName>Banditties of Murderers </persName>and
<persName>outlawes</persName>&#8212; There seems to be some difficulty between the <persName>three
Allied Powers</persName> against <placeName>Turkey </placeName>about the division of what may be
conquered from <placeName>Turkey</placeName>. <placeName>France </placeName>and <placeName>England </placeName>hang Back; but
<placeName>Russia </placeName>will go on single handed If they should decline We have
no certain Accounts of Actual fighting being commenced Nor of the
<persName>Russian Army</persName> crossing the <placeName>Pruth</placeName>. The <persName>Greeks </persName>will no doubt 
become indepent of <placeName>Turkey </placeName>tho. not yet acknowledged, there is a
great Commotion in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, the <persName>English </persName>are Arming and so the
<persName>French</persName>. The <persName>Brittish </persName>are withdrawing their <persName>Troops </persName>from <placeName>Portugal</placeName>
and the <persName>French </persName>from <placeName>Spain</placeName>&#8212; <persName>Lord Wellington the Present prime
Minister</persName> has gone over to <placeName>France</placeName>, for something about <placeName>Greece </placeName>and
<placeName>Turkey </placeName>it is seposed. The Sperit for Internal improvement in the
<placeName>U. S.</placeName> was never at such a height <placeName>Rail ways</placeName> are taking place of
<placeName>Canals</placeName> as having the advantage of costing one third less, not being
interrupted by <persName>Frost</persName>, the <placeName>carriages propelled by Steam</placeName> can freight<pb n="83"/>
as low and move Eight Miles an hour, whereas <placeName>Canal Boats</placeName> go only
four.&#8212;</p>

<p>I had <date n="Winter - 1827">last winter</date> a Visit from <persName>Geo. Sibley</persName> of <placeName>Missouri </placeName>his <persName>wife</persName>
and her <persName>sister Miss Easton</persName>. they spent two Months with us and
took away with them <persName>Mrs Sibley</persName>, <persName>Hopkins Sibleys widow</persName>, and
her Daughter <persName>Ann</persName>. and son <persName>Harry</persName>; <persName>George </persName>has lived at <placeName>Fort Ozage</placeName>
and they all left here for that place, but on arriving at <placeName>S. Charles</placeName>
where <persName>Judge Eastons family </persName>Reside, <persName>George </persName>on Visiting and going
over a Tract of Land he had owned for 15 years near that place
which he never before had examined was persuaded to settle there
and there they all are, they live in the <placeName>Town </placeName>the land they are 
improving comes within half a Mile; the <placeName>Ozage farm</placeName> and stock are
kept up where they have an hundred Breeding Mares and Jennies
etc. <persName>Judge Easton </persName>has the Dropsey and cannot live long, they
give an account of the Beauty and improvements of <placeName>St. Louis</placeName>,
Increase of Population and Wealth surpassing any Town in the
West, <placeName>Cincinnati </placeName>Excepted.&#8212; they speak of the New Splendid
<placeName>Churches</placeName>, <placeName>Court </placeName>and <placeName>Market House</placeName> as in an superior stile, the
<placeName>Jefferson Barracks</placeName> <placeName>6 miles below where two Regiments of U. S.
Troops are kept</placeName> called the <placeName>School of practice</placeName> they mention as an
Elegant Establishment giving great life and vareity to <placeName>St. Louis.</placeName>
the <persName>Troops </persName>that were at <placeName>Council Bluff</placeName> are movd down a few miles
above <placeName>Old Fort Ozage</placeName> and is called the <placeName>Cantonement Levinsworth
</placeName>where is a <persName>Regiment</persName>, the <placeName>State of Missouri</placeName> is rapidly advancing
in population Wealth and improvements and are for the Reelection
of <persName>Mr. Adams</persName> <persName>Col Benton</persName> to the contrary notwithstanding&#8212;</p>

<p>Our Town of <placeName>Natchitoches </placeName>improves slowly, we have a large
tolerable handsome and well finished <placeName>Catholic Church</placeName> Nearly done
a good looking <placeName>Belfrey </placeName>and a good Bell. Several <placeName>New Houses</placeName> have
been built since you were here, but the distraction of the <placeName>great fire</placeName>
is scarsily repaired, all the <placeName>Small Towns on the Steam Boats
navigable Waters</placeName> seem not to flourish. If an <persName>inhabitant </persName>wants a
Twist of Tobacco he sends for it by a Steam Boat to his <persName>Agent </persName>in
<placeName>N. Orleans</placeName>, it is sure to come in a few hours, at half what the little
<persName>Jew </persName>shops would take for the Same Article&#8212;<placeName>Alexandria </placeName>from that
cause, the Overflow and unhealthiness of the place is almost 
abandoned   <placeName>Houses </placeName>and <placeName>Lotts </placeName>have fallen 800 pr Cent or More.&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>Planters </persName>in this <placeName>Parish </placeName>since the fall of Cotton (many of
them) are preparing for sugar, the Ribbon Cane brought from
<placeName>China </placeName>comes to perfection in about a Month less time than the
<persName>Creole </persName>cane no doubt from the experiments already made it will
succeed well in this <placeName>Parish</placeName>; but you have the soil and climate for
that Article; but cannot be extensively used without <persName>Slaves</persName>.&#8212;<pb n="84"/></p>

<p>Our Election for <persName>Govr Members of Congress</persName> and <persName>state Legislature</persName>
is just over have not got the Returns for <persName>Govr</persName>, or <persName>Congress</persName>,
<persName>Judge Derbigney</persName>, <persName>Butler</persName>, <persName>Marigney </persName>and <persName>Genl Thomas</persName> are the 
<persName>Candidates for Congress</persName> in this <placeName>district </placeName><persName>Brent </persName>and <persName>Overton</persName>, we have
from this <placeName>Parish </placeName>in Our Legislature A man by the name of <persName>Dyers
Debleau</persName> and <persName>Benja Matyear</persName>.-&#8212; <persName>Johnston </persName>Our Present <persName>Sheriff </persName>was
married a few days ago to the Daughter of <persName>Mr Benjm Bullitt</persName>&#8212;
<persName>Col Quarles</persName> of <placeName>Arkensas </placeName>to <persName>Madme Grosvenor</persName>&#8212; <persName>Mr. Cable</persName> and his
<persName>wife </persName>live apart. Several Accidents have hapened by steam Boat
Boilers Bursting, the car of Commerce lately, and killed and
wounded 57 <persName>persons</persName>. Two have been Burnt and one sunk in <placeName>Red
River.</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I did not see <persName>Capt. Jones</persName>, probably when he called I was out
about three Miles where My <persName>family </persName>are at a <placeName>Summer residence</placeName>;
where we have good Water and Air. No Musketoes and Milk not
Bitter, <persName>Mr Cable</persName> has informed me he had sent you a Packet of
papers which will keep you Along till you Receive more-&#8212; If the
Govt of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>was better organised, so that one might be 
protected in person and property and Religion I should feel Enclined to
move into it.</p>

<p><date when="1828-07-17">17th-July</date>. By the Steam Boat Beaver we have the Election 
Returns so far as to assertain that <persName>Judge Derbigney</persName> has a Majority
of Votes for <persName>Governor</persName>, that <persName>Judge white</persName> a young man (son of
<persName>Doctr White</persName> who died <persName>Parish Judge of <placeName>Attackapa</placeName></persName>) and lately been
Acting as <persName>City Judge of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></persName>, has been <persName>Elected Member
of Congress</persName> in place of <persName>Mr. Livingston</persName>; <persName>Derbigney </persName>and <persName>White </persName>are
for the Reelection of <persName>Mr. Adams President</persName>. <persName>Mr. Livingston</persName> for
<persName>Jackson </persName><persName>Mr. Marigney </persName>and <persName>Judge Butler</persName> opposed to <persName>Derbigney </persName>as
Governor are <persName>Jacksonites</persName>. The Votes of <placeName>Louissiana </placeName>will be for
<persName>Adams (President</persName>). <persName>Mr. Gurley</persName> of <placeName>Batton Rouge</placeName> (<persName>Adams</persName>) is 
Reelected by a large Majority. <placeName>Missouri </placeName>and <placeName>Illenois </placeName>for the 
<persName>administration </persName>; and we now believe <persName>Adams </persName>will certainly be Reelected&#8212;- I
sepose you were Acquainted with Our <persName>Captain Grosvenor</persName>; while
he was in your <placeName>Country</placeName>: Accounts Came on here Satisfactory to
his <persName>wife </persName>that he had another <persName>wife </persName>in <placeName>New York</placeName>, she had a decree
Nullifying her Marriage with <persName>Grosvenor</persName>, and was in <date n="03-xx-1828">March last</date>
married to a <persName>Col Quarles</persName>, a <persName>Lawyer </persName>from <placeName>Little Rock</placeName> in <placeName>Arkensa
Territory,</placeName> the <persName>Col </persName>after living here with her a short time went to
<persName>Arkensas </persName>and Returned sooner than he had appointed he soon 
appeared dissatisfied and went away Again, it is thought will not
soon if ever Return to her again. The <persName>Col </persName>is a light made, small
Man Very Genteal, well informed, a <persName>Schollar</persName>, and stands high at
the Bar   is I should think under 85.&#8212; there is a <persName>Col Oden</persName> living<pb n="85"/>
here from <placeName>Arkensa </placeName>also, a Man of Wonderfull Physical and 
Intellectual powers, was, but not now an intimate friend of <persName>Col Quarle</persName>'s&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>John Sibley </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>P. S&#8212;you have not informed me about my claim on the <placeName>Estate</placeName>
of <persName>Mc. Farlane</persName>.&#8212;Since Writing the above we have had more 
particularly the Return of our Election <persName>Derbigney </persName>will be our <persName>Governor</persName>-
White for <persName>Congress </persName>in place of <persName>Livingston</persName>. <persName>Gurley </persName>Reelected&#8212;
<persName>Overton </persName>in place of <persName>Brent</persName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
