<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1678">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Commodore David Porter, 02-16-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-10">08-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Commodore David Porter
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 166-168
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-02-16">02-16-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Urging him to apply to government for a grant of land in Texas. Description of the country; population, cattle raising, cotton, opportunities for developing trade with England, which resents tariff of the United States, coasting trade, and foodstuffs.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felepe de Austin</placeName><date when="1829-02-16"> 16 Feb. 1829</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir:</p>

<p>I had the pleasure of seeing <persName>Capt. A. Thompson</persName> of the <persName>navy </persName>during
his visit to the <placeName>coast of Texas</placeName> <date n="Fall - 1828">last fall</date>, and in a conversation with
him I learned that you had it in contemplation to procure a <placeName>grant</placeName>
from Government on the <placeName>Guazacualco river</placeName> with the view of 
establishing a number of <persName>families</persName>, and the <persName>Cap.</persName> suggested the possibility
of your giving a preference to <placeName>Texas </placeName>when fully apprised of its
advantages in point of soil, locality, and temperature.   Never 
having seen any part of the <placeName>Guazacualco country</placeName> I cannot pretend to a
correct opinion as to its relative advantages or disadvantages when
compared with <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and can only say that the discription I have
recd of it from several intelligent <persName>men </persName>who professed to have 
explored it has left an impression on my mind that, as a country, <placeName>Texas</placeName>
is greatly its superior.   It is true that our climate will not admit
of the culture of coffee or cacao, and other <placeName>tropical </placeName>productions but
we can boast of the quality and abundance of our cotton crops and
sugar and all the other productions of <persName>Louisiana </persName>and <persName>Mississippi</persName>
succeed very well.    The <placeName>pasturage</placeName>, or "<placeName>range</placeName>" as we term it, is
certainly superior to any thing I have ever seen in any <placeName>country</placeName>, and
the <placeName>facilities </placeName>for raising Cattle horses, mules, sheep and hogs, etc.
almost exceeds credibility.    The general appearance of this <placeName>country</placeName>
is pleasing and in many places beautifull, being diversified with
extensive broad <placeName>Prairies </placeName>clothed with the most luxurient growth of
grass and <placeName>groves of timber,</placeName> <placeName>rivers </placeName><placeName>creeks </placeName><placeName>streamlets </placeName>and elevated
<placeName>undulating tracts.</placeName>    The latter, in general commence from <placeName>thirty to
fifty miles from the coast</placeName> and extend far into the <placeName>interior </placeName>before
the <placeName>country </placeName>becomes hilly   The  facilities  of interior navigation
are considerable and susceptible of extensive improvements, and no
country is better adapted for the cheap construction of good roads,
our <placeName>harbors </placeName>will not admit vessels of the largest class, but are 
sufficiently deep for brigs and the smaller class of merchant ships and
are very safe and secure from gales   The climate of <placeName>Texas </placeName>I deem
to be decidedly superior in point of health and salubrity to any 
portion of <placeName>north America</placeName> in the same parallel   The margins of our<pb n="167"/>
<placeName>rivers </placeName>in common with all the <placeName>rivers of the world</placeName> are somewhat 
subject to fever and agues and other complaints incident to similar
situations but I think that the practical experience of seven years
justifies me in saying that the <placeName>rivers of Texas </placeName>are less liable to 
diseases than <placeName>any river of the U. S.</placeName> <placeName>below latitude 36</placeName>. Situations back
from the <placeName>rivers</placeName>, or <placeName>near the Coast</placeName> are remarkably healthy&#8212;</p>

<p>The munificent and liberal policy of the Govt towards <persName>emigrants</persName>
has drawn many very worthy and valuable <persName>settlers </persName>from the <placeName>United
States of the north </placeName>and they bring with them the enterprise, 
perseverance and industry which forms so prominent a trait in the
national character of our <placeName>native country.</placeName> When I Commenced
this <placeName>settlement </placeName>in <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date>. <placeName>Texas </placeName>was an <placeName>uninhabited desert</placeName>. This
<placeName>colony </placeName>at the present has about <persName>3000 inhabitants</persName> and <placeName>settlements </placeName>are
<placeName>extending in other sections</placeName>. The great interprise and industry
of the <persName>north American emigrants</persName> must and will make this a rich
and valuable <placeName>country</placeName>. We shall next year be able to export a 
considerable amt. of cotton and it is considered by many that if the
" Tariff System " is continued by the<persName> Govt of the<placeName> U. S</placeName>.</persName> a 
discrimination will be made by <placeName>G. Britain</placeName> in the article of cotton which will
give to that of other <placeName>countries </placeName>a decided advantage in the<placeName> English
market</placeName> over the <placeName>United States</placeName>&#8212;be this as it may the <persName>planters of
<placeName>Texas </placeName></persName>can compete with those of the <persName>U. S</persName>. for the means of 
subsistence here can be raised cheaper and no capital of consequence will
be required, at least for several years, to procure land. And besides
this labor here will produce more than in any part of the<placeName> U. S.</placeName>
within my knowledge, not even excepting the <placeName>Red River country</placeName>,
owing to the superior fertility of our soil.</p>

<p>Should the suggestion made by <persName>Cap Thompson</persName>, that you might
possibly prefer this <placeName>country </placeName>to <placeName>Guazacualco </placeName>be correct, and you
should wish for information as to any particular <placeName>sections </placeName>I will take
great pleasure in affording it so far as may be within my power.
I believe that the <placeName>country </placeName>embraced within the following limits has
not been granted to any <persName>Empresario</persName>, that is, <placeName>begining at the Mouth
of the San Jacinto River</placeName> and <placeName>folowing up it ten leagues</placeName> (which is
the extent of the reserve made by the law of <date when="1824-08-18">18 August 1824</date> of <placeName>lands
bordering on the coast</placeName> thence <placeName>Eastwardly following the said reseive
line to the 20 league reserve</placeName>, thence <placeName>northwardly following this last
line to the main road leading from Nacogdoches to Nachitoches</placeName>,
thence<placeName> Eastwardly along that road to the Sabine,</placeName> and <placeName>down the
Sabine to its Mouth and along the coast to the mouth of San
Jacinto</placeName>&#8212; The <placeName>20 league reserve line </placeName>spoken of is also agreable
to the Genl colonization law of <date when="1824-08-18">18 Aug. 1824</date> which reserves <placeName>ten
leagues on the coast</placeName> and <placeName>20 leagues on the boundary line of the U. S</placeName>.</p>

<p>The above <placeName>tract </placeName>is about <placeName>120 miles north and south</placeName> and <placeName>60 east
and west</placeName> and will admit of good <placeName>settlements</placeName>.    The <placeName>Naches </placeName>and<pb n="168"/>
<placeName>Trinity rivers</placeName> run through it both navigable and they both afford
good pine cypress and cedar oak and ash timber in abundance and
numerous situations on creeks for <placeName>Mills</placeName>. The proximity of this
tract to the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> would cause it to settle rapidly&#8212; The <placeName>Naches</placeName>
discharges into <placeName>Sabine Lake</placeName> which may be connected with an 
eastern arm of <placeName>Galveston Bay</placeName> by a cut of not more than two or three
Miles through low prairie as I am told.</p>

<p>I expect that a <persName>cousin </persName>of mine <persName>Mr John Austin</persName> will visit <placeName>vera
Cruz</placeName> shortly with the Schooner Eclipse for the purpose of procuring
a <persName>Mexican </persName>register in proper form. A provisional pasport has
been issued for her by the <persName>Comt Genl Bustamte</persName> which I am informed
is sufficient to carying the cargo from here she is owned entirely
by <persName>Mexican citizens</persName> We shall be able next year to supply a 
considerable amt. of Beef Pork, lard, Bacon and peas and Butter and
Sweet Potatoes should those articles be wanting for naval supplies,
they perhaps may be had on better terms from here than from any
other quarter of the <placeName>Mexican territory</placeName>&#8212;¦</p>

<p>With the most sincere desires for your health and happiness I
have the honor to remain your Most Obt. Sert.</p>

<p>[Indorsed:] Letter to <persName>Commodore Porter</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
