<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1511">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Thomas F. McKinny to Stephen F Austin, 03-11-1828</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Thomas F. McKinny</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-30">07-30-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nacodoches, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 24-26
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1828-03-11">03-11-1828</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Efforts of a disgruntled vagabond to disturb the country. High-handed proceedings of the military commandant, Piedras.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Nacodoches </placeName><date when="1828-03-14">March 14 1828</date></p>
<p>Dier sir</p>

<p>yours of the <date when="1828-01-29">29th of Jany</date> has been over looked in the <placeName>post office</placeName>
until this <date when="1828-03-14">morning </date>otherwise I should have immediately complied
with your request I do assure you I am at all times ready to check
when in my power any thing like perturbattion of the <persName>inhabitants</persName>
not only of your <placeName>Colony </placeName>but any other part of the <placeName>Country </placeName>my 
sincere disire is that the <placeName>Country </placeName>prospers and any thing which would
have a contrary effect would be repugnant to my feelings</p>

<p>That <persName>Dayton </persName>has made an attempt to raise a <persName>party </persName>there is no
doubt though from the best information we can get on the subject
there has not more than eight or ten <persName>men </persName>been so base as to join
him&#8212;<persName>Dayton's </persName>respectability in your <placeName>Colony </placeName>is much more 
extensive than in any part of this <placeName>country </placeName>and the general opinon is
that the only revenge he seeks is to practise villiany be it of 
whatsoever nature or at whatsoever place that opportunity may serve   a<pb n="25"/>
few men have been provoked to connive at his attempt from the
treatment they have received in this <placeName>country </placeName>because that <persName>Dayton</persName>
declared he would commit outrages upon this <placeName>country </placeName>would bring
down the <persName>Indians </persName>upon them and other threats to that purport.</p>

<p>In <date n="12-xx-1827">December last</date> there was a [daj] designated for the <persName>inhabitants</persName>
[to meet for the] purpose of swearing allegiance [to the State 
Constitution?] <persName>Burril Thompson</persName> and <persName>Demi . . . ed </persName>and <persName>Burrel </persName>mani-
fested [some reluctance to] take the necessary oath and ... his hand
to assign his name a[nd] ... the day when <persName>Piedras </persName>who w[as 
presiding?] . . . snatched the list from his [hand. Piedras ordered?]
him and Hase to march forthwith for the <placeName>uni-?]ted States</placeName> without
any charfges being made] against them? or any oportunity [given
them for any] kind of defence it is unnecessary to say to you that
such a course was productive of displeasure among the <persName>inhabitants</persName>
and until this day the cause of their banishment is unknown. The
<persName>Alcalde </persName>who accompanied <persName>Piedras </persName>for the purpose of cooperating in
his measures was applied to in order to ascertain the motives or the
crime of which those men were charged his reply was that he was
not consulted in the matter nor was the cause made known to him
and he himself disapproved of the course.</p>

<p><persName>Piedras </persName>has persued an arbitrary course during his time here and
the civil <persName>authorities </persName>of the place have hitherto been no obstacle in
his progressions though the extreme weakness of the <persName>individuals</persName>
in whom those <persName>authorities </persName>are reposed serve in some measure as an
apology for his doing so provided he proceeded correctly himself.
For some imprudent conduct of the <persName>Coles </persName>and others to <persName>Elisha
Roberts</persName> and <persName>family </persName>which conduct amounted to nothing more than
hooping and howling as aparcel of <persName>blackguards</persName> frequently do and
killing a dog of <persName>Roberts</persName>'s they were arrested by the <persName>Military </persName>put
in strings conducted to <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>commited to <placeName>prison </placeName>bail refused
without a trial for something like ten days when the trial 
commenced by the <persName>Military </persName>and the <persName>prisoners </persName>asked [for] permission
to interogate the <persName>witnesses </persName>who replied in [a harsh and?] haughty
manner that he would proceed ... or custom of the <placeName>country</placeName>
and during their [trial] frequently was heard say that it seemed
[to him that] <persName>americans </persName>were accustomed to treat the [officers? with]
disrespect though he had brought [a guard with?] him and would
sustain him self that . . . had acted cowardly in consequence
of . . . was now in disrepute and many other . . . vincing
that he wished to awe or [intimidate the] <persName>inhabitants </persName>into obedience
. . . kind were productive of nothing good . . . <persName>Ahumado </persName>is
still venerated among us and he could effect more here with his
walking staff than <persName>Piedras </persName>with all his bayonets.   It is to be regreted<pb n="26"/>
that <persName>Piedras </persName>brought with him to this place prejudices against the
<persName>American inhabts</persName> which will be difficult to remove.</p>

<p>Another circumstance which produced considerable excitement
was two men engaged in a combat when an old <persName>gambler </persName>by the name
of <persName>ward </persName>interfered in order to make peace at which time a <persName>soldier</persName>
arrived with his bayonet in his hand and observing a pocket knife
in <persName>Wards </persName>hand and he engauged peremptorily ordered him to put
the knife in his pocket <persName>Ward </persName>did not understand only from his 
manner which was menacing and did not obey the order until spoken by
an <persName>American </persName>who explained to him what the <persName>soldier </persName>had said <persName>Ward</persName>
immediately put the knife in his pocket though by this time the
<persName>combatants </persName>had retired the <persName>soldier </persName>proceeded to call a <persName>guard </persName>who
arrived <persName>Ward </persName>was pointed out by the insulted <persName>soldier </persName>to the guard
who without any thing like an inquiry proceeded to beat <persName>Ward </persName>with
their muskets in a beastly manner broke his arm in two places in that
situation conducted him to <placeName>prison</placeName>.   <persName>Piedras </persName>observed he would make
a fit subject for sweeping the streets for the next six months and it
was with difficulty that he could be prevailed upon after being 
informed of the circumstances to let <persName>Ward </persName>out of <placeName>prison </placeName>these 
circumstances I witnessed myself and if <persName>Ward </persName>had been a respectable
m[an] . . . the excitement which prefvailed] . . . would have been
serious ... He is now punishing a <persName>citizen </persName>. . . ducting from this
place . . . giving him a certain num[ber] . . . making him carry
a chai[n] . . . man deserves punishmen[t] ... to do so the truth
of . . . There is nothing like money . . . <persName>inhabitants </persName><persName>Piedras </persName>has
been borrowing on the faith of the Gov1 for some time past and his
paper is in circulation for the amount of several thousand dollars
still the inhabitants are satisfied that he has a quantity of money
on hand and are at a loss to know his motive for retaining it some
of us are rather suspicious of his principles and rather doubt his
attachment to the Govt though we may not be justifiable in so doing
it is a thing which we by no means make publick</p>

<p>I should be glad to hear from you relative to your trip to the
<placeName>interior </placeName>the probable success of our<placeName> Ayish Byou </placeName>petición when we
may hope for relief of those who are in suspence in this <placeName>quarter</placeName></p>

<p><persName>Thomas F McKinney </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
