<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1307">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Henry Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 10-20-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Henry Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-15">07-15-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1478-1479
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-10-20">10-20-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Experiences in Mexico. Questions concerning trade with Texas. Demand for live oak.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New York</placeName> <date when="1826-10-20">20 Oct 1826</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr Stephen F Austin</persName></p>
<p>My dear sir</p>

<p>There is so little intercourse between your <placeName>country </placeName>and this that
it is almost as difficult to communicate with you as tho you were in
the <placeName>moon</placeName>&#8212;I accidentally heard by a <persName>gentlemen </persName>in <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> who
had been at your <placeName>settlement </placeName>that you were still alive and progressing
well with your <placeName>colony </placeName>altho published dead several times not only in
our <placeName>papers </placeName>but also in the <placeName>Mexican Sol</placeName> with an Obituary notice</p>

<p>I have been myself nearly two years in <placeName>Alvarado, Vera Cruz</placeName> and
<placeName>Nacotalpam</placeName>&#8212;in the latter place I established a <placeName>Cotton Gining
Mill and press</placeName> for cleaning Cotton at the place of growth and thereby
relieving the <persName>manufacturers </persName>of the tripple expence of Carriage to
<placeName>puebla</placeName>&#8212;but the <persName>Mexican Manufacturers</persName> would not spin cotton
cleaned by machinery and the price for exportation would not pay
which compelled me to abandon the experiment with a loss of 4000$
in a year and one half hard labor</p>

<p>I observed at <placeName>Nacotalpam </placeName>that the <placeName>low land</placeName> abounded with live
Oak but the high price of labour and the difficultys thrown in the
way of all operations attempted by <persName>strangers </persName>will not permit the
cutting of it for exportation with advantage</p>

<p>This timber is now in request here and should the genuine live
Oak be plenty <placeName>on the banks of the rivers in your neighbourhood</placeName> 
advantage might be drawn from it unless the <persName>Govt </persName>should interpose
some impediment to its exportation Will you do me the favor
to inform me whether it is to be had in your <placeName>quarter</placeName>, if so the
quantity and size, the facilitys in obtaining it&#8212;the probable cost
&#8212;whether <persName>men </persName>could be had there to cut it or must [it] be brought
out&#8212;the duties and impositions which might be incurred etc</p>

<p>The present mode of obtaining it in <placeName>florida </placeName>is to send out strong
<persName>parties </persName>with small vessels to transport it to the shipping place then
purchase the privilege of cutting and do the work <persName>themselves</persName>&#8212;-
The <persName>Mexicans </persName>of the <placeName>bajos of Vera Cruz</placeName> do not value this timber
and appear to be ignorant of its durability&#8212;Care must be taken
to distinguish between the Genuine live Oak and the bastard live
Oak which is much like it but will not last&#8212;There are no doubt
<persName>men </persName>with you perfectly well acquainted with it&#8212;</p>

<p>Should there be any opening for profitable operations of any
sort in your <placeName>quarter </placeName>you will oblige me by giving the needful 
information I am now doing nothing&#8212;business of every kind is 
extremely dull and as I am poor with a large <persName>family </persName>to support I am
perforce ready to embark in any operation which offers reasonable<pb n="1479"/>
advantages and with fair prospects of success there will be no
difficulty in raising sufficient capital</p>

<p>Cotton has revived a little in <placeName>England </placeName>by the last advices but
will probably continue low through the year&#8212;Hides and pork and
beef if to be had at your <placeName>place </placeName>might turn to acct as also bacon
cured in the <persName>Mexican </persName>manner for the <placeName>Havana </placeName>market&#8212;The Black
beans of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>called frijoles if raised in quantity would be an
excellent article of export&#8212;</p>

<p>If there is any regular mode of communicating with the <placeName>U S</placeName>
your <placeName>place </placeName>please inform me of it, as we shall always be happy to
hear of your welfare and to acquaint you with ours My younger
brother <persName>John P</persName> is established here as a <persName>commission Mercht</persName> under
the firm of <persName>Austin and Tailer</persName> their correspondent in <placeName>Orleans </placeName>is
<persName>Saml. T. Coit</persName> who will forward any letters sent to him</p>

<p>Cordially and Sincerely your friend and <persName>kinsman</persName></p>

<p><persName>Henry Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>I took the liberty of braking the seal of this letter and was 
agreeably surprised.</p>

<p>Yr <persName>Brother</persName>
______                      <persName>J E B Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
