<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1169">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to W. S. Hall?, 05-xx-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-20">06-20-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        W. S. Hall?
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1350-1351
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-05">05-xx-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-20" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reprimanding him for carelessness in executing orders to press equipment for Indian campaign.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date n="xx-xx-1826">[May &#8212;, 1826?]</date></p>

<p>I have learned with much regret that some confusion and 
contention has arisen in your <persName>company </persName>in consequence of your proceedings
under my order of the <date when="1826-05-01">1 day of May last</date> relative to pressing horses
and arms for the late expedition&#8212;The words of that part of the
order are "You are authorized to press guns and equipments for
those who have none whereever you can procure them"&#8212;It was
known to me that a number of <persName>men </persName>were unequiped and unable to
equip themselves and it was deemed a just sacrifice to the public
interest to compel those who did not go on the Campain, and had
horses or arms, to furnish them&#8212;The order did not particularly
specify that you should not press from those who were going on
the <persName>expedition</persName>, or who had voluntarily fitted out others, or that
you should use some precaution in pressing from those who were the
least able to spare the articles or that you should not press for
those who were able to equip themselves&#8212;such a specification was
not deemed necessary for it was presumed you knew the situation
of every individual in the <persName>Company </persName>and would use that discretion in
the execution of the order and make that distinction which peculiar
circumstances might require&#8212;I find that the order was not 
sufficiently specific altho no difficulty has occurred that I have heard of
in any other <persName>company </persName>but yours. The moment the articles were
pressed they were placed under your care and it was your special
duty to see them returned to their <persName>owners</persName>, every horse gun etc should
have been delivered to his <persName>owner </persName>as soon as the expedition was over
and it was your duty to have seen it done&#8212;This was not stated
in the order neither was it necessary, for the articles were taken
for public use and it was your duty as the <persName>Commander of the 
Company</persName> to see that they were properly taken care of and duly returned.</p>
<p>All orders for pressing in future should any ever be issued which
it is not probable there ever will will be so limited and specific as
to prevent the recurrence of any such difficulties in future&#8212;</p>

<p>The public good requires that  dissentions  amongst the  people
should cease&#8212;every reason that can exist in any <placeName>country </placeName>for union
<pb n="1351"/>
and harmony operates here at this time with peculiar force&#8212;
threatened with an <persName>Indian </persName>war we should be united&#8212;<persName>Strangers </persName>in a new
<placeName>Country </placeName>we should establish our characters as quiet harmonious
and good <persName>citizens</persName>&#8212;It is therefore hoped that all further difficulties
on the subject of the pressing business will cease and no more 
conversation will be had on the subject&#8212;</p>

<p>yours respectfully</p>

<p>With a view to correct public opinion and put a stop to any
futher converstion on the subject refered to in the following letter
the<persName> Alcalde of <placeName>victoria</placeName></persName> will post it up at 
<placeName>BolIvar</placeName> for public 
information&#8212;</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
