<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1422">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>C. B. Penrose to Stephen F. Austin, 06-27-1827</title>
            <author>
                <persName>C. B. Penrose</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-26">07-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1663-1665
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1827-06-27">06-27-1827</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Desires to establish a distillery in Texas, and submits proposal for admission of molasses free of duty.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe De Austin</placeName>   <date when="1827-06-27">June 27th 1827</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr Penrose</persName> respectfully presents to <persName>Col. Austin</persName>, the following
subjects for his consideration, and on which he would request an
answer, whenever the <persName>Col's</persName> convenience will permit&#8212;</p>

<p>1st <persName>Mr. P</persName>&#8212; in conjunction with a <persName>planter of Louisiana</persName>, proposes
erecting in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, an extensive <placeName>Distillery </placeName>for the manufactory of
Rum, but as the law " Granting certain privileges to the <persName>Citizens
of Texas</persName> " under which <persName>Mr P</persName>&#8212; would expect to import Melasses for
the maintainance of his <placeName>Distillery</placeName>, appears to clash with a 
subsequent law of the <persName>Genl Govt</persName>, <persName>Mr P</persName> to place the matter beyond a doubt
would solicit from the <persName>Govt</persName>, the privilege of introducing from
<placeName>Louisiana </placeName>or elsewhere, an adequate supply of melasses, for a Term
of years, free of duty, or untill the <persName>Citizens of the Colony</persName> who have
turned their attention to the culture of the sugar cane, could afford
the material in sufficient abundance, when <persName>Mr. P</persName>&#8212; would pledge
himself to confine his purchases to the <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212;The capital which
<persName>Mr. P</persName>&#8212; would invest in the prosecution of his design, would be
little short of $10,000 and as the greatest part of that sum would
be expended in the <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212;and as the <placeName>houses </placeName>and other fixtures
when erected, would be an important and valuable acquisition to
the <placeName>Colony</placeName>, <persName>Mr. P</persName>&#8212; would therefore, solicit the cooperation of <persName>Col
Austin</persName> in obtaining the privilege refered to. Should the <persName>Genl Govt</persName>
grant <persName>Mr P</persName>&#8212; the privilege of introducing Free of duty&#8212;one 
hundred thousand Gallons of Melasses, annually he would also suggest
to <persName>Col Austin</persName>, the reasonableness of his asking an exclusive privi-<pb n="1664"/>
lege. <persName>Mr P</persName>&#8212; would invest a large capital in a doubtful adventure,
he stakes his all, with his time and attention for years&#8212;and should
ultimate success, or entire ruin to himself, be the result of his 
enterprise, he conceives himself meriting the encouragement and 
protection of the Govt for introducing a manufactory heretofore 
unknown, or pursued upon a very limited scale&#8212;</p>

<p>2nd What quantity of <placeName>Land</placeName>&#8212;might <persName>Mr. P</persName>&#8212;expect to derive from
the Govt as a donation and where situated ?&#8212;</p>

<p>3rd <persName>Mr P</persName>&#8212; is particularly solicitous to be informed by <persName>Co1 Austin</persName>
of the various markets of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;What quantity of Rum could
be annually disposed of, in each place, and the probable price, and
also the safest and cheapest means of transportation to the <placeName>interior</placeName>?</p>

<p>4th   Whether 1st or 4th proofs would meet the readiest markets?</p>

<p>5th If <persName>Co1 Austin</persName> is of opinion that some point on the <placeName>Brassos</placeName>,
would be the most eligable position for the proposed establishment&#8212;
<persName>Mr. P</persName> would request him to designate the place, having a regard to
the facility of transportation to the various ports of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>6th <persName>Mr P</persName>&#8212; would require for his establishment, a large quantity
of scantling and Cypruss plank, but as the latter cannot be easily
obtained in the <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212;<persName>Mr. P</persName>&#8212;would wish to get permission to
bring from <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>&#8212;Cisterns ready made, or plank for the 
purpose of making them&#8212;</p>

<p>7th Could <persName>artizans </persName>and <persName>day laborers</persName> be obtained in the <placeName>Colony</placeName>
or would <persName>Mr P</persName> have to bring them from <placeName>U&#8212;S</placeName>?</p>

<p>8th Are not the <placeName>banks of the Brassos</placeName> well wooded, and if so, what
kind of timber is generally found?</p>

<p>9th Should <persName>Mr P&#8212;</persName> find it necessary to purchase a vessel, what
tonage would <persName>Co1 Austin</persName> recommend ? and what steps would <persName>Mr P</persName>&#8212;
have to pursue, to place his vessel under the <placeName>Mexican </placeName>Flag&#8212;</p>

<p>10th What is the regular army of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;and what number of
<persName>Seamen</persName>? how are they provissioned? might not<persName> Mr P</persName> dispose of a
considerable quantity of Spirits annually&#8212;to the Govt for their
<persName>army </persName>and <persName>navy</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Should the privilege solicited&#8212;be granted, it will be in the name
of <persName>Joseph B. Wilkinson and Clement B Penrose</persName>, Trading under the
name of <persName>Penrose &amp; Co</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Would it not be profitable to establich a <placeName>sugar house</placeName>?</p>

<p>My Dear Sir</p>

<p>The foregoing memorandum I have hastily sketched out, there are
other objects connected with my plan, which I will discuss with you
when your liesure will permit; in the meantime the only apologys I
can offer for the trouble I give you, is the assurance of my warm
thanks for the friendly reception which you have given me&#8212;and to
remind you of the friendship which has so long subsisted between<pb n="1665"/>
our <persName>Families</persName>&#8212;I must also trouble you to enquire for me at <placeName>San
Antonio</placeName> the price of 1st rate cognac Brandy and Annisette cordials&#8212;
I have of the first upwards of 100 Gals, and of the latter, say
240 Gals,,&#8212;put up in casks of 12 Galls&#8212;if it is not too much trouble
you might possibly dispose of it, for me, deliverable here to some of
the <persName>traders </persName>of that place, I presume it is worth, from 3 to 4$ per
Gallon&#8212;will you My Dear Sir, at all events, write to me, as early
as your convenience will admit of,</p>

<p>If I have to go to <placeName>San Antonio</placeName>&#8212;I conceive the cheapest way,
would be to employ mules&#8212;but as they are not to be had here I have
to request, as a particular favor, that you would send them in&#8212;I
will require ten&#8212;and <persName>Mr McKinstry</persName> who will accompany me will
want eight more&#8212;and also two horses to ride&#8212;will you when you
write inform me whether Dry Goods are abundant or scarce in <placeName>San
Antonio</placeName> and <persName>Mr. McKinstry</persName>'s prospects in going there. I shall not
want the mules until I hear from you&#8212;If what I ask should in the
least interfere with your convenience, I beg you will tell me so 
without ceremony&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>C. B. Penrose</persName></p>

<p><persName>Col. S F Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
