<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1209">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>B. J. Thompson to Stephen F. Austin, 07-22-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>B. J. Thompson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-23">06-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nacogdoches, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1386-1387
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-07-22">07-22-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Turbulence at Nacogdoches. Asks Austin to indorse his request for permission to organize a volunteer
company for protection against Indians</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            
<p><placeName>State of Chuahuila and Texas</placeName></p>
<p><placeName>District of Nacogdoches</placeName> <date when="1826-07-22">22 July 1826</date></p>
<p>DrSiR</p>

<p>In my Communication to you of <date n="02-xx-1826">Febuary Last</date> as Respects 
obtaining a <placeName>grant </placeName>for Land in your <placeName>coloney </placeName>I Received a verbal Answer
by my <persName>father </persName>that you had Disposed of all your Land That you was
orthised to Let out at that Time&#8212;under those considerations I 
contracted for a claim of Land in this<placeName> section of country</placeName>&#8212;but sir heave
not abandoned the Idia of obtaining a <placeName>grant </placeName>of Land in your <placeName>Coloney</placeName>
when you are orthised to Let the same&#8212;</p>

<p>I could be verry well satisf yed to stay in <placeName>this section of the country</placeName>
If I could Do it in Peace But we are in a verry confused situation, no
Harmoney Existing, in society owing to the malesetious and 
Restless Disposition of one individual who is <persName>James gains</persName>&#8212;But sir I
will not Enter into a Detail of our grevances but will Refare you to
<persName>Judge Williams</persName> The Berier a worthy <persName>sitizen </persName>of this <placeName>Nabourhd </placeName>for
Infermation&#8212;When the<persName> People of this <placeName>section of country </placeName></persName>lernd that
your <placeName>colony </placeName>was Like to be Ingaiged in a war with the <persName>savages </persName>on
our <placeName>fruntears </placeName>I was seelisited to Raise or attempt to Raise a <persName>company
of volanteers</persName> to assist your or Do and perform all services Required<pb n="1387"/>
in Defence of our <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;I applied to the sd <persName>James gains</persName> and the
<persName>alcalde of <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></persName> who assumed the commend of the <persName>Malitia </persName>of
this <placeName>Districk </placeName>for Permeetion to Raise a <persName>company </persName>of that kind which
was granted</p>

<p>on the <date when="1826-07-12">12 of this Instant</date> I Drew and article (which you will see
in my communication Through you to the government&#8212;marked No
(1) my first attempt and my success, and on the <date when="1826-07-21">21st</date> I receved the
order from the <persName>alcalde </persName>that you will find marked in said 
communication No (2) forbiding me to Proseed any further I concluded to
stay any further Proseeding untill I could ask the Permission of
government for order to organise a <persName>company </persName>of that kind or 
Directions to Desist and abandon the Idea of any further Persuit on the
subject I have taken the liberty to make my communication through
you to the <persName>governor of these States</persName>, If you can feel a willingness to
assist us I know It is in your Power and your friendship would be
greatfully Remembered by the good <persName>People of this <placeName>District </placeName></persName>I hope
sir from our long acquaintance you could not harbor any Idia of any
unfriendly motives I had in my attempt to Raise sd <persName>Company </persName>I
do assirt to you upon the honer of a man that It was from the Purest
motives and only to Raise the <persName>company </persName>for the Purpose as mentioned
in my communication and to Establish Peace and Hormioney in the
<placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;If you concer in the steps I heave taken I hope sir you will
Lend me your assistance in sending on my Patisction to government
in a maner that you think will be Recived making any alteration you
may Deem nessary not to alter the Intent or meaning there off&#8212;I
should be much Pleased to heave your oppinion on the subject and
what Ever you advise I will cheerfully submit to I could Raise a
Hundred stout hardy Resolute men men to assist you If nessary
well armd and acquipt all we want is the sanction of government
which I hope we will obtain</p>

<p>My <persName>Father </persName>and <persName>Brother </persName>wishes to be Remembered to you&#8212;Pleas</p>

<p>to Remember me to your <persName>Brother</persName>, and Accept for your self the Best
wishes</p>
<p>Your verrey Humble servent</p>

<p><persName>B, J, Thompson</persName></p>
<p><persName>Col. S, F, Austin</persName>   </p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
