<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1127">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>C. Dyer,David Hamilton, William Spence, Joseph Newman, Nicholas Whitehead, John Clark, Thomas J. Rabb, Charles Henderson, Moses Windham, William Luce, Alexander Brown, ANdrew Rabb, John Ingram, Gabriel Straw Snyder, Andrew Rabb to Unknown, 04-27-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>C. Dyer,David Hamilton, William Spence, Joseph Newman, Nicholas Whitehead, John Clark, Thomas J. Rabb, Charles Henderson, Moses Windham, William Luce, Alexander Brown, ANdrew Rabb, John Ingram, Gabriel Straw Snyder, Andrew Rabb</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-11">06-11-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1319-1321
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Affidavits</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-04-27">04-27-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Affidavits concerning an attack on Tonkaway Indians.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>"This is to certify that <persName>Mr. Martin Allen</persName> told me that he was
with the <persName>company </persName>who made the late attack upon the<persName> Tonkua 
Indians</persName>; and that he was very much opposed to shooting, he also
stated, that when he came <placeName>near the camps</placeName> he saw the <persName>Indians </persName>in
great confusion; one standing up talking Spanish, and shewing
every appearance of friendship; frequently heard him say amigo&#8212;
<persName>Mr. Allen</persName> also stated that he ran forward and halloed don't shoot,
dont shoot, and did every thing in his power to prevent shooting;
but that it had no effect untill part of the <persName>men </persName>had fired.

</p>
<p><date when="1826-04-27">April, 27,1826</date></p>

<p>(Signed)           <persName>C. Dyer</persName>."<pb n="1320"/></p>

<p>In consequence of reports which have been put in circulation by
<persName>Mr. Martin Allen</persName>, calculated to prejudice the <persName>public </persName>against the
late encounter with the <persName>Tonkua Indians</persName>, we do hereby certify that
the conduct of <persName>Mr. Allen</persName> on that occasion was altogether contrary to
what he has since stated it to hare been&#8212;We believe, according to
the conduct of<persName> Mr. Allen</persName> at the <placeName>camp</placeName>, and his subsequent declaration,
that he did his utmost to kill an <persName>Indian</persName>, and that he lost his hat in
endeavoring to get a Shot&#8212;We believe that the conduct of the 
<persName>Indians </persName>was such as to induce a reasonable expectation that they
would not submit to lighter punishment than that of killing-&#8212;They
shewed no disposition either by words or signs, to give the <persName>company</persName>
a friendly reception.&#8212;Nor did they cry out Amigo as has been
stated by <persName>Mr. Allen</persName>&#8212;<persName>Mr. Allen</persName>'s alleged mediation in favor of them
is without foundation It has been stated that the <persName>company </persName>entered
the <placeName>Indian camps</placeName> with their guns cocked and presented; this we
consider as a malicious and unfounded falsehood
<date when="1826-04-23">April 23, 1826</date>>
</p>

        <p> (Signed)  <persName>David Hamilton </persName><persName> Charles Henderson</persName></p>
<p><persName>William Spence </persName><persName>Moses Windham</persName></p>
<p><persName>Joseph Newman</persName><persName>William Luce</persName></p>
<p><persName>Nicholas Whitehead</persName><persName> Alexander Brown</persName></p>
<p><persName>John Clark</persName><persName> Andrew Rabb</persName></p>
<p><persName>Thos. J. Rabb </persName> <persName> John Ingram</persName></p>

<p>"This is to certify that a party of <persName>Tonkua Indians</persName> came, a few
days before the late attack was made upon them, and encamped
 <placeName>within half a mile or three quarters of myhouse</placeName>;&#8212;They remain at
that camp about two days; on the second day six of my hogs were
missing; I supposed they had been killed by the <persName>Indians</persName>, because
they slept at <placeName>home </placeName>every night, and none of them had been killed
by vermin for a considerable time before, and I believe nothing else
could have killed so many in one day&#8212;One of the <persName>Indians </persName>I knew
to be of the <persName>party </persName>that broke open my <placeName>house </placeName>upwards of <date n="05-xx-1825">twelve
months ago</date>.</p>

<p><date when="1826-05-01">May 1, 1826</date></p>

<p>signed           <persName>Gabriel Straw Sxyder</persName> "</p>

<p>"I do hereby certify that a party of <persName>Tonkuas </persName>came to my <placeName>house </placeName>a
few days before the late attack was made upon them; my <persName>wife </persName>being
alone, and not knowing what <persName>Indians </persName>they were, was very much
alarmed at the sight of them,&#8212;She immediately left the <placeName>house</placeName>
and endeavored to get to the <placeName>field </placeName>where I was at work; on her way
to the field she saw two or three <persName>Indians </persName>coming towards her, she
then started to run, one of them ran after her with a large butcher
knife in his hand, caught her by the hand and endeavored to make
her return to the <placeName>house</placeName>, but finding she was determined not to com-<pb n="1321"/>
ply, he took her shoes off her feet; She then began to halloo for me,
upon which he let her go and said amigo; not understanding him
she kept on to the field; I immediately went to the <placeName>house </placeName>but the
<persName>Indians </persName>were gone and had left her shoes in the yard
</p>
<p>April 27,1826</p>
<p>signed           <persName>C. Dyer</persName>."</p>

<p>" We certify that a few days previous to the late affair with the
<persName>Tonkuas</persName>, a <persName>party </persName>of them came to our <placeName>camp </placeName>and stole upwards
of five bushels of corn which lay at a short distance from the <placeName>camp</placeName>;
they also took a few pounds of meat, cut up too gunrods and two
strait edges that were used in hewing, and carried off a whet stone;
the meat might possibly have been destroyed by vermin but the
other things could have been taken by nothing but the <persName>Indians</persName></p>

<p><date when="1826-05-02">May 2,1826</date></p>

<p>signed           <persName>And. Rabb</persName></p>

<p><persName>Thos. J. Rabb</persName>."</p>

<p>I certify that the above certificate of <persName>And. and Thos. J. Rabb</persName> in
regard to the conduct of the <persName>Indians </persName>at their camp is correct.
<date when="1826-05-02">May 2,1826</date></p>
<p>
(Signed)           <persName>John Ingram</persName></p>
<p>[Endorsed by <persName>Austin</persName>:] relative to the attack on the <persName>Tonkaways</persName>
on <placeName>Peach Creek</placeName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
