<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1077">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Mrs. Emily Perry to Stephen F. Austin, 04-10-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Mrs. Emily Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-07">06-07-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J. E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mine a Breton, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Natchitoches, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1072-1074
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-04-10">04-10-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-07" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Biographical.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mine á Burton</placeName> <date when="1825-04-10">April 10th 1825</date>.</p>
<p>My Dear <persName>Brother</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I received your short epistle some time since giving me the pleasing
news of your safe arrival at <placeName>home</placeName> I had become extremely anxious
for you, the letters that you wrote from the <placeName>diferant towns on the
River</placeName>, for some cause or other were a great while coming to hand
I received a letter from My Dear <persName>Stephen</persName> dated in <date n="12-xx-1825">December</date> which
gave me much more satisfaction, and pleasure, than the one received
by <persName>Mr. Hale</persName> in his last he appears to be reconciled and pleased with
my choice of a <persName>companion</persName>; and I have not the least doubt but when
he comes to know <persName>Mr. Perry</persName> better that he will approve of my
choice still more<pb n="1073"/></p>

<p>Your <persName>friends</persName> are all well, as far as I know. <persName>Uncle Austin's
family</persName> still remain as they were when you left this, nothing is done
towards closing the <placeName>estate </placeName><persName>Moses</persName> lives at the place, and has the four
<persName>boys </persName>with him, and<persName> Eliza</persName> the girls, <persName>Margaret</persName> has never return'd to
live with <persName>Mrs. S. Perry</persName> neather do I know weather they intend to
let her, poor <persName>Girls </persName>through the foolish pride of their elder <persName>sister</persName>
they are prevented from receiving many advantages that they other
wise would have&#8212;<persName> William</persName> has got into some kind of business in
<placeName>Georga</placeName> that brings him in three hundred Dollars a year&#8212;and is
not expected in this <placeName>country </placeName>for two or three years&#8212; <persName>Cousin
Adeline</persName> was married on the <date when="1825-12-23">23rd of December</date> and commenced house
keeping in a short time after, in the house that <persName>Lewis</persName> had his <placeName>office</placeName>;
<persName>Mrs. Henry Elliot</persName> has established herself at this place and has a
very good <placeName>school</placeName>; and I hope will be much more fortunate than she
was at <placeName>St. Louis</placeName>&#8212; I expect a visit from <persName>Mrs. Carr</persName> in <date n="06-xx-1825">June</date>, she has
had a very long and seviar fit of illness, which come very near 
terminating her valuable life&#8212;</p>

<p>I hope my Dearest <persName>James</persName> you will exert your self to try and 
perswaid our Dear <persName>Brother</persName> to visit this <placeName>Country</placeName>; you know very well
how necessary it is for him to come on, and their is but one thing
that I know of to prevent him, and your exertions aded to his own
I am sure would overcome that difficulty, for I well know that
<persName>Stephen</persName> will never visit <placeName>Missouri</placeName> untill he has it in his power to
sattisfy every clame that is against him, and I trust it will not be
long before he will be able to realize as much Money as will set him
clear of the world, and have something considerable to compensate
him for all the fatigue boath of body and mine, that he has suffered
for the Last six years. O it will be a most joyful period to me, when
I shall have the pleasure of embracing my dear <persName>Brother</persName>, the 
companion of my Youth, and presenting to him my Young and Growing
<persName>Family</persName>, I still flatter my self that I shall yet live to enjoy many
happy days [in the] society of my <persName>Brothers</persName>, and perhaps be a
neig[hbor] <persName>Mr. Perry</persName> wrote a very long letter to <persName>Stephen</persName> 
[sometime] since, which I hope will come safe to hand,&#8212;I was pleased, and
provoked my dear <persName>Brown</persName> at [your] letter or note, you must have
been very [much pressed] for time; for you did not write more than
a doz[en Lines] you certainly could not of been at a loss, for 
[material] when writing to your <persName>Sister</persName> who feels the [greatest] interest
in every thing that concerns you; pr[ay] take on all the things that
you started with, or did - - - safe, I am fearful that you lost
some of your clothes [you] left one of your new shirts at<persName> Elias
Bates</persName>; which [I will] send on to you by <persName>Esq. Andrews</persName>, who expects
to [go in the] Faul, he has sold his farm for five hundred Dollars&#8212;
The <persName>Children</persName> are all well, and often taulk of you   <persName>Austin</persName> pro-<pb n="1074"/>
gress[es] very well at <placeName>school</placeName>, they say that [you must] keep their
poneys for them;&#8212;for that they intend [going] as soon as <persName>Uncle
Stephen</persName> or <persName>Brown</persName> gits Married&#8212; My Dearest <persName>Brother </persName>I beg of
you to write [often] you cannot conceive the pleasure <persName>Mr. Perry</persName>
[and I] feals when ever we receive letters from you. [Be assur]ed
that they shall be punctually answered ea[ther by him] or myself,
<persName>Mr. Perry</persName> joins with me and the <persName>Children</persName> in [praying for] the
health happiness and prosperity of your self and <persName>Stephen</persName>; I [hope
you will] not forgit to send <persName>Mrs. John Perry</persName> the Seeds you promised
her, she has [gone to] <placeName>Orleas</placeName>, for a short time&#8212;
</p>
<p>Your Affectionate <persName>Sister, Emily</persName></p>

<p><persName>Col. Stephen F Austin</persName> [for <persName>J. E. B. Austin</persName>] <placeName>San Felipe de Austin
</placeName><placeName>Rio Brazos, Province of Texas </placeName>To the care of <persName>Jared Cable Esq</persName><placeName>Natchitoches Louisianna</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
