<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1255">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Elias R. Wightman to Stephen F. Austin, 08-23-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Elias R. Wightman</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-09">07-09-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1436-1437
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-08-23">08-23-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Application for town site.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>The <persName>Petition </persName>of the undersigned respectfully REPRESENT, that
haveing removed to this <placeName>country</placeName>, with an intention of settling in it
permanently as one of the <persName>settlers </persName>which you are authorized to 
introduce, as <persName>Empresario</persName>, He has examined a piece of <placeName>land on the east Side
of the Rio Colorado</placeName>, being <placeName>near its mouth and being the extremity of
the high Prairie</placeName>; and the most suitable place for the landing of
<persName>families</persName>, who emigrate, by water, to that part of the <placeName>country</placeName>.</p>

<p>At this time there are no <placeName>settlements </placeName>of any kind, <placeName>at, or near, the
said landing-place</placeName>, which render it both dangerous, and inconvenient
for <persName>Emigrants </persName>to disembark there; dangerous, in consequence of 
exposure to the <persName>Karonkawa Indians</persName>, who are hostile, and infest that
part of the <placeName>Bay-Shore</placeName>, Inconvenient oweing to the want of <placeName>Houses</placeName>,
to receive <persName>Emigrants</persName>, and store up their property, on this first 
landing. In consequence of which many are detered from emigrating to
that part of the <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;A number of my <persName>friends</persName>, and 
acquaintances and particularly <persName>H. H. League</persName>, <persName>James C. Ludlow</persName> who have
explored the <placeName>country</placeName>, and entered into arrangements, with you as
<persName>Empresario </persName>for their reception as <persName>settlers </persName>together with a number
of other <persName>families</persName>, whom they expect to bring have a desire to land
at the above mentioned place provided suitable <placeName>buyldings</placeName>, can be
provided for the security of their <persName>families</persName>, and, products and they
have requested me to erect, such necessary <placeName>buyldings </placeName>provided it meets
with the approbation of the constituted local authority of the 
<persName>Government</persName>.</p>

<p>Therefore your <persName>Petitioner </persName>prays permission to occupy said place
for the above purposes and that a <placeName>grant </placeName>of one League of land may
be made to him at said place, to erect such <placeName>buyldings </placeName>as he may put<pb n="1437"/>
up, in consideration of the great Service he will render the <placeName>Colony</placeName>,
and the <placeName>Country </placeName>by facilitating emigration, and in order to inable
him to support his <persName>family </persName>on said land&#8212;</p>

<p>(Signed)          <persName> Elias R. Wightman</persName></p>

<p>considering the exposed situation of <persName>Emigrants </persName>to this <placeName>Country</placeName>
who land <placeName>at the mouth of the Colorado River</placeName>, in consequence of causes
set forth in the foregoing Petition; And haveing fully considered of
the necessity of such an establishment, as the one proposed, and the
general utility that would result to the <placeName>Country </placeName>therefrom, Therefore
I <persName>Stephen F. Austin Empresario</persName>, and <persName>Judge of this Jurisdiction</persName> do
hereby grant the <persName>Petition </persName>presented by the said <persName>Elias Wightman</persName>, to
occupy said place and to buyld the necessary <placeName>houses </placeName>for the 
accommodation and Security of <persName>Settlers </persName>referring him to the Government of the
<placeName>State</placeName>, or the <persName>Commissioner </persName>appointed by the Government for this
<placeName>Colony </placeName>to apply for a title to the land which he solicits with the
understanding that this permission is to be subject to the approval
of the said <persName>Government</persName>, or <persName>Commissioner </persName>as they may deem proper,
and Knowing the great expense and hasard attending the Execution
of such Improvements and <placeName>buyldings </placeName>as are contemplated in 
consequence of the hostility of the <persName>Indians</persName>, and the remoteness of the
<placeName>Settlements </placeName>I do recommend the <persName>Petition </persName>of the said <persName>Elias Wightmen
</persName>for the grant of a League of Land, to the particular attention of
Government, or <persName>Commissioners</persName>, and should it be consistent with the
laws to make such <placeName>Grant </placeName>I recommend that it be made as prayed for&#8212;</p>

<p><placeName>Sn Felipe de Austin</placeName></p>

<p><date when="1826-08-23">August 23d 1826</date></p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
