<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1831">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 01-03-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-17">08-17-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Dr. Hutchison
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 317-318
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-01-03">01-03-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Urging him to move to Texas, and showing advantages of doing so at once.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin,</placeName> <date when="1830-01-03">Jany 3, 1830</date></p>
<p>Dr brother and Sister</p>

<p>Altho, I have written three letters to you within the last two
weeks on the subject of your removal to this <placeName>country</placeName>, I again repeat
the same advise contained in my other letters, least they may have
miscarried.<persName> Dr. Hutchison</persName> of the<placeName> Boons Lick country</placeName> takes on
this. He will remove, and perhaps <persName>Genl T. A. Smith </persName>(a <persName>brother</persName>
of <persName>Jack</persName>'s, tho quite a different man) will also remove in the <date n="Fall - 1830">fall</date>.
When such men as <persName>Genl Smith</persName> begin to turn their attention this
way, you may be sure the <placeName>country </placeName>must rise. I have lately made an
arrangement for a large emigration of <persName>men </persName>of the first respectability
from <placeName>North Alabama </placeName>round <placeName>Tuscumbia</placeName>, <placeName>Huntsville </placeName>etc they are all
<persName>men of wealth.</persName> Within the last two months one hundred and fifty
three <persName>families </persName>have arrived and they are generally of the better
class and <persName>men of property</persName>. In a year more this <placeName>colony </placeName>will be filled
up, <hi rend="italic">now then is the time</hi>, if you remove soon you must make a 
fortune. The land I have asked for, for you and <persName>Emily </persName>I have no doubt
will be granted&#8212;that is <persName>Eleven Leagues</persName> but the title will be void 
unless you remove. I have asked two years for you to remove in, but
am of opinion that only one year will be granted. I can do 
something for you now but after my colonizing business is done, the door
will be closed in comparison to what it is now.</p>

<p>The whole expenses of a <placeName>League </placeName>to a <persName>settler </persName>is about $150, and
there is 4, 5, and 6 years to pay a part of that. Many of the <persName>settlers</persName>
are poor and will give one half to any one who clears out and pays
the expenses on the <placeName>whole League</placeName>.</p>

<p>In <date n="11-xx-1830">November next</date> the <placeName>custom house</placeName> will be established and duties
collected, for the law which exempted <placeName>Texas </placeName>from all duties for
seven years will expire in <date n="11-xx-1830">November</date>, so that you ought to be here
with an assortment of goods before <date n="11-xx-1830">November</date>.</p>

<p><persName>Slaves </persName>cannot be introduced as <persName>slaves</persName>, but as <persName>indented </persName>or <persName>hired
servants</persName>. I shall start in about <date when="1830-01-13">ten days</date> to survey the <placeName>land I have
petitioned for</placeName>, for you, and select a <placeName>building place</placeName>, and then write
more particularly. If you will send on a trusty <persName>man </persName>with two or
three <persName>hands </persName>to build some <placeName>cabins </placeName>it would not be amiss to do so.
Stock cattle can be got for goods and if you can bring on a good
<persName>family </persName>to put on your land and tend stock you might soon have a
1000 head. Beeves may be shipped <placeName>from the spot to Orleans </placeName>not
more than four days run&#8212;in fact to include all in a few words
<hi rend="italic">you must remove and that immediately</hi>.</p>

<p>My constitution is failing rapidly, and I want you here, to see
my <persName>sisters children</persName> all provided for before I die.</p>

<p>Bring all kinds and barrels of fruit seed of the best kind.<pb n="318"/></p>

<p>In dry weather there is a very good <placeName>wagon or carriage road</placeName> <placeName>from
Alexandria to this place</placeName>. You can take choice of roads either to
send everything by water, and bring the <persName>family </persName>out in a carriage
from <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, or embark the <persName>family </persName>in <placeName>Orleans </placeName>and come by
water. The <placeName>road </placeName>is a very good one and much used and it is settled
and safe, the <placeName>settlements </placeName>tho are thin. You must bring bedding
and furniture. I have nothing of that kind and want some for
myself.</p>

<p>Send your articles or goods to <persName>James W. Breedlove</persName> <placeName>New Orleans
</placeName>with instructions to ship them to <persName>John Austin</persName> <placeName>Brazoria Texas.</placeName>
Also send your letters <hi rend="italic">postpaid </hi>by the same channel. Close your
affairs in that <placeName>country </placeName>and push on as fast as possible. I have
applied for a grant for <persName>Henry Austin</persName> who is now running a steam
boat on <placeName>Rio Grande.</placeName> If you come by land bring a decent carriage,
you will need it here, and if not, it can be sold. We are beginning
to get <hi rend="italic">up </hi>in this <placeName>country </placeName>and decent and fine clothes have taken
the place of buckskin.</p>

<p>Present my respects to my old friend <persName>Saml Perry</persName> and tell him my
advise is to quit that cold region and emigrate to <placeName>Texas</placeName>. With
his capital he might make a princely fortune here.</p>

<p>Do the same to my old friend <persName>John Perry</persName> and to his lively and
agreeable <persName>Lady</persName>. Why not all come? They can command my
friendship, and I can do something for them if they come quickly.</p>

<p>What are <persName>Elias Bates</persName> and <persName>Honey </persName>doing? Also <persName>James Austin's
children.</persName> I would get them <placeName>land </placeName>if they would come but I shall not
write to them anymore for I wished them all to move years ago,
and they [have] not even answered my letters. Bring <persName>Adeline</persName>.
She can get a league of land and a <persName>husband </persName>afterwards.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin.</persName>    [Rubric]</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
