<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1345">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John Sibley to Stephen F. Austin, 03-12-1827</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John Sibley</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-19">07-19-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Col. Thorn
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Natchitoches, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Nacogdoches, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1615-1616
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1827-03-12">03-12-1827</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-19" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Report that United States has acquired part of Texas. British designs on Cuba.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Natchitoches </placeName><date when="1827-03-12">March 12. 1827</date></p>
<p>Dr. Sir.</p>

<p>I had the pleasure to Receive your letter by <persName>Col Milam</persName> dated
<placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName><date when="1827-03-04">March 4th</date>&#8212;for which I thank you. You say you
had not Recd a packet I sent you by <persName>Mr. Dubois</persName> when I mentioned
that to <persName>Col. Milam</persName> he informed me that <persName>Dubois </persName>had not arrived
when he left you&#8212;I Embrace the Opportunity by <persName>Col Thorn</persName> of
sending you a few <placeName>papers </placeName>to which Refer you for the news as we
have it. several circumstances have Occurred corroborative of the
Report of <placeName>Taxas </placeName>or some part of it being ceded to the <placeName>United States</placeName>
it will in a short time be officially communicated<persName> Genl Gains</persName> left
here <date when="1827-03-12">this Morning</date> we shall heare from him from <placeName>Baton Rouge</placeName>
some new disposition of the <persName>U. S. Troops</persName> in this <placeName>quarter </placeName>will soon
be made a <persName>Regiment </persName>probably will soon be Rendezvoued at 
<placeName>Cantonment Jessup</placeName>&#8212; If it was possible for you to Remain in the
<placeName>district of Nacogdoches</placeName> for a short time I have no doubt but you
may be farther informed on that subject, it may be of great 
Interest. Our <persName>Congress </persName>Rose the <date when="1827-03-04">4th of March</date> without finishing one
half of the Business before them it may be necessary for the
<persName>President </persName>to call the <persName>members </persName>together again before the Meeting
Ordinary. Our Relations with <placeName>England </placeName>may Require it. There is
some Reason to believe <placeName>England </placeName>may attempt to occupy <placeName>Cuba </placeName>that
we cannot agree to, that Govt has already shut their <placeName>West India
Ports</placeName> to our Vessels, they would do the same in <placeName>Cuba </placeName>did they
command that <placeName>island</placeName>&#8212;<placeName>England </placeName>is now engaged in defending 
<placeName>Portugal </placeName>against the agressions of <placeName>Spain</placeName>, when that affair is finished,
which cannot last long they will be Looking Out for new 
Employment for their immence Land and Naval forse, the Bermes
War in <placeName>India </placeName>is settled.&#8212;</p>

<p>I send you some More <placeName>News papers </placeName>There is a man leaving here
by the name of <persName>John Williams</persName>, who says he lived some time in the
<placeName>Trinity Bay</placeName>, he says he has a Grant from you of a League Square
of Land you will oblige me if you will inform me if his Right
is a good one and if he should transfer his Right if it would be good,
and what formality would be required in Case of a sale. As I
contemplate moving into that <placeName>Country </placeName>in some future time I feel
Enclined to secure some Land for the Benefit of my <placeName>children</placeName>&#8212;Some
suspension of our correspondence did take place. I am not 
disposed to discuss the subject relative to who was in fault. I dislike
to look backwards, much more than forward.&#8212;You will greatly
Oblige me by attending to my demand against the State of <persName>John
McFarlane</persName> I am told his place is valuable. I will take that in<pb n="1616"/>
full discharge of my judgement provided by your Permission I can
obtain a Right.&#8212;you will Add to my present Obligations to you
If you will give me such information about it as the case will
suggest to you I might wish to know. Our <persName>Legislature </persName>will rise
this week, the <placeName>River </placeName>is in fine Steam Boating Order. I know of
nothing important the <persName>Legislature </persName>has done It has been occupied
much in private matters, giving the Right of granting divorces to
the <placeName>District Courts</placeName>, and seperating the corporation of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
are the principal things.</p>

<p>If I could have known at what time you would have been at
<placeName>Sabine </placeName>I certainly would have met you there, we wish much to
have some arangement about our Exchange of Mails from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>When you see your <persName>Brother </persName>please to present to him my 
compliments and Best wishes. I wish he would write to me occasionally
a correspondence with him would give me pleasure. I shall be
glad to serve him and you in any way in my Power. I Expect
<persName>Judge Johnston</persName> in three or four Weeks, his family will remain
at <placeName>Washington </placeName>of course his visit to <placeName>Louisiana </placeName>will be short.
</p>
<p>John Sibley</p>

<p><persName>Hon S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Honble. Stephen F. Austin </persName><placeName>Nacogdochis</placeName>-by <persName>Col
Thorn</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
