<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1081">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Aylett C. Buckner to Stephen F. Austin, 04-20-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Aylett C. Buckner</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-07">06-07-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Colorado, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1076-1077
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-04-20">04-20-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-07" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Thinks Austin is treating him unfairly in distribution of land. Recites his claims and makes a strong case.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Colorado</placeName> <date when="1825-04-20">20th April 1825</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p>The <placeName>lands</placeName> I made choice of was never taken by any <persName>person </persName>
previous to my locations one of which I have been informed you have
taken from me after having your word which I conceived sufficient
I should have one league and a half: I wrote to you to reduce the
quantity of my land rather than people should blame you on my
account&#8212;</p>

<p>Now Sir in <date n="xx-xx-1812">1812</date> and <date n="xx-xx-1813">1813 </date>I fought for that independence under
which we now live Commanded by <persName>Guterrez</persName> and advanced property
for the good of the <persName>Expedition</persName>; after which I was conserned with
<persName>Genl Menes [Mina]</persName>: after which with <persName>Genl Truspilassos</persName> and <persName>Long</persName>
and lost considerable property taken by <persName>Enatio Paris</persName> all of which
I believe I can make manifest to the world: In addition I was
one of the first <persName>men </persName>who built a <placeName>Cabbin </placeName><placeName>on this River</placeName>, the first <persName>man</persName>
who had a plough stuck in the field I have kept a house ever since
I have been settled in your<placeName> Colony</placeName> I have never asked the first
Cent for a <persName>man </persName>eating under my Roof and have fed as many and
I believe more people than any man in this <placeName>Colony</placeName> Yourself not
excepted and have not recd the first cent I have lost as much and
I believe more property by the depradations of <persName>Indians</persName> than every
other man on this <persName>River</persName> or perhaps in the <persName>Colony</persName> with very few
exceptions Consequently I consider Myself as Much entitled to be
satisfyed as other men ought to be and My impressions were that
you would not take away my land even if you did not think proper
to give Me what you said you would; but that I might apply to
<persName>Government</persName> for the <placeName>lands </placeName>which I located and if I cannot obtain
satisfaction from you I shall most certainly loose No time in 
having recourse to our Government stating all the rights and reasons
of my demands&#8212;</p>

<p>Now Sir I will appeal to your-self or any candid man whither
other men ought to have more <placeName>land </placeName>or has a better right to request
more than Myself or Not   I know no other reasons of their getting<pb n="1077"/>
better treated except that they have more Money&#8212;I have viewed
every thing in as fair a light as I could; from report I know that
sum men get half a league and dont pay a cent because the other
half is transferred to <persName>You</persName> or <persName>Your Brother</persName> I know that lands are
unequilly divided I do not considder Myself a perfect <persName>simpleton</persName>
neither am I blind My Eyes are open and I look and watch with
vigilence: My demands are small compared to what the demands
of others are and in as Much as My sufferings have been great and
in the hight of friendship I hope you will grant them which are
My two <placeName>locations</placeName> I have previously Made if You refuse granting
that which I think the Government will generously bestow on me
I shall apply to that <persName>authority </persName>which governs us both for so much
as I think in justice I am lacking&#8212;</p>

<p>As I shall have <persName>Company </persName>in a short time to go with and the
means of going I wish you to give me a positive and speedy answer
so that I May know what to do</p>
<p>Yours Eespectfully</p>
<p>
<persName>A.   C.  Buckner</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
