<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1754">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>H D Thompson to Stephen F Austin, 08-19-2010</title>
            <author>
                <persName>H D Thompson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-12">8-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 247-248
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="2010-08-19">08-19-2010</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Giving account of the illness and death from yellow fever of Austin's brother, James Brown
Austin. The Spanish invasion of Mexico.  New Orleans August 19th 1829</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, <date when="1829-08-19">August 19, 1829</date>.</p>
<p>Respected Sir</p>

<p>It is a painefull task for me to Communicate the unwelcome 
tydings to you of the loss of so near and so dear a <persName>friend </persName>to you as well
to his <persName>wife </persName>and <persName>famaley</persName>; though gods will&#8212;to take him from this
troublesome <placeName>wourld</placeName>&#8212;we aught not to Repine&#8212;but hope for his
greater happyness in the next the attachment I had for your
brother<persName> J. B. ostin</persName> was not a little I Can ashure you&#8212;though we had
not seen each other&#8212;since the year <date n="xx-xx-1825">1825</date>&#8212;at the town of <placeName>Matamores</placeName>,
when we became acquainted and was pritty much to geather&#8212;
Boarded in one house, and spent our times simeler&#8212;another 
oppertunity afforded us a renewel of our acquaintence, though of but
vary short duration   several times I Called on<placeName> board of the vessel</placeName><pb n="248"/>
to see him but each time found him absent and anxiously imployed
in his buiseness&#8212;on <date when="1829-08-11">tuesday morning the 14</date> we by axident met
each other in <placeName>Charter. St</placeName>&#8212;he being some what altered in the face
than at the time we had last seen each other, I did not amediately
Recognize him but he knew me at once in the Course of our 
Conversation he observed you had received a letter from me and would
have written but for some thing that intervened; we was both glad
to see each other it then being a bout a quarter past 6 a m. oClock
and the weather being excessively hot&#8212;<persName>Mr ostin</persName><persName> Captn Harris</persName> and
myself went in to <placeName>Swansons Coffee house</placeName> to take a meeting and
friendly glass&#8212;we Done So&#8212;parted and was soon to meet a gain-
that <date when="1829-08-11">evening </date>was the time he lotted to Call at my <placeName>house</placeName>&#8212;to 
Consult on various subjects&#8212;one of which was that of the Brig Gen1
Moralies&#8212;which I have Command of&#8212;but poor man that was our
last interview&#8212;at a bout <date when="1829-08-11">one oclock that Same day</date> he was takeing
with a pain at the pit of the stummac and a slight paine in the
head he had, complained in the morning while in Company with
<persName>Captn Hs</persName> and my self&#8212;of being a little unwell. I observed to him
he ought to make use of a umberrela he replyed that he was acustome
to being in the sun&#8212;and apprehended no danger, my not being
acquainted of his being takeing down so ill&#8212;-was the Cause of my
not being with him in his last moments&#8212;which I would done
Chearfully, Could but been of service I have no doubt but he 
Received every attention from <persName>Mr Williams</persName>. <persName>Mr Coliens</persName>&#8212;and others
belonging to the<placeName> house of <persName>Mr Coliens</persName>.</placeName> <persName>Mcfarling </persName>was his <persName>phisition</persName>
he hearetofore was varry fortunate with his <persName>patience </persName>I Cannot
say wheather the time was not prolonged in Calling for medicle
ade&#8212;</p>

<p>he expired on <date when="1829-08-14">friday morning</date> at three oClock and I am told 
without much agany or pain he was entered in a <placeName>tumbe </placeName>arected for him
at five oClock P, M-&#8212;and had a deasent funerel his loss is much
Regretted by all-&#8212;that knew him I am well a waire my self I lost
a friend-&#8212;may heaven Rest his soul in peace-&#8212;Comforte and provide
for his esteemed <persName>wife </persName>and <persName>famoley </persName>whom is left behind to lement his
death&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>H. D. Thompson</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Colonol. S. F. Austin</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>P. S; I Received a letter Dated <placeName>veracruze </placeName><date when="1829-07-31">31st of July</date>, Stateing
that <persName>Commodore David Porter</persName> was still in <placeName>mexeco </placeName>and that he was
some what indisposed. <persName>Congres </persName>is to Convene-&#8212;amediately. none
of the <persName>spannish fleete</persName> has yet been seen of <placeName>veracruze</placeName>-&#8212; several 
gunboates and some pecises of Cannon has been sent down to 
<placeName>Campeachy</placeName>&#8212; a Report sais that three thousand <persName>troopes </persName>had landed <placeName>15
leagues to the south of tampeco</placeName>&#8212;- now is the time to harvest if the
<persName>mexecans </persName>would only grant Commicions for the sea is Covered with<pb n="249"/>
old <persName>spanyards </persName>and their property never Could there be a greater
harvest Could there be Commissions for <persName>Privateers </persName>obtained, the
Brig Genl Marallas ought to been Cruizeing this 4 or 6 months past
She Could not helped makeing a fortune for all <persName>hands </persName>how easy
Could she picked up some of the transports, one that has arived
hear with 500 <persName>troopes </persName>there would been no dificulty in Captoring
the whole of them&#8212; they are now incamped at the <placeName>english turn</placeName>,
it is saide weighting the arivle of Some armed vessel to take them
off&#8212; the fever Rages hear vilently from the <date n="08-01-1829  to 08-08-1829">first to the eighth of
this month </date>there was 180 interments greater part of whome was
<persName>Catholis </persName>and old <persName>Spanyards</persName>. 60 hours after they are takeing is
about the time they last&#8212; the fever is Considdered to be of 
different tipe, to what has been heare to <hi rend="italic">fore </hi>their is more shiping now in
<placeName>port </placeName>than ever has been known at <date n="Summer - 1829">this season of the year before</date>&#8212;
two vessels arived from the <placeName>Riogrand </placeName>with <persName>Passengers </persName>and money
one Reports that the<persName> St ana</persName>, <persName>Captn potter</persName> was seen on the <date when="1829-08-06">6, inst</date>&#8212;off
the <placeName>Brasses </placeName>Sttiango standing to the S E. she sailed the day 
previous to them.&#8212; their is hourly expected some arivles from 
<placeName>veracruwze</placeName>, by which we Contemplate hearing some favourable tydings
Relative to the <persName>Navy </persName>being fited out&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Colonal Ostin</persName></p>

<p>Sir if I can in any way be of service to you hear you have ownly
got to Command me,</p>

<p><persName>H. D. Thompson</persName>    [Rubric]</p>
<p><persName>S. F. Osten Esqr</persName></p>

<p><placeName>St Philipy. Osten Settlement
Provence.   Texes   Mexico</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
