<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1028">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Archibald Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 01-30-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Archibald Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-05-25">05-25-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1027-1029
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-01-30">01-30-1825, 01-31-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-05-25" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Plans for trade with Texas and asking for information about products.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            
<p><placeName>New York</placeName> <date when="1825-01-30">Jany 30, 1825</date></p>
<p><persName>Stephen Austin Esq</persName>.</p>
<p><placeName>St Phillippe,</placeName></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I have had the pleasure of two letters from you, in reply to the
enquiries, made by me some time since, I was much gratified to hear
you had effected arrangements in regard to your <placeName>Colony </placeName>, to your
must sanguine expectations, and that it was in a flourishing condition
&#8212;I felt very much disposed to send a Vessel with the articles
you stood in need of&#8212;I could not make up my mind to go myself,
immediately, leaving a situation where I now get $1200. per annum,
which enables me to support my <persName>family</persName>, to venture upon an uncertanty
&#8212;I represented the advantages that would probably arrive
from a commercial Intercourse with your <placeName>Colony </placeName>, to <persName>John </persName>, he was
pleased with the project, and expressed a disposition to become 
interested, we however concluded to wait the arrival of <persName>Henry </persName> who
was soon expected, under the persuasion that he would become 
Interested, and perhaps go himself&#8212;He did arrive and on perusing
your letters appeared much pleased and talked strongly of going
himself, and so it continued doubtful until a few weeks ago, when
he made up his mind suddenly to go to <placeName>Alvarado</placeName> with the intention
of Establishing himself at <placeName>Xalapa</placeName> in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, in the Commission
Business, for which place he sailed about Ten days since, and most
unfortunately for me, he took your letters with him; particularly,
as the day after he sailed, <persName>John </persName> informed me that a Friend of ours,
would like to join us in the proposed expedition&#8212;Since which, I
have seen the Gentleman alluded to, and find he is anxious to enter
into the Business, and thinks we can proceed in it, among ourselves
without any difficulty&#8212;</p>

<p>the principal stumbling Block, is the uncertainty of punctual 
returns in such articles as will answer, for the Investments we may<pb n="1028"/>
make&#8212;Cotton of a good staple would of course answer very well,
and be perfectly satisfactory, if at a price that would pay a fair
profit when brought to this market; to do this it would of course
require to be well cleaned, and pressed so as to make good stourage
on ship board&#8212;this we have no doubt may be accomplished eventually, 
but we see no immediate prospect of it&#8212;when we send a Vessel,
we intend to send a Gin, and probably a pressing machine, both
which will be very essential with you&#8212;perhaps you make a press
with you that would answer the purpose for the present, but our
patent pump presses I pressume will be important for you, when you
get well underway with your <placeName>cotton plantations</placeName>&#8212;please inform me
on this point&#8212;Had my own means admitted of it, I would have had
a Vessel off long ago, with the articles you wrote for&#8212;Hogs, I am
informed by a Gentleman who has resided in <placeName>Mahtanzes</placeName>, are pro™
hibited in <placeName>Cuba</placeName>, and Horses would be too cumbersome for the 
discription of vessel we propose sending&#8212;Corn is but a poor article to
ship, except to the <placeName>Western Islands</placeName>, <placeName>Tenriffe</placeName> etc, and there it would
probably not answer, so much is shipped from hence&#8212;I regret 
extremely that <persName>Henry </persName> should have taken the letters away, as it leaves
me quite in the dark, in various particulars such as the proper place,
for the vessel to run for the courses, signal poles etc the <persName>Tribe of
Indians that you are at war with</persName>, being between your residence, and
the <placeName>entrance to the River</placeName> is rather against the concern&#8212;</p>

<p>It is thought advisable under all circumstances, to write you a gain,
and urge your immediate reply to several enquiries, which if tangible, and can be carried into effect, would probably be very important,
such as&#8212;Is there a road that Goods can be conveyed upon to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>,
or to the borders, or dividing line between you and <placeName>Mexico</placeName> ? what is
the distance? could not there be an arrangement made, to receive
goods calculated for the <placeName>Mexican market</placeName>, on your <placeName>Territory [Mexican Texas]</placeName>, or on
the dividing line of the <placeName>Mexican Territory</placeName> ?•&#8212;in barter for Cochineal,
Vanilla, Pimento, Indigo, and for Specie&#8212;Could they be conveyed
without being subject to Duty, and without risk? what would be
the time required, and what would be the Expense&#8212;does your <placeName>Colony </placeName>
produce Cochineal, or Indigo ? or do they, or will they bring either
to it, or would they if a temptation is held out?&#8212;we should like to
send a <persName>confidential agent</persName> to communicate with you, and to attend to
our business; but it will not justify it at present&#8212;</p>

<p>We wish you to be very particular in the list of articles that will
answer best to send, and the returns, the kind and quantity of 
Tobacco&#8212;the Mill stones I have not forgotten&#8212;I should suppose some
of our patent corn cleaners would be desirable&#8212;are you not in want
of many kinds of agricultural Implements? How would the 
apparatus for a Distillery answer?&#8212;If we could once get underway I<pb n="1029"/>
have no doubt we might be mutually advantageous to each other
with your aid in this business, I promise myself very favorable 
results ; I am confident you will grant it freely, as I am persuaded it
would be more gratifying to you, to do business with your connections 
and friends, than with strangers&#8212;I should be much delighted
to see you here, but I pressume that is out of the question at present,
perhaps <persName>your Brother</persName> may come, however&#8212;</p>

<p>I sincerely condole with you, on the loss of your dear <persName>Mother </persName>, it
must have deprived you, of much joy that you had anticipated in
making her happy the remainder of her life&#8212;Poor <persName>Horace</persName> is gone
also; I have no doubt he had much to contend with during the latter
part of his life&#8212;</p>

<p>I observe by last Evenings paper, that <persName>the Senate</persName>, on Wednesday
last, passed by a large majority to a third reading the Bill, authorizing 
abroad to be marked out from <placeName>Missouri</placeName>, to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;This I should
suppose would be a good thing for you&#8212;pressume it must pass very
near you&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Mr Honey</persName> has arrived at <placeName>Baltimore</placeName> from <placeName>St. Louis</placeName>, will proceed
<persName>Mr Dall</persName> informs us to <placeName>Washington</placeName>, and then make <placeName>New York</placeName> a
visit&#8212;we shall be glad to see him, never having that pleasure, and
through him, shall hear I pressume many particulars about our
friends, those few that are left, (and of those that are gone) in that
quarter, of whom we have heard but very little for years past&#8212;we
have heard within a few days of the marriage of <persName>Mary Holley</persName>s
Daughter <persName>Harriet [Holley]</persName>, to <persName>Mr. Bran</persName>t of <placeName>Kentucky</placeName>, I know not whether
you ever saw her or not&#8212;</p>

<p><date when="1825-01-31">Jany 31</date>. from this morning paper&#8212;"In the Senate the Bill
authorizing the <persName>President </persName> to cause a road to be marked out be-
tween the <placeName>western frontier of Missouri</placeName> and the <placeName>Internal Provinces of
Mexico</placeName>, was read a third time passed and sent to the House for con-
currence&#8212;" I wish you to state the prices of such articles as you may
recommend will command with you&#8212;With my compliments to your
<persName>Brother </persName>, I remain with sincere regard, and affection</p>

<p>Your friend</p>

<p><persName><persName>Arch Austin</persName> </persName>   [Rubric]</p>




        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
