<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1816">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Jose Antonio Navarro, 12-24-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-16">08-16-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Jose Antonio Navarro
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Bexar, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 302-303
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-12-24">12-24-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Thinks Navarro's income as collector of customhouse at Galveston will be small. Future depends on policy of the Government. Late decree concerning slavery retards development. Commerce in the colony.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1829-12-24">24th of December [1829]</date></p>

<p>My esteemed <persName>friend </persName>:&#8212;</p>

<p>I received your letter of the <date when="1829-11-29">29th of last month</date> and I give you my
sincere thanks for the just reflections that you make relative to the
loss by early death of my <persName>brother</persName>. The mail arrived very late and
is now leaving and I have not time to write much.</p>

<p>In regard to the employment that the <persName>Government </persName>has given to
you as <persName>administrator [of the port] of Galveston</persName> I believe like you
that for some time it will not produce sufficient to live upon. If it
shall or shall not be productive in the future depends entirely on the
progress of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and it appears that this is doubtful on account
of the last decrees sent out by the <persName>legislature </persName>extraordinary and
unknown in the Constitution which has been established in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>.
I think if the <placeName>country </placeName>was well established the office would be of
sufficient consideration.<pb n="303"/></p>

<p>The <persName>father-in-law of Don Samuel</persName> lives on <placeName>San Jacinto</placeName>, and has
a boat suitable for going from the landing on that <placeName>river </placeName>to the
<persName>island of Galveston</persName>. If you think of making a visit you can do so
in this way without difficulty. The <placeName>Island </placeName>is depopulated and I
am of the opinion that now the <placeName>custom House</placeName> should be at <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>
on the <placeName>Brazos</placeName>.</p>

<p>The 75 lbs. of Coffee are in <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>and as soon as <persName>Soe</persName> comes I
will see that he takes it if he can do so.</p>

<p>I cannot say positively when the vessel will leave for <placeName>Orleans</placeName>.
The interest which my <persName>brother </persName>had in her has been sold&#8212;I will write
to <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>upon this particular and will advise you.</p>

<p>I shall be much pleased to see you here. I live with <persName>Don Samuel
</persName>and you must come direct to our <placeName>jacal </placeName>it is <placeName>one mile from the villeta</placeName>.</p>

<p>I shall not speak of the last letters, because I have no time to
answer them by this mail. I shall rest in the confidence and wisdom
of the <persName>authorities </persName>there. The memorial of our worthy <persName>chief of
department</persName> is most helpful, and can not fail to carry much influence.</p>

<p>By the next mail I shall write to you about your estimate 
concerning lands and shall only say now that if I can get the money I shall
return the estimate.</p>

<p>In regard to the decrees I shall only say that in not more than one
or two months at most notices of them will be spread through the
<placeName>Gazetas of Orleans</placeName> for from there they will receive notices every day
from <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, <placeName>Tampico </placeName>and <placeName>Matamoras</placeName>. I doubt not that there
are some in <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>whom, I shall see and speak to of this
matter with pleasure.</p>

<p>Give my respects to your <persName>brothers </persName>and to <persName>Mr. Ruiz</persName> and to your
<persName>father</persName>.</p>

<p>Your friend                                                  <persName>E. F. Austin.</persName></p>

<p>(P. S.) I forgot to say that you can come with mules and horses,
I think the first you can sell for money although this is an article
which is very scarce, and there is no certain market for anything in
money.</p>

<p><persName>E. F. A.</persName></p>

<p>Addressed to <persName>Jose Antonio Navarro</persName>   <placeName>Bejar</placeName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
