<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1120">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stpehen F. Austin to Captian Richard Fields, other chiefs and warriors of the Cherokee Nation , 04-24-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stpehen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-10">06-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Mr John R. Foster
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Captian Richard Fields
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         other chiefs 
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        warriors of the Cherokee Nation
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1307-1309
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-04-24">04-24-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asking cooperation and outlining plan for campaign against Waco and Tahuacano Indians. Austin's
relations with Shawnees in Missouri.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>My FRIENDS AND BROTHERS,</p>

<p>The <persName>Mexican Government</persName> have called on the new <persName>settlers </persName>of this
<placeName>Colony </placeName>to fight their <persName>enemies </persName>the <persName>Wacos </persName><persName>Tawakanies </persName>and <persName>Toweass Indians</persName>
Indians. The <persName>cherokees </persName>and their <persName>friends </persName>the <persName>Shawnees </persName>and 
<persName>Delawares </persName>are also new <persName>Settlers</persName>; like us they have come to seek a new
<placeName>home </placeName>in this <placeName>country </placeName>and procure <placeName>lands </placeName>from the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName>,
and like us they also owe obedience to the orders of the Government
and are bound in duty to fight the <persName>enemies </persName>of the <persName>Mexican people</persName>.
I can with confidence answer for the <persName>cherokees </persName>that they are good
<persName>warriors</persName>, but as yet they have not had an opportunity of proving
to their new <persName>friends </persName>the <persName>mexicans </persName>how useful they can be&#8212;you have
no doubt been anxious to do so and have always been ready to turn
out and fight for your new <placeName>country</placeName>, you sent me word by <persName>Mr John
Cummins</persName> and <persName>John Miligan</persName> that you would join us to fight the<pb n="1308"/>
<persName>wacos </persName>whenever I called on you. I have always looked upon you as
<persName>friends </persName>who could be depended on I am happy to inform you that
an opportunity now offers for you to shew the Govt that you are
both good <persName>warriors </persName>and good <persName>citizens</persName>. The <persName>men </persName>of this <placeName>Colony </placeName>will
attack the <persName>waco </persName>and <persName>Tawakany </persName><placeName>villages on the Brazos </placeName>on the 
morning of the <date when="1826-05-25">25 of may next</date>, and I now call on you both as an <persName>officer</persName>
of the Mexican Govt and as a <persName>friend </persName>and <persName>brother </persName>to aid us in the
war with those <persName>Indians</persName>. My plan is for the<persName> Militia of this Colony</persName>
to attack the <persName>waco </persName>and <placeName><persName>Tawakany </persName>villageson the main brazos river</placeName>
at day light on the <date when="1826-05-25">25 of May</date> and for the <persName>Cherokees </persName><persName>Shawnees </persName>and
<persName>Delawares </persName>to attack the <placeName><persName>Tawak[an]y </persName>village on the head of the
Navisotabout 30 miles east of the Brazos </placeName>at the same moment. As
soon as the <placeName>villages </placeName>are destroyed, you will send a <persName>party </persName>in to the
<placeName>villages on the river </placeName>to look for us and we will then make such
arrangements as may be deemed necessary. It is my wish to distroy
the <placeName><persName>Toweass </persName>villageon Red River</placeName> before I return <placeName>home </placeName>and if you
have <persName>men </persName>enough to spare to detach a <persName>party </persName>to attack that <placeName>village</placeName>
at the same time we attack the others it would be best, to do so.
If this cannot be done bring all your <persName>men </persName>to the <persName>Tawakanies </persName>and we
will fit out a <persName>party </persName>to attack the <persName>Toweass</persName>&#8212;My <persName>friends </persName>I have 
informed you of my plans I have placed great confidence in you for
you are the only <persName>persons </persName>out of this <placeName>Colony </placeName>that I have called on
for aid&#8212;I am the <persName>friend </persName>of the <persName>cherokees</persName>, and wish to give them an
opportunity of shewing the <persName>Government </persName>what good <persName>soldiers </persName>and
faithful <persName>citizens </persName>they will make and I have no doubt if you turn out
in this expedition and distroy the <placeName><persName>Tawakany </persName>village on the head of
the Navisot</placeName>, that it will be the means of securing you <placeName>land </placeName>in the
<placeName>country </placeName>for as many of your <persName>Nation </persName>as wish to remove here&#8212;I have
no authority to promise you land, but I will promise my aid and
friendship in your favor with the <persName>Government </persName>and I have no doubt
of succeeding, but you must first show the <persName>Government </persName>that you are
both able and willing to fight for them. I will also befriend the
<persName>Shawnees </persName>and <persName>Delawares</persName>. Some of them may know me My <persName>father</persName>
has had <persName>hundreds of them</persName> at his home at the <placeName>Lead Mines</placeName> in 
<placeName>Missouri</placeName>, he was a <persName>short fat man</persName> and lived at a place called <placeName>Mine á
Burton</placeName>, he traded with the <persName>Shawnees </persName>and <persName>Delawares </persName>and was their
friend I was then a <persName>little boy </persName>and have often played with the
<persName>Shawnee children</persName>&#8212;we are now men and let us fight in union and
together as we used to play&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>bearer </persName>of this is <persName>Mr John R, Foster</persName> I have sent him express
to see you and wish you to write me a positive answer by him
wheither you will join us in this war and wheither you will attack
[the] <placeName><persName>Tawakany </persName>villageon the head of the Navisot </placeName>at the time 
appointed.   And how many <persName>men </persName>you can furnish<pb n="1309"/></p>

<p>I wish you to keep the business a profound secret from the 
<persName>Keechies</persName>. <persName>Ananies </persName>and all those <persName>small tribes</persName>&#8212;They are bad <persName>Indians</persName>
and are at war with the <persName>mexicans </persName>and friendly with the <persName>Tawakanies</persName>.
also keep it a secret from the <persName>Americans </persName>and <persName>Spaniards </persName>for some of
them might give our <persName>enemies </persName>notice My men on the <placeName>Colorado </placeName>killed
eleven <persName>Tawakanies </persName>and two <persName>Keechis </persName>on the <date when="1826-04-03">3d day of this month</date>&#8212;
they came into the <placeName>settlement </placeName>to steal horses&#8212;</p>

<p>I wish you to send me an <persName>express </persName>to the home of <persName>John P Coles</persName>
<placeName>ten miles below the San Antonio road</placeName> on the <placeName>east side of the Brazos
river</placeName> to inform me when you start on the expedition and how many
men you will take so that I may know to a certainty how to make
my arrangements</p>

<p>Your friend and Brother,                                         <persName> S. F. A.</persName></p>

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1826-04-24">April 24, 1826</date>&#8212;-</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
