<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1316">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Baron de Bastrop, 11-03-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-15">07-15-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Baron de Bastrop
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1486-1488
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-11-03">11-03-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Suggestions for legislation&#8212;judicial system, digest of laws, sub-political chief, recording titles, land fees, appointment of commissioners to extend titles,</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>To the <persName>Baron de Bastrop member of the State Legislature from
Texas</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>One of the most important subjects to the <persName>people </persName>of the <placeName>State of
Cuahuila and Texas</placeName> is a speedy organization of the <persName>Judiciary </persName>on a
system which promises permanency uniformity in the 
interpretation of laws, and convenience to the <persName>people</persName>&#8212;A <persName>Superior Court</persName> to
sit at <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>and at <placeName>Bexar </placeName>alternately, and <persName>subordinate Circuit
Courts</persName> would probably be the best. The <persName>Department of Texas
</persName>might be divided into two Circuits <placeName>from the Sabine to the Baca</placeName> to
form one, and thence <placeName>to the Western limit of the Department</placeName> to
form another, and the <placeName>balance of the State</placeName> to be divided as 
circumstances may require with a <persName>Judge </persName>in each <placeName>Circuit</placeName>. The <persName>Circuit
Courts</persName> might have final appellant Jurisdiction in all cases sent up
from <persName>Alcaldes </persName>and original jurisdiction in all Civil and Criminal
Cases beyond the Jurisdiction of <persName>Alcaldes</persName>, and the <persName>Superior Court</persName>
appellant jurisdiction from the Circuit Courts in all civil cases over
a certain amount, and original jurisdiction in cases of great 
importance. The <persName>Circuit Courts</persName> to have jurisdiction in all cases of
probate and settling Estates, recording will[s] etc. regulating the rates
of ferriage and granting licenses to <persName>ferrymen</persName>, <persName>tavern keepers</persName> etc.<pb n="1487"/>
etc. and in case the trial by <persName>jury </persName>is not allowed their decision in
Criminal Cases should be subject to the revisal of some <persName>Superior
tribunal</persName> so as not to give one <persName>man </persName>the power of deciding finally in
Case of Life and death. The Circuit Courts for this Circuit might
hold three terms <placeName>at this place</placeName>, and three terms at <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>in
the year; say in this place on the <date n="10-xx-xxx">second Mondays of October,</date> 
<date n="02-xx-xxxx">February</date> and <date n="06-xx-xxxx">June</date>, and at <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>on the <date n="12-xx-xxxx">second Mondays of
December</date>, <date n="04-xx-xxxx">April </date>and <date n="08-xx-xxxx">August</date>. There should be a <persName>clerk </persName>appointed
at each place where the <persName>Circuit Courts</persName> are held to keep the records
of said Court [to] issue process etc and his fees clearly defined by
law.</p>

<p>There should be a <persName>sheriff </persName>or <persName>alguacil </persName>in each place where said
<persName>Court </persName>is held to execute its orders and decrees and his duties and
fees defined.</p>

<p>There should be a <persName>Notary Public</persName> for this <placeName>Colony </placeName>and one for
<placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>with his fees clearly defined.</p>

<p>The <placeName>jurisdiction </placeName>of the <persName>Alcaldes </persName>and their specific duties and
powers should be clearly defined even to the furnishing of forms
so as to give uniformity to their proceedings.</p>

<p>Judicial proceedings in the department of <placeName>Texas </placeName>originally had
in the English language when translated by the proper <persName>person</persName>
should have the same validity as if originally had in Spanish.
Without this the new <persName>settlers </persName>will be totally debarred all access to
courts of Justice for not one in a hundred understands Spanish&#8212;
Also there should be some provision for the appointment of 
<persName>translators </persName>and their perquisites or fees fixed by law.</p>

<p>There should be a complete digest of all the laws in force, 
published in a bound book and generally circulated gratis to every
<persName>officer </persName><persName>civil judicial</persName> and <persName>militia </persName>throughout the <placeName>State </placeName>and sold to
the <persName>people </persName>on moderate terms.</p>

<p>Owing to the distance <placeName>from the new Settlements to Bexar</placeName> and
the inconvenience that will arise in Communicating with the Govt
by the <persName>Alcaldes </persName>individually there should be a <hi rend="italic"><persName>Gefe Subalterno</persName></hi>
(Subaltern Civil Chief) to reside at <placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> whose
authority should extend <placeName>from the Sabine to Labaca</placeName>, or two <persName>Chiefs</persName>
of this description, one for the Country <placeName>from Sabine to Neches</placeName>
and another <placeName>from there to Labaca</placeName>&#8212;This <persName>Chief </persName>or <persName>Chiefs </persName>should
understand both Spanish and English and be the organ of 
Communication between the <persName>Govt </persName>and the <persName>Alcaldes </persName>and the other 
<persName>subordinate officers</persName> of the <placeName>jurisdiction</placeName>, and be a <persName>subordinate executive
officer </persName>subject to the orders of the <persName>Chief of Department</persName> and <persName>Govor</persName> of
the <placeName>state </placeName>etc.&#8212;he should have a <persName>Secretary </persName>legally appointed and
his fees for translating and other perquisites as well as his duties
clearly defined by law. If such a <persName>chief </persName>is not appointed great in-<pb n="1488"/>
convenience will arise in communicating with each <persName>Alcalde </persName>
separately by the <persName>Chief of Department</persName> in consequence of the want of
a knowledge of the Spanish Language and Customary forms of
doing business.</p>

<p>All deeds or Mortgages for real Estate should be recorded in the
<placeName>office of the <persName>Notary </persName></placeName>in a bound book or should there be no <persName>Notary </persName>in
the <placeName>office of the Clerk of the Circuit Court</placeName> within three months after
they were executed or be void.</p>

<p>I deem it very important that there should be a clear 
understanding with the <persName>Govt </persName>as to the fees which the <persName>Empresario </persName>can ask and
receive from the <persName>Settlers </persName>for he must be at a great expence, for 
<persName>translators</persName>, <persName>Clerks</persName>, attending in person to the Surveying, locating the
<persName>Settlers</persName>, showing new <persName>Emigrants </persName>the <placeName>Country</placeName>, making presents to
<persName>Indians</persName>, keeping an open house, as he must do for some time for
persons who come into explore the <placeName>Country </placeName>and many other expences
which at first view do not appear important but at the end of a year
amt to a large sum.</p>

<p>Also the manner of running the <placeName>division line along the reserve
on the Coast</placeName> should be defined&#8212;The law calls for the " <placeName>Gulf of
Mexico </placeName>" as the base, and to leave the margin of the <placeName>Gulf </placeName>and<placeName> meander
round the lakes</placeName> such as <placeName>Galveston </placeName>and <placeName>Matagorda </placeName>will entirely be a
departure from the law&#8212;it appears to me equally as proper to follow
<placeName>up a River</placeName> to its head because it discharges <placeName>into the Gulf</placeName> and to
begin the measurement there, as to follow <placeName>round the meanders of a
Lake or shallow Bay</placeName> that has a <placeName>narrow inlet</placeName>. The expense of runing
this line will be very great if the <placeName>lakes </placeName>are to be meandered, and who
is to pay it. I think the <placeName>line </placeName>ought to be nearly straight and the <placeName>out
side of the Coast</placeName>, that is the <placeName>shore of the " Gulf of Mexico "</placeName> taken as
the base to measure from.</p>

<p>Many old claims are said to exist on the <placeName>Trinity</placeName>, <placeName>Neches </placeName>and in the
<placeName>Nacogdoches district</placeName>&#8212;there ought to be <persName>commissioners </persName>appointed
with full power to decide on them finally so that it may be known
what <placeName>land</placeName> is vacant and what is not, if this is not done several claims
may be set up for the same <placeName>land </placeName>and hence will arise endless lawsuits
and confusion, and it will also be impossible for the <persName>Empresario </persName>to
know what <placeName>lands </placeName>he can settle or what are taken up by previous
claims for the records of most of these old claims are said to have
been lost in the revolution which renders it difficult to decide from
any legal written evidence as to their validity</p>

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date n="11-03-1826+">3 November 1826</date></p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin    </persName>[Rubric]</p>

<p>[Endorsed:]-Reflections sent to the <persName>member of the Legislature of
this state for <placeName>Texas</placeName>,</persName> the <persName>Baron de Bastrop</persName>&#8212;copy</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
