<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1439">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Phineas Smith to J. E. B. Austin, 09-23-1827</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Phineas Smith</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-26">07-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J. E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Lebanon,</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Natchitoches, Louisiana; San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1683-1684
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1827-09-23">09-23-1827</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Acknowledging news of his brother's death.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Lebanon</placeName> <date when="1827-09-23">Sept. 23.1827</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>Your letter under date of <date when="1827-07-16">16 July last</date> announcing the intelligence
of the decease of my dear <persName>brother </persName><persName>George Smith</persName> has reached me.
The melancholly tidings contained in your letter though I had longed
feared its arrival, does notwithstanding deeply affect my heart.
Though fully apprized of the fatal nature of the malady with which
my deceased <persName>brother </persName>was affected yet upon the arrival of the 
melancholly news of his death, I found that I had entertained more hope
of his recovery than I was conscious of.    I hoped to have seen him<pb n="1684"/>
once more on <placeName>earth</placeName>&#8212;to have clasped him in my arms, and to have
mingled my tears with his. These hopes are now utterly blasted,
still I have a hope of a meeting with my departed <persName>brother</persName>, that is
inconceivably more precious and charming to the soul, than every
earthly hope united&#8212;it is the hope of meeting him in <placeName>heaven</placeName>. The
tenor of several of his last letters to me indicated a mind deeply
impressed with a sense of the uncertainty of every earthly thing,
and the infinite importance of being prepared for the retribution of
eternity. A more particular account of his temper and views in his
last days would have been highly gratifying, whether he gave 
evidence of a sanctified heart and leaned upon the arm and trusted in
the righteousness and blood of <persName>Jesus Christ</persName> the only mediator
between a holy <persName>God </persName>and guilty man&#8212;These things I take to be
implied in his remark "that his last moments, were devoted to his
<persName>God</persName>," but if the account had been more full in relation to some
particulars it would have been very pleasing to me. Perhaps it may
be convenient to write me hereafter on these points. I feel under
lasting obligations to you for your kindness to my deceased <persName>brother</persName>,
but I exceedingly regret the calamity, that eight months should
transpire after his death before I received the melancholly 
intelligence.</p>

<p>You observe that my <persName>brother </persName>made a will and that you are his
<persName>executor</persName>. In the days of my prosperity I advanced considerable
sums to assist my <persName>brother George </persName>to an education which has never
been refunded. I suppose my legal claim upon my late beloved
<persName>brother</persName>, at the time he left this part of the world was a thousand
dollars. If therefore any thing can be saved for me justice seems to
demand it. Should there be a <placeName>tract of land</placeName> I hope it will be such an
one as to induce me to go to <placeName>Texas </placeName>as a residence. This my <persName>brother
George </persName>once had in view (my removal to <placeName>Texas</placeName>) and it is possible it
may yet be effected. Please to write me as soon as possible after you
have closed the concern of my <persName>brothers </persName>state.</p>

<p><persName>Phineas Smith</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>James B. Austin Esqr.</persName><placeName> San Felipe de Austin (Texas)</placeName>
Care of <persName>Stephen F Austin Esq.</persName> by way of <placeName>Nachitoches (Lou)</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
