<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1685">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Green DeWitt to Stephen F Austin, 03-03-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Green DeWitt</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-10">08-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Gonzales, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 175-177
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-03-03">03-03-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reporting depredations of Indians in his settlement and battle with Tahuacanas. Recommends appointment of Rangers to patrol the frontier.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Gonzales </placeName><date when="1829-03-03">March 3rd 1829</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir The <persName>indians </persName>have been commiting such outrages on the
<persName>people of this <placeName>colony</placeName></persName>, by killing a few hogs and stealing one horse;
and robed the <placeName>camp </placeName>of some <persName>men </persName>who were sawing some plank <placeName>3
miles above this place on the Guadalupe River</placeName>&#8212;the hogs were stolen
below&#8212;<placeName>on the River</placeName>, by the <persName>Tankawas</persName>&#8212;, horse was stolen by the
<persName>cados </persName>and taken from them again on the waters of the <persName>St Marcus</persName> by
a party of 19 <persName>men </persName>which I sent after them, the <placeName>Camp </placeName>above 
mentioned was robed by the <persName>Tawaccanies</persName>&#8212;of about $100 worth of
Tools&#8212; I sent a <persName>party </persName>of men out to find their course&#8212;after a
march of 4 days on foot&#8212;they returned and reported that there were
four in number&#8212;when they commited the theft, but were joined by
about 25 more at the <placeName>Cappoto</placeName>&#8212;and bent their course for <placeName>LaBahia</placeName>,
and crossed the <placeName>San Antonio road 24 miles west of this place</placeName>&#8212;I
raised a party of 17 <persName>men </persName>besides myself and followed them within
<placeName>about 15 miles of LaBahia </placeName>finding on their trail parts of saws which
they had broken which convinced us they were the same <persName>indians</persName>
there they had fallen in with a bout 40 more who had been encamped
there during the last Storm, on that evening we struck their trail
on their way from <placeName>LaBahia </placeName>with a Caviard of a bout 50 horses.&#8212;I
put three <persName>spies </persName>ahead with orders to report should they see any
<persName>Indians </persName>in a bout one hour, one of the <persName>spies </persName>discovered an <persName>Indian</persName>&#8212;
riding down from a <placeName>prairie hill</placeName>; when he broke in to full speed 
without reporting what he had seen&#8212;he was too far ahead to hear me
when I ordered him to keep order&#8212;consequently he went on and
those who had good horses went on&#8212;others whose horses were tired
were <placeName>a mile behind</placeName>&#8212;when I arrived there were five <persName>men </persName>on the
ground&#8212;and them scatered for the distance of two hundred yards&#8212;
I ordered them to form <placeName>in a small bunch of muskeet trees</placeName> in about
100 yards of the <persName>Indian </persName>horses&#8212;4 <persName>men </persName>besides myself formed there&#8212;
when <persName>Capt McCoy</persName> who was <placeName>in the rear of me</placeName> order a retreat to
better ground, and reported that the <persName>Indians </persName>were a bout to cut off<pb n="176"/>
our <persName>men </persName>who were on tired horses and intirely behind us&#8212;this put
the <persName>men </persName>in confusion, and the <persName>indians </persName>having made a bold charge
upon us with a hot fire&#8212;in order to cover their own <persName>men </persName>who were
then securing their horses&#8212;<persName>John and Andrew Tumlinson</persName> who had
tied their horses in the edge of the same thicket where the <persName>Indians</persName>
were, got almost surrounded one of their horses being slightly hit
by a ball, broke a way and joined our horses the other horse being
tied with two hard knots, was siezed by an <persName>Indian </persName>in a few Steps of
<persName>John T,</persName> whose gun would not fire&#8212;the <persName>Indian </persName>untied the ho[r]se
which got frightened at him; broke loose and Joined our <persName>company</persName>
the <persName>Indians </persName>followed those <persName>men </persName>a few yards and stopt, two of whom
were shot down by our <persName>men </persName>They then retreated in to their thicket,
carrying off their <persName>dead</persName>&#8212;we were not able to charge in to their hold
without great loss, as they were too superior in number&#8212;therefore
we took our stand in the <placeName>fork of a small creek </placeName>in their view in order
to draw them out&#8212;where we could be Sheltered by a few muskeet
trees; where we remained for some time, but without any attack&#8212;
we then with drew Slowly for a few hundred yards when we 
discovered them in full chase on horse back&#8212;we then took our stand
and drove them with the loss of two more of their number; it then
being after dark we Struck our course for <placeName>home</placeName>; as I did not wish
to hazard the lives of any the <persName>Citizen </persName>on such unequal grounds; for
we were compelled to fight them at a place of [their] own selection;
and which was almost impenetreble.</p>

<p>I have given you this detail of the affair precisely as it was
tra[n]sacted, in order to show you we were not the <persName>agressers</persName>, but
were persuing our property and were fired upon first by themselves.
Your Old friend <persName>Don G. Flores</persName> was robed of his horses<placeName> between
this and San Antonio </placeName>and went home on foot as I am informed&#8212;.
I have received information from <placeName>Bexar</placeName>&#8212;that the <persName>Indians </persName>have
stolen a great many horses from that place and that there are 200
<persName>Soldiers </persName>now in persuit of them. The fact is I believe the <persName>Caddos</persName>
<persName>Wacos </persName><persName>Comanches </persName>and <persName>Tawaccanies </persName>are all concerned in the affair;
and unless there is some precaution taken they will harrass the
<persName>people </persName>on the <placeName>frontiers </placeName>of both of these <placeName>Colonies</placeName>; and the only means
will be to keep <persName>troops </persName>of some discription on the alert from the
<placeName>Colorado </placeName>to the <placeName>Guadalupe</placeName>, and thence to <placeName>San Antonia</placeName> which would
be the means of giving information of their approach and put people
on their guard so that they could protect them selves and property.
I would wish you to take these things in to consideration; and should
you approve of the measure&#8212;use your influence to affect it, either
by a<persName> Company of Rangers,</persName> or the <persName>public troops</persName> which would be a
great security to the <persName>people of <placeName>San Antonia</placeName> and <placeName>LaBahia </placeName></persName>as well
as to <placeName>American Settlements</placeName>.<pb n="177"/></p>

<p>I have addressed a short note to the <persName>Alcalde at <placeName>San Felipe</placeName></persName> on
the subject of the expected election at this place which is very much
wished for and needed as well for the Organization of the <persName>Militia</persName>
as that of a <persName>civil officer</persName> in this place which I hope you will urge as
soon as possible, as our Safety greatly depends on a well Organized
<persName>Militia</persName>.</p>

<p>Our place is strenghening fast, <persName>Mr. Lockhart</persName> has arrived in the
<placeName>Bay of Aransas</placeName>&#8212;with 55 <persName>souls </persName><persName>men </persName><persName>women </persName>and <persName>Children </persName>bound for
this place; he himself has been up and returned to the <placeName>Bay </placeName>with
Waggons Carts and horses for their transportation; and will arrive
in a few days&#8212; I would be happy to hear from you; often and get
the news of the day, and have your opinion on the best means and
measures in case the <persName>Indians </persName>should prove hostile.</p>

<p><persName>G. DeWitt</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Col Stephen F Austin</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
