<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1768">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John M McCalla to Stephen F Austin, 10-06-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John M McCalla</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-15">08-15-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Mr Gregg
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Lexington, Kentucky</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 261-263
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-10-06">10-06-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Henry Clay, the evil genius of Kentucky. Andrew Jackson.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Lexington </placeName><date when="1829-10-06">October 6th 1829</date></p>
<p>My dear friend.</p>

<p>Just <date n="10-xx-1828">one year ago </date>you wrote me a letter from <placeName>Texas</placeName>, by <persName>Mr Gregg,</persName>
and now by the same gentleman I send a reply. I shall be glad to
renew and to perpetuate our old friendship, which on my part, I
assure you is undiminished. I never recall the happy days of 
boyhood, but you appear in the list of remembered <persName>friends</persName>, and many
scenes which we enjoyed together are among the " greenest spots " in
my recollections. Our female friends <persName>Eliza </persName>and <persName>Paulina</persName>, for whom
we both had pretty strong <hi rend="italic">penchants</hi>, I see occasionally, but that
<placeName>little " paradise "</placeName> in which we were both sometimes admitted, is grown
up with weeds, and its <persName>fair inhabitants</persName> transplanted to other scenes,
and surrounded by other objects. The first you know married <persName>Thos
A Marshall</persName>. She lives in <placeName>Bourbon county</placeName>, has 6 or 7 <persName>children</persName>, breeds
like a rabbit, and looks almost as well as ever. <persName>Paulina </persName>was married
to <persName>Brooks </persName>who died and she remained some years a <persName>widow</persName>, and <date n="04-xx-1828">18
months since</date> married a second time, to <persName>Capt. Maurice Langhorne</persName>
who now keeps a <placeName>large house of entertainment</placeName> at <placeName>Louisville</placeName>. I
saw her last week, she does not look so well as formerly, in 
consequence of a spell of fever. She is however pretty much the same,
especially the tone of voice, and her lively agreable manner. <persName>Mrs
January </persName>is still living, also her sister <persName>Sally (Mrs Todd)</persName>. <persName>Jas. B
January</persName> is barely living being much reduced by excessive 
intemperance. <persName>Mrs Todd</persName> has a large <persName>family</persName>. <persName>Will O Butler</persName>, who married
<persName>Levi Todds sister</persName>, has no children. <persName>Nannette Price</persName> who married
<persName>Tom Smith</persName> is also laughed at as childless, altho her <persName>husband </persName>is
pretty generally blamed for it. I have heard several jokes against
<persName>Smith </persName>coming from <persName>Mr Clay</persName> and the <persName>ladies of the family</persName>.<pb n="262"/></p>

<p><persName>Mr Clay</persName> is now here with his <persName>family</persName>. He is in my opinion, the
<persName>evil genius of <placeName>Kentucky</placeName></persName>. He set in motion all the springs of 
discord, and keeps society in a continual excitement. He appeared as
<persName>counsel </persName>at the trial [of] <persName>Wickliffe's son</persName> for the murder of the <persName>editor
of the Gazette,</persName> and volunteered on the occasion, and has not appeared
in any other case before or since. He has been lately on trip to the
<placeName>lower part of this state</placeName> making speeches at dinner parties and 
keeping all his engines in motion against <persName>Genl Jackson</persName>. As for the
<persName>President</persName>, he goes on as he has always heretofore done, attentive to
<hi rend="italic">his </hi>duty, and making all under him do their duty. His health has
been somewhat injured by confinement but a visit to the seashore
restored his health, and he is now progressing rapidly in the reform
of the abuses which existed in the administration. It is melancholy
fact, that great abases had grown up, and many who wore the front
of honesty were guilty of great dishonesty and peculation. Party
spirit still runs high, and the growlings of the storm are still heard
although its main fury was exausted in the late election, <persName>Genl
Jackson</persName>, if he lives, will be re-elected as <persName>President</persName>.</p>

<p>I am sorry to pereieve that <placeName>Mexico </placeName>is again exposed to <placeName>foreign</placeName>
war as well as intestine divisions. We are all anxious to purchase
<placeName>Texas </placeName>from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and the subject is beginning to excite a great
deal of warm discussion in our public prints. If <placeName>Mexico </placeName>will 
dispose of it on reasonable terms, I believe our <persName>government </persName>will no
doubt be glad to obtain it, and I am sure it will meet the almost
universal desire of our <persName>citizens</persName>. The consequences to the <persName>holders
of property</persName> in <placeName>Texas </placeName>would be very important, and it would 
promote the happiness and prosperity of all the <persName>citizens </persName>of the <placeName>province</placeName>.
A great many <persName>citizens of <placeName>Kentucky</placeName></persName> would move to your <placeName>settlement</placeName>
instantly, if it were under our government.</p>

<p>In relation to your last and most important particular, to wit <hi rend="italic">the
<persName>widow</persName></hi>, I can safely say that if you will come on here, and plead
your own cause I can point out to you both <persName>maids </persName>and <persName>widows</persName>, who
would make your heart go pit apat, and who would doubtless be
willing <hi rend="italic">to emigrate</hi> to any part of the known <placeName>world </placeName>with clever
fellows. Only let me know that you will pay us a visit and I will
arrange matters and things so far as, that if you can be satisfied
with beauty, good temper, and affectionate dispositions, you shall
have a fair opportunity to lay siege forthwith. I should indeed be
truly glad to see you here once more, and to shew you my four <persName>children</persName>,
 my <persName>eldest </persName>a boy going on thirteen years of age, and my 
<persName>youngest </persName>a girl (I have two of each) about 13 months old. Two of them
are talking to me and playing round me and far as their prattle
can go, disturbing me.<pb n="263"/></p>

<p>Wishing you that success and prosperity, which your interprize
and industry so well deserve, I am as "in auld lang syne' Your
affectionate friend</p>

<p><persName>Jn° M. McCalla</persName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin Esqr</persName> <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
