<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1933">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Unknown, unknown</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-21">08-21-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 386-391
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Argument</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date>unknown</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Argument by Austin for repeal of the anti-immigration article of the Law of April 6, 1830.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>At the period of Mexican independence in <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date>, <placeName>Texas </placeName>was 
uninhabited by a civilized <persName>population</persName>, except the towns of <placeName>Bexar </placeName>and
<placeName>Goliad</placeName>-&#8212; It was infested by numerous bands of hostile <persName>Indians</persName>
who sallied forth at pleasure to rob and desolate the <placeName>settlements </placeName>on
the <placeName>rio Bravo</placeName>, extending their depradations into the <placeName>mountains </placeName>to
the <placeName>neighborhood </placeName>of <placeName>Monclova </placeName>and <placeName>Monterey</placeName>, and along the <placeName>coast of
Tamaulipas</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>The system of <placeName>frontier </placeName>defence used by the <persName>Spanish Govt</persName> of 
establishing <placeName>military posts</placeName> or <hi rend="italic">presidios </hi>was never an effectual barrier,
for when those <placeName>posts </placeName>were in their best state of armament, the most
that was done was to protect the immediate <placeName>vicinity </placeName>without being<pb n="387"/>
able to cover the whole <placeName>country</placeName>, or prevent the <persName>Indians </persName>from 
harassing the <placeName>frontier settlements</placeName>, and committing robberies on the <placeName>public
roads</placeName></p>

<p>The natural consequence was, that the civilized <placeName>settlements </placeName>were
limited to the <placeName>garrisoned towns</placeName>. A few scanty <placeName>villages </placeName>were thus
sustained like isolated specks in the midst of a <placeName>wilderness </placeName>at an
enormous expense to the <persName>govt </persName>and a great waste of men and money&#8212;
A <placeName>country </placeName>thus situated could evidently yield no revenue in return
for the millions expended in its defence; it could not advance much
in population or improvement, nor add anything to the physical
force of the nation, but on the contrary, weakened it.</p>

<p>It may therefore be said with truth, that under the old system of
<hi rend="italic"><placeName>presidial </placeName></hi>defence, the whole of that part of the <placeName>Mexican territory</placeName>
situated <placeName>north and east of a line from near <hi rend="italic">Soto la Marina</hi> on
the gulf of Mexico to the Gulf of California </placeName> was an expence and a
dead weight to the government.</p>

<p>The experience of years had already convinced the <persName>Spanish 
authorities</persName> of the<placeName> internal provinces</placeName>, of the absolute inefficacy of the old
system of <placeName>frontier </placeName>defence, and that the only effectual and 
permanent barrier was population, the <placeName>settlement </placeName>of the <placeName>frontier </placeName>by a
hardy and interprising race of people before whom the <persName>savages</persName>
would retire, or become submissive</p>

<p>The result of this new opinion was a total change of the ruinous
restrictive system which had for centuries locked up the whole of
the <persName>Spanish </persName>possessions from the rest of the <placeName>world</placeName>&#8212; The first step
that was taken towards the new system of <placeName>frontier </placeName>defence was
the <placeName>grant </placeName>to<persName> Moses Austin</persName> on the<date when="1821-01-17"> 17 January 1821</date>, to settle a <placeName>colony</placeName>
of <persName>Forth Americans</persName> in the <placeName>wilderness of Texas.</placeName></p>

<p>During that year, <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821,</date> the independence was achieved, and the
lights of liberal and republican principles shed their benign 
influence over the whole <placeName>country</placeName>. One of the first acts of the new 
<persName>government </persName>was to open the door to the emigration of <persName>foreigners</persName>, the
colonization laws were enacted, and <persName>emigrants </persName>were expressly and
earnestly invited to enter. Under the faith and operation of those
laws the settlement of <placeName>Texas </placeName>was commenced, and its <placeName>wilderness </placeName>was
rapidly changing its <placeName>uninhabited state and wild aspect</placeName>, and 
yielding to the progress of <persName>civilized population</persName>, led on by enterprise and
perseverance.</p>

<p>The <persName>emigrants </persName>to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, it is well known, have never received
any succors from the <persName>government</persName>&#8212;no <placeName>garrisons </placeName>were sent to 
protect them during their infancy from the hostile <persName>indians </persName>who then
filled every part of the <placeName>country</placeName>, They have never cost the government
one cent&#8212;all they have ever recd was permission to settle in the
<placeName>country</placeName>, and a title for the <placeName>lands </placeName>they redeemed from the <placeName>wilderness</placeName>,<pb n="388"/>
<placeName>lands that were then valueless</placeName> to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>or to civilized man&#8212; Left
to their own resources and daring enterprise, they have conquered
a <placeName>wilderness</placeName>, and made known to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and to the <placeName>world </placeName>the true
value, and developed the resources, of a <placeName>large portion of the Mexican
territory</placeName> which was before hid in obscurity,&#8212; They have also
greatly contributed to the new system of <placeName>frontier </placeName>defence by means
of population and fully tested its efficacy, for the <persName>savages </persName>have 
retired before them, as they will continue to do, if the same system is
pursued, until they are reduced to full subjection or settled in
<placeName>villages </placeName>as <persName>agriculturists</persName>.</p>

<p>It is certainly a natural and very rational inquiry. What 
inducements, what incentives, what hopes, could have operated so 
powerfully upon the minds of the <persName>emigrants </persName>to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, as to have given
them fortitude to brave the dangers of savage <persName>foes</persName>, to dispise the
hardships and privations of the <placeName>wilderness</placeName>, to support them through
tryals and privations at which the stoutest hearts shrink&#8212; The
cries of their little <persName>children </persName>even for bread, the well founded fears
and despondency of their <persName>wives</persName>, surrounded as they were the first
years of the settlement, by <persName>Indians</persName>, famine, and sickness and by
the dark gloom of moments when even hope almost recoiled from
the future?&#8212; What impulse of freedom and deeply imbeded hope
bore them up and carried them through <hi rend="italic">such </hi>difficulties?&#8212; Was it
the bare expectation of getting a <placeName>piece of land in a wild wilderness</placeName>
and there living on the mere products of their manuel labor, and
degenerating into the habits of wild <persName>Indians</persName>? No&#8212;common sense,
and the characters and former habits of those <persName>settlers</persName>, unite in 
saying NO&#8212; But on the contrary the great and nerving hope that
bore them onward, was to redeem this <placeName>country </placeName>from the <placeName>wilderness</placeName>,
and convert it into the abode of <placeName>civilization</placeName>, of abundance and 
happiness, and by <hi rend="italic">that </hi>means to repay themselves, their <persName>wives </persName>and
<persName>children </persName>for the hardships and sufferings of their early settlement,
and also to repay the <persName>government </persName>more than thousand fold for the
privilige of settling in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and of making <placeName>wild lands </placeName>valuable,
that before were valuless&#8212;</p>

<p>On what grounds was such a hope as this founded? It was
founded on the colonization laws, on the general, liberal and broad
invitation given in those laws to the whole <placeName>world </placeName>to come and settle
in <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;on the faith of the Govt that such an invitation would
not be <hi rend="italic">thus </hi>given merely to draw a few unsuspicious <persName>emigrants </persName>to
this <placeName>wilderness </placeName>and <hi rend="italic">then </hi>to close the door and shut them out 
forever from their <persName>friends </persName>and <persName>relations</persName>, and in fact from the balance
of the civilized world, when years of struggling through difficulties
had just begun to realize their hopes&#8212; Could the first <persName>emigrants</persName>
have supposed that they would have been deprived of the privilege
of settling by their sides a <persName>son </persName>or <persName>daughter</persName>, an aged <persName>father </persName>or wid-<pb n="389"/>
owed <persName>mother</persName>, a <persName>brother </persName>or <persName>sister</persName>, an old and affectionate <persName>friend </persName>or
<persName>neighbor </persName>of other days and of other <placeName>countries</placeName>, because they did
not emigrate on this or on that particular day? Could they have
supposed that the general invitation of the colonization laws were
mere time serving and temporary expedients which were to be
changed without any apparent reason and without any violation of
duty on the part of the first <persName>emigrants</persName>, is it reasonable to suppose
that they would have labored as they have done, suffered what they
have suffered, to bring forward this <placeName>country</placeName>, and give value 
character, and credit to it? No&#8212;they built their hopes on the 
permanency of the colonizing system, on the faith of the government
pledged in their colonization laws, on the broad basis of 
philanthropy and republican freedom which they supposed had been
adopted as the foundation on which the social institutions of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>
were erected&#8212; Those hopes were certainly not entertained 
without a sufficient cause, and neither are they now destroyed 
notwithstanding the restrictions which are imposed by the law of <date when="1830-04-06">6 April
1830</date> which totally interdicts the emigration of <persName>North Americans
</persName>for it is confidently believed that those restrictions grew out of
peculiar circumstances, party excitements and hasty jealoucies
which no longer exist&#8212;</p>

<p>It seems to have been received as a correct opinion that the 
<persName>inhabitants of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> wished to separate from <persName>Mexico </persName>and unite with the
<placeName>U. S. of the North</placeName>&#8212; It seems that the virulence of party feelings
even went so far as to suspect that a friendly and republican govt
whose <placeName>territory </placeName>is already too great for its population, wished to
sieze upon <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; such opinions and suspicions are evidently at
variance with the conduct and avowed wishes of those <persName>emigrants</persName>,
and with the true and substantial interests of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, on the one hand;
and with the good faith and established policy and principles of the
<persName>Govt of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName></persName>, on the other&#8212; <placeName>Texas </placeName>could gain nothing by a
separation from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, except a removal of the ruinous restrictions
that now impede its progress in population and wealth, and if those
restrictions were taken off, there is not a rational <persName>man </persName>in the <placeName>country</placeName>
who would not oppose a separation&#8212; The true interests of <placeName>Texas</placeName>
are to become a <placeName>State of the Mexican confederation,</placeName> and this is the
desire of its <persName>inhabitants</persName>&#8212; By the law of <date when="1824-05-07">7 of May 1824,</date> forming the
<placeName>State of Coahuila and Texas</placeName>, the latter was only provisionally 
annexed to the former, untill it possessed the necessary elements to form
a<placeName> state of itself</placeName> and this very law was another inducement to the
<persName>emigrants </persName>to preserve, for it held out the inducement amounting
even to certainty, that <placeName>Texas </placeName>would be a <placeName>State </placeName>so soon as its 
population and resources were sufficient. Moral obligation, and interests
are the two great cords that bind <placeName>communities</placeName>, <placeName>states </placeName>and <placeName>nations</placeName>
together&#8212;   In no instance can the principle of interest be stronger<pb n="390"/>
than in the present one, supposing the restriction against emigration
to be taken off</p>

<p><placeName>Texas </placeName>must he an <placeName>agricultural country</placeName>, and the most of its 
agricultural productions will find a much better <placeName>market </placeName>in the <placeName>Mexican
ports</placeName> than in those of any part of the <placeName>world</placeName>. The <placeName>interior </placeName>trade by
land will also be very important. At this time, this trade is 
principally carried on <placeName>through Missouri to New Mexico and Chihuahua
</placeName>but the geographical situation of the <placeName>country </placeName>and the practicability
of <placeName>roads from the harbors of Texas,</placeName> evidently indicate that the 
natural channel of that trade, is from those <placeName>ports</placeName>, in preference to the
<placeName>circuitous route by Missouri through a foreign country</placeName>, subjecting
merchandise to a double duty which they would be exempt from if
taken from the <placeName>ports of this nation</placeName>&#8212; The <persName>manufactures of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>
abounding as this <placeName>country </placeName>does in facilities for their establishment
would evidently lose by a separation from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. In fact there is
not one interest in <placeName>Texas </placeName>that would not be injured by a separation
not one that would not be materially benefited by the erection of this
country into a <placeName>state of Mexico.</placeName></p>

<p>This being the case, why drive the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> to desperation
by a system of restriction, that is at varience with the inducements
and well founded hopes first held out to the <persName>emigrants</persName>, and with
the true interests of the <placeName>country</placeName>? The 11th article of the law of
<date when="1830-04-06">6 April 1830</date> totally prohibits the immigration of <persName>North Americans,</persName>
and suspends contracts previously entered into by the government
thereby depriving the present <persName>settlers </persName>of the consolation of settling
there <persName>relatives </persName>and <persName>friends </persName>along side of them. It also cuts off all
hope of future advancements for years to come and condemns this
country to a <placeName>wilderness</placeName>. The hope of bringing out <persName>emigra[n]ts
</persName>from <placeName>Europe</placeName>, is a faint and distant one, and will require many years
and a vast amount of capital to accomplish it. And besides, what
security or guarantee have they, in coming here, that they will not
also be deprived of the privilege of bringing out their <persName>relations </persName>and
<persName>friends </persName>after they have suffered years of hardships in preparing a
<placeName>home </placeName>for them, as the <persName>settlers </persName>from the <placeName>U.S</placeName>. have been by the law
of <date when="1830-04-06">April 6, 1830</date>?</p>

<p>under this view of the subjects, it certainly appears evident that
that part of the law <date when="1830-04-06">of 6 April 1830 </date>prohibiting the immigration of
<persName>north Americans</persName>, is unjust and at varience with the faith and pledges
of the <persName>Govt </persName>and with the true and substantial interests of <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;
That law will not, and cannot prevent the introduction of hundreds
and thousand into <placeName>Texas</placeName>, who, if they do not receive the sanction
of the Govt to remain and acquire <placeName>real estate</placeName>, will, as a matter of
course, become restive and perhaps, jeopardize the public tranquility
But, on the other hand, by opening the door for admission of honest<pb n="391"/>
and honorable <persName>men </persName>of high character and property, the moral 
influence of such men will correct and direct public opinion, and make
the moral tie, as well as that of interest, which does and ought to
bind <placeName>Texas </placeName>to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>indisoluble&#8212;</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
