<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1144">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to J. J. Ross and A. C. Buckner, Unknown</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-17">06-17-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J. J. Ross 
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        A. C. Buckner
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1332-1333
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-05-13">05-13-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Instructions for expedition against Indians.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>(private)</p>

<p><persName>Mr Foster</persName>, the <persName>express </persName>sent by me to the <persName>Cherokes </persName>returned this
<date n="05/13/1826">evening at 6 o'clock,</date> he brought me a letter from the <persName>chiefs </persName>of that
<persName>Nation </persName>in which they say that they can raise 350 <persName>men </persName>and are ready
and anxious to join us in the War as soon as their crops are laid by
and the <placeName>rivers</placeName> fall which at this time are very high&#8212;<persName>Foster </persName>also
says that he met with an old <persName>Apadachy Chief</persName> of the <persName>liaches </persName>who he
had seen before and Knew, this <persName>chief </persName>told him that the <persName>Wacos</persName>
and <persName>Tahuacanies </persName>had called a great Council of the <persName>Comanches </persName>and
all the small <persName>tribes </persName><placeName>beyond the Trinity river above the road </placeName>except
the <persName>Cherokees</persName>, that this <persName>council </persName>was to meet Soon and the objects of
it was to unite all those <persName>tribes </persName>to distroy the <persName>Americans </persName>on the 
<placeName>Colorado </placeName>and <placeName>Brazos</placeName>, and they were very mad and were determined to
have satisfaction at the <placeName>Trinity </placeName>he was told by <persName>Mrs. Trammel</persName> that
5 <persName>Keechis </persName>had been there the day before and that they told a <persName>Spaniard</persName>
that they intended to kill all the <persName>Americans</persName>. She took an old <persName>Aynye
chief </persName>into the <placeName>house </placeName>and asked him and he told her yes it was true
they were all mad but would not kill her as she had treated them well,
he also said that 200 of them were embodied to aid the <persName>Wacos</persName>. The
old <persName>Apadachy chief</persName> also told <persName>Foster </persName>that the <persName>Wacos </persName>were offering a
good horse for ten loads of powder and lead and a good mule for 20
loads&#8212; He says the <placeName>Trinity </placeName>and <placeName>Naches </placeName>are <placeName>out of their banks</placeName> and
thinks that no body of <persName>Indians </persName>can cross at this time to aid the
<persName>Wacos</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Under these circumstances I am decidedly of opinion that the 
<persName>expedition </persName>should be immediately pushed for the <persName>Wacos</persName>, if we delay it
will give them time to procure arms etc. to call in the aid of their
<persName>friends</persName>&#8212;and to make the treaty which is spoken of <persName>Capn Hall</persName>
will be here <date when="1826-05-14">tomorrow night</date>, he camps at the <placeName>water hole</placeName> <date when="1826-05-13">to night</date>.</p>

<p>I wish one or both of you to come over here immediately in order
to make the final arrangements for the trip owing to 
circumstances it might be improper for me to go in person. I can however
with propriety order out 200 <persName>men </persName>under the command of an <persName>officer</persName>
appointed for that purpose to cut off the 200 Who I am informed are
imbodied and who it is probable will endeavor to join the <persName>Wacos</persName>&#8212;
I have ordered out <persName>Spies </persName>along the <placeName>La Bahia road</placeName> towards the 
<placeName>Trinity</placeName>&#8212; <persName>Sims </persName>writes me that he has a <persName>party </persName>of active and confidential
<persName>Spies </persName>out on the <placeName>San Antonio road</placeName> nearly over to the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>,
another <persName>Company </persName>is out on the <placeName>La Bahia road</placeName>, they have as yet
seen no <persName>Indian </persName>sign in that quarter&#8212;dispatch is now important, the
men here are all ready, <persName>Sim's Company</persName> is also ready and there is
about 20 <persName>volunteers </persName>of <persName>strangers </persName>all anxious for the trip Keep your
<pb n="1333"/>
men in readiness&#8212; let them be provided with provisions, 
whenever you can get it so as not to produce delay I will see that it is
paid for&#8212; out of the general contribution which is about to be
raised all over the <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212;you can March from there and embody
at the <placeName>San Antonio road</placeName>, the day it not fixed yet and will not be
untill I see or hear from you for it will depend on wheither your
<persName>companies </persName>are ready or not&#8212; all the others are ready at a short
notice for they have not been harrassed as your men have&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>[S. F. Austin.]</persName></p>

<p>[Endorsed:]  Copy Letter sent to <persName>Ross </persName>&amp; <persName>Buckner </persName><date when="1826-05-13">May 13 [1826 ]</date></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
