<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1447">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Victor Blanco, 10-11-1827</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-26">07-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Victor Blanco
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Saltillo, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1697-1698
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1827-10-11">10-11-1827</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Petition to establish a town.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>To his <persName>Excellency the Governor of the <placeName>State of Coahuila and Texas</placeName></persName>
.</p>

<p><persName>Citizen Stephen F. Austin</persName>, most respectfully represents to <persName>Your
Excellency</persName>, that he has been solicited by several of the <persName>inhabitants</persName>
of <placeName>Bexar</placeName>, to settle some <persName>families </persName><placeName>on the borders of the River 
Colorado</placeName>, at the place <placeName>where that river is crossed by the road leading
from Bexar to Nacogdoches</placeName>, in order to found a <placeName>town</placeName>, <placeName>at the above-<pb n="1698"/>
mentioned crossing</placeName>, with a view not only to afford the necessary
<placeName>facilities </placeName>to the <persName>travellers </persName>of that road, but also to penetrate with
the new <placeName>settlements</placeName>, further into the <placeName>interior of the country, towards the <persName>Savage Tribes</persName>, but as this <placeName>road is the Northern boundary of the
Colony</placeName></placeName>, I have already contracted, and as the best site for the 
settlement of the Town, is <placeName>on the Eastern bank of the river Colorado</placeName>,
<placeName>above the said road</placeName>, and <placeName>beyond the limits of any colonization 
contract</placeName>, I am unable to effect the <placeName>settlement </placeName>proposed, without 
entering into a new contract, with the <persName>Government</persName>, for the purpose, and
believing that the Settlement of said Town, will be highly 
beneficial affording <placeName>facilities </placeName>for travelling, and to the mails and <persName>Troops</persName>,
frequently passing from <placeName>Bexar </placeName>and <placeName>Nacodoches</placeName>, and also prevent
in some degree the incursions of the <persName>Indians</persName>, who are continually
harassing the <placeName>neighborhoods of Bexar</placeName>,<placeName> La Bahia</placeName>, and the new 
<placeName>Settlements</placeName>, and infest the <placeName>roads</placeName>, I have considered it my duty, in
order to promote the welfare and progress of <placeName>that section of the
State</placeName>, to lay the matter before your <persName>Excellency</persName>, and recommend the
establishment of the before-mentioned <placeName>town</placeName>, offering on my part,
to discharge all the duties of <persName>Empresario</persName>, in effecting the same,
and to settle <placeName>in the vicinity of the town proposed,</placeName> the <placeName>lands which
may not be within the limits of any Colonization Contract</placeName>; 
provided the favors and privileges allowed to <persName>Empresarios </persName>are granted
to me, and also that one of the stipulations of the Contract is, that
each <persName>Colonist </persName>is to pay the sum of Thirty Dollars, for my services,
in attending to their business, and making the translations to the
completion of the title to their lands, by the <persName>Commissioner </persName>
guaranteeing the contracts made between the <persName>Colonists </persName>and myself, I offer
to settle <persName>One hundred families</persName> in this <placeName>new Colony,</placeName> but upon the
conditions, that should there not be a sufficiency of land, within the
limits assigned for the said <placeName>new colony</placeName>, to locate them in conformity
with the law in the case; Your Excellency will permit me to 
complete to them the quantity deficient, within the limits of the <placeName>colony</placeName>
which I have already contracted with the <persName>Government </persName>of this <placeName>State</placeName></p>

<p><placeName>Saltillo</placeName>, <date when="1827-10-11">Octr. 11, 1827</date>.</p>
<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
