<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1832">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Eliza W Austin to Mrs Emily Perry, 01-06-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Eliza W Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-17">08-17-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mrs Emily Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brazoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 318-319
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-01-06">01-06-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Austin's labors. Progress of the colony.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Brazoria </placeName><date when="1830-01-06">Jan. 6th, 1830</date>.</p>
<p>My dear <persName>Sister </persName>:</p>

<p>In answer to your very kind letter, I scarcely know what to say.
You must long before this heard of the death of your dear <persName>Brother</persName>.
You my dear <persName>Sister </persName>can well imagine what my feelings are; looseing
all that was Dear to me in this <placeName>world</placeName>, my <persName>Husband</persName>, my <persName>friend</persName>, my
<persName>protector</persName>, my all. But my <persName>Sister </persName>there is no remedy for the decrees
of providence, but submission. <persName>Brother Stephen</persName> was at the same
time very sick and not expected to live. We all thought that every
moment was his last but God was merciful to us, and spared him
to take care of his dear <persName>little Stephen</persName>. Our <persName>Brother </persName>is very anxious
for <persName>Mr. Perry</persName> to move to this <placeName>country</placeName>, but I dare not flatter myself<pb n="319"/>
with an idea of seeing you so soon, if <persName>Stephen </persName>was sure that you
would move in the <date n="Spring - 1830">spring</date>, he would fatten up and be a different
man, he is now nothing but a mere shadow, and if he does not quit
his desk, ride about and take more exercise, his life will be but short.
Next week he is a going out with the <persName>Surveyors </persName>and will spend a
month or more in the <placeName>woods</placeName>, he thinks in that time he will gain his
health. As I think it is not prudent for me to keep <placeName>house </placeName>alone in
this new <placeName>country</placeName>, I intend to have me a room put up joining <persName>Capt.
Austin</persName>s, he has always been to me a <persName>brother </persName>and<persName> his wife a sister</persName>.
We have lived together so long that I cannot think of leaving them
untill you move to <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>. I then will devide my time. This
<placeName>country </placeName>is improving very fast, there is 8 or 10 rich <persName>gentlemen </persName>from
<placeName>Tennessee </placeName>and <placeName>Alabama </placeName>come here to purchase <placeName>land </placeName>and will bring
their <persName>families </persName>this <date n="Spring - 1830">spring </date>and I sincerely hope that land will then
take a rise and pay <persName>Brother Stephen</persName> for all his trouble, My <persName>Sister</persName>
my constant prayer will be for you to move to this <placeName>country </placeName>and
cheer up <persName>Stephen</persName>. I am my-self well enough but if you was here
to tease and plague him, we could make him throw off that gloomy
melancholy look and once more show a smiling countenance.</p>

<p><persName>Little Stephen</persName> has been very sick with a singular breaking out.
I at first thought it was the hives. he is now getting much better
and thank you very much for his cap and beeds. he could walk a
few steps before he was taken sick. He is now beginning to talk,
he sends his love to all his little <persName>cousins</persName>. <persName>Mr. John Austin</persName> joins me
in love to you.</p>

<p><persName>Eliza W. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>Mrs. Emily M. Perry</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
