<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1688">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>David G Burnet to Stephen F Austin, 03-10-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>David G Burnet</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-10">08-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Cincinnati, Ohio</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 179-180
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-03-10">03-10-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Recent political unrest in Mexico has deterred many from emigrating to Texas. Comments on Jackson's Cabinet,</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Cincinnati </placeName><date when="1829-03-10">10 Mch 1829</date></p>
<p>My Dear Sir</p>

<p>It is not long since I availed myself of an opportunity presented
by a <persName>friend </persName>going direct to <placeName>Natchitoches </placeName>to Send Several packets of
<placeName>letters and newspapers</placeName> to <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; Knowing as I do by experience
the great zest with which <placeName>new[s] papers</placeName> are received in those secluded
<placeName>regions</placeName>, I take an other favourble opportunity of transmitting a
batch of them by the way of <placeName>Orleans</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Since my last communication nothing of much interest has 
transpired in relation to the prospects of emigration&#8212; the panic 
occasioned by the late change in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>has I fear effectually deterred
many from venturing upon the untried Scenes of a new <placeName>Country</placeName>&#8212;
a want of confidence in the Stability of the government is an 
objection difficult to surmount, and with the testimony lately presented
to the public mind it is next to impossible to remove the distrust.<pb n="180"/></p>

<p>I calculated with much certainty upon a very respectable <persName>company</persName>
forming in this state to go to my <placeName>Colony</placeName>, and although they have
not definitely abandoned the project, I entertain serious 
apprehensions that they will do so I shall remain here longer than I have
heretofore contemplated in the hope that something may still be
done&#8212;that I may at least get one good stool pigeon for to return
without, would be to have come for nothing&#8212;</p>

<p>The most momentous political event that has transpired of late
is the appointment of the new <persName>Cabinet Ministers</persName>&#8212;the selection has
proven an almost universal disappointment, and a very general
and a high degree of disgust even among the <persName>partizans of the new
President</persName>&#8212; Old <persName>Firginy</persName> is quite in the dumps, she hasn't
even a little finger in the pie&#8212;her <persName>Jackson </persName>zeal is cooling as fast
as if it had been immersed in ice water, and I doubt not she will
soon repent of her folly&#8212;The <persName>Cabinet </persName>is unquestionably, by large
odds&#8212;the weakest and most inefficient that this government has ever
witnessed-&#8212;-<persName>Van Buren</persName> is artful, intriguing and by no means 
conscious bound&#8212;his political experience is limited&#8212;he had principally
figured in the State politics of <placeName>New York</placeName> where he was the invariable
and inveterate opponent of <persName>DeWitt Clinton</persName> and his policy which
has contributed so much to the aggrandisment of that <placeName>State</placeName>&#8212;He
and <persName>Calhoun</persName>, who it is understood will be brought in to the<persName> privy
council</persName>, will be like two dogs at a bone, pulling different ways and
ever and anon, growling at each other&#8212;they are decidedly hostile
and mutually jealous&#8212;both look to the succession and both I trust
will be disappointed&#8212;<persName>Calhoun </persName>has more talents than the whole
<persName>Cabinet </persName>the <persName>old Chief</persName> included, and no one doubts but he will give
tone to the whole <persName>administration</persName>&#8212;<persName>Jackson</persName>'s deplorable incompetency
will soon be developed so that he who runs may read&#8212;<persName>Ingham </persName>is a
second rate man in all things but party zeal, and many beleive he has
an " itching palm "&#8212;<persName>Branch the North Carolinian</persName> is perhaps worthy
of his <placeName>State</placeName>, famed for pitch and sweet potatoes&#8212;<persName>Eaton </persName>is probably
the most obnoxious of the whole tribe&#8212;his late matrimonial 
connection has rendered his appointment peculiarly odious to the <persName>petticoat
politicians of the <placeName>Capital</placeName></persName>&#8212;his <placeName>Spouse </placeName>late the widow <persName>Timberleck</persName> is
notoriously considered of bad fame at <placeName>Washington </placeName>where she was
reared These political notions are not merely my own, for you will
readily imagine that I take little active interest in the strifes of this
<placeName>Country</placeName>&#8212;being a <persName>Coahuilatexanian</persName> I do not feel authorised to 
meddle with public matters here, but I cannot help seeing and hearing
and drawing inferences&#8212;If friend <persName>League </persName>should see this let him
put on his very best humor before it is presented to him-&#8212;-</p>

<p>Remember me very Sincerely to all <persName>friends</persName>, <persName>Williams</persName>, <persName>Brown</persName>
etc. etc.   In great haste</p>

<p><persName>Col Austin</persName>                                                           <persName>David G. Burnet</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
