<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1733">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James F Perry to Stephen F Austin, 07-19-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James F Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-12">08-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Potosi, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas via New Orleans</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 229-231
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-07-19">07-19-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning a land claim in Virginia. Economic depression in Missouri.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Potosi Mo</placeName> <date when="1829-07-19">July 19 1829</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Friends</persName></p>

<p>We have been waiting with anxiety to receive a line from You   we
have not had a letter from either you or <persName>Brown </persName>since last November<pb n="230"/>
since we have directed our letters by the way of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> we
dont know wheather you receive them as we have wrote several to
which we have not recd answers from Information from <persName>Judge
Carr</persName> and from other reports we been flatering ourselves with a visit
from you the ensueing <date n="Fall - 1829">fall </date>we would be all verry much rejoiced to
see you in <placeName>Missouri </placeName>once more. I wrote to you sometime since
respecting a claim of your <persName>Fathers </persName>in <placeName>Wyth Go, Va</placeName> I Recd two
letters lately on the subject one from a <persName>James Graham </persName>who wishes
to purchase it the other from a <persName>Mr James McGarock</persName> an old 
acquantance of<persName> E Bates</persName> to whom I wrote on the subject he states
there is a <placeName>claim of 2000 acres</placeName> which he says is worth 500$ and would
have been worth 1000$ if the Timber had not been cut off by the
<persName>Neighbours </persName><persName>Graham </persName>offers 500$ for the <placeName>land </placeName>just for our quit claim
Deed togather with a Power to sue for Damages don on the premicies
if you visit this <placeName>Country </placeName>this fall perhaps by going to see it it may
be worth more or if you dont visit this <placeName>country </placeName>soon perhaps it might
be best to sell it for what it will bring as there is <placeName>Iron works</placeName> near
it and they are destroying the timber I intend writing to <persName>Mr
McGarock</persName> to take care of it I dont wish to sell our interest in it
unless you and <persName>Brown </persName>sell for if we sell our Interest it will give
the person who purchases it a licence to strip the land of Timber
and render [it] worth nothing let me know soon what is best to
be don.</p>

<p>On the <date when="1827-07-23">23d July 1827</date> I enclosed to you a note on <persName>Bartlet Sims
in favr of Alfred Lougraben </persName>(?) for $798.61. dated <date when="1803-08-16">16th augt 1803
</date>which you have never acknoledged the rect of please say whether
you have recd it or not and if you have what prospect there is to
collect it as he has enquired of me about it. I also promised to
enquire of you for <persName>Capt John Hutching</persName> what the prospect would
be for him to collect a debt which <persName>Capt Bell</persName> owed him. if you think
he can collect it he will go on to your <placeName>Country </placeName>for that purpose I
beleave you know all about the transaction between <persName>Bell </persName>and 
<persName>Hutching </persName>it was money <persName>Hutchings </persName>paid for him as his security and if
he is worth it he should pay the debt, it amounts to about $1000.
business at the <placeName>Mines </placeName>has become verry dull the <placeName>Fever River Mines
</placeName>has stocked the market Lead is now only worth $2.50 at the <placeName>river</placeName>
our firm has lost very considerably in the fall of lead the last year
we have made and have Materials on hands to make in all about
1.200.000 lbs on which we will loose from 50c to 2$ per 100 at the
present prices which will make us considerable looses after all the
profits of smelting and the Sale of Medz [merchandise] in payment
for the <placeName>mine Lands</placeName> are not considered so valuable in <placeName>M°</placeName> as they ware
a few years ago.   I have nothing more to add   <persName>Emily </persName>will fill up the<pb n="231"/>
balance   My best respects to <persName>Brown </persName>and his <persName>Lady </persName>and except my
best wishes for your self</p>

<p><persName>James F. Perry </persName>  [Rubric]</p>
<p>Dear <persName>Brother's </persName>and <persName>Sister</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I take <persName>Mr Perry</persName>s place at the desk to add a few lines, and to
thank My Dear <persName>Sister </persName>for her welcom Epistle which I received a
few weeks ago, and O! how happy would I be could I but clasp
my Dear little <persName>Nephew </persName>to my bosom may he continue to grow and
thrive, and become every thing his fond <persName>Parents </persName>could wish is the
sineear prayer of his <persName>Aunt</persName>&#8212; I should like very much to know what
you and <persName>Sir James</persName> are thinking about, not a line have I received
from eather of you since <date n="11-xx-1828">last November</date>, Your letters I expect have
been lost, we do not hear from you as frequently now, as when we
directed by the way of <placeName>Nathetoch [Natchitoches]</placeName>; I have been 
flattering myself all summer with the pleasure of seeing you this Fall;
but shall not look for you untill I see you; our <persName>Friends </persName>and <persName>relations</persName>
are all well I had a visit from <persName>Adeline</persName>, last week, tell <persName>Brown </persName>that
if he was still <hi rend="italic">Single </hi>he might now entrap the <persName>Young widdow</persName> she
looks remarkably well, and is quit lively&#8212; the <persName>Children </persName>are all
well, your namesake says that he wants to see <persName>Uncle Stephen</persName> he
must come and bring him a Spanish Horse; if <persName>Brown </persName>should want a
<hi rend="italic"><persName>clerk</persName></hi>, <persName>Austin </persName>will Shortly be cabable to Fill that office;</p>

<p><persName>E M. Perry</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Col. Stephen F Austin</persName><placeName> San Filipi D Austin</placeName> <placeName>Rio
Brasas Texes</placeName>&#8212;To the care of <persName>Mr Masil White Merchant</persName> <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
