<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1684">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John A Williams to Stephen F Austin, 03-02-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John A Williams</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-10">08-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Pine Bluff, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 174-175
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-03-02">03-02-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Thanking Austin for assistance in getting land for settlers on the Trinity, and warning him against certain inhabitants of that section.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Pine Bluff</placeName> <date when="1829-03-02">2nd March 1829</date></p>
<p><persName>Col Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir. Your favour of the <date when="1829-01-31">31st Jany</date> came to hand and its 
contents has been duly considered, The course you propose for us to
persue relative to the <persName>commissioner </persName>accords with my opinion intirely
but my extreme bad health I fear will prevent my adopting the course
you have suggested</p>

<p>Permit me to inform you that the success which has crowned
your late efforts on the subject of our land petition has gained you
much applause among the <persName>inhabitants of <placeName>Trinity</placeName></persName>. But I fear it
will work a great injury to yourself at least, for new favours in the
opinion of the multitude beget new obligations, and as emty 
acknowledgments are the only tribute they expect will be exacted for the
important servises you have rendered, you may expect future 
aplications in abundence and perhaps I shall be the first to draw on your
benevolence <date when="1829-03-01">yesterday </date>one of the <persName>inhabitants of this <placeName>vicinage</placeName></persName>, and
soil [?] set out for the <placeName>interior </placeName>on some weighty mission, the object
of which I do not exactly comprehend, not belonging to their <persName>cabinet</persName>.
I have not been honoured with a sight of their embassage nor 
credentials but I expect they will stop at <placeName>san Filipe </placeName>and perhaps exhibit
their documents to you. The request I now have to make is this
that should this important personage honour you with a call, that
you receive him with just such marks of distinction as his 
occupation his station in life and the importance, or non importance of his<pb n="175"/>
mission merits and no more, and further I would observe we wish the
great favour which the <persName>Mexican government </persName>has though[t] fit to
bestow upon us in granting us land to be caried into effect without
being contaminated with foul hands, I should not have said any
thing on this subject had it not been for the great industry, intreague
and management with which some petitions of sale has I am 
informed, have been goten up and Subscribers obtained</p>

<p><persName>Jno A. Williams </persName>   [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
