<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1040">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James F. Perry to Stephen F. Austin, 02-14-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James F. Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-05-28">05-28-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mine a Burton, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Natchitoches, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1041-1043
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-02-14">02-14-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-05-28" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Business. Presidental election. Family news.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mine a Burton</placeName> <date when="1825-02-14">Feby 14th 1825</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>We received your letter of the <date when="1824-12-17">17th of December last</date> about <date when="1825-02-04">ten days
since</date> and at your request I now address you. <persName>Brown Austin</persName> started
from <placeName>Herculaneum</placeName> about the <date when="1824-11-03">3d day of November</date> on the <date when="1824-11-23">23d</date> of the
same month he wrote to us from <placeName>Natchez</placeName>&#8212; he had got there safe
and well and I expect he is with you long ere this. We are anxiously
looking every mail for a letter from him from <placeName>Natchetoches</placeName>. With
respect to your sister and myself moving to that <placeName>Country</placeName> we have
not yet come to any determination. I have some thoughts of visiting
your <placeName>Colony</placeName> and if I am pleased with it we may move there but I
have some Scrouples to surmount before, I can get my own 
consent to leave my <placeName>native Country</placeName>, to leave the best Government in the
world for a strange <placeName>Country</placeName> and strange Laws causes cerious 
reflections, but perhaps on visiting the <placeName>country</placeName> and becoming acquénted
with your Laws and your Government Settles down on Republican
principles as there is now every prospect that it will I may become
reconciled to change <placeName>country</placeName>. I will now state to you our prospects,
with industery and econemy   I know we can make an independent<pb n="1042"/>
living here but I never expect to be able to live here in affluence or
to make a fortune. I beleive it was before you left this <placeName>Country</placeName> that
<persName>Samuel Perry</persName> and myself entered into <persName>partnership</persName>&#8212;he had all the
capital I get the one third of the profets. We are still doing 
business, on the same footing, and we have made some money from a
rough calculation we made <date n="02-xx-1824">about a year ago</date> I think I may safely
state that if a dividend was now made my part would amount to
from 8 to 10,000 Dollars in <persName>negroes</persName> goods money and Lands, which
would be a tolarable start in a new <placeName>Country</placeName>. <persName>Saml</persName> and <persName>Myself</persName>
have made no new arrangement since my marage but I expect we
will have to soon. I have not purchased a house yet as I dont wish
to purchase untill we determine where to settle permantly as I am
not fond of moving. Now I have gave you an Idea of our 
curcumstances and prospects I wish you to write to me your Ideas of that
<placeName>country </placeName>both with regard to it[s] government and Laws and its
natural advantages do you think with what we could take with us
and with industry and economy that we could make a fortune in a
few years give us your opinion if you advise me I will visit your
<placeName>colony</placeName> but unless I thought we could better our cituation I would
rather live here as I feel much attached to our <placeName>native country</placeName> and
Laws, it would certainly be my wish to live near you if it could be
so for all our benefits. <persName>Chester Ashley</persName> is now in this <placeName>country</placeName>. I
have not yet seen him, but expect to see him before he returns and
will make inquiery respecting the<placeName> little Rock</placeName> Business. With respect
to the <placeName>Mine A Burton Property</placeName> I can not at this time give you much
satisfaction respecting it. <persName>Price</persName> and <persName>Ruggles</persName> and <persName>W. M</persName> and <persName>J
Perry,</persName> has a lawsute pending in the <persName>supreme Court</persName> respecting 250
acres which your <persName>Father </persName>conveyed to <persName>Ruggles</persName> and <persName>James Bryan</persName> to
secure them for being his security in <placeName>Bank</placeName>. <persName>Bryan</persName> sold his part to
<persName>W M</persName> and <persName>J Perry</persName>.<persName> Price</persName> obtained a judgment against <persName>Ruggles</persName> and
<persName>Perry</persName> for 3,500 Dollars it was removed to the <persName>Supreme Court</persName> and
will be tryed I expect in <date n="05-xx-1826">May next</date>&#8212; <persName>Perry and Ruggles Lawyers</persName>
say that your <persName>Fathers Heirs</persName> could recover the whole or Part of the
<placeName>tract </placeName>so I am told but I intend consulting <persName>Judge Cook</persName> (who is one
of them and Knowes all about the situation of it) as soon as I can
see him and I will than give you a more satisfactory acfc of it. Our
<persName>Legislature </persName>is now in Session and has been ever since the <date when="1824-11-03">3d monday
in November</date> and is not expected to rise before the <date when="1825-02-26">26th</date> or <date when="1825-02-26">26th 
Istant</date>. they are reviseing the whole code of Laws and are making
many very material alterations whether for the better or worse time
will determine the last act we had from <persName>Saml Perry</persName> who is still a
<persName>member of the senate</persName> he states they had passed 140 laws and had 30
or 40 more to act on   Your old Friend <persName>Judge Benton</persName> has been re-<pb n="1043"/>
elected to the <persName>U. S. Senate</persName> not with standing the most outrageous
Slander was circulated against him by his <persName>enemies </persName><persName>Rectors</persName>, <persName>Benton</persName>
<persName>Govnr Mc Nair</persName> and others it is not yet known who will be our next
<persName>President </persName>went to the <persName>house of Representatives</persName> <persName>Jackson</persName> had the
highest vote <persName>Adams</persName> next and <persName>Crawford</persName> next <persName>Clay</persName> was left out
<persName>Crawford</persName>s friends have no hopes the contest will be between <persName>Jackson</persName> and <persName>Adams</persName>.</p>

<p>There is now here an <persName>agent </persName>to lease the <placeName>U. S. Lead mines</placeName> he has
granted some leases, the <persName>miners</persName> are not willing to Submit he
leases under a Law of <date n="xx-xx-1807">1807 </date>which is thought here does not autherise
the leasing of them, if his <placeName>leases </placeName>are inforsed it will make a great
alteration in the Lead business I think for the worse the <placeName>leases</placeName>
are for 3 years. <persName>Mrs Henry Elliott</persName> is in this place teaching <placeName>school</placeName>
from her present prospects she expects to have a large <placeName>School</placeName>
against next <date n="summer- 1825">summer</date>. She wishes to be remembered to you. Your
<persName>Sister </persName>and <persName>Children </persName>are well <persName>Joel</persName> and <persName>Austin</persName> are going to School
<persName>Guy</persName> and<persName> Mary</persName> Grow finely. Write to us by every oppertunity
as we are always anxtious to here from you.<persName> Wm</persName> and <persName>Jn° Perry</persName>
are well <persName>Will</persName> has no wife and <persName>John</persName> has no Children. <persName>Mrs Sam1
Perry</persName> has been in <placeName>St Louis</placeName> all winter with her <persName>Daughter </persName><persName>Mrs Farris</persName>
<persName>Sam1</persName> writes to us offin they are all well a Brother of the Handy
which <persName>Saml</persName> Shot made an attempt to Shoot <persName>Saml </persName>in <placeName>St Louis </placeName>not
long since but <persName>Saml</persName> jumped in on him and took his pistol from
[him] prevented him from shooting and let him go again. Old
<persName>Bissel</persName> and <persName>Price</persName> are Blamed for seting him on.<persName> Emily </persName>joins me
in our Best wishes for your wellfare and prosperity also give our
best respect to your <persName>Brother Brown</persName> and permit me to subscribe
myself your <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p><persName>Jas F. Perry</persName></p>

<p>In your next please direct us how to direct our letters if this
is not the right</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Co1- Stephen F Austin</persName><placeName> Rio Brazos </placeName><placeName>Province of
Texas</placeName> To the Care of <persName>Jared Cable Esqr</persName> <placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>&#8212;¦</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
