<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1977">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Texas Gazette, 07-03-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-23">08-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Texas Gazette
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 437-440
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-07-03">07-03-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Calming popular apprehension over the law of April 6, 1830.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>We this day publish a translation of the law passed by the 
National Congress, on the <date when="1830-04-06">6th of April last</date>, and also, the official
letter of his <persName>Excellency General Manuel de Mier y Teran,</persName> to the
<persName>Empresario of this colony</persName>.</p>

<p>By an attentive perusal of the law it will be seen, that the 
privileges granted in it relative to the coasting trade, and to the introduc-<pb n="438"/>
tion of provisions and lumber free of duty into the <placeName>ports of Galveston
and Matagorda </placeName>are of the highest importance to the prosperity of
<placeName>Texas</placeName>, and must tend most efficiently to promote its rapid 
advancement.</p>

<p>The encouragement offered for the establishment of <placeName>manufactories</placeName>
is also important, and there cannot be a doubt that many 
enterprising <persName>capitalists </persName>will turn their attention to that branch of 
industry. Perhaps no <placeName>country </placeName>combines more real advantages than
are presented in <placeName>Texas </placeName>for the establishment of cotton and woolen
<placeName>factories</placeName>. The raw material of the best quality can be raised in the
greatest abundance, and cheaper than in any other part of <placeName>North
America.</placeName> Our soil yields the most luxuriant growth of cotton of
the best quality. Our natural <placeName>pasturage </placeName>for sheep, in the 
<placeName>undulating and hilly sections in the northern parts of Texas,</placeName> are surpassed
by none in any <placeName>country</placeName>; and countless thousands of them may be
raised, with no other expense than a few shepherds. Provisions
may be easily produced. Good situations for machinery, with water,
steam, or ox power are numerous. Our <placeName>harbors </placeName>are sufficient for all
the purposes of commerce. Our communications with the <placeName>Mexican
ports</placeName> are open and unembarrassed. The <placeName>markets</placeName>, in those <placeName>ports</placeName>,
are the best in the <placeName>world</placeName>, for the sale of cotton or other woolen
goods, such as might be manufactured in <placeName>Texas</placeName>. In short, all that
nature and a liberal and munificent government can do has been
done, and nothing is now wanting but capital, enterprise and
industry.</p>

<p>The 10th. article of the law clearly secures the rights of the
<persName>colonists </persName>who are already settled. It also guarantees the rights of
all the <persName>emigrants </persName>who are comprehended in the contracts of 
<persName>empresarios </persName>whose<placeName> colonies are established</placeName>, and permits the full 
completion of such contracts, to the full number contracted for. So that
emigration to the <placeName>colony </placeName>is not stopped as was erroneously rumored.
The <persName>settlers </persName>who are not comprehended in any <placeName>colony</placeName>, may also be
provided for, as will be seen by reference to the powers granted to
the General Government [Commandant] in the 3rd article.</p>

<p>The official letter of his<persName> Excellency General Teran,</persName> the 
<persName>commissioner of the General Government</persName>, under the 3rd article, is very clear
and explicit, as to the interpretation of the law, and as to the just
and liberal views of the General Government, under whose 
instructions he is acting.</p>

<p>The name of this distinguished <persName>patriot </persName>and scientific <persName>general </persName>is
closely connected with some of the most interesting events in <persName>Mexican</persName>
history. A <persName>soldier </persName>under the banner of freedom from the first epoch
of the revolution, he has uniformly been a firm defender of the rights
of his <placeName>countrymen</placeName>.   As a <persName>legislator in the first constituent congress</persName>,<pb n="439"/>
his voice was raised in opposition to despotism and in favor of a
free, liberal and constitutional government. As <persName>secretary of war</persName> he
established system and organization in the army after the convulsions
of the <persName>Emperor</persName>'s short reign. At <placeName>Tampico </placeName>the <persName>invaders </persName>of his
<placeName>country </placeName>sank before his military genius, and received from his
humanity that protection and succor which their prowess could not
secure to them. As <persName>commandant general of the eastern military
department and commissioner of the General Government for 
regulating the colonies of Texas</persName> and establishing new ones, he will 
provide for the defense and permanent security of <placeName>Texas </placeName>from the
<persName>Indians</persName>, and lay a foundation for such additional colonial 
<placeName>establishments </placeName>and <placeName>maritime towns</placeName> and fortifications as may be necessary
to advance its prosperity.</p>

<p>The section of <placeName>country east of this colony</placeName> and particularity the
<placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>and <placeName>Ais district</placeName>s, demand the prompt attention of
government. The land affairs of those sections require adjustment,
and a totally different organization of the local government is much
needed. Instead of having the whole civil and judicial power of
the <persName>local government</persName> vested in <persName>alcaldes </persName>elected annually, it would be
better to have a separate <placeName>partido </placeName>laid off with a <persName>chief of partido</persName>,
and in addition to the <persName>alcaldes </persName>there ought to be a <persName>juez de letras, or
judge learned in the law</persName>, appointed in the manner prescribed in the
constitution, with a salary to insure a man of talents and 
qualifications. It is sufficient to merely know how the <persName>local government</persName> of
that section of <placeName>country </placeName>is and always has been organized to 
understand the causes of all the little <placeName>local </placeName>difficulties which have arisen
there. It cannot be supposed that an <persName>alcalde </persName>annually changed and
elected by popular vote from the mass of a people speaking a variety
of languages and who are themselves in general ignorant of the
laws should be capable of discharging so important and responsible
a position as that of a <persName>judge</persName>, whose jurisdiction embraces the 
investigation of all matters of controversy and all criminal cases without
limit. Under three hundred dollars his jurisdiction is final, over
that sum there is the right of appeal to the <placeName>supreme court at Saltillo</placeName>,
<hi rend="italic">six hundred miles distant</hi>. The <persName>alcaldes</persName>, however, cannot give final
judgement in any important civil case and in no capital criminal
case, without first consulting the <hi rend="italic"><persName>assesor general</persName></hi>, or <persName>attorney general
</persName>who lives at <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>. It is very evident that such a system cannot
secure to the people, nor to the government the benefits which 
organization and regular administration of the laws are designed to 
produce. The objections to the present <persName>alcalde </persName>system will apply more
or less to every part of the state, and are very evident. They are
severely felt here as well as elsewhere, for although the public 
tranquility has never been interrupted in this <placeName>colony </placeName>from its first<pb n="440"/>
establishment up to the present time, yet great individual 
inconvenience is daily experienced from this mode of administration of
the laws.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
