<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1998">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James F Perry to Stephen F Austin, 07-18-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James F Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-23">08-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Hugh McGuffen Esq
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Potosi, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 457-458
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-07-18">07-18-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Preparations for removal to Texas. Slaves. Austin's reserve.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Potosi Mo</placeName> <date when="1830-07-18">July the 18th 1830</date></p>
<p>Dr Sr</p>

<p>I got <placeName>home </placeName>on the <date when="1830-06-12">12th June</date> found all well with the addition of a
fine <persName>Son</persName>, I would have wrote to you sooner but from the unsettled
state of my business I heardly knew what to say. I find it will be
a tedious task to settle it all up and take more time than I expected,
from the most moderate calculation<persName> S. Perry</persName> and myself made we
calculated we had on hands lead to pay all the debts of the firm and
have some left. <persName>S. Perry</persName> has returned he only sold part and from
the present prices I am afraid there will not be enough to pay off
the debts of the firm, which will derange my calculations verry
much I will of necessity have to remain here untill they are all
paid. We have a considerable sum in the <placeName>Country </placeName>but times are so
dull and money so scarce it is verry dificult to make collections I
am anxious to move <date n="Fall - 1830">this fall</date> but I find it will be imposible <persName>Emily</persName>
is not willing to move in the <date n="Spring - 1831">spring </date>for fear of sickness for my
part I think there would be no danger if we could get there in <date n="03-xx-1830">March</date>
or <date n="04-xx-1830">April</date>, but I expect we will be governed by your advice. I sold
our <placeName>house and lots we live on</placeName> to <placeName>Hutchings </placeName>for <persName>Bell</persName>s notes and
expect to sell another <placeName>place </placeName>in a few days to <persName>John Perry</persName> for goods
to be recd in <placeName>Phila </placeName>If I do so I will be in <placeName>Phila </placeName>the last of <date n="09-xx-1830">Sept</date>. if
I can get off if not I will send <persName>Mr Hunter</persName> with that we will have
about 2000$ to lay out in goods in addition to our present stock
which is not less than 3000$ we will try and get them in in the month
of <date n="11-xx-1830">November</date>.</p>

<p>While on the <placeName>bay </placeName>you promissed to give me a copy of an endenture
to take on our <persName>negroes</persName>, Which was forgot in the hurry at <placeName>S Felipe
</placeName>please send me one. from all the laws I see on the subject I am
apprehensive an endenture on those under age would not be good
we have Eight and only 3 or 4 of them is of age give me your
advise on that matter to loose them after I get them there would
be a serious loss to me. There has been a considerable stir here
about <placeName>Texas </placeName>but the unsettled state of the Govrnt is a great obsticle.
A good many talks of going but I doubt whether many will move
or not <persName>S. T Dunklin</persName> says he will go to see it this <date n="Fall - 1830">fall </date>I told
him you had reservd a tract for him <placeName>near the bay</placeName> <persName>John Jones</persName> talks
of starting in <date n="11-xx-1830">September </date>by land When I read your letter which
was recd in my absence stating the particulars of the <placeName>grants </placeName>you<pb n="458"/>
obtaine'd for us I was mortifyed not because the <placeName>grants </placeName>ware
different from what I understood but at your silance on that subject
to me. What the object of your silance was I am at a loss to 
conceive. When with you on the <placeName>bay </placeName>I thought you was verry reserved
towards me but did not expect you would have been reserved in
anything that related to the sole object of my journey to that
<placeName>country</placeName>. Why not tell me the nature of the <placeName>grants </placeName>and how you
intended to locate them. This I certainly think you ought to have
don. from my understanding of your letter the intention of the
<placeName>Grant </placeName>to <persName>Emily </persName>is for her <persName>eldest children </persName>which was perfectly right
in you to do so when you had it in your power. And it would
have been much more satisfactory to me if you had desclosed your
views to me there. With regard to these <persName>children </persName>I have no 
reflections to make on myself I have always don for them and by them
as well as I would have or could have don if they had been my own.
Through the hole course of my life I have ever acted candidly
towards both <persName>relatives </persName>and <persName>friends </persName>and hope ever so to do and
would wish them to act so towards me. this I believe is the best
course to gain and retain the confidance of each other.</p>

<p>The suit in <placeName>N Jersey</placeName> is expected to be determined in <date n="10-xx-1830">October</date>
next <persName>S. Perry</persName> is in a verry delicate health I think it doubtful
whether he is long for this <placeName>world</placeName>. A great many of our <persName>friends</persName>
here think we are going a wild goos chase when we start for <placeName>Texas</placeName>.
Is <persName>James Austin</persName> alive yet I am afraid not. I have not seen 
<persName>Hammond </persName>I dont know whether he is going to <placeName>Texas </placeName>or not. <persName>Woodson</persName>
was here last week to talk of moving <persName>Henry Bates </persName>I hear has give
out the notice   I have nothing more to ad.   alls well,   adue&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>James F. Perry</persName></p>

<p><placeName>Potosi Mo</placeName> <date when="1830-07-19">July 19 1830</date></p>

<p>[Addressed] : <persName>Col Stephen F Austin</persName> <placeName>San Filipe de Austin Texas
</placeName>To the Care of <persName>Hugh McGuffen Esq</persName> <persName>post Master <placeName>Sabine Post
office   Louissianna</placeName></persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
