<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1819">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John Austin to Stephen F Austin, 12-27-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-17">08-17-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brazoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 304-306
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-12-27">12-27-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Urging Austin to take a rest and to collect debts from those owing him. Plans for Mrs. J. E. B. Austin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p>I received yours of the <date when="1829-12-18">18th inst</date> by <persName>Mr. Smith son in law to Ellis</persName>.
I am very sorry to hear that you do not recover your health I am
sure that your confinement at <placeName>San Filipe</placeName> tends greatly to retard the
recovery of your health and I would advise you by all means to go
<placeName>into the woods </placeName>this <date n="WInter - 1829">winter </date>and to arrange your business so as to take
a trip to the<placeName> U. States,</placeName> <date n="Summer - 1830">next summer</date> a trip of that kind would be of
great service to you I have no doubt and I see no reason why you
should not take some time to yourself after serving seven years
apprenticeship to the Colonizing trade, but to say the least it is
nessisary for you to leave the <placeName>office </placeName>if it is only for a change of<pb n="305"/>
business I know that you have become tired of being cursed by
<persName>persons </persName>who have received the most favours by your exertions and
at your hand but you know it is the way of the world those who
are most Virtuous or most patient are not known until they are
tried therefore I suppose it is nessisary to give them a trial I think
that you have been tried sufficeintly to retire a short time from trial
make these <persName>men </persName>who want land now pay up and those who are
oweing you on the <placeName>old colony</placeName> pay they may grumble some but let
them do so they will do it at any rate;&#8212;</p>

<p>you observed that you thought you had had written a cross letter Just
before you started to me if so I never have received it I have never
received a letter from you saying that you were going to <placeName>San
Antonio</placeName> if I had received such a letter from you I would have
concluded that you were Scolding for my own benefit or giveing me
good advise   I never have received the cross letter&#8212;</p>

<p>You asked my opinion concerning the Situation of <persName>Eliza </persName>had I
not expected you here long before this I would have given it to you
at <placeName>San Felipe </placeName>When I was last there she has been positive about
keeping <placeName>house </placeName>by herself untill lately within a few days she has
been living with us at my <placeName>house </placeName>where she will always be welcome
if she can make herself so I think that she has discovered the many
difficulties that would attend the house keeping or living by herself.
She says that she never will go home to her <placeName>Fathers House</placeName> on any
account and will not hear a word about the matter&#8212; I have 
advised it to her as the most prudent step and I thought the Most
pleasant to herself but when she read the letter which you wrote
to her and sent by me she said in the most positive manner that
she never would live with her <persName>parents </persName>again now if she can 
content herself at my <placeName>House </placeName>I think it will be best to move the <placeName>log
house</placeName> unfinished <placeName>on my lot </placeName>and finish it for her to live in if you think
so I will do it but when the <persName>Commissioner </persName>leaves there I wish you
would take a few days time and come down here then we can settle
upon some plan for future operation, if there is any <persName>porter </persName>in the
Vessel I will have some for you I wish you to come soon that some
arrangement Can be made with <persName>Harris </persName>at the <placeName>Gin </placeName>the business
will not detain you more than three or four days at this and the
<placeName>Gin</placeName>, <persName>Mr Westall</persName> has an account for Boarding I do not know the
amount I presented his Bill and have not yet settled with him on
account of the Bill he has against yourself and <persName>Brother </persName>he will
present it when Called upon I intend to allow it should he present
it before I see you as I suppose he would not bring a wrong bill
I wish that you would make some of those <persName>persons </persName>who are oweing
you pay up in produce or Cotton   if they would do so I want the use<pb n="306"/>
of some money untill I can collect   I wish to pay all demands in
<placeName>Orleans </placeName>as soon as possible&#8212;</p>

<p>Nothing new the vessel has not yet arrived</p>

<p><persName>John Austin  </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName>&#8212;</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
