<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1611">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>J E B Austin to Stephen F Austin, 09-16-1828</title>
            <author>
                <persName>J E B Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-08">08-08-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 107-109
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1828-09-16">09-16-1828</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Plans for building gin and other business. Glad Austin is paying more attention to his own interests.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1828-11-16">September 16th 1828</date>:</p>
<p>Dr <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>I received your letter by <persName>Mr. McNutt</persName>, <persName>John </persName>has concluded to
go up to <placeName>Sn Felipe</placeName> and will take up the papers you enclosed&#8212; <persName>Cap.n
Martin</persName> will go up with <persName>John </persName>to arrange the bonds for the money<pb n="108"/>
he has loaned us, he lets us have the use of the Money three years
at 6 pr cent, and we are to give him good security.   We stated to
him that we would either give you as Security, or execute a 
Mortgage on this <placeName>place</placeName>&#8212; he says either will do&#8212;and if the loan was
for a shorter period he would not require security, you can do as
you think best in the subject.&#8212; I have noticed the contents of
your letter relative to the management of this place and am much
pleased with your ideas of Economy as they accord precisely with
my own, and afford me much satisfaction to perceive you 
determined to pay more attention to your own interest than heretofore,
a thing I have so oftened wished-&#8212; I am sensible if you continue
in the same way of thinking, a few years will entirely relieve you
from embarassment, and enable you to spend the remainder of
your life in ease and comfort. As to our future plans I have 
concluded to remain here for the <date n="xx-xx-1828">present year</date>; and am now employed
putting the <placeName>Gin </placeName>in good order for the present crop&#8212; My calculation
was if <persName>Williams </persName>joined us to have gone to <placeName>San Felipe</placeName>, but not 
receiving an answer from him on the subject we conclude that he has
probably abandoned the idea-&#8212; I wish to get <persName>Leal </persName>and his <persName>wife </persName>down
as soon as possible, and I want them started down while <persName>John </persName>is
at <placeName>Town </placeName>if they want any assistance <persName>Leal </persName>may hire <persName>Francisco</persName>, 
<persName>Antones Son</persName>, who knows the way&#8212;and i will pay him here&#8212;</p>

<p>There are some things at town that I want to get down as I
have little or nothing to commence housekeeping with and it they
are left there may get lost, and if brought here will be saved, and be
of service to me&#8212; I will try and get <persName>Keller </persName>to go up in his boat and
bring down everything that you may not want&#8212; I am anxious to
get as many cattle as I can and if you can procure any I will attend
to the Collection of them. The cattle that is owing to <persName>Betts </persName>I want
for <persName>Bowen </persName>and <persName>Betts </persName>has promised me to settle with him. I have
two cows and two heifers at <persName>Robins</persName>; and the cows I expect have
calves, and perhaps the heifers I want <persName>Leal </persName>to get <persName>Francisco </persName>and
drive them down I purchased in the first place three cows&#8212;and
two heifers&#8212;one cow I let <persName>Sam Pettus</persName> have and the others are
still there&#8212; Enclosed I send an a/c against <persName>Battles </persName>which you can
charge on y.r Books in y.r Settlement with him, remember that all
goods furnished him is cash&#8212;also all debts paid by us for him is
the same&#8212; I also send two other against <persName>Slaughter </persName>which you can
also charge</p>

<p>I have paid <persName>Phillips </persName>and <persName>Slaughter </persName>considerable which can be
ascertained by having My a/c with <persName>Richardson </persName>and <persName>Davis </persName>drawn off
also&#8212;charge <persName>Slaughter </persName>with one dollar paid <persName>McKinstry </persName>and 
<persName>Phillips </persName>1.88 paid <persName>W. C. White</persName>&#8212;<persName> Widow Gilbert</persName> has an a/c against
us    part is paid which can be ascertained by referring to my a/c with<pb n="109"/>
<persName>R P D</persName>. in y.r Settlement with <persName>Phillips </persName>ask him if he procured
any thing on my a/c from <persName>McKinstry</persName>&#8212; <persName>Battles </persName>took some powder
from the <placeName>old office</placeName> to pay a <persName>Spaniard </persName>for coming down here&#8212; also
he has made use of considerable plank for himself which he must
be charged with If I can leave <placeName>home </placeName>I will come up and arrange
these a/cs myself but I shall be so confined that I think it doubtful
whether I can leave <placeName>home</placeName>. If you have any notes or a/cs due in this
<placeName>Settlement </placeName>if you will send them down by <persName>John </persName>we will Collect them
this <date n="Fall - 1832">fall</date>- <persName>John </persName>will go to <persName>Jackson</persName>s sale and if there is any thing
to be sold that will be of service to us he may purchase&#8212; I am
going to make a crop this season and if the <persName>Negroes </persName>hire low we
should like to hire them&#8212; The window Glass is in the <placeName>old house</placeName>
back of the <placeName>office</placeName>&#8212;two boxes 10 by 12. and one 8 by 10. the paint
is in the same <placeName>house </placeName>also the oil&#8212; I think the best plan is to hire
the house to <persName>Whiteside</persName>s he ought to give at least 20 or 25 dollars
p.r Month.</p>

<p><persName>Bowen </persName>has arrived&#8212;poor <persName>McKinstry </persName>is dead&#8212;it is very Sickly
in <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName>&#8212;   <persName>Eliza </persName>sends her love&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>J. B. Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>P. S. <persName>Eliza </persName>has two heifers at town one of them is in the bend
below cow a black&#8212;and the other is at<placeName> <persName>Kuykendal</persName>s</placeName>, a muly- if
<persName>Leal </persName>can find them I want him to drive them down</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
