<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1857">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John W Faulkner to Stephen F Austin, 02-23-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John W Faulkner</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-18">08-18-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Wigginsville, Clarke Co, Alabama</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Province of Texas by way of New Orleans</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 335-336
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-02-23">02-23-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Forty citizens wish information of conditions in Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Wigginsville Clarke Co.<lb/>
Alabama</placeName> <date when="1830-02-23">23rd Feby 1830</date>.</p>
<p>Sir</p>

<p>You will excuse the liberty I have taken in addressing you a few
lines on the subject of inquiry about <placeName>your country (Texas)</placeName> first I
wish you to inform me where bouts is the <placeName>largest sea port Town</placeName> on
<placeName>theither [either] of the Bays</placeName> and the prospects of its being the
largest and the best back and up country to support it, with the
helth of either place etc also what business is doing and likely to
continu, and at what advance are Dry Goods sold at on the <placeName>New York
</placeName>or <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> cost the advantages and disadvantages of getting
them to the <placeName>town </placeName>etc. also should be glad to recie the laws of your
<placeName>count[r] y</placeName> for my own and my <persName>frinds</persName> [and] <persName>neighbors </persName>use and if
liked will no doubt leave this for yurs this <date n="SPring - 1830">spring </date>or <date n="Fall - 1830">fall</date>, also let
me know if <persName>negroes </persName>can be brought in to that <placeName>country</placeName>, <persName>Capt. Wyley
White Brother of Joseph White </persName>of your <placeName>country </placeName>informs me that
the <placeName>River Brassoss</placeName> is the largest and most <placeName>navagable Stream</placeName> in that
<placeName>country </placeName>with <placeName>good lands</placeName> on it and speaks of <placeName>a Town at the mouth
of the River on the Bay by the name of Boliver</placeName> and that a very
respectable business is doing in it and is likely to be a very large
Town and he thinks the largest in that <placeName>Country</placeName>.</p>

<p>Your ideas on this subject knowing that they must be weighty (?)
the best that could be produced would be very thankfully recd by
abut 40 very respectable <persName>citicens </persName>who feal great interest in the
siteation of that entry the advantages and disadvantages.</p>

<p>If you have a <placeName>map </placeName>of the <placeName>country </placeName>or can draw one showing the
<placeName>Rivers </placeName><placeName>Towns </placeName><placeName>bays </placeName>and <placeName>country </placeName>designating the <placeName>Rich Land</placeName> etc.
they also would be very thankfully recvd at this <placeName>office</placeName>. Let me
know if there is not frequently vessels from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> and
<placeName>Mobile to Boliver </placeName>or any other <placeName>towns </placeName>on the <placeName>bays </placeName>that <persName>persons </persName>going
to and from might be accomodated with this facility together with
any other information that may present itself to your views will be
most thankfully recvd (also let me know if goods are sold on a
credit like they generally is in <placeName>Alabama </placeName>and greatly oblige yours</p>

<p><persName>John W. Faulkner</persName></p>

<p>is your <placeName>country </placeName>at warre with <placeName>Spain </placeName>now or not as I see <placeName>Mexico</placeName>
is which is thought here will affect <placeName>Texas </placeName>as it is under the same<pb n="336"/>
<persName>Governmt </persName>but again it is said those <persName>persons </persName>living in <placeName>Texas </placeName>is not to
engage in war or to take sides or to be called on for 12 years to come
is this a fact or not.</p>

<p>which is the <placeName>best Town in Texas </placeName>for Merchandising and what kind
of Goods is most suitable for the <placeName>country</placeName>, my ides are such as
Domestieks and Hard war such as farming articals etc. Shoes Hats
and the reda made clothing etc and but few very fine goods.</p>

<p><persName>John W. Faulkner</persName> free p. m.</p>

<p>[Address:] <persName>Col Austin</persName> <persName>Town of Austin Province of Texas
</persName>The <persName>Post Master at <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></persName> will please forward this by the first
vessel or privil cvyance to greatly oblige the writer,</p>

<p><persName>J. W. Faulkner</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
