<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1451">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to J. R. Poinsett, 11-03-1827</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-26">07-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J. R. Poinsett
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Saltillo, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1703-1705
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1827-11-03">11-03-1827</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Transmitting petition from David G. Burnet asking permit to establish a colony from Ohio in the border reserve. Exclusion of slavery checks immigration from Southern States; presumes the Government will encourage movement from the free States.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Saltillo</placeName>, <date when="1827-11-03">November 3, 1827</date>
</p>
<p><persName>Hon. J. R Poinsett</persName>,</p>

<p>Sir&#8212;¦ At the request of my friend <persName>Mr David G. Burnet</persName> of
<placeName>Ohio </placeName>I inclose you two letters of recommendation, one from the
<persName>Hon. H. Clay</persName> and the other from the <persName>Hon. E. A. Brown.</persName></p>

<p><persName>Mr. Burnet</persName> has obtained from the <persName>Gov't of this <placeName>State </placeName></persName>authority
to colonise a district of <placeName>Country lyying west of Nacogdoches</placeName> and as
it is a small strip he wishes to annex to it a <placeName>portion of country ex-<pb n="1704"/>
tending East from said village to the Sabine river,</placeName> but as this latter
is embraced <placeName>within the twenty border leagues reserved by the 
Colonization Act</placeName>, it cannot be colonized without the previous permission
of the <persName>President </persName>and <persName>Mr. Burnet</persName> has presented a memorial to that
effect which goes on by this mail to the <persName>minister of relations</persName> 
recommended by this Gov't.</p>

<p>His object in directing his attention to this enterprise is to settle
a number of reputable <persName>farmers </persName>from the <placeName>State of Ohio</placeName>, who find it
inconvenient to provide lands in that <placeName>country </placeName>for their large and
increasing <persName>families </persName>owing to its excessively high price. The 
morality, industry and agricultural enterprise which characterize the 
<persName>inhabitants of <placeName>Ohio </placeName></persName>are well known and proverbial, slavery is 
unknown amongst them, they are " principled " against it, every man
is a <persName>laborer</persName>, and in this particular to their other recommend able
qualities, they unite a principle which is in strict accordance with
the broad ideas of liberty and universal emancipation laid down in
the State Constitutions, and so strenuously urged in legislative 
deliberations&#8212;</p>

<p>The restrictions as to Slavery in this <placeName>State </placeName>present very material
obstacles to the settlement of <placeName>Texas </placeName>by <persName>emigrants from the <placeName>southern
States</placeName></persName>, and should it be the wish of the <persName>Mexican Gov't,</persName> to convert
that fine portion of its <placeName>territory </placeName>from a <placeName>savage wilderness </placeName>and 
useless dead burthen on the <placeName>nation</placeName>, to a populous, civilized and 
cultivated state capable of contributing a material quota towards 
national incomer wealth and prosperity, sound policy, and expediency I
should presume would approve of a decided encouragement of <placeName>Ohio</placeName>
and other northern emigration. As regards national policy, I can
see no objection to <persName>emigrants </persName>from our <placeName>sister republic</placeName>, similitude
of political institutions, unity of genl interests, absence of cause for
a difference in local interests and enthusiastic love of liberty, present
natural and mutual guarantees of perpetual harmony and peace 
between the two <placeName>nations</placeName>. Not so with the <placeName>nations of Europe</placeName>, who are, and must ever be the natural <persName>enemies of <placeName>American </placeName></persName>prosperity; and
besides, the kind of <persName>emigrants </persName>that may be brought from <placeName>Europe </placeName>for
colonizing purposes will not be of the class calculated to advance the
<persName>lower orders of Society </persName>for the purpose of filling a contract, they
will not in general possess the enterprise, perseverance and morality
so indespensable to settle a wilderness, whereas <persName>emigrants </persName>from the
<placeName>north</placeName>, to these and many other good qualities will add Capital&#8212;such
<persName>emigrants </persName>certainly cannot be compared with the overflowings of
the redundant population of <placeName>Europe</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Mr. Burnet</persName> is in <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>and in obedience to his wishes, as
well as to comply with my duty as a friend, I have troubled you<pb n="1705"/>
with this letter, and solicit such aid with the minister of relations in
favor of the application as may be consistent.</p>

<p>I embrace this opportunity to present my warmest wishes for your
health and happiness and big you to accept the assurance of respect
and esteem with which I have the honor to remain
your very Obt. Servt.</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>&#8212;</p>
<p>P. S.    Any communications relative to <persName>Mr Burnet</persName>'s business which
you may think proper to make will reach their destination directed
to me " en la villa de<placeName> San Felipe de Austin, Texas,</placeName> (por el <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>)"</p>

<p><persName>Estevan F. Austin</persName>.</p>
<p><date when="1827-11-05">Nov. 5</date>&#8212;I enclose copies of <persName>Mr. Burnet</persName>'s petition and the "in-
forms " of the Govt.</p>

<p><persName>A.</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
