<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1792">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to John Durst, 11-17-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-16">08-16-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        John Durst
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Nacogdoches, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 288-289
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-11-17">11-17-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Advising memorial to government urging exemption of Texas from the emancipation decree. Argues that it is unconstitutional. Opposition must be temperate but firm. State officials are standing against it</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1829-11-17">Nov 17. 1829</date></p>
<p<persName>>Mr John Durst</persName></p>

<p><persName>Nacogdoches</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir I have recd your letter by this days mail dated the <date when="1829-11-10">10th
instant,</date> on the subject of the decree of the <persName>President </persName>freeing all the
<persName>Slaves</persName>.</p>

<p>You say to me in your letter "in the name of God what shall we
do.&#8212; do for God's sake advise me on the subject by return of mail,
we are ruined for ever should this measure be adopted "</p>

<p>What the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas </placeName></persName>have to do, is to represent to the 
<persName>Government</persName>, through the <persName>Ayuntamientos </persName>or some other channel, in a very
respectful manner; that agreeably to the constitution, and the 
colonization laws <hi rend="italic">all </hi>their <persName>property </persName>is guaranteed to them without 
exceptions in the most solemn and sacred manner-&#8212; That they brought
their <persName>slave </persName>property into the <placeName>country </placeName>and have retained it here,
under the faith of that guarantee, and in consequence of a special
invitation publically given to <persName>emigrants </persName>by the <persName>Government </persName>in the
Colonizacion law to do so&#8212;that they have taken an oath to defend<pb n="289"/>
the constitution and are bound to do so. That the constitution of
the <placeName>state </placeName>expressly recognises the right of property in <persName>slaves</persName>, by
allowing six months after its publication for their introduction into
the <placeName>State</placeName>&#8212;That they <hi rend="italic">will </hi>defend it, and with it, their <persName>property</persName>.</p>

<p>There ought to be no vocifirous and visionary excitement or noise
about this matter&#8212; Our course is a very plain one&#8212;calmn, 
deliberate dispationate, inflexible, <hi rend="italic">firmness</hi>; and not windy and ridiculous
blowing and wild threats, and much less any thing like opposition
to the <persName>Mexican </persName>constitution, nothing of this kind will do any good,
it will in fact be unjustifiable, and will never be approved of by me
but on the contrary opposed most decidedly. I will <hi rend="italic">not </hi>violate my
duty as a <persName>mexican citizen</persName>.</p>

<p>The constitution must be both our shield, and our arms, under it,
and with <hi rend="italic">it </hi>we must constitutionally defend <persName>ourselves </persName>and our
<persName>property</persName>.</p>

<p>The <persName>chief of department Dn Ramon Musquiz,</persName> has taken a firm
and noble stand, he has suspended the publication of said decree,
and has represented in a very able manner against it. If he should
finally be compelled to publish and circulate it, the <persName>Ayuntamientos</persName>
must <hi rend="italic">then</hi>, take an unanimous, firm, and <hi rend="italic">constitutional </hi>stand. The
people will unanimously support them.</p>

<p>I know nothing of the <persName>men </persName>who compose the <persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>of
<placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>, if they are true <persName>patriots</persName>, and true <persName>friends </persName>to themselves
and to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, they will not suffer that decree to be published or 
circulated in that <placeName>municipality </placeName>and they will take the stand I have
indicated or some other that will preserve the constitution and our
constitutional rights from open and direct violation</p>

<p>These are my ideas on the matter. I have said the same to my
<persName>friends </persName>in <placeName>Bexar</placeName>, and when the decree arrives officially (which it has
not yet) I shall say the same to the <persName>Govt</persName>&#8212;What I do in this matter
will be done openly&#8212;<placeName>Mexico </placeName>has not within its whole <placeName>dominions</placeName>
a man who would defend its independence, the union of its 
<placeName>territory</placeName>, and all its constitutional rights sooner than I would, or be more
ready and willing to discharge his duties as a <persName>Mexican citizen</persName>; one
of the first and most sacred of those duties is to protect my 
constitutional rights and I will do it, so far as I am able. I am the
owner of one <persName>slave </persName>only, an old decreped <persName>woman </persName>not worth much,
but in this matter I should feel that my constitutional rights as
a <persName>Mexican </persName>were just as much infringed as they would be if I had
a thousand, it is the principle and not the amount, the latter makes
the violation more agravated, but not more illegal or 
unconstitutional</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin  </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p>P. S.   Let me know what your <persName>Ayto</persName>. will do&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S. F. A </persName>  [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
