<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1825">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John P Austin to Stephen F Austin, 01-01-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John P Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-17">08-17-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 313-315
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-01-01">01-01-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Prospects of purchase of Texas by the United States. Terms of recognition of land grants.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><hi rend="italic">Duplicate</hi></p>

<p><placeName>New York</placeName>, <date when="1830-01-01">January 1, 1830</date></p>
<p>My dear Sir,</p>

<p>I took this liberty some few weeks since, which letter I hope
came safe to hand. I now confirm its contents, and remark that
nothing has been done <hi rend="italic">Publicly</hi>, at <placeName>Washington</placeName>, relative to the
<placeName>Texas Country</placeName>; as the <persName>President </persName>was silent on the subject in his
message, so also have <persName>Congress </persName>been <hi rend="italic">thus far</hi>, and it is perhaps
probable that any thing in contemplation, either on the part of the
<persName>administration</persName>, or the <persName>Congress</persName>, will be delayed until late in the
session, to gain time, for <persName>Mr. Poinsett</persName>'s return to <placeName>Washington</placeName>, or for
further advice from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. <persName>Persons however high in office</persName>, it is
said, and others at <placeName>head quarters</placeName> whose opinions are entitled to
some credit have, <hi rend="italic">I know</hi>, expressed opinions favorable to the
obtainment of that <placeName>Province</placeName>, and it is admitted to be understood
that this <persName>Government </persName>have determined on the measure provided it
can be <hi rend="italic">reasonably obtained</hi>. But when the thing will be formally
moved is uncertain and may depend on many circumstances which
are not within my reach to divine. The project is now making
some noise in the<placeName> English papers</placeName>, and perhaps will call forth a
protest from <placeName>Spain</placeName>. Yet it appears probable that sooner or later
<hi rend="italic">and I believe ere long, </hi>the change will be brought about some how or
other by amiable negotiation. There seems (as far as I have been
able to learn) a considerable disposition to speculate in the <placeName>Texas lands,</placeName>
 which can only be accounted for on the supposition that they
will soon belong to the <placeName>U. States</placeName>.</p>

<p><date when="1830-01-09">January 9th.</date> Since the above I have reason to believe, (by 
information received from <persName>persons </persName>who have good means of judging
at <placeName>Washington</placeName>) that the <placeName>Texas </placeName>negotiations, <hi rend="italic">although in embryo
yet</hi>; are still going on, and something has no doubt been fixed on
by this Government, <hi rend="italic">that is</hi>, the acquisition for reasonable 
considerations, and I further learn, that this <persName>Govt</persName>, will probably not be
satisfied with the sovereignty of that <placeName>territory </placeName>alone, but must have
something more, that is all the lands they can get, to reimburse the
payment and satisfy the people, and make the measure popular.
I<hi rend="italic"> am also informed</hi>, it is (or more properly speaking) <hi rend="italic">will be </hi>
determined among other things that, <hi rend="italic">all </hi><placeName>grants </placeName>whatever, having
relation to that <placeName>country </placeName>(<hi rend="italic">and particularly land, grants</hi>) will be
strictly scrutinzed and if found informal, or not duly given, or the
conditions of the said grants not fully complied with,<hi rend="italic"> will not be
recognized as valid by this <persName>Govt</persName>.</hi>   Those of a fair legal character<pb n="314"/>
and whose conditions are fully complied with, will doubtless, on
principles of justice be confirmed. I loose no time in giving you this
information (in confidence) which I am satisfied comes from a
correct <persName>source</persName>. Having the best of opportunity of obtaining the
earliest information, and such as can be relied on, as to the views of
<persName>both Governments</persName> will give me pleasure to communicate it to you,
feeling confident, [it] can but prove of interest, and tend to guard
you against <persName>speculators</persName>. A <persName>special minister </persName>arrived here a few
weeks since from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, (one high in favor with its <persName>President</persName>) and
now on his way to <placeName>Washington</placeName>, if not full power to act, is authorized
to listen to such proposals as our Govt, may have to offer touching
the purchase of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and there appears on the part of the <persName>Mexican
Govt,</persName> a strong disposition to cultivate a friendly feeling with this
<persName>Govt</persName>., and at the same time no little jealousy towards the <persName>powers of
<placeName>Europe</placeName></persName>, and not without good cause from what recently came to
light respecting their views towards both <placeName>Columbia </placeName>and <placeName>Mexico</placeName>.
All of which will attribute much to aid the purchase of <placeName>Texas </placeName>on
more favorable terms, and which I have no doubt now occupies the
attention of this Govt, and under existing circumstances should not
be surprised if an early transfer took place. Letters from <placeName>Vera
Cruz </placeName>state that<persName> Mr. Poinsett</persName> and <persName>secretary </persName>had taken passage in the
packet ship Virginia to sail about the <date when="1829-12-15">15 Dec</date>. for this <placeName>port</placeName>. We are
without news from <persName>brother Henry </persName>since last I wrote, which left him
at <placeName>Matamoras</placeName>, to proceed on his second trip <placeName>up the river </placeName>in a few
days. With the hopes of soon being favored with a letter, I close
in haste, as the packet sails in a few moments</p>

<p><persName>Jno. P. Austin.</persName></p>

<p>P. S. The enclosed queries, (from the <placeName>daily advertiser</placeName> of <date when="1829-12-31">last
thursday</date>) proposed to his <persName>Highness Prince Paul William of
<placeName>Wiirtemberg</placeName></persName>, <hi rend="italic">are from a source whence his movements are well
known</hi>, and fully explain the motives of his <persName>Highness </persName>scientific
researches.</p>
<p><date when="1830-01-22">January 22d 1830</date>.</p>
<p>Dear Sir&#8212;</p>

<p>Referring to above duplicate of my last report leaves me now
but little to add further than a confirmation. <persName>Mr. Poinsett</persName> did
not arrive in the Virginia as was anticipated, but promised would
embark in the Falmouth sloop of war, which remained at <placeName>Sacrificios</placeName>
on the<date when="1829-12-22"> 22nd of December</date>. Among the <persName>Virginia passengers </persName>were
<persName>Col. José Maria Tornell, Minister plenipotentiary from Mexico to
this Govt,</persName> and<persName> Col. Mejia secretary of legation </persName>with their <persName>families</persName>.
They leave <date when="1830-01-23">tomorrow </date>for <placeName>Washington</placeName>, where they will meet <persName>col.
-----</persName>, referred to in the above, who arrived there some weeks since,
as a <persName>special agent from Mexico</persName> and whom <persName>Col. Tornell</persName> says enjoys<pb n="315"/>
the unlimited confidence of <persName>Guerrero</persName>. Should I get anything of
importance, [I shall] loose no time in communicating it.<persName> Brother
Henry</persName> writes from <placeName>Matamoras </placeName><date when="1829-12-02">Dec. 2d </date>that, that <placeName>country </placeName>
heretofore so healthy, the last of <date n="09-xx-1829">September </date>a flood came in, which would
have enabled him to go quite to <placeName>Sante Fe</placeName>, but he was unable to
avail himself of it, for it brought with it a pestilence which 
prostrated every body and that he was the only one of the <persName>boat's crew</persName>
who escaped it. He had made a second trip to <placeName>Camargo </placeName>and on
his return trip had but <persName>two well men</persName> and when he wrote was
thus unable to move the boat as his <persName>engineer </persName>and men were too
feeble to do anything. I hope you have communicated with him
as it might prove mutually advantageous.</p>

<p><persName>John P. Austin. </persName>   [Rubric]</p>
<p><persName>Col. Stephen F. Austin, </persName><placeName>San Felippe de Austin, Texas.</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
