<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1785">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Hugh B Johnston to Stephen F Austin, 11-09-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Hugh B Johnston</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-16">08-16-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Trinity, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 283-284
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-11-09">11-09-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Danger of Indian war. Much apprehension aroused by migration of Indians from the United States. Hopes Austin can stop the movement.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Trinity</placeName></p>
<p><persName>Col Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dear Sir We have had Some apprehensions of an <persName>Indian </persName>war
hear, we heard a great talk respecting it from Some particular <persName>Indians</persName>
of the <persName>Coushatties </persName>in consequence of Which I payed them a visit in
company with <persName>Capt. Orr</persName> we held a taulk with all the principle
<persName>chiefs </persName>they denyed ever hearing any thing like a casperacy against
the <placeName>american Collany,</placeName> also appeared to be very friendly, and above
all things, to be at piece and friendly with the <persName>Americans </persName>this I 
believe to be the truth with the great majority of the <persName>coushatties </persName>and
<persName>Allibamas </persName>but I am fully of the oppinion that there has been a 
considerable talk of War among the differant <persName>tribes </persName><placeName>north of this</placeName> and
that the <persName>Shawenees </persName>which was hostile to the <persName>Americans </persName>in the last
war was the principle adgitators, the <persName>indians </persName>States that all of the
auld<persName> creek Indians</persName> is on <placeName>this side of the Mississippi</placeName> and is comeing
to settle among them I have had it from good authority and I 
expect that you are not unapprised of the fact, that they or apart of
them are now on the confines of this <placeName>country</placeName>, and are makeing 
application for <placeName>land in the Texas</placeName>, now Sir if these <persName>Indians </persName>which are
said to be from five to eight thousand Strong with all the balance of
those detached warlike <persName>tribes </persName>are allowed to settle in this <placeName>country</placeName>, I<pb n="284"/>
think it not hard to predict the consequence. I think from the 
conversation which we had on the subject a year or two ago, your views
correspond with that of my own, Now Sir I think that our hope is
in you to stop this great evil, by a true reppresentation to the 
goverment of the inevable ill consequence which must result some day or
other from suffering those <persName>hell hounds</persName> to settle among us, if they
do not proclaim immedeate war or commence hostilities they will be
for ever stealling and robing whear ever they have the chance if once
they feel them selves strong please to right to me by the first 
oppertunity and communicate you Ideas to me on the Subject ard what
you think can be done, I hear that the <persName>commishernor </persName>has gone on
to <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>perhaps he could put a stop to those fatile 
invitations by some of our great <persName>men </persName>to those <persName>Devils </persName>visiting <placeName>Texas </placeName>but
you know best,   I remain yours with Esteem</p>

<p><persName>Hugh B Johnston</persName></p>
<p><date when="1829-11-09">Nov the 9th 1829</date></p>

<p>Los 8000 <persName>indios </persName>de qe. hable el <persName>capitán Johnston</persName> son del<persName> tribu
Moscogue</persName> ó <persName>creek </persName>y ya han emigrado al <placeName>territorio de Arkansas</placeName> 
<persName>Johnston </persName>es <persName>capitán de la milicia sobre el <placeName>rio Trinidad</placeName></persName></p>

<p><persName>Austin    </persName>[Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
