<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1891">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Edwin L Pettit to Stephen F Austin, 04-05-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Edwin L Pettit</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-19">08-19-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 357
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-04-05">04-05-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-19" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reporting revolutionary conditions in Mexico. A bill has been framed by the Government to stop immigration to Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>New Orleans April 5th 1830</p>
<p>Dear Sir;</p>

<p>By the Schr. Pocahontas which leaves this <date when="1830-04-06">tomorrow </date>for <placeName>Texas</placeName>
I take liberty of writing you, and sending the <placeName>N. A. Review</placeName> 
containing an interesting peice on <placeName>Texas</placeName>.&#8212; I have succeed in recovering
the amt of the insurance on my Vessel and am anxiously waiting the
next Vessel from <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> (which is hourly expected) to determine
whether to proceed to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, you are doubtless in possession of what
is transacting in that <placeName>city</placeName>, and I presume that <persName>Genl. Teran</persName>, as well
as the <persName>troops </persName>and the national Sch. of War, Mosque will have arrived&#8212;
by the last accounts from <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, It appears that a <persName>committee
of Congress</persName> have reported a project of a Law (which If passed
will violate the Public Faith in the instance of your contracts with
the Government) to stop the Emigration of <persName>Americans </persName>to <placeName>Texas</placeName>,
The Brig of war Bravo was also preparing for sea to arrive <placeName>between
Tampico and Galveston Bay,</placeName> Between us in confidence from all
I have been able to learn the <placeName>country </placeName>is very unsettled, the <placeName>States<pb n="358"/>
of Yucatan and Tabasco</placeName>, have determined to split off unless a central
Government is Established, and it is my opinion that <persName>Genl. Santa
Ana</persName> is only waiting until the <persName>present administration</persName> becomes a little
unpopular to raise a Grito, and place himself at the <persName>Head of the
Republic</persName> as <persName>Dictator</persName>,&#8212; The <persName>present administration</persName> are taking
some high handed Measures, at <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, the <persName>Commandant of the
Marine</persName> has been taken from his <placeName>station </placeName>and dismissed the service
without even the form of a tryal, Commissions which were issued
by <persName>Guerrero </persName>to <persName>privateers </persName>have also been taken from them when
just ready to sail (after incuring all the Expense of fitting out) &#8212;
Poor <persName>Thompson </persName>who went from this place to <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> recently
has been arrested there and confined to the <placeName>Congresso 74</placeName>. and I
am free to confess that I entertain some fears myself if I return
that I my take up my summer quarters in the <placeName>Castle of San Juan
de Ulloa</placeName> for overstaying my leave, however the next accounts will
determine me, if I believe there is a probability of being arrested I
shall be sent down by the <persName>consul </persName>as <persName>bearer of Dispatches</persName> for the
<persName>Government </persName>which will protect me until my arrival in the <placeName>City
of Mexico</placeName> where I can resign&#8212;</p>

<p>Meanwhile old foolish <persName>Ferdinand </persName>is preparing another expidition
to reconquer <persName>Mexico</persName>&#8212;8000, <persName>men </persName>have saild from <placeName>Cadiz</placeName>, to be 
followed by 7000 more and also a new <persName>Governor for the <placeName>Island of
Cuba</placeName></persName>, but it is doubtful, if they gett farther than <placeName>Cuba </placeName>for the
present (unless they turn their attention to <placeName>Hayti </placeName>the <persName>President </persName>of
which has Declared wars against <placeName>Spain</placeName>,) as I am told by some
<persName>gentlemen </persName>recently from <placeName>Havana </placeName>that the <persName>Troops </persName>there manifest
such a reluctance to embark for <placeName>Mexico </placeName>from the severe loss the last
expedition sustained, that nothing short of a revolution will be the
consequence if they are driven to the last extreemity&#8212; amongst
other projects before <persName>Congress </persName>is one to repeal the law of <date n="xx-xx-189">last
year</date> prohibiting the admission of foreign Cotton goods, so you
may perceive that no dependence can be placed on the acts of the
Goverment, the fact is Such a man as<persName> Santa Ana</persName> is much wanted
at the Head of affairs, one who has energy enough to adhere to 
measures when once adopted, and who will by the bayonet if it be 
necessary, quiet the <placeName>country </placeName>and end this grito work,&#8212;</p>

<p>I fear the law alluded to to stop emigration will pass&#8212; I do not
presume to advise you what course to persue it would be 
presumption in me to do so, but If I might be allowed to express an opinion
it is that whatever may be done by the<persName> Present Party</persName>, no difficulty
will exist when they go out to get things put on their proper and
former footing by their <persName>successors </persName>who I think inevitably must be<pb n="359"/>
<persName>Santa Ana</persName> or <persName>Guerrero</persName>, therefore it occurs that it would be most
prudent to keep quiet for the present at least and watch how 
affairs are going to turn&#8212; If I go to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>you may rest assured
if I have any influence there it shall be exerted for you, and I shall
certainly see <persName>Genl. Santa Ana</persName> before I leave that part of the 
<placeName>country</placeName>.&#8212; and whatever course you may eventually adopt you can 
depend on one person at least to act or suffer with you&#8212;</p>

<p><date when="1830-04-07">April 7th</date> the Schr. Nimble so anxiously expected arrived <date when="1830-04-06">yesterday</date>
and the accounts by her are very discouraging It is said that 
<persName>Guerrero </persName>has taken the field, and that <persName>Genl. Montes de Oca </persName>and others
have formed here not that this part is discouraging I alluded to
such parts as interested myself. We have <placeName>Mexican papers</placeName> to the <date when="1830-03-19">19th
Ult</date>. I see by the proceeding of <persName>Congress </persName>that the <persName>Eastern 
department</persName> has been divided and a <persName>Commandancia General</persName> for the <placeName>State of
Coahuila and Texas</placeName> will be Established at <placeName>San Antonio de Bejar.
</placeName>That <persName>Troops </persName>are ordered from <placeName>different sections of the country</placeName>&#8212;
to <placeName>Texas </placeName>quite from <placeName>Oajaca</placeName>, I am inclined to think if <persName>Guerrero </persName>assumed a prominent stand the <persName>troops </persName>or at least those the present
party can rely on will be detained and I am not sure that the <placeName>Texas</placeName>
story is [not] used as pretext for removing such part from the 
<placeName>Capital </placeName>and <placeName>neighbourhood </placeName>as have not the confidence of the present
gang&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>Bravo Brig of War </persName>was still at <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>&#8212; <persName>Thompson</persName>
sends me word not to come there at present&#8212;as I am entered as A
<persName>deserter </persName>for overstaying my leave he is still arrested and is very
like to continue so for some time&#8212; I think I shall go down and take
the worst of it If I am quartered in the <placeName>Castle </placeName>this ensuing <date n="Summer - 1830">summer</date>
I shall have one consolation at least, that I am out of the reach of the
Yellow fever meanwhile by the next vessel that leave this for <placeName>Texas</placeName>
You will be informed if I go and as I do not on any account mean to
abandon my intentions relative to the <placeName>land </placeName>I applyed for I beg you if
the grant has been received from the <persName>Governor </persName>to retain for me such
as you may believe to be the best that can be located, and select for
me as you may believe to be most desirable and I assure you I shall
be satisfyed&#8212; If you deem my correspondence of any value I assure
you I shall be extreemly happy to hear from you, and all letters 
addressed to <persName>Mr. Breedlove</persName> will be forwarded to me whether I am to
the <placeName>north </placeName>or <placeName>South</placeName>&#8212;and I will endeavour to be punctual&#8212;you will
see that I have written this without much care or conections so I beg
your indulgence of its numerous imperfections,&#8212;</p>
<p><persName>Edward L. Pettit</persName>    [Rubric]</p>
<p>To <persName>Col Stephen F Austin</persName>   <placeName>Texas</placeName>
</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
