<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1312">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>J. E. B. Austin to Stephen F. Austin, 10-31-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>J. E. B. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-15">07-15-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin(
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Carlos, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1482-1484
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-10-31">10-31-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Horse trading in Mexico. Political gossip.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Sn Carlos</placeName> <date when="1826-10-31">Octr 31st 1826</date>.</p>
<p>My Dr <persName>Brother</persName>.</p>

<p>I arrived at this <placeName>place </placeName>on the <date when="1826-10-19">19th inst</date>. I found <persName>Dn Luciano</persName> 
absent,&#8212;but I immediately proceeded to his <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Rancho de la Luz</placeName></hi>. (<placeName>4 Leagues from this</placeName>) where he was. The <hi rend="italic">old <persName>Ranchero</persName></hi> was much
surprised, but overjoyed to see me:&#8212;After the usual salutations,
inquiries after friends, Acquaintances, etc had passed, I made known
the Object of my visit; he replied, that but one obstacle presented
itself to prevent my taking in 12. <hi rend="italic">Manadas</hi>:, or 300 head, (which
is the numr <hi rend="italic">he himself</hi> proposed)&#8212;That obstacle was the excessive
drouth, that prevailed throughout this section of the <placeName>State</placeName>, and
which, had caused his herds to ramble to a great distance. After
remaining at the <placeName>Rancho </placeName>three days, undetermined what to do, I
found myself compelled to return to this <placeName>place</placeName>; as the <placeName><hi rend="italic">water pool</hi>at the Rancho</placeName>, was entirely exausted, and the animals were 
beginning to perish.&#8212;In this perplexity, I concluded to remain untill
the arrival of the mail, and then start for the <placeName>Brazos</placeName>, with a view
of returning in the <date n="SPring-1827">Spring</date>, or <date n="Summer-1827">summer</date>, as I had become fully convinced that an attempt to have taken in any number of horses at
this time would have been attended with considerable loss&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Dn Luciano</persName> informed me that it had not rained here for one
year&#8212;While I remained in this state of suspence, the weather 
suddenly changed, and in the short space of <hi rend="italic">three hours</hi> fell the most
tremendous torrent of rain I ever witnessed; The water rushed from
the <placeName>Mountains </placeName>with such impetuosity, that every thing was swept<pb n="1483"/>
in the values beneath; in an instant, all the Empty <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Tanques </placeName></hi>were
filled, and there is a supply of water for nearly a year to come&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Dn Luciano</persName> soon informed me that he intended to collect his
scattered flocks immediately, and I could take the number he had
offered;. I shall wait untill he herds them, and take a part of the
amt he has offered say 150 or 200 head.</p>

<p>I hope to start from here, by the <date when="1826-11-12">12 of Novr</date> and be with you by
the<date when="1826-12-15"> 15th</date> or <date when="1826-12-20">20th of Decembr</date></p>

<p>The mule project I am compelled to abandon, owing to their
scarcity and dearness, $50 to $70 pr. pair is what is currently given
by the <persName>Mexicans</persName>&#8212;I shall not take time to go and see <persName>Dn Felipe</persName>,
altho I am confident I could procure both mules and horses from
him.</p>

<p>I am tired of this <placeName>Barren Mountainous Country</placeName>, and wish to get
back once more to <placeName>Sn Felipe </placeName>after seeing as much of the <placeName>Country</placeName>
as I have I shall know how to justly appreciate the fertility of our
<placeName>Texas </placeName>soil&#8212;</p>

<p>I wish you to have the <placeName>lot </placeName>refenced very strong or one of the
<placeName>back lots</placeName> it will be necessary to keep the Manadas at <placeName>home</placeName>, untill we determine where to put them, and prepare <placeName>pens </placeName>for their 
reception etc; I shall take in a sufficient number of <persName>Vaceros </persName>to attend to
them: and I flatter myself that in a short time we shall have a snug
little <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Rancho</placeName></hi>&#8212;then you or myself (or <persName>both of us</persName>) must get a <hi rend="italic"><persName>wife</persName></hi>
and forget the cares and perplexities of the world, in the pleasures
to be found in a <hi rend="italic">Pastoral life.</hi> During my short stay among these
<placeName>mountains</placeName>, I have ceased to wonder why so many <persName>persons </persName>labour
under (what is called) the <hi rend="italic">Blue Devils</hi>, Horrors Hippo, or 
whatever else you may please to call those fits of Apathy we find attending
most persons at certain times, in a greater or less degree&#8212;and which
is a complaint you are not altogether clear of&#8212;but I sincerely hope
that since I have left <placeName>home </placeName>you have not been visited by a single
symtom; for <hi rend="italic">God </hi>knows I have been tormented enough for us
both.</p>

<p>I have lived the Solitary, ever since I have been here. <persName>Dn Luciano
</persName>is a perfect hermit&#8212;since his return from <placeName>Bexar </placeName>he has resided at
his <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Rancho de la Luz</placeName></hi>: rarely has communication with any one,
except his <persName>Vaceros </persName>Comes to <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Town </placeName>to Hug</hi> his <persName>Frigoña</persName>, once a month.
Spends good part of his time Sleeping and eating.</p>

<p>he says he has procured his discharge from the <persName>Army </persName>and 
henceforward he intends to live (<hi rend="italic">Una </hi>Vida sosegada) I tell him we wish
to live a <hi rend="italic"><persName>Ranchero's </persName>life</hi> but attended with a <hi rend="italic">little </hi>more variety.</p>

<p>I wrote you from <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>on every point of importance. I hope
ere this the <persName>slave </persName>question is decided; the <persName>Baron </persName>promised to write
to you immediately after the question was decided.<pb n="1484"/></p>

<p>You have many warm <persName>friends </persName>in <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>&#8212;Among them you may
Count on <persName>Dn Ygnacio Arizpe the Govr of the State</persName>, also <persName>Gonzales</persName>,
it will be fortunate for the <placeName>Colony </placeName>If he can be reelected and what
little <hi rend="italic">aid </hi>the <placeName>colony </placeName>can render him should be done with pleasure-
As he entertains the sincerest friendship towards <hi rend="italic">your <placeName>Colony </placeName></hi>in
particular; also any thing that you wish to communicate to <persName>Govr </persName>you
can do it with Confidence through <persName>Padilla </persName>you have not a warmer
<persName>friend </persName>in the <placeName>Country </placeName>than he I have nothing more to say at 
present&#8212;I will try and eat my <hi rend="italic">Christmas dinner</hi> with you&#8212;should you
happen to <hi rend="italic">visit </hi>up <hi rend="italic">the river</hi> present <hi rend="italic">my respects to the <persName>female part of the family</persName></hi></p>

<p>Remember me to <persName>Williams</persName>&#8212;and <persName>John</persName>&#8212;I hope the <placeName>Gin </placeName>is in 
operation by this time&#8212;Also present <hi rend="italic">my respect to <persName>Eliza</persName></hi> and <persName>Mrs. <hi rend="italic">Pickit</hi></persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Jas E B Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>P S. I wish the most particular care taken of my horse. I have
seen but two or three&#8212;that I would rather have since I left <placeName>home</placeName></p>

<p>P. S. <date when="1826-11-01">Nov. 1st.</date> I waited untill the arrival of the mail before I
closed my letter confident of receiving a letter from you&#8212;but judge
of my surprise when the mail arrived not to find a letter from you&#8212;
I have received but one short letter from you since I left <placeName>Bexar</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I have lost the two horses (both pacers) that I received from
<placeName>Paras</placeName>&#8212;I suppose they have willingly returned to their <placeName>pasturage</placeName>.
those togather with a mule lost in <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>that cost me $30&#8212;and some
other trifles to the am1 of 15 or $20 entitle me to a free pass through
the <placeName>country </placeName>as every <persName>Americano </persName>has to pay the <persName>rougues </persName>an 
initionati[n]g fee&#8212;I hope since the rain I shall have better luck.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
