<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1992">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 07-14-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-23">08-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Price
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Morgan
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 451-453
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-07-14">07-14-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Hostility to Americans in Mexico subsiding. Orders various books. Is to be elected to the legislature.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Dr <persName>Brother</persName>,</p>

<p>In addition to the memorandum I sent you in my letter of the
other day, I wish you to get me copies of the constitutions of<pb n="452"/>
<placeName>Columbia</placeName>, of<placeName> Buenos Ayres</placeName> of <placeName>Chili</placeName>, of <placeName>Peru</placeName>, and what is called
the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Bolivia</placeName>n Code</hi> or constitution given by <persName>Bolivar </persName>to <placeName>upper Peru</placeName>
or <placeName>Bolivia</placeName>, they are all in Spanish&#8212; I think you can get them
at some of the bookstores, or perhaps from some individual who
has been to those <placeName>countries</placeName>.</p>

<p>In place of the scarlet jacket which I wrote for get me a blue
clothe vest to suit the surtout and not a scarlet one &#8212; bring me a
good raisor or two.</p>

<p>you must be particular if you come by <placeName>land </placeName>to have contracts
with the <persName>servants </persName>or the <persName>officer </persName>at <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>will interpose some
difficulties.   If you come by water contracts are also necessary.</p>

<p>I hope you may get here by <date when="1830-12-01">1 of Decr</date> for it is possible I may
have to leave here in the <date n="Winter - 1830">winter</date>, the mail of today brings me letters
stating that I shall be voted for at <placeName>Bexar </placeName>to represent <placeName>Texas </placeName>in the
<persName>state Legislature, </persName>if so I shall be elected of course, for in this <placeName>colony</placeName>
I shall not loose a vote, and but few if any at <placeName>Goliad </placeName>and 
<placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>they have started me at <placeName>Bexar </placeName>the whole thing originated
with the <persName>native Mexican population</persName> of that place and <placeName>Goliad</placeName>&#8212;
I had no idea, and no wish for such a thing I cordially detest
politics in any <placeName>country</placeName>, and our affairs in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>have been so 
entangled by some one (and it is suspected by an <persName>american</persName>) that I
dread entering within their reach&#8212; True it is that the prejudices
against <persName>north Americans</persName> are subsiding in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, but still, there
are some remnants of bitter feeling left among the uninformed who
believed that <persName>Poinsett </persName>was the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> Government, and that all 
<persName>north Americans </persName>were connected with his intreagues&#8212; The situation
will be an unpleasant, and perhaps a critical one, but an honest
and prudent course has always carried me safely through many
difficulties in this <placeName>country </placeName>and I have faith that it will continue
to do so.</p>

<p>The election is next <date n="08-xx-1830">month</date>&#8212; The <persName>Legislature </persName>meets <date when="1831-01-01">1 of 
January</date>&#8212; there are two <persName>members </persName>only from all <placeName>Texas</placeName>: tho after this
year we shall have several more owing to an increase of population,
and the ratio is to be new moddled next session.</p>

<p>The result of the election will be published after it is over&#8212; 
contrary to the custom in the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> but little is said about elections and
there is but little electionering in this <placeName>country</placeName>, a <placeName>candidate </placeName>who says
any thing himself, to influence votes can be deprived of his seat&#8212;
this has prevented open and public electionering&#8212;</p>

<p>"Remember me to <persName>Mr Learning</persName> and see about the <placeName>Maps</placeName>&#8212; I 
perceive they are out, I want a number on rolers&#8212; they are for 
presents to <persName>Mexicans </persName>and of course I wish for the best&#8212; <persName>Tanner </persName>will
realise more by that <placeName>map</placeName>, than by any thing he ever published in his
life and I rejoice that he will do so&#8212;   tho I need some cash to pro-<pb n="453"/>
cure a few choice Spanish, and English books of a literary and 
historical character to try and improve my mind which needs it much,
for during the ten years I have spent in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, but few books have
come within my reach&#8212;</p>

<p>farewell may heaven bless you and land you and <persName>sister </persName>and the
<persName>young one[s]</persName> safe in the "<placeName> wilds of Texas</placeName> "</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p><date when="1830-07-14">July 14 1830</date></p>

<p>I am greatly in need of <hi rend="italic"><persName>Waits </persName>State papers</hi>, published in <placeName>Boston</placeName>.
I had them in <placeName>Missouri </placeName>but lost them in <placeName>Arkansas</placeName>&#8212; A number 
subscribed for them at the <placeName>Mines </placeName>and I think a set might be got there
cheap.&#8212; In my other letter I wrote to you to get me a blue undress
Military surtout with a standing collar trimmed with black silk
cord&#8212;yellow bridle bits yellow spurs and yellow stirrups, these I
need very much and a pair of boots</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr James F. Perry</persName> Care of <persName>Price and Morgan</persName>
<placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
