<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1227">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>H. H. League, James C. Ludlow, Elias Wightman, Richard Matson. to Stephen F. Austin, 08-02-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>H. H. League, James C. Ludlow, Elias Wightman, Richard Matson.</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-01">07-01-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1395-1397
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Petition</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-08-02">08-02-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-01" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">HPetition for permit to establish a town on the Colorado River and Matagorda Bay.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>To the <persName>Honorable Stephen F. Austin Empresario, Military and 
Political chief of Colony No 1</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>The Petition of the undersigned <persName>Citizens </persName>of said <placeName>Colony </placeName>most 
respectfully beg leave to set forth and show</p>

<p>That Whereas: We the said <persName>Petitioners</persName>, having viewed the 
<placeName>Matagorda Bay</placeName> as the most important and safe <placeName>Harbor </placeName>on the <placeName>Coast of
the Department of Texas</placeName>, and in fact the only one which can, and
will be recognized by <persName>men of Enterprise</persName> both of adopted <persName>Mexicans</persName>,
<persName>natives</persName>, and those of <placeName>foreign nations</placeName> as the general grand, mart and
emporium of commerce to which all business must, and will center
and a point to which, all the produce of the <placeName>Country </placeName>must find its
way to the <placeName>market of the contry</placeName>, as well [as] that of <placeName>foreign markets</placeName>
by means of the ready admission of vessels of every descriptions
which no other <placeName>port </placeName>on the <placeName>coast </placeName>is susceptable of&#8212; And further
taking into consideration the ease and facility of a ready 
communication between that point and the eastern&#8212;by means of an inland
navigation&#8212;almost furnished by nature from said <placeName>bay of Matagorda
</placeName>to that of <placeName>Galveston</placeName>&#8212;These with many other reasons, have directed
our attention to said <placeName>Bay </placeName>and well knowing the far superior <placeName>country</placeName>
admiting the most dense <placeName>settlements </placeName>and most extensive bodies of
productive <placeName>lands</placeName>, and the partiality of <persName>Emigrants </persName>to settle on the
<placeName>Brazos</placeName>, <placeName>Bernard</placeName>, <placeName>Bay Prairie</placeName>, and <placeName>Colorado </placeName>and the vanity of any
calculation&#8212;that the <placeName>western colonies</placeName> could ever rival or come in
competition with this most superior fertile and rich section of the
<placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;Induced us to hope that there might be a possibility of
finding a site for the establishment of a <placeName>town </placeName>at or <placeName>near the mouth
of the Rio Colorado </placeName>though every one informing us of its 
impracticability for want of sufficient depth of water over the Bar etc.&#8212;</p>

<p>But if this should be the case (which we hope can be overcome by
assiduity and perseverence) still we have to suggest to your Honor,<date n="1396"></date>
that we do not hesitate to think according to our best judgment and
the means we had in our power to ascertain facts necessary to 
predicate any just ideas&#8212;that there may still be a <placeName>town </placeName>erected on the
<placeName>east side of the Rio Colorado</placeName> some <placeName>two or three miles from the
mouth, and on the margin of the Bay</placeName>&#8212;We discovered to our 
admiration and surprise&#8212;one of the most beautiful situations for the
building a large commodious and tasty commercial <placeName>town </placeName>that our
utmost imagination could conceive. A large <placeName>amphitheatre</placeName>, a 
<placeName>semicircular Bluff</placeName> of about 6 or 8 feet above high-water mark of very
perminant dry soil, and ascending back to an extensive and beautiful
<placeName>prairie</placeName>, about 2000 bars in diameter, making a very regular 
curveresting one end on the <placeName>Rio Colorado</placeName> and the other on the <placeName>bay </placeName>the
margin of both being remarkably straight and regular&#8212;in the front
of this <placeName>amphitheatre </placeName>is a low rich <placeName>marsh prairie</placeName> though no stagnant
waters the beauty of the whole and particularly the <placeName>Colorado </placeName>is past
discription.</p>

<p>We are very confident that a mere trifle will open a <placeName>canal </placeName>from
the <placeName>Colorado </placeName>through this low land to the <placeName>Bay</placeName>, and a <placeName>bayou </placeName>already
flows up to meet it, which must have a full communication with the
<placeName>Bay </placeName>as it had the appearance of being agitated by the swells from the
<placeName>Bay</placeName>, though we were not prepared to examine for the want of a
water-craft&#8212;and here it is certain that vessels can lie safely at anchor
and be admitted into the <placeName>Colorado </placeName>by means of this <placeName>Bayou</placeName>, and
<placeName>Canal </placeName>should there be insupurable obsticles to ascending the <placeName>river</placeName>,
which we trust is not the case. We will now only refer you to a
diagram accompanying this petition, as nigh the true Situation as we
are able to delineate without an actual survey.</p>

<p>And therefore in consideration of the above.</p>

<p>We your <persName>Petitioners </persName>beg leave to ask the favor of a <placeName>grant </placeName>of land
embracing said site with the privileges of laying out said 
contemplated <placeName>town</placeName>, Binding ourselves immediately to erect and 
maintain a <placeName>post of defence</placeName> against the hostile <persName>Indians</persName>, and commence the
building of <placeName>warehouses</placeName>, and other necessary <placeName>Houses </placeName>for the 
reception of <persName>Imigrants </persName>as expected (in case of a grant) from <persName>Missouri</persName>
and <persName>Tennessee </persName>as well as elsewhere&#8212;Subjecting ourselves to all the
rules and regulations of Government to taxes imports, tonage and
duties of whatever descriptions, name or nature, conforming 
ourselves to the laws of the Government regulating <placeName>ports </placeName>and <placeName>harbors</placeName>.</p>

<p>And that we may avail ourselves of the advantage of your 
knowledge and experience in the laws and customs of the <persName>Mexican 
Government</persName>, as well as your patronage, and advice, and direction, we would
solicit, your participation, equally with your <persName>Petitioners </persName>in all its
profits and emoliments to which entent we bind ourselves to convey
an equal right whenever we shall be ennabled so to do.   We would<pb n="1397"/>
further Submit to your consideration and inspection a plan of the
<placeName>Town </placeName>to [be] laid out------</p>

<p>If the granting for the express purpose of a <placeName>Town</placeName>, is not 
compatible with the nature of your <persName>authorities </persName>of which we are 
uninformed, We your <persName>Petitioners </persName>in such case would beg leave that a
<placeName>League</placeName>, as above defined may be granted for the purpose of 
stockraising&#8212;</p>

<p>And further if a grant to an <persName>individual </persName>would be more consistent
than to the <persName>Company</persName>&#8212;-We would nominate <persName>Conl- Matison</persName>, as the
<persName>grantee </persName>who is bound to make conveyances to the <persName>company</persName>. Our
intentions are to reduce it to five shares, for although yours inclusive
would make seven, two we consider as merely nominal which <persName>Mr.
Ludlow</persName> engages to extingush by contract, and substitute his own in
lieu thereof&#8212;</p>

<p>Considering the vast importance to your <placeName>Colony </placeName>and in particular
the early, and immediate attention which we would bestow, and 
gaining the advantage of the first <placeName>Port</placeName> where provisions and 
accommodation can be afforded and a safe protection guaranteed to vessels, which
must give it every advantage over every other in said <placeName>Bay</placeName>&#8212;not
naming our opinion of the practicability of making an <placeName>artificial pass</placeName>,
<placeName>through the peninsula</placeName> <placeName>between the Bay and main Gulph</placeName> together
with the many other advantages which we will in a personal 
interview explain. We do not hesitate to think and hope that your
Honor will deem [it] of the highest interest to the Government in
General but the most important in particular to this Section and
[your] own <placeName>Colony</placeName>, more especially&#8212;</p>

<p>That your honor may so consider and grant the prayers of your
<persName>Petitioners </persName>and Undersigned is our most earnest Solicitations, and
as in duty bound will ever pray etc.&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>H. H. League</persName></p>
<p><persName>James C. Ludlow</persName></p>
<p><persName>Elias Wightman</persName></p>
<p><persName>Richard Matson</persName></p>

<p><placeName>Sn Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1826-08-02">2d August 1826</date></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
