<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1866">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Amos Edwards to Stephen F Austin, 03-11-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Amos Edwards</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-19">08-19-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Monroe Edwards
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Davis Point, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 338
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-03-11">03-11-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-19" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Application for land. Colonial conditions.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Davis Point</placeName> <date when="1830-03-11">March 11th 1830</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>When I came on found my <persName>hands </persName>here trying to make some 
improvements and I concluded to settle here altho there is not a tree
of timber suitable for building or fencing <placeName>nearer than 5 miles of
this point</placeName> nor any running fresh water<placeName> within 4 miles</placeName>, the place
is well calculated for keeping stock which is one of my principle
objects in settling here and I intend planting and raising as much
corn potatoes and other necessary articles as I can with my force
but it will be attended with a great deal of labour and expense
extra of a situation that is convenient to Timber and water. I
hope therefore that you will let me have a piece of <placeName>Timbered land</placeName>
that lies most convenient to this place which is on, what is called
here <placeName>Dixon's Bayou, about six miles off </placeName>which would enable me to
improve this place so as to make it beneficial to the public and
myself and particularly as this league will not embrace timber
enough to make one fourth of the <placeName>buildings </placeName>and fencing necessary
to answer my purpose, and that little is <placeName>5 miles to six from this
point</placeName>. It was customary formerly for <persName>sellers </persName>to get a certain
quantity of <placeName>arrable land </placeName>and a larger quantity for stock and other
purposes and if it is in your power to grant the like quantity to
any <persName>individual </persName>I hope you will extend your goodness to me, as I
have brought a large <persName>family </persName>to this <placeName>country </placeName>some of whom have
caused other useful <persName>emigrants </persName>to come marry and settle in the
<placeName>country </placeName>and I have yet several young <persName>children </persName>to provide for and
shall myself try to be as usefull to the Government as my 
circumstances and abilities will permit. I regret that you did not come
to <placeName>this part of the country</placeName> as you intended when I saw you that
you might see the land here and country generally, and I also
regret that it is not in my power at this time to leave here to go
and see you myself for I am yet living in a <placeName>tent </placeName>and must stay
to try to have a <placeName>shelter </placeName>made for my <persName>family </persName>and put in a crop to
make us some bread etc.    But I send my <persName>son </persName>to transact my busi-<pb n="339"/>
ness for me with full power to do all that is necessary for me relative
to lands in this <placeName>colony </placeName>which I hope will be sufficient without my
personal attendance at <placeName>St. Fillippe</placeName>. he can explain to you the
situation of this place better than I can by letter at present, as he
has travelled all over the land.</p>

<p><persName>Amos Edwards</persName></p>

<p>P. S. I am requested by my <persName>son in Law Mr. Ritson Morris</persName> to
name to you that he wishes to get a <placeName>league of land adjoining the
one I am on</placeName>, lying on <placeName>Clear Creek</placeName> as he intended moving his <persName>family</persName>
on it as soon as he can go home and settle up his business there
which will be <date n="Fall - 1830">next fall</date> early, it is <placeName>the tract on which <persName>Anson
Taylor</persName> lived </placeName>and I bought his improvements and have a respectable
<persName>family </persName>now living on it and there will be <placeName>twenty five acres in 
cultivation this season</placeName>, it is very desirable to have my <persName>children </persName>near
me and if they can get the land they will all settle within your
<placeName>colony</placeName>. I wish also to get <placeName>a league near me</placeName> for <persName>Doctor Heard</persName> who
will come here before long and in the mean time I will have a
respectable <persName>family </persName>on it improving the land. My <persName>son </persName>will designate
the <placeName>land </placeName>for the <persName>Doctor </persName>provided you consent to let him have it.</p>

<p><persName>A. E.</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Col. Stephen F. Austin</persName>, <placeName>Austin</placeName>.   <persName>Monroe Edwards.</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
