<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1294">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Humphry Fullerton, General, 10-02-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-12">07-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Humphry Fullerton
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         General
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1469-1470
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-10-02">10-02-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Immigration. Swiss colonists. Slavery. Constitution.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1826-10-02">October 2 1826</date></p>
<p><persName>Genl Humphry Fullerton</persName>,</p>

<p>Dr Sir, I was truly gratified to learn by your letter to <persName>Major
Burnett</persName> that you had arrived at home safe in <date n="07-xx-1826">July</date>, that your health
was improving and that you had received applications from near
one hundred <persName>families </persName>who wished to emigrate to this <placeName>colony</placeName>, and
more were daily applying&#8212;</p>

<p>The forty <persName>swiss families</persName> you speak of from <placeName>Vevey </placeName>will be 
valuable acquisition as <persName>cultivators of the vine</persName>, a species of culture which
I have no doubt will succeed well and yield great profits in 
proportion to the Capital and labor employed. The climate and soil are
said, by those who profess themselves <persName>judges</persName>, to be well adapted
to the cultivation of the vine, we cannot decide from actual 
experiments for none of consequence have been made&#8212;wild grapes are
very abundant in sandy soils throughout the <placeName>country </placeName>and of a good
quality, well flavored.&#8212;</p>

<p>It is important that you should send on as soon as possible a
list of the <persName>families </persName>who are coming on stating the name of the <persName>head
of the family</persName>, age, where born, <placeName>last place of residence</placeName>, wheither
<persName>married </persName>or <persName>single</persName>, number of male and female <persName>children</persName>, ages, number
of <persName>hirelings</persName>&#8212;occupation&#8212;age of <persName>wife</persName>&#8212;This list is necessary in
order to enter them in the records of the <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>In regard to the fees I am as yet unable to inform you&#8212;The 
<persName>commissioner </persName>has not come on and I have received no final instructions
on the subject&#8212;I am certain however that they will not exceed
about four cents pr. acre including surveying fees and all charges
and six years will be allowed to pay a part of them. Such 
arrangements can no doubt be made with the <persName>surveyors </persName>in regard to their
fees as will make the payment easy</p>

<p>The <persName>Government </persName>move very slow&#8212;and sometimes produces 
embarrassments and frequently disappointments and I wish the <persName>families</persName>
who are coming on to understand that I am not in any manner to be
accountable or censurable for embarrassments occationed by the 
delays of the <persName>Government</persName>&#8212;So far as depends on me their business
shall be promptly and faithfully attended to. we as yet have no
constitution for this <placeName>state </placeName>altho the <persName>Legislature </persName>or congress convened
to frame it have been two years in session&#8212;there is a prospect that
it will be completed in all this <date n="Winter -1826">winter</date>&#8212;The question as to the 
admission of slavery is undecided tho I think it probable that the 
unrestricted admission of slavery will not be permitted&#8212;those now in
the <placeName>country </placeName>will probably be held as <persName>slaves </persName>for life, what will be done
with their <persName>descendants </persName>is doubtfull<pb n="1470"/></p>

<p>The <persName>Commissioner </persName>of the <placeName>old Colony</placeName> I expect will be here in all
this <date n="10-xx-1826">month </date>or <date n="11-xx-1826">next </date>in company with that of the new one; and as soon
as the affairs of the <placeName>former </placeName>are finally closed the surveys of the <placeName>latter</placeName>
will commence and not before, by that time the list of <persName>families </persName>above
spoken of can be sent on and the land laid off for them&#8212;</p>

<p>I am in very bad health which must be my excuse if I have not
written as fully as you wished&#8212;hoping to see you and the <persName>families</persName>
in the course of the coming <date n="Winter - 1826">winter </date>I remain</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
