<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1963">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 06-16-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-21">08-21-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 419-421
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-06-16">06-16-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Instructions for shipping goods to Texas. Rumors in Mexico that United States will take Texas by force of arms.   Anxious to close his public business and rest.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Dr <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>I returned from <placeName>Bexar </placeName>in much better health than when you left
here&#8212; There appears to be some clouds hanging over this <placeName>country</placeName>,
tho I apprehend nothing from them, and my opinion as to your
removal here is the same as when you left. If you come by land
write to <persName>Breedlove </persName>for a passport and state the number of your
<persName>family</persName>. The law requires all persons to bring passports and it
should be done because it is the law.</p>

<p>The <persName>custom house officer of <placeName>Galveston</placeName></persName> has fixed his office for the
present <placeName>at the mouth of the Brasos river&#8212;</placeName>vessels must be cleared<pb n="420"/>
out for <placeName>Galveston</placeName>, and if you send a vessel from <placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>clear
out for <placeName>Galveston </placeName>and not for the <placeName>Brasos </placeName>but come to the <placeName>B</placeName>. if you
wish from <placeName>Phia </placeName>you can get debenture allowed, but in <placeName>new Orleans
</placeName>you cannot</p>

<p>They have some very erroneous ideas in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>relative to <placeName>Texas</placeName>,
but I think that a few months will convince them of their error&#8212;
The last dates from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>says that the <placeName>united States of the north
</placeName>are about to send a large <persName>army </persName>to take this <placeName>country </placeName>by force etc,
etc. how they should entertain an idea that the <placeName>U S.</placeName> is unfriendly
I can not conceive&#8212;</p>

<p>All kinds of provisions and lumber are free and no duties will
be collected untill after <date n="12-xx-1830">November </date>as I informed you when here&#8212;</p>

<p>Poor <persName>James </persName>died before I returned from <placeName>Bexar </placeName>and I did not
see him&#8212;</p>

<p>I am making final arrangements to close all my business this <date n="Fall - 1830">fall</date>
and <date n="Winter - 1830">winter</date>, and prepare myself to spend my time in a retired and
quiet manner with you&#8212;</p>

<p>I was very well received at <placeName>Bexar </placeName>and all things stand well with
the <persName>State authorities</persName>&#8212; They wish me in <placeName>Bexar </placeName>to go to the
<placeName>Legislature </placeName>but I have refused&#8212; The fact is that unless I can take
some rest I shall not live much longer for I am nearly worn down&#8212;
for nine years since I came to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, my mind has had no rest,
nothing to releave it from continued cares and anxieties&#8212; I have
felt towards all the <persName>settlers </persName>as tho. they were all my <persName>relations</persName>,
Some of them have not merited the anxiety I have suffered for
them I have been a faithful servant of this Govt, and have 
performed much important service for it&#8212; wheither I shall receive
thanks, or abuse, is doubtful, <persName>Poinsett </persName>has left an impression in
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>which has reduced the <persName>North American </persName>character to a low
grade there.&#8212; I do not pretend to say that he has done right, or
wrong, for I know nothing about his conduct-&#8212; he has certainly
been the most unfortunate <persName>minister </persName>that was ever sent to any Govt.</p>

<p><persName>Gen Teran </persName>has not yet left <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>and the news of the
<persName>Spanish </persName>invasion will probably prevent his coming on.</p>

<p>Every thing is peace and quietness in <placeName>Texas </placeName>and so likely to
remain.</p>

<p><persName>Col Milam</persName> says that the <placeName>roads </placeName>are good for a carriage all the
way to <placeName>Nachitochs </placeName>and he advises you to remove by that route&#8212;
it will be a very long and tedious journey, but you and <persName>Emily </persName>must
decide, inform me which route you will take so that I may provide
the nessery matters for you&#8212;- I have an idea of puting up a
<placeName>House </placeName>in this place which will do for you to winter in&#8212; The
<placeName>Steam Saw mill</placeName> is in operation and works well<pb n="421"/></p>

<p>A new <persName>Commissioner </persName>will be on shortly and I shall soon complete
all the titles&#8212; Did you call on the <persName>Comte at <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName></persName>and how
did he treat you. Inform me wheither you intend sending out goods
from <placeName>Pa</placeName>. it will be best to land them in the <placeName>Brasos</placeName>, I think, tho if
the vessel is large she must come into <placeName>Galveston </placeName>I expect your best
plan will be to ship them to <placeName>Orleans </placeName>and thence to this <placeName>country</placeName>.
I will write by every opportunity, both to <placeName>Potosi </placeName>and to 
<placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>to the care of <persName>Price and Morgan</persName></p>

<p>Tell all the <persName>emigrants </persName>to call on <persName>Breedlove </persName>for a passport, because
the law makes it necessary&#8212;</p>

<p>remember me to the <persName>children</persName>, I have received several letters from
you of old date since you left and one from <persName>Emily</persName>. I saw <persName>Sam
Browne</persName> <date when="1830-06-15">yesterday</date>, he is in very good health, but I had not time
to Say more than how do you do, to him for it was mail day&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin </persName> [Rubric]</p>

<p><date when="1830-06-16">June 16 1830</date></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
