<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1843">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>J Child to Stephen F Austin, 01-24-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>J Child</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-18">08-18-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Natchez, Mississippi</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 323-325
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-01-24">01-24-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Suggests a plan for hastening the settlement of Texas. Does not care whether slavery is permitted or not.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Natchez </placeName><date when="1830-01-24">Janry 24, 1830</date></p>
<p>Dear Col,</p>

<p>Since I visited <placeName>Texas </placeName>in the year <date n="xx-xx-1822">1822</date>, at your request for the 
purpose of aiding in the establishment and support of your <placeName>colony</placeName>, it is
well known to you that my exertions have been unremitting in the
promotion of the original plan of the <placeName>settlement</placeName>, and perhaps my
subsequent absence has been more beneficial to the undertaking, than
I could have been by remaining among you. And at the same time
I flatter myself that something has been gained on the scores of
individual fortune and reputation both.<pb n="324"/></p>

<p>At the present crisis however a thought has struck me, that a
movement might be made highly beneficial to the <placeName>colony</placeName>, in strict
pursuance of the views and policy of the<persName> Mexican government</persName> and
in accordance with your own. A movement, which <placeName>England </placeName>must
approve and to which the <placeName>U. States</placeName> can raise no substantial 
objections, as it will have a direct tendency to perpetuate a friendly
understanding between the <persName>three powers</persName>, my efforts in the service
of <persName>Mexican</persName> Independence, and to suppress subsequent revolt, in
<placeName>Texas</placeName>, are also well known to you and the government.</p>

<p>With this project in view, which I will hereafter more fully
detail, I was on the eve of visiting the <placeName>city of Mexico</placeName> to confer with
the <persName>general government</persName> on the subject- But thinking perhaps that
your powers were already amply sufficient to authorise a beginning
and having made up my mind to abandon the plan, unless it should
meet with your approbation, it was thought most adviseable to 
consult you in the first place. Since my first visit to <placeName>Texas </placeName>in <date n="xx-xx-1812">1812</date> it has been my uniform opinion that, this <placeName>section of the country
</placeName>is destined to become the strongest arm of the <placeName>Mexican Republic</placeName>.
At that early period I fixed on the site you now occupy, as the
future <placeName>seat of government</placeName> unless the <placeName>opposite point on this side
the river bottom</placeName> should be deemed more eligible on account of wood
and water, A<placeName> military lookout post at fort Bolivar,</placeName> a <placeName>trading
establishment at the head of the navigation on the Buffalo Bayou</placeName>
connecting these <placeName>settlements </placeName>with your Town on this side and 
securing the trade and attachment of the <persName>Indians </persName>and <persName>whites </persName><placeName>on the
waters of the Trinity</placeName>, and extending the same line on the other side
to the <placeName>navigable waters of the St. Bernard.</placeName> With this view let the
<persName>Mexican government</persName> open a <placeName>land office</placeName> at <placeName>St. Felipe de Austin </placeName>with
full powers to make indefeasible complete <placeName>grants </placeName>of land to actual
<persName>settlers </persName>at a price certain for any quantity not exceeding 640, or
1,000 acres, let them invite the <persName>Mexicans </persName>in the <placeName>interior </placeName>to move
down and settle in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and permit <persName>foreign emigrants</persName> of good
character and small capital with industrious habits to settle 
permanently among them, whose attachment will <hi rend="italic">ex necessitate rei </hi>be
stronger in favor of their <placeName>adopted country</placeName> than any other, and my
word for it, in three or four years we will give a spur to commerce
and agriculture greatly enhancing the price of lands, and converting
the present drone like apathy that broods over those delightful
regions into the busy hum of the beehive in May.</p>

<p>This done, I will undertake to establish the <placeName>trading house on
the Buffaloe</placeName> and make a <placeName>settlement </placeName>of some 100 or more persons,
and it will not be material with me whether slavery is tolerated
or not.</p>

<p>Be so good as to inform me whether you approve of the 
experiment, and if so whether you deem it within the scope of your<pb n="325"/>
powers to authorize me to commence it upon my own plan or one
of your own suggestion,</p>

<p><persName>J[oshua] Child</persName></p>
<p><persName>Col Ph Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
