<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1867">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Elias R Wightman, 03-12-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-19">08-19-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Elias R Wightman
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Matagorda, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 339-341
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-03-12">03-12-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-19" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Surveying, school, instructions for obtaining Land titles.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Matagorda</placeName> <date when="1830-03-12">Friday March 12 1830</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p>I have been here and at the <placeName>old landing opposite</placeName> this, since last
<date when="1830-03-01">Monday week</date>, and am compelled to leave for <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>without 
seeing you, which is a very serious disappointment.</p>

<p>It was my original intention that you should have the surveying
of <placeName>all the vacant lands on this river below <persName>H. H. League</persName> and <persName>Betts</persName></placeName>,
and all <placeName>Trespalacios</placeName>, <placeName>Prairie</placeName>, and <placeName>Cany Creek below <persName>Curtis</persName></placeName>, and I
fully expected you at <placeName>San Felipe</placeName> when the <persName>Commissioner </persName>was there.
But you did not come, and I heard you had engaged in a <placeName>school</placeName>
which I of course supposed would occupy all your time and as
I heard nothing from you, was left to conclude that you did not
wish for any surveying. Notwithstanding this, however, when 
<persName>Selkerk </persName>came over I wrote you, and stated that this job had been
intended for you, and if you wished it, to go on with it, or if not to let
<persName>Selkerk </persName>have your compass so that he might do it, or for you
and him to do it jointly, or make any arrangement with him on the
subject you thought proper and could make. My object was to get
the work done without delay.    About 18 days after <persName>Selkerk </persName>left<pb n="340"/>
me to come over here, I went to the <placeName>mouth of Karankaway on the
east side</placeName> and <placeName>along the bay in sight of the timber of Trespalacios</placeName>,
and thence <placeName>up that Creek on the west side</placeName> in search of you or <persName>Selkerk</persName>,
but seeing no smokes in that direction, I could not but conclude from
the time that had elapsed, that something had prevented either of
you from starting, and that you had abandoned the job, I was alone
and on a borrowed mule, and thought it very doubtfull wheither I
could get over at this place, and therefore struck <placeName>a north course for
<placeName><persName>Alley</persName>s</placeName>.</placeName> On my arrival there I met <persName>Burnham</persName>, who informed me
you was to start from here in a few days. I only remained three
days at home, and then proceeded to the head of <placeName>Trespalacios </placeName>send
followed it down untill I found <persName>Selkerk </persName>and <persName>Cook </persName>and directed them
to stop at <placeName>the west point of Trespalacios Bay</placeName>, for I had left orders
for <persName>Ingram </persName>to finish the <placeName>east side of Karankaway</placeName>. I expected to
find you here, and that the whole meandering could be ploted in
two or three days and the tracts all laid off on the map, after which
they could have been run, but your absence has totally deranged all
my calculations, and compelled me to make new arrangements, for
I must be at <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>on <date when="1830-03-14">Sunday </date>or <date when="1830-03-15">Monday </date>next</p>

<p>I wish you to make a connected plot of all the meanderings on
a scale of 2000 varas to the inch, which is the scale used in all the
work, and I will try and return here sometime in <date n="05-xx-1830">May </date>or <date n="06-xx-1830">June</date>, or
if you can send the plot up to the <placeName>office </placeName>I can there lay oil the
tracts as they are taken, for there is to be some <placeName>quarters </placeName>and some
<placeName>Leagues </placeName>intermixed, I shall be at <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>about 10 days, from
there to <placeName>Galveston bay</placeName>, by way of <placeName>San Felipe</placeName>, and thence <placeName>up the
Colorado above the San Antonio road</placeName>, so that you see I have work
chalked for myself until <date n="06-xx-1830">June </date>at least, and it is in fact quite 
doubtful whether I can be here again before <date n="Fall - 1830">next fall</date> or <date n="Winter - 1830">winter</date>.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Another matter</hi> The <persName>families </persName>who came with you to the <placeName>country</placeName>
have never been to the <placeName>office</placeName>. I know not where they all want
their land, ever since the <date when="1829-11-20">20 of Novr last</date> they were informed by
my advertisement what they ought to do. they have neglected their
own affairs and if they suffer for so doing, they can blame no one
buf themselves. I wrote you that all their business should be done
without advancing one cent except the stamp paper which is fifty
cents for each, so that they have no excuse,</p>

<p>I will once more inform what they <hi rend="italic">must </hi>do. They must each of
them, (that is the <persName>heads of families</persName>) go in person to the <placeName>office </placeName>and
there enter their names and a list of their <persName>families </persName>and each one
must take the oath prescribed by law and procure a certificate of
reception as <persName>settlers </persName>in my <placeName>colony</placeName>, and they must each of them state
where they want their <placeName>land </placeName>and have an entry made of it. When
this is done it can be surveyed and not before.   This is too important<pb n="341"/>
a matter to be neglected any longer. If they take money to pay
the stamp paper they can have their petitions made out in Spanish
by <persName>Williams </persName>and sign it, and then they need not return to <placeName>San
Felipe</placeName> any more untill they go after their titles. Will you do those
<persName>families </persName>the favor to attend to this matter and inform them what
they must do. <persName>Williams </persName>will be at the <placeName>office </placeName>if I am not and can do all that is necessary.</p>

<p>The object of the certificate of reception is to place a legal 
document in the hands of each one, that he was recd, as a <persName>settler </persName>by me
under my contract with gvt. and as such is entitled in virtue of my
contracts and the law to a certain <placeName>portion of land</placeName>. I have adopted
this plan for the safety of the <persName>emigrants </persName>in case of my death before
they get their titles in full, for should I die at this time what legal
proof have any of the <persName>families </persName>who came with you that they form a
part of my <persName>settlers </persName>? they have none for there can be no legal register
of their names untill they have taken the oath. I wish this matter 
attended to, for it is becoming rather dangerous to calculate too much
on my life. My health is greatly impaired and is getting worse, and
I have reason to fear that in case of my death, the <persName>emigrants </persName>would
have to wait a long time before they get their titles. I therefore
again repeat:<hi rend="italic"> neglect this matter no longer.</hi></p>

<p>It was my wish to come to some final plan as to this <placeName>place</placeName>&#8212;but
your absence has defeated that, and it must be defered to some other
period. There is in human affairs a <hi rend="italic">certain time,</hi> a point when the
iron is hot, which ought never to be neglected&#8212;that point in your
affairs was when the <persName>commissioner </persName>was at my <placeName>house</placeName>. You could then
have had all your affairs arranged, and now I fear there will be some
difficulty to get a tract for you as the <persName>heirs </persName>of your deed, father, but
all that can be done by me <hi rend="italic">shall he done.</hi> A petition in Spanish must
be drawn up on stamp paper and signed by you and the other <persName>heirs</persName>,
and I will then manage it to the best advantage for you, but untill I
get that petition with the signatures to it I can do nothing for you.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
