<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1271">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Gaines and J. E. B. Austin to Jose Antonio Saucedo, 09-05-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Gaines and J. E. B. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-12">07-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Jose Antonio Saucedo
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nacogdoches, Texas and Saltillo, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1446-1447
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letters</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-09-05">09-05-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reporting turbulence at Nacogdoches and accusing Austin of disloyalty to the Government.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName><date when="1826-09-05">Sept 5. 1826</date></p>
<p>His <persName>Excellency Don Jose Anto Sausido</persName>.</p>

<p>Most excellent sir I have this Year omitted writing as I am
unable to write Spanish and had every confidence business would 
eventually close to the general good of the Government Yet I have seen
all the Year the machines of disappointed impure services 
disappointed <persName>speculators </persName>disappointed <persName>Rouges </persName>disappointed Office hunters
opponents and striving in opposition and each one striving to carry
his point but all unanimously opposing the law and authority</p>

<p>They began on the <date when="1826-03-19">19th March</date> by declaring the documents from
your <persName>excellency </persName>was forged and the <persName>Authority </persName>here was arbitrary
this part was without effect yet they continued in imprinting of this
on the minds of the people untill a certain <persName>Col. Pettis [Pettus]</persName> from
<placeName>Austin's Colony</placeName> arrived here at the <placeName>Irish Bayou </placeName>  he declared at<pb n="1447"/>
<placeName><persName>Chandler</persName>s Store</placeName> in the presince of <persName>Chandler Elbert Hinds Esqr</persName> and
many <persName>others </persName>that there was no law nor <persName>authority </persName>in this <placeName>country </placeName>that
all they had was from Your <persName>excellency </persName>and that you yourself had no
authority and that <persName>Austin </persName>commanded to the <placeName>Sabine </placeName>this 
immediately took effect with all who could not be received in the <placeName>country</placeName>
and all who opposed the Law and authority <persName>Burrill Thompson</persName> 
immediately commenced to raise a <persName>Company </persName>among them declaring they
would not suffer in future any man to be turned out of the <placeName>country</placeName>
and that they would put down the Authority and establish one of
their own they all declared by the powers to desist <persName>Burrill 
Thompson</persName> declared to me there was no law nor <persName>authority </persName>there and that He
would persist in regulating His <persName>Company </persName>and had this meeting and
agreed to send <persName>John A. Williams</persName> to <persName>Stephen F. Austin </persName>to sanction
agreable to what <persName>Pettis </persName>had told them It appears <persName>Austin </persName>became
anamoured with this plan and sent a large document to <persName>Benjamin
Edwards</persName> who remains here as the agent of <persName>Haden Edwardsthe 
Empresario</persName>  and disclosing many secrets on Slavery among them the said
<persName>Edwards </persName>went immediately to the <placeName>Irish Bayou</placeName> and set in on the 
<persName>Company </persName>Him and <persName>John A Williams </persName>and<persName> Burrill Thompson</persName> and has
eventually succeeded to effect a confusion among them as no 
dependence can be placed among them and the said <persName>B. Edwards</persName> has this
morning sent <persName>Chaplin </persName>among them with a large Packet against the
<persName>authority </persName>of this place what this may end in God only knows the
<placeName>House of <persName>Dill </persName>and <persName>Dust [Durst]</persName></placeName> has worked on the mind of their
<persName>Friends </persName>as they keep a <placeName>Boarding House</placeName> for the <persName>Empresario </persName>It has
touched the minds of some of the<persName> old Citizens </persName>in a word much 
confusion remains here and all has originated from the <persName>Empresario</persName>.</p>

<p>I received a Letter this morning from<placeName> Austin's Colony </placeName>this day and
am informed that they are worse there than here and I presume the
confusion came first from them or the cause.</p>

<p><persName>Austin </persName>has requested the <persName>Alcalda </persName>of this place to check me as He
said I was in the habit of informing the <persName>Government </persName>continually the
dangers of a rebellion All I have to say on this subject is Had he
fought for the Freedom of this <placeName>Country </placeName>and spent all he had He
would be a man particular in defending it But Your Excellency will
see no <persName>Empresario </persName>can comply with their obligation to this 
Government agreeable to Laws and eventually if the calculations fail all
interest for the <persName>Government </persName>will fail and the result will be confusion
which I do not consider is at hand I dont say that a rebellion is in
hand Judge yourself what I do say from your own opinion I want
your <persName>Excellency </persName>to send <persName>Troops </persName>to enforce the Laws and every where
establish order every where I am ready to aid you at all times I shall
use evry exertion in my power untill the return mail and if times cant<pb n="1448"/>
be altered I must leave my <persName>Family </persName>and then Contend Myself in 
person for the Laws and Authority untill I Die</p>

<p>God and Liberty</p>

<p>I remain your Excellencies most obt very Humble Servant</p>

<p>(Signed)          <persName>  James Gaines</persName>.</p>

<p><placeName>Satillo </placeName><date n="10-7-1826">Oct. the 7. 1826</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I send you a Copy of a Letter wrote by <persName>Mr. James Gaines</persName> to this
<persName>Government </persName>stating what you will see in said letter You have that
<persName>poisinous serpent</persName> who underhanded is writing against you all you
ought to take care of Him for if He dont injure you it is not for the
want of trying you will see by His letter that I drew off word for
word.</p>

<p>I wish you to let all the <placeName>Ayish Bayou</placeName> know it and see what He and
his <persName>Brother in Law</persName> wishes to do if it was in their power <persName>Norris </persName>has
written to the same effect this is wrote by a <persName>Friend </persName>who dont sign his
name for good reasons but you will know who he is in a short time.</p>

<p>Ponga mi Rubrica no mas </p>

<p>To <persName>Mr. Joseph Dust [Durst]</persName> </p>

<p>A true copy taken from the original in the <placeName>secretary's office </placeName>
<placeName>Saltillo </placeName><date when="1826-10-06">Oct. 6th 182</date>6</p>

<p><persName>Jas E. B. Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>
<p>P. S. In some places I have corrected the spelling and in others have
left it as it is in the original, which is so badly written that it was
with much difficulty the meaning could be ascertained.&#8212;[Austin] </p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
