<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1287">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>H. H. League to Stephen F. Austin, 09-20-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>H. H. League</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-13">07-13-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Aysh Bayou, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1459-1460
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-09-20">09-20-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Immigration from Tennessee.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Iesh Bayuo</placeName> the <date when="1826-09-20">20th Sept 1826</date></p>
<p><persName>Col Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>D sir it has been <date when="1826-08-23">28 days</date> since we left <placeName>San Felipe</placeName> and we have
Came 235 Miles Our <persName>company </persName>was nearly all sick when we started
and have been much worse on the Boad than they were before, we
have lain hear about a week on account of the ill health of<persName> Mr Jn
Robison</persName> who has-been thought dangerous a part of the time but is
no[w]Convelescent and thinks he will be able to Travil on <date n="0-19-1826">tomorrow</date>,
I Expect you learned from <persName>Mr McNeal</persName> the circumstance of my 
geting crippled by a fall from a horse from which I have suffered Much
and am not yet Recovered but have my health perfectly in all Other
Respects. I have recived two letters from <placeName>home </placeName>since I left your
<placeName>town </placeName>one from my <persName>wife </persName>dated <date when="1826-08-06">6 August</date> which informed me that
thare would be considerable Emigration from <placeName>Tennessee </placeName>to your
<placeName>Coloney </placeName>this <date n="Fall- 1826">fall</date>. I <date n="9-20-1826">this morning</date> Recived another from <persName>william
D Horton</persName> my <persName>Brother in law</persName> who Visited the <placeName>country </placeName>with me, you
may perhaps Recollect I told you that he Rote to me from <placeName>Nachitoches</placeName>
on his Return that he had declined coming to the <placeName>country</placeName>, he tells
me in his presint communication that he was Very sick and low 
spirited at the time he rote and thought at that time he would not come
but on Regaining his health he changed his notion he informs me
that he has procured the Ten <persName>families </persName>that you granted me 
permition to Settle in your <placeName>coloney </placeName>as was agreed on between him and
me before we parted and himself and them are all prepairing to come
to the <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;on the first Rise of the <placeName>River</placeName>, he also informs me that
my <persName>Father in law</persName> and <persName>Doctor Porter</persName> a <persName>brother in law</persName> together with
a considerable number of <persName>Gentlemen </persName>from the Vicinity of <placeName>Nashville</placeName>
will visit your <placeName>country </placeName>this <date n="Winter-1826">winter</date>. Could I have known all this
before I left <placeName>San Felipe</placeName> I should not have went <placeName>home </placeName>at all for he
informs me that he is prepairing to bring my <persName>family </persName>Out. and it
would have been highly Important for me to have Remained and
made preparations to Recive them as well as the other <persName>Emigrants</persName>,
but as I am On the way I will continue On and assist them in getting
out as soon as possible.  I wish you if it is possible to Reserve a <placeName>League<pb n="1460"/>
of land</placeName> for <persName>William D. Horton</persName> on the <placeName>Barnard </placeName>or <placeName>Bay Priarai</placeName> and
if that can not be done as near as Possible to my <placeName>League at <persName>Ginning</persName>s
o[ld?] camp on the Collorado River</placeName>, you will also confur on me a
grate favour by paying some attention to the selecting and surveying
the <placeName>ten Leagues above the Labaha Road</placeName> as it is likely my <persName>settlers</persName>
will wish to go on Immediately, and above all I wish you without
fail to write to me at <placeName>Nashville </placeName>On the subject of Slavery and the
provisions of the constitution generally. I shall in a few days leave
the <persName>company </persName>and go on to <placeName>Nashville </placeName>as Speedily as possible and it
would be a matter of the highest importance to Recive a 
Communication from you as soon as I get <placeName>home </placeName>for should slavery be abolished
it would produce some Change in my seletion of <persName>Emigrants </persName>I shall
be at a loss in my arrangements until I heare from [you].    Give my
Respects to <persName>Majr Burn[e]t</persName> <persName>Mr Williams</persName> etc</p>

<p><persName>H. H. League</persName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
