<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1015">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James A. E. Phelps to Stephen F. Austin, 01-16-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James A. E. Phelps</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-05-23">05-23-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Pinckneyville, Mississippi</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1020-1021
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-01-16">01-16-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-05-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Fever of emigration in Mississippi and "adjoining State." Report concerning abolition of slavery has
checked movement.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            
<p><placeName>Pinckneyville Mi</placeName>. <date when="1825-01-16">Jan 16th 1825</date></p>
<p>Col. <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>
<p>Dr. Sir</p>

<p>Agreeable to mutual promise I have the pleasure of now addressing 
you by mail, and of informing you that after a journey of 18
days from <placeName>St Felipe De Austin</placeName> I arrived safe home: with the exception 
of some bad weather, and some high water, a pleasant journey. The 
emigrating, or <placeName>Texas</placeName> <hi rend="italic">fever</hi> prevails to an extent that your
<hi rend="italic">wishes</hi> would no more than anticipate&#8212;It has pervaded all classes
of the <persName>citizens of this state</persName> and the adjoining; from the <persName>men with
capital</persName>, to the man that wishes to acquire a liveing&#8212;Nothing appears 
at present, to prevent a portion of our <persName>wealthy planters</persName> from
emigrating immediately to the <placeName>province of Texas</placeName> but the uncertainty 
now prevailing with regard to the subject of slavery&#8212;There
has been a parragraph that has gone the round of <placeName>Nuse paper publication</placeName> 
in the <placeName>Middle States [U.S.A]</placeName>, perporting to be an extract from a
<placeName>Mexican paper</placeName>; which precludes the introduction of <persName>negro property</persName>
into the <placeName>Mexican Republick</placeName>, without exception: Subjecting the persons 
so offending to the severest penalties, and also an immediate
emancipation of thos <persName>slaves</persName> now belonging to the <persName>citizens</persName> of the
<placeName>province of Texas</placeName>; and fredom to the <hi rend="italic"><persName>slave</persName></hi> that <hi rend="italic">touches</hi> the soil of
<placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>If this be a fact it will check the tide of emigrating <hi rend="italic">spirits</hi> at
once: and indeed it has had its influence already&#8212;I have pledged
myself to my <persName>friends </persName>to ascertain the fact if possible; and I know
of no other way to satisfy the publick mind on the subject, but by
application to yourself for a copy of the new constitution, and a
promulgation of the same so soon as practicable&#8212;I have ventured
to contradict so much of the report and publication as relates to
your <placeName>colony </placeName>, upon the authority of your self, so far, as garranteeing
the right of that species of property under consideration&#8212;That por-<pb n="1021"/>
tion of the <placeName>Mexican Republick</placeName> is becoming every day more and
more an object of interest with this portion of the <placeName>United States</placeName>&#8212;
There is not a day passes that I am not calld on to give (the superficial) 
information that I am in possession of as regards <placeName>your country</placeName> : 
and have to regret that I am not able to satisfy the eager, yet
not <hi rend="italic">idle</hi> curiosity of my friends&#8212;If slavery is tolerated by the new
constitution I could wish, for the benefit of your self, and others
that you would petition the government for extension of territory,
and colonial location, so as to comprise the <placeName>Trinity [River] and its waters</placeName>:
Three Hundred <persName>familys </persName>more can be settled in less than two years&#8212;</p>

<p>A very considerable number of <persName>Gentlemen of fortune</persName> will visit
the <placeName>colony</placeName> this <date n="Spring- 1825">Spring</date>, from this section of Country&#8212;with a view
of becoming <persName>citizens</persName>&#8212;I will inform you further on the subject in
due time&#8212;</p>

<p>The death of my <persName>Father in Law</persName> during my absence has deranged
my calculations in some degree, as it may cause some delay in the
moving of my <persName>family </persName>but it is more than probable that the whole
family of <persName>Col Kirby</persName> will move when I doo&#8212;Please give my best
respect to <persName>Capt Austin</persName> and <persName>Mr Williams</persName>. Tell the latter that I
am anxious to hear from him, and likewise to receive a map of the
<placeName>colony </placeName>, which he promised&#8212;</p>

<p>Be so good as to designate the bounds of my Labours an the Deed
so soon as surveyed, and send me a coppy</p>

<p><persName>James A E Phelps</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
