<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1806">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>David G Burnet to Stephen F Austin, 12-04-1829</title>
            <author>
                <persName>David G Burnet</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-16">08-16-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Cincinnati, Ohio</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 296-299
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1829-12-04">12-04-1829</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reports concerning negotiations of the united States for purchase of Texas. Speculations in Texas lands.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Cincinnati</placeName> <date when="1829-12-04">4 Decr 1829</date></p>
<p>My dear Sir</p>

<p>The return of our worthy <persName>friend </persName><persName>Genl Fullerton</persName> affords me
another opportunity of troubling you with a letter&#8212; Well now
I do verily believe that some of my late letters have been a trouble
to you&#8212;but I dont see the use of having a <persName>friend </persName>unless we can
trouble him now and then-&#8212;</p>

<p>The principal burden of my last letters (and I have written you
five or six within two months) has been the probable purchase of<pb n="297"/>
<placeName>Texas </placeName>by this <persName>government</persName>&#8212; This subject has somewhat died away
here and the excitement produced by its first agitation in the <placeName>public
papers</placeName> has measurably subsided&#8212; The <placeName>newspaper </placeName>discussion of it
was I believe first Started by <persName>T. H. Benton</persName> whom you know&#8212;
Some <persName>writer </persName>in <placeName>Nashville </placeName>rung the second peal, and anon the matter
was taken up by a variety of <persName>scribblers</persName>, both <persName>friends </persName>and <persName>foes </persName>to the
contemplated acquisition&#8212; My original opinion, as expressed to you
in my first letter on the subject, has been somewhat modified but
not essentially changed&#8212; I still believe the purchase will be made,
but not so speedily as I then apprehended&#8212; It seems to me that
<persName>Mr Poinsett</persName> has rendered himself too much an object of jealousy,
and become too unpopular in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>to negocíate a treaty on so
delicate and important a subject as the relinquishment and the 
acquisition of so valuable a <placeName>territory</placeName>&#8212; Rumor says that <persName>Mr Hughes</persName>,
who was recently superseded as <persName>charge d'affairs at the <placeName>Netherlands</placeName>
</persName>will be appointed to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and I think the report very likely to
be correct&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Mr Hughes</persName> is now in <placeName>Europe </placeName>and probably will not arrive in this
<placeName>country </placeName>before spring&#8212; Should he be sent to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, he could not
reach there until late in the <date n="Fall - 1829">fall</date>, for he would not venture himself
at <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> during the <date n="Summer -1829">summer </date>or <date n="Fall - 1829">autumnal </date>months&#8212; If then it
shall fall to his lot to negotiate the treaty, it will not be practicable
for him to perfect it until late in the ensuing <date n="Winter - 1829">winter</date>, and hardly in
time to submit it to the <persName>senate </persName>of <date n="1830-1831">1830-31</date>&#8212; It will doubtless be
a part of the policy of the <persName>administration </persName>to bring it in before the
sages of the land, near the close of their session when the ranks of
the <persName>opposition </persName>may be a little thinned and those who remain are
pretty well fagged and out of tune for a fierce onset&#8212; It is 
therefore not probable in my opinion that you will belong to <persName>Uncle
Sam</persName> <hi rend="italic">before </hi><date n="03-xx-1831">March </date>or <date n="04-xx-1831">April of 1831</date>&#8212;and I do really hope that I
shall be able before that time, to have my <placeName>Colony </placeName>fully Settled and
so firmly fixed as not to be disturbed by the arch cupidity that has
too often characterised our good <hi rend="italic"><persName>Uncle's </persName></hi>dealing with <persName>large land
claimants</persName>&#8212; I have but little time to write, but I send you a packet
of <placeName>news papers</placeName> from which you will [be] able to glean more of the
late doings in the <placeName>world </placeName>than I could give you in a week&#8212; I 
observed in one of the <placeName>national Journals</placeName> which I send you, a letter
from <placeName>San Felipe</placeName> touching the <placeName>advertisment </placeName>by <persName>Dennis A Smith</persName>
of 48,000,000 of acres of <placeName>Texas lands</placeName>&#8212; I was truly rejoiced to see
that <placeName>publication</placeName>&#8212; They have an <placeName>agency </placeName><hi rend="italic">here </hi>and when it was
first established I was detirmined to expose the imposition as I then
considered it by a <placeName>publication </placeName>under my own proper name&#8212; The
<persName>agent </persName>here called on me on the subject and I stated to him very
frankly my views concerning it and told him that I should feel com-<pb n="298"/>
pelled if they put out an <placeName>advertisement</placeName>, to enlighten the public
mind on the matter&#8212; He assured me that no money should be
paid over to the alleged <persName>proprietors </persName>until they gave entire 
satisfaction as to title&#8212; I then concluded not to interfere and make
myself many <persName>enemies </persName>for I have learned from experience that 
<persName>enemies </persName>made in this way have much more zeal, than any <persName>friends </persName>whom
the doing of Such a service might procure a body&#8212; so I even
resolved not to meddle with the matter, but I have freely spoken of
it to many <persName>gentlemen in this <placeName>City</placeName></persName> and have communicated my views
to two respectable <persName>citizens of <placeName>Baltimore</placeName>&#8212;
</persName></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Peck</hi>, who left here a few days ago for <placeName>Orleans</placeName>, tells me that
<persName>Willson </persName>is selling <placeName>Texas lands</placeName> in <placeName>New York</placeName> at 2 cents an acre&#8212;
<persName>Willson </persName>told me last <date n="Summer - 1829">summer</date>, that he had a <placeName>grant </placeName><hi rend="italic">in fee</hi> for 8,000,000
acres&#8212; Is it so qu[i]en sabe, as we <persName>Mexicans </persName>say&#8212; Certain I am
that these things are doing an injury to all of us&#8212;- the detection of
one fraud in relation to <placeName>Texas lands</placeName>, will entail suspicion upon us
all, and it is outrageous that honest <persName>men </persName>should suffer for the 
misdeeds of a few <persName>sharpers</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I have some expectation of forming a <persName>company </persName>in <placeName>Baltimore </placeName>for
the settlement of my <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212; Should it be done we shall 
proceed rapidly in the work&#8212;a few weeks will determine&#8212; I am
exceedingly desirous to get back&#8212; Should our friend <persName>Padilla </persName>be
with you I beg you will mention me to him&#8212;- I wrote to him and
also to the <persName>Governor </persName>some time ago and enclosed my letters to
<persName>Williams </persName>and I hope they have not miscarried&#8212; I have since then
written to the <persName>Governor</persName>, inclosed to you, and sent a duplicate I
would write to both by this opportunity but have not much time
and am not yet able to speak positively as to my success or my return
to <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I received a <placeName>nacogdoches paper</placeName> <date when="1829-12-03">yesterday </date>containing an obituary
notice of your amiable and lamented <persName>brother </persName>and I have taken [it]
to the <placeName>Gazette office</placeName> to have it published here&#8212; It occurred to me
that there might be some <persName>friends </persName>and <persName>relatives </persName>who had not heard
of his decease, and besides it would be a gratification to my own
feelings to give currency to that modest tribute of respect for the
memory of a <persName>friend </persName>whom I much esteemed&#8212;</p>

<p>I send a half barrel of buck wheat meal directed to <persName>League</persName>, to be
divided between <persName>Williams </persName>and himself&#8212; Should you be at 
house-keeping you must make a tripartite division of it, for I have sent
it under a presumption that you <hi rend="italic">were not</hi>&#8212; My <persName><placeName>Texas </placeName>friends</persName>
are so frugal of their time or their paper that I am left entirely to
presumptions on all matters relating to them&#8212; The <hi rend="italic">one </hi>letter from
you and one from <persName>Williams </persName>at <placeName>Orleans </placeName>are all the evidence I have
that I am remembered on the <placeName>Brasos</placeName>&#8212;   I have never received one<pb n="299"/>
line from <hi rend="italic"><persName>League</persName></hi>&#8212; I beg you will write to me by the first opportunity as it is probable I shall be here long enough to receive it if
not here, will have it Sent after me&#8212; do write any how and give
me all the news, for I am exceedingly in the dark in respect to <placeName>Texas</placeName>
affairs&#8212; Farewell&#8212; May God bless you in all things&#8212; 
Remember me to all <persName>friends</persName>&#8212;and should you have opportunity remember
me particularly to <persName>Mrs. Long</persName>&#8212; I heard long ago that she had left
<placeName>San Felipe </placeName>and was living <placeName>on the river below</placeName> and therefore have
not mentioned her in my former letters&#8212;in haste.</p>

<p><persName>David G. Burnet   </persName> [Rubric]</p>
<p><persName>Col. Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
