<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1005">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Robert Lewis to Stephen F. Austin, 01-09-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Robert Lewis</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-05-21">05-21-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Santa Rosa, Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1013
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-01-09">01-09-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-05-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Difficulties of trade in northern Mexico. Indians troublesome.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Santa Rosa</placeName> <date when="2010-01-09">January 9th 1825</date></p>

<p>Col. <persName>Austin</persName></p>

<p>D. Sir I arrived at this place the <date when="1824-11-11">11th Novr</date> the <persName>Comisary </persName>made
many diffieuties, respecting the duties, I told him I was not liable
to pay duties, as he demanded he would not suffer me to sell without
paying. I applied to the <persName>Alcalda</persName> and got him to witness the taking
of an Inventory of the goods and let the sales go on, and for me to
go to <placeName>Saltillo</placeName> and on my return if I did not convince them I was
not subject to pay duties, I would pay them, on my return I offered
to pay the duties he refusd to take them, nor would not suffer me
to go without leaving my goods in his possession or giving security
for the whole amount, stating he had represented my case to the
<persName>Comisary Gel</persName> at <placeName>Saint Luis Potosi</placeName>, and that he might order him
to take possession of them and from his misrepresentation, he
ordered him to take possession of them and to forward my paspor[t]s
or other papers to him stating they must be forwd etc I
wold not let him take possession he cald on the <persName>Alcalda</persName> to assist
him in taking possession of them. I cald on the <persName>Alcalda</persName>, as a <persName>Civil
Officer</persName> to protect me and my goods, and offered him security as if
I was liable to pay duties, the <persName>comisary </persName>objected to the security
without, they would put in pawn in money Money pater [plata] or,
paster [pasta], to the amount of the goods, I told the <persName>Alcalda</persName>, I
was willing to give security, agreeable to law and would not give
security in any other way, and after a few days, the <persName>Alcalda</persName> took
the security. A large mijority of the <persName>people of this place</persName> are
convinct the <persName>Comisary</persName>'s treatment to me are improper, he is very
uneasy at this time respecting his treatment towards me, it will
be 2 or 3 weeks yet I expect before I git returns from the <persName>Comisary
Gel</persName> The <persName>Governor</persName> has granted to me and <persName>Bynum</persName> <placeName>10 Leagues of
Land</placeName> which I hope will meet your approbation, as it will not be
any thing against your private Interest, or the public good,&#8212;I have
several times spoke of <persName>Nixon</persName>, and find he is very unpopular in this
part of the <placeName>Country</placeName>, I named to <persName>Barron</persName>, of his threats against
you,&#8212;sales are very dul owing to the scarcity of money and an 
overstock of goods in the country,&#8212;I expect it will be 3 months yet
before my return,&#8212;<persName>The Indians</persName> are very troublesome they do a
grate deal of mischief, killing people and taking of Caviards,&#8212;I
wish you to forward the inclose to <persName>Col Bynum</persName> by the first safe 
opportunity.</p>

<p><persName>Col S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p><persName>Robert Lewis</persName>[Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
