<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1845">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>R Stowers to Stephen F Austin, 01-26-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>R Stowers</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-18">08-18-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monclova, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 325-326
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-01-26">01-26-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Rumors of negotiations by the united States for purchase of Texas. Bustamanto changing the government of Mexico.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mon Clover</placeName> <date when="1830-01-26">Jany 26 1830</date></p>
<p>My Dear Sir</p>

<p>I have just recd pr the hands of <persName>Antonio Manches</persName> letters from
the <placeName>U. S</placeName>. bearing the disagreeable and unpleasant information of<pb n="326"/>
my worthy <persName>friend </persName>and <persName>relative </persName><persName>Samuel Summer</persName>'s being murdered
<date n="Summer - 1829">last summer </date>on the <placeName>Sante Fe road </placeName>by the <persName>Indians</persName>, also suspicions
that we are likely to sustain a considerable loss from certain 
imprudences of the man I left in charge of our business in<placeName> New
Mexico</placeName>, these circumstances render it highly necessary that I
should repair hence soon as possible and these circumstances will
further prevent my returning to <placeName>Texas </placeName>for some time, but so soon
as I can settle our business in <placeName>New Mexico</placeName> I shall return by the
way of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, this I think will be some time <date n="Fall - 1830">next fall</date>, the goods
here I shall leave with <placeName>Mr. Woodson</placeName> to sell and make returns.
Our sales have been very good in this section, but light profits.</p>

<p>The <persName>Mexicans </persName>are much agitated at this time relative to a change
of their Government. <persName>Bustamante </persName>seems to be the prime mover
of a <persName>central Govet</persName> and it seems from the best information I can
gather here, that he is very likely to carry his point, has many
<persName>followers</persName>. they urge as a principal reason for a change the 
expense of supporting the <placeName>different states </placeName>under the present form,
which argument has a priestly sway among the common people.
I have but little doubt myself, but what a central form would suit
them much better than the present, provided they had less 
<placeName>Territory </placeName>to govern, but it seems that <persName>Uncle Sam</persName> is pestering them
for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, at which some of them in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>kick against might
and main, but I think will ultimately bring them under, the <placeName>U. S.
</placeName>has, as they say has offered to loan them six millions of dollars,
if they would relinquish to her <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I have not much idea that
a very speedy change will take place, but am now inclined to
think it will ultimately, provided it could get through the <persName>senate</persName>
of the <placeName>U. S. </placeName>Here lies the rub. I presume it is hardly necessary
to name to you that we are all somewhat creatures of interest. I
am so much so that I have thought proper to solicit from you
a <placeName>grant </placeName>for a small piece of Land say a League, should you think
proper to receive the application, you would render me a lasting
favour by selecting me a piece of your own choice, and should
you need any assistance call on my particular frds <persName>Mr, Williams
</persName>and <persName>McKinstry </persName>to assist you, and any trouble and expense that
may be attending it, I will readily reimburse on my arrival with
you. Tender my best respects to <persName>Mr. and Mrs. Williams</persName> and all
my old frds in yr. city.</p>

<p><persName>E. Stowers</persName></p>
<p>P. S. Please write me on recpt. of this to <placeName>Chihuahua</placeName></p>
<p>[Addressed] Al <persName>Sor D Esteban F. Austin</persName>   <placeName>San Felipe de Austin
Texas</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
