<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1879">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James F Perry to no recipient, 03-21-1830  -  05-07-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James F Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-19">08-19-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        no recipient
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Not sent</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Not sent</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 347-350
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Diary</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-03-21">03-21-1830 - 05-07-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-19" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">James F. Perry's diary of journey from Potosi, Mo., to Texas, March 23, 1830-May 8, 1830.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Potosi Missouri</placeName> <date when="1830-03-21">Sunday [Mch 21st 1830]</date></p>
<p>1/2 after 9 o'clock <persName>J. F. Perry </persName>started on a visit or rather for the
purpose of viewing<placeName> Austins Colony</placeName> in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, arrived at <placeName>Hercu-<pb n="348"/>
lanium</placeName> on the <date n="03-21-1830.">same evening</date> there I had to remain the <date when="1830-03-22">22d </date>and <date when="1830-03-23">23rd</date>
waiting for the steam Boat North America for a passage to <placeName>New 
Orleans.</placeName> Met <persName>James A. Austin</persName> who starts in company with me with a
view to settle himself in <persName>Texas</persName>, the S. B. N america ari'd the eving of
the <date when="1830-03-23">23d </date>during my stay here the S. B <persName>Diana </persName>passed down for 
<placeName>Louisvill </placeName>Three Steam Boats passed up <date when="1830-03-24">24th </date>wednesday, arrived at the
<placeName>cliff of Selma</placeName> here we remain'd taking in Lead untill <date when="1830-03-25">25th </date>thirsday
12 o'clock started about 12 o'clock passed the S. B.&#8212;&#8212;&#8212; for <placeName>St
Louis</placeName></p>

<p><date when="1830-03-31">March 31st Wednesday</date> Land at <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> about 1/2 past 2 o'clock P M. remained in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> untill <date n="04-9-1830">friday the 10th day of
April</date> at 12 oclock saild <placeName>in the Schooner Pocahontas</placeName> for the<placeName> port of
Brazoria</placeName> in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, <persName>Capt Carpenter</persName> master with 12 <persName>Cabin pasengers</persName>
viz <persName>Mr Mills</persName> and<persName> Brother Mr Grason</persName> <persName>Mr Dawson</persName> <persName>Mr Jameson.</persName> <persName>M
Brown </persName><persName>Mr. Jones</persName> and <persName>Mr Lefwick </persName>of <placeName>virga </placeName>and <persName>Syghts </persName>from <placeName>New
Yourk</placeName></p>

<p><persName>James A Austin</persName> and myself and about 25 or 80 deck <persName>pasengers</persName>
among home [whom] are a nomber of <persName>weomen </persName>and <persName>children </persName>among
them was <persName>Majr Brygs</persName></p>

<p><date when="1830-04-09">friday night</date> from 8 oclock in the morning lay at anker until 
morning <placeName>7 or 8 miles above the S. W Pass of the Mississippi</placeName></p>

<p><date when="1830-04-10">Saturday morning 11th</date> histed sail about 8 oclk am took in the
<persName>Pilot </persName>a few miles above the bar. got to sea and discharged the <persName>Pilot</persName>
lay to anker <placeName>for [four] or five miles S. W of the bar</placeName> for want of
wind until</p>

<p><date when="1830-04-11">Sunday Morning 12th</date> histed sail under a light wind</p>

<p><date when="1830-04-13">Tuesday morning</date> about 9 or 10 oclk <placeName>in sight of Galveston Island
</placeName>said to be 45 miles long on which stands only 3 solitary Live oak at
some distance apart I suppose Judging from the distance we was
from them that they must stand <placeName>one or two miles apart</placeName> came too oft
the<placeName> month of the Brazoses</placeName> in the evening there not being water to
carry us over the bar lay at ancker untill <date when="1830-04-14">Wednesday Morning 15th</date> I
with a nomber <persName>passengers </persName>went on shore in the Boat to <persName>Mr. Micheles
</persName>who lives emediately at the<placeName> mouth of the Brazoes L 28° 57' 
Longetuted</placeName><persName> Mr Mitchel</persName> has a small <placeName>salt works</placeName> in opperation from which
he makes from 8 to 10 bushel pr day worth at the works $1.00</p>

<p>60 Gal. water make 1 bushel all <placeName>along the sea coast is prairia and
salt marches for two or thr[ee] miles back</placeName> when the appearance of
fine timber, the soil on the <placeName>Prarie </placeName>is sand except in the <placeName>salt
Marches</placeName>, which is clay, the land appears to be level as far as can be
seen back (<persName>Michel </persName>makes use of drift wood entirely for to make salt
of which there is a great abundance but up <placeName>along the coast</placeName> and more
particularly <placeName>near the mouth of the Brazos</placeName> nothing can be raised near
the <placeName>sea cost</placeName> that groes high in concequence of the heavy winds off sea<pb n="349"/>
good Brick can be made anywhere on the <placeName>sea board</placeName>. <persName>Mr. Michals
</persName>chemney is built with very good Brick made <placeName>close to his hous</placeName>&#8212;the
cattle appears to be in fine order and the place healthy</p>

<p><date when="1830-04-14">Wednesday 15th</date> the vessel got <placeName>over the bar</placeName> after much dificulty
she struck verry hard on it and the wind beat her back <placeName>into a bason
formed by the bar</placeName> and a bar which puts out from <placeName>West side of the
brases emideately at the mouth</placeName> but with two or three hours hard
work she was got into the <placeName>Brasos </placeName>where we lay until <date when="1830-04-15">thirsday 
morning</date> saild and warped up the <placeName>Brasos</placeName>, This day about 15 or 16 miles
<date when="1830-04-16">Friday morning 16th</date>. myself and 4 others left the vessel in the
boat and arrived at <placeName>Brasoria </placeName>at 2 oclock P. M. I went in compy
with <persName>Sayer</persName>. to <placeName><persName>Josiah H Bell</persName>s</placeName> <placeName>12 miles north on the San Felepe road
</placeName>that evening next morning <date when="1830-04-17">Saturday 17th </date>returned to <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>and
found the vessel had arrivd returnd to <placeName><persName>Mr. Bell</persName>s</placeName>, <date when="1830-04-18">18 Sunday </date>
returned to <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>for <persName>James Austin</persName> to [ok] him to <persName>squir Bell</persName>s then
left, borrowed a mule from <persName>squire Bell,</persName> and continued on at 4 oclock
P M. in company with a <persName>Mr Anderson</persName> to se <persName>Col Austin</persName> who we heard
was in the <placeName>neighbourhood of Harrisburg</placeName>. cross the <placeName>brasos </placeName>that 
evening <placeName>12 miles from <persName>Bell</persName>s in a N E. direction</placeName> at what is call'd <placeName>Boliver</placeName>
where a <placeName>Town </placeName>had been Laid out and abandoned. <persName>Mr Warren Hall
</persName>was at this place where we remaind for the night was very politely
treated by <persName>Mr Hall </persName>continued our course in the morning <placeName>6 miles
through the Brasos Bottom</placeName> which very heavy timbered and great
quantities of cain growing on it to <persName>Mr Hodges</persName> where we took 
Breakfast it rained considerable this morning here we met with <persName>Wm Harris
Esqr</persName> who informed us<persName> col Austin</persName> was on<placeName> Galveston Bay </placeName>or 
<placeName>Dickersons Bayou</placeName> as he had left him the <date when="1830-04-17">day before</date> on <placeName>Clear Creek about
25 Miles distant</placeName>, and agreed to get a <persName>hand </persName>or pilot us himself if we
would wait untill <date when="1830-04-20">Tuesday'morning</date> which we did remain at<persName> Mr
Harris </persName>and about 1/2 mile from where we breafasted where we was
verry friendly treated <date when="1830-04-20">Tuesday Morning</date> Started in compy with a
<persName>Mr Boatright</persName> crossed the head water of <placeName>Chocolate Bayou</placeName> <placeName>Halls creek
</placeName><placeName>dickersons Bayou</placeName> and <placeName>Cleare Creek</placeName> recrossed <placeName>Clear Creek</placeName> and
camped on <placeName>Dickesons Bayou </placeName><date when="1830-04-21">wednessday morning 21st</date> continued a
East course and struck&#8212;<placeName>Galveston Bay</placeName> at <placeName>davises Point</placeName> at bout 9
oclock A M where we found <persName>Col. Austin</persName> just ready to start with the
<persName>Surveyors </persName>who we [re] meandering the <placeName>bay coast </placeName>and <placeName>Dickesons
Bayou</placeName> <persName>Mr Anderson</persName> Started from this place for <placeName>St. Felepe</placeName> by the
way of <placeName>Harrisbourg</placeName>. I remained with <persName>Col Austin </persName>and the <persName>Surveyors</persName>
untill <date when="1830-05-02">Sunday morning 1st May</date> when <persName>Col. A.</persName> and myself left the
<persName>surveyors </persName>for <placeName>Harrison on the brasos</placeName> got to <persName>Mr. Hall</persName> that night
who lives just <placeName>at the Timber of the Brasos Bottom at the edge of the
Prararie </placeName><date when="1830-05-03">Monday May 2d</date> left <persName>Col A </persName>at <persName>Squire Harris</persName> he remained
here to get some provisions for the <persName>surveyors </persName>and was to met them<pb n="350"/>
<placeName>at the mouth of Pleasent creek on Chocolate Bayou</placeName> and agreed to
meet me in <placeName>San Felipe</placeName> on <date when="1830-05-10">Monday 9th May.</date> I returned to <placeName><persName>Mr.
Bell</persName>s</placeName> to see <persName>James Austin</persName> and found him geting some better but
still in a verry delecate and doutfull state of health <persName>Mr. Bell</persName> taking
particular and motherly care of him and if he can be restored 
attention and good nursing he must recover under his care, remained
here two days and a half&#8212;and then left in comy. with <persName>Squire Bell
</persName>on <date when="1830-05-07">fridy the 7</date> for <placeName>San Philipe de Austin</placeName>, arrived at <placeName>san Felepe
Satarday</placeName> the <date when="1830-05-08">8th</date> after dark. <placeName>San Philepe</placeName> is verry pleasently 
situated on the <placeName>W. side of the Brasoses 85 miles from the mouth on
a high praria</placeName>&#8212;the prararia comes to the <placeName>river </placeName>at this place and the
<placeName>Bank on the side the Town is situated is much higher than any
I have saw on the river</placeName> it [is) said it is 61 or 60 feet high there is
perhaps------<persName>famalies </persName>residing in it among which there is 3 <placeName>Taverns</placeName>
7 or 8 <placeName>Trading establishments</placeName> <placeName>grog shops</placeName> and <placeName>Stores </placeName>one <placeName>Black
smith shop</placeName> one <placeName>printing office</placeName>.</p>

<p>The country from the <placeName>mouth of the Brasos</placeName> for five or six Miles
is all a <placeName>prararia </placeName>near the <placeName>sea shore</placeName> sandy then low and marchey.
gradually rises a little untill the timber commences is generaly a
clay land, and looks poor much appearences of Craw fish, although
the land looks unproductive, there is emence coats of fine Grass
growing on it and affords emence pasturage for Stock of all kind,
from where the Timber commences <placeName>on the Brasos </placeName>the <placeName>Bottom of
the Brassos</placeName> are heavely timbered as far up as I have yet been say
from <placeName>one to six and eight miles on each side of the river</placeName> and in
some places wider the timber consists of live oak Large quantities
of it Black- oak Bed oak post oak white oak pecan Ash mulberry
Ellam cottonwood and sundry other not recollected the undergroth
is wild peach sasafras</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
