<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB1885">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 03-28-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-19">08-19-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Potosi, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 351-353
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-03-28">03-28-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-19" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Urging him to hasten to Texas. Rapid immigration of excellent character.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Filipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1830-03-28">March 28 1830</date></p>
<p>My Dear Brother and Sister,</p>

<p>I wrote you many letters during the months of <date n="12-xx-1829">Decr</date>, and <date n="01-xx-1830">Jany</date>.
they were in substance all of the same tenor. I informed you that
it was my advise and my wish that you should remove here as<pb n="352"/>
soon as possible with all your <persName>family </persName>and property and that I had
petitioned the <persName>Governor of the state</persName> to grant you <placeName>Eleven Leagues
of land</placeName>. I now have the pleasure to inform you that I <date when="1830-03-27">yesterday</date>
received the <placeName>grant </placeName>from the <persName>Governor</persName>, he has had the goodness
to grant to <persName>James F. Perry </persName>and to his <persName>wife Emily Margarita Austin</persName>
<placeName>Eleven Leagues of land to be selected on any vacant lands in Austin's
colony</placeName> and he has issued all the necessary orders to the <persName>General
land Commissioner </persName>to give a patent in due form as the colonization
law requires. The <placeName>grant </placeName>is however subject to the condition that
you remove and settle here with your <persName>family </persName><date when="1832-01-01"><date when="1832-01-01">within two years from
the first day of last January</date></date>. In eleven Mexican leagues there is
within a fraction of forty eight thousand eight hundred and thirty
acres english measure. Under the present law as it now stands
you cannot sell any of this land, untill after several years, but
I did not ask for it with an expectation that you wished to sell
any of it now. My object was to secure a fortune for your <persName>children</persName>
and this was the reason why I asked for it in both of your names,
by the laws of this <placeName>country </placeName>the <persName>husband </persName>and <persName>wife </persName>can hold 
property separately. This grant as it now stands belongs to both of
you, one half to each, so that my <persName>sisters children by Bryan</persName>, as her
<persName>heirs </persName>will be entitled to their full share.</p>

<p>I have now done all that I can do. You have got the highest
<placeName>grant </placeName>that can be given by the laws of this country to any one
which is eleven Leagues as you will see by examining the 12th
article of the national colonization law of <date when="1824-08-18">August 18 1824</date> in the
translations which I sent you. It is<hi rend="italic"> what very few people can get</hi>,
and it will be trifling with fortune not to accept it.</p>

<p>You are allowed two years to remove, but I most earnestly advise
you to remove <hi rend="italic">immediately</hi>. I shall expect to eat my <date when="1830-12-25">next Christmas</date>
dinner with you all. do not disappoint me. The object is of too
much importance to be neglected. You have no idea at all of this
<placeName>country</placeName>, nor of the great emigration that is daily coming to it, nor
of the <hi rend="italic">character </hi>of the <persName>emigrants </persName>We are getting the best <persName>men</persName>,
the best kind of <persName>settlers</persName>, pay no attention to rumors and silly 
reports but push on as fast as possible. We have nothing to fear
from this <persName>Govt</persName>, nor from any other <placeName>quarter </placeName>except from the <placeName>United
States of the North</placeName>. If that govt, should get hold of us and 
introduce its <hi rend="italic">land system</hi> etc etc thousands who are now on the move
and who have not yet secured their titles, would be totally ruined,
The greatest misfortune that could befall <placeName>Texas </placeName>at this moment
would be a sudden change by which many of the <persName>emigrants </persName>would
be thrown upon the liberality of the <persName>Congress of the <placeName>United States
of the north</placeName></persName>&#8212;<hi rend="italic">theirs would he a most forlorn hope</hi>. I have no idea
of any change unless it be effected by arbitrary force, and I have
too much confidence in the magninimity of my<placeName> native country</placeName><pb n="353"/>
to suppose that its govt, would resort to that mode of extending
its already unweildy frame over the <placeName>territory </placeName>of its <persName>friend and
neighbor</persName> and <placeName>sister republic</placeName>. All the <persName>families </persName>you bring with you
shall be received by me so far as my authority and my duty will
permit. You will of course bring non nor suffer none to come in
company with you who are not good honest <persName>citizens</persName>, and above all,
you will exclude <persName>drunkards</persName>. I have been heretofore so much troubled
with that beastly portion of the human race, that my dislike to them
has grown into a very strong prejudice.</p>

<p>I need not say to you that I am ready to do all that a friend and
relation can do consistent with his means and situation, to benefit
all my poor <persName>relations</persName>, or all my rich ones, if any such there be&#8212;
Where are <persName>Horace Austin's children</persName>, <persName>James Austin's</persName> etc, etc. I can
advance them nothing in money. I am myself poor as to disposable
means and am embarrassed with debts, but I can benifit them in
getting land, and the day is not far distant when <placeName>Texas land </placeName>will
be worth money.</p>

<p>I have raised the name of my <persName>family </persName>to a respectable standing in
this <placeName>country</placeName>, and my <persName>relations </persName>need not be ashamed to own that they
are my <persName>relations</persName>. I hope that my heart is what it always was&#8212;too
much alive perhaps to sensibility, but never deaf to the calls of
justice or of friendship, or of my kindred.</p>

<p>Love to my little <persName>nephews </persName>I hope soon to see them and I hope to
live untill I see them above the reach of poverty. I saw my <persName>little
boy Stephen</persName> a few days ago. he is with his <persName>mother </persName>at <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>,
he was near death a month since, but has recovered and is getting
hearty. <persName>Eliza </persName>sends her love to you, and will make your house her
home when you get here. I have told her that you would make
her welcome. As for me, the whole <placeName>colony </placeName>is my <placeName>home</placeName>. My 
business necessarily requires my presence in many parts of it. I have
just returned from the <placeName>woods </placeName>and in a few days go out again to
<placeName>Galveston Bay</placeName> to locate and survey your <placeName>land</placeName>. When you all get
on we will settle down somewhere all together.</p>

<p>Remember me to <persName>Judge Carr</persName> and tell him I recd the box of fruit
seed he had the goodness to send me for which I sincerely thank
him.   do not fail to bring all kind of fruit seeds and some roots.</p>

<p>Remember me to all the <persName>Perry family</persName> to my good friend <persName>Bruffee</persName>
and to all others who have any remembrance of their old <persName>neighbor</persName>.</p>

<p>Young <persName>Hinkson </persName>has settled here and has selected a good tract of
<placeName>land on tide water of Matagorda Bay</placeName>. Let me know as soon as
possible when you will be here that I may make my calculations.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr. James F. Perry</persName>  <placeName>Potosi Missouri</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
