<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB2007">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Unknown to Unknown, 05-xx-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-12">12-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1106-1108
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-05">05-xx-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Regulations for immigrants. (1) Report intentions and file character certificate on arrival. (2) Get permission to select land. (3) Arrange to pay certain fees, including $60 to the empresario for each league.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[May?&#8212;, 1825.]</p>

<p>Regulations to be observed by <persName>persons who wish to settle in the
<placeName>Colony</placeName></persName> which the <persName>Govt </persName>have authorised <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> to 
establish in <placeName>Texas </placeName>by Contract dated <date when="1825-04-27">April [27] 1825 </date>being the <placeName>second
Colony</placeName> of said <persName>Austin</persName></p>

<p>Art 1st <persName>Every person wishing to become a settler </persName>must immediately
after his arrival present himself to me and signify his desire to that
effect and leave with me recommendations from the <persName>Authorities </persName>of
the place where he moved from Accrediting his Cristianity morality
and good habits which will be laid before the <persName>Commr </persName>as the Law 
requires&#8212;he will also deliver in writing a statement of his name,
whether married or single, his <persName>family </persName>specifying their number and
sexes, the <placeName>place of his nativity</placeName>, his age, where from last, and his
occupation as prescribed in the 3d article of the Colonisation Law,
and he will at the same time take the oath prescribed by the 3d
article of the instructions to the <persName>Commissioner </persName>to support the federal
and state Constitution and the General and State Laws of his
<placeName>adopted Country</placeName>, his name will then be entered in the <placeName>register book
of the Colony</placeName> and from that time and not before he will be considered
an <persName>applicant</persName>, and as such entitled by Law to the priviledges granted
to the <persName>Colonists</persName>&#8212;the oath must be taken before the <persName>Commissioner </persName>or
in his Absence before the <persName>Alcalde</persName>.</p>

<p>Art 2d after Complying with the foregoing Article and receiving
a permission in Writing from the <persName>Empresario </persName>to select <placeName>Land </placeName>as one
of the <persName>Colonists </persName>he will proceed to make his selection on 
<placeName>unappropriated Lands</placeName> and give notice at the <placeName>office of the <persName>Empresario</persName></placeName> of his
selection Within 30 days after the date of his permission in order
that an entry may be made of the same and instructions issued to the
<persName>surveyors </persName>to survey it as the Law and their instructions require the
<persName>applicant </persName>will also at this time present his petition to the 
<persName>Commissioner </persName>on stamp paper in due form and in Spanish.</p>

<p>Art 3d On the presentation of the petition as stated in the 
foregoing article satisfactory arrangements must be made to the 
<persName>Commissioner </persName>for the payment of fifteen Dollars to him, and five dollars into
the <placeName>office to <persName>Mr Samuel M Williams</persName></placeName> and on receipt of the title five
dollars more being for his services in extending and copying the
title, this is exclusive of stamp paper</p>

<p>Art 4th The <persName>Empresario </persName>as the <persName>general Agent of the Colonists</persName> has
procured at his own expense and Labor, the priviledge of ennabling
them to obtain Complete titles to land without the delay and expense
and perplexities of personal applications at the <placeName>seat of Govt</placeName> by each
individual&#8212;he has all the Labor of the translations&#8212;the 
examination of the <persName>surveyors </persName>returns and translating them, the receiving,
registering and locating of <persName>Colonists</persName>, also heavy responsibilities and<pb n="1107"/>
much Labor of a Complicated and perplexing Nature&#8212;and as his
Whole time must necessarily be devoted to the service of the 
<persName>Colonists</persName>, and under heavy expences, he in justice and equity has a right
to expect a proper remuneration from them and the 9th article of
the Colonisation Law gives him a legal right to exact it. his object
is to receive from the <persName>settlers </persName>a small recompence in Comparison with
the benefits he procures and the Labor he undergoes for them.</p>

<p>Every <persName>settler </persName>therefore who applies for admission into my <placeName>Colony</placeName>
will be bound to pay me Sixty dollars, if he is entitled to <placeName>a League
and thirty</placeName> if only to a quarter of a League&#8212; Ten Dollars of which
sum must be paid at the time of obtaining the permission spoken
of in the Second article, Twenty Dollars in Six months after the
date of said permission, and the balance Thirty Dollars in 18 months
from the date of sd permission.&#8212; the payment of which must be
secured by Note and lien on the Land granted.</p>

<p>5th In future No respect or preference will be given to any 
<placeName>settlement </placeName>improvement or selection whatever made by any person Who
shall not have Previously Complied with the foregoing regulations,
(excepting however those who have at this time actually made 
improvements who are allowed until the <date when="1825-10-01">first of October</date> to make 
application as required in the foregoing articles.</p>

<p>The payments on a quarter of a League must be made as follows
Ten Dollars on the receipt of the permission as aforementioned and
the balance in 6 months thereafter.</p>

<p>6th Should I be absent from this place <persName>Mr Samuel M Williams
</persName>is authorised to receive applications and grant permissions as 
prescribed in the first and second articles of these regulations</p>

<p>[Recapitulation]</p>

<p>on making application to the <persName>Empr</persName>__________________________  $10.</p>

<p>on presentation of petition which must be within 30 days after
application to the <persName>comr</persName>___________________________________    15.</p>

<p>to be paid into the <placeName>office </placeName>at the same time____________________      5.</p>

<p>on receipt of title to be pd. into the <placeName>office</placeName>______________________      5.</p>

<p>Stamp paper for original and copy__________________________      2.</p>

<p>Six months application to the <persName>Empro</persName>_______________________    20.</p>

<p>one year after ditto to do__________________________________    20.</p>

<p>18 months after do to do________________________________________  25.</p>

<p>4 years after date of title to the <persName>Ayto</persName>__________________________    10.</p>

<p>5 years after do to do_______________________________________    10.</p>

<p>6 years after do to do________________________________________  10.</p>

<p> 132.<pb n="1108"/></p>

<p>The above is exclusive of surveying fees which will be paid to the
<persName>surveyors </persName>at the rate of 4 Dollars pr. mile.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
