<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB2019">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Martin F Maher to Stephen F Austin, 06-04-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Martin F Maher</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-13">12-13-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Mr Mathew Adams
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1118-1119
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-06-04">06-04-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Administration of estate of David J. Marple.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName><date when="1825-06-04">June 4th 1825</date></p>
<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin Esqr.</persName></p>

<p>Sir Being appointed <persName>Agent </persName>by the <persName>widow of the Late David
J Marple</persName> (Deceased) to settle up his concerns in your <placeName>Colloney</placeName>,
and my Business here, not permitting my leaveing <placeName>Home </placeName>this season,
I have appointed <persName>Mr Mathew Adams my Atty</persName> to act for <persName>Mrs.
Marple</persName> in my place, and forward by this Gentleman <persName>Mrs Marple</persName>s
Power of Atty to me, and mine to him, together with a letter from
<persName>Mrs M</persName> to yourself, and sundry letters from <persName>Mr. Cummings</persName> and
<persName>Mr. Tomblison</persName> to her, relative to her <persName>late Husband</persName>s Personal 
Effects, <persName>Mrs. Marple</persName>, as also myself, rely with Implicit confidence on
your friendly aid and assistance in seeing that Justice is done hir and
Three <persName>Orphan Children</persName>, in Leequidating, the Accts of her <persName>late 
Husband</persName>, with these Gentlemen&#8212;I have instructed <persName>Mr Adams</persName> to be
soly guided by your instructions in all his movements with <persName>Mr 
Cummings</persName> and <persName>Tomblisons</persName></p>

<p>The <persName>Widow </persName>is very desirous to have the Deed of the Lands Granted
to her <persName>late Husband</persName> executed in doing of which her wish is to have
it so that an Equal Share will be comeing to each of his three
<persName>Children </persName>and that part allowed for herself separate&#8212;as her Object
at present is to get more <persName>settlers </persName>on it for a term of years untill 
herself and <persName>Children </persName>Can move on to it&#8212;I have promised <persName>Mrs Marple</persName>
to procure a number of <persName>settlers </persName>from <placeName>Urope </placeName>to go on to it next
seoson&#8212;Which shall Be Complyed with as soon as the Deeds are
Received, and I am Justafied in sending over for them; all of which
I trust will be accomplished on the return of <persName>Mr Adams</persName>.</p>

<p>I would also wish to have a statement from yourself, the terms on
which <persName>famileys </persName>wd Be admitted to settle on your <placeName>lands</placeName>&#8212;the articles
of produce that can be raised there, the Laws that you are Governed
by, if any Taxes are to be paid, what <persName>Mechanicks </persName>are most wanted,
with any other Information you think proper to communicate as
on sending for <persName>settlers </persName>for <placeName><persName>Mrs. Marple</persName>s tract</placeName> and the terms you
admitt <persName>settlers </persName>on will Justify me in encouraging twenty or thirty<pb n="1119"/>
additional <persName>Families </persName>to accompany them, I will do so And I have
very little Doubt, if once the Ice is broke there will be a number of
<persName>Families </persName>over every year. If on the receipt of <persName>Mrs. Marple</persName>s 
Documents and your Information on the subject of <persName>New settlers</persName> are
satisfactory, I calculate by <date n="Spring-1826">next spring</date> to accompany A number of
<persName>New Settlers</persName> to <placeName>yr Quarter </placeName>and spend afew weeks there untill they
get fairly under way&#8212;</p>

<p>I beg leave once more to call your attention to <persName>Mrs. Marple</persName>s
affairs as I assure you she is Left very destitute, and is wholly 
depending on her <persName>friends</persName>&#8212;which must be very distressing to a <persName>woman</persName>,
who never new before her <persName>Husband </persName>left home what it was to want
for any thing necessary to her comfort.</p>

<p>Hoping Shortly to hear from you and by that means, be 
instrumental in forwarding her agreeable News. I Remain Sir yrs. very
Respectfully</p>

<p><persName>Martin F Maher</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
