<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB2002">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>R M Carwright to Stephen F Austin, 05-25-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>R M Carwright</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-12">12-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Harrisburg, Buffalo Bayou, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1102-1103
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter/ Court Case</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-05-25">05-25-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asking instructions for procedure in selling property under an execution. Judiciary.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Harrisburg Buffalow Bayou</placeName><date when="1825-05-25"> May the 25th 1825</date></p>
<p><persName>Stephen F. Austen Esqr</persName>. Sir I have been appointed <persName>constable</persName>
to act in the case between <persName>cartwright </persName>and <persName>Nelson </persName>and <persName>Benjamin
Carico</persName> <placeName>on board of the schooner Mary</placeName>, and am without law or 
instructions you will do me a singular favour if you would send me
written Instructions so I may be able to do my duty I will give you a
copy of the Execution and letter from the <persName>Alcalde</persName></p>

<p>Messrs, <persName>H. Cartwright</persName> 
"           <persName>Nelson </persName>
Vs 
<persName>Benjamin Carico</persName> &amp;
<persName>Schooner Mary</persName> </p>

<p><placeName>Austins Colony District of San Jacinto
</placeName>the <persName>Constable of said  <placeName>District</placeName></persName> is hereby
commanded to seize and Expose to public
sale according to law the property of 
<persName>Benjamin Carico</persName> the <persName>defendant </persName>in the above
suit or so much thereof as may be necessary to pay <persName>Jessie H, 
Cartwright</persName> and <persName>Jessie Nelson the plaintiff</persName> in the above suit the sum of
five hundred and forty two dollars and costs of suit being the amount
of a judgement entered in my <placeName>office </placeName>on the <date when="1825-05-21">21st day of May 1825
</date>against said <persName>Carico </persName>in favour of <persName>Jesse H Cartwright</persName> and <persName>Jesse Nel-<pb n="1103"/>
son</persName> and should the said <persName>Carico </persName>have no property the <persName>Constable </persName>is
commanded to take the Body of said <persName>Carico </persName>and bring him to me at
my <placeName>office   </placeName>Given the <date when="1825-05-21">21 day of May 1825</date></p>

<p><persName>Humphry Jackson</persName></p>
<p><persName>Mr Robert Cartwright</persName></p>

<p>Dear Sir <persName>Mr. Straing</persName> has handed me an <placeName>advertisment </placeName>for the
property which you have Executed of <persName>Capt Carico</persName>, I think you are
rather too premature I think you ought to have waited to the ten
day was expired that was allowed him to find security I have got
no law respecting this point I only give it as my opinion it was my
intention when it was issued and it is my impression yet that you
ought then to go no farther than execute to the ten days was expired
that was allowed him to find security for an appeal.</p>

<p><persName>Mr. Strange</persName> has stated to me that you wished to know if you
ought to have the property valued. I have now [no] law 
respecting it I give it as my opinion that it ought if you sell at 
<placeName>harrisburgh </placeName>and the property <placeName>on board of the vessel</placeName> I think the property
ought to be present at the sale if it could be got there it does not
look right to me to have them a part when it is possible to have
the property present I hope you will not allow or give reason for
a slur to be cast on the district it is the first execution that has
been Tride before me, I would have been more free to your <persName>brother</persName>
in giving my opinion the other day on the points I did not feel
right at my self to do any business at that time I am with 
Respect Yours</p>

<p><persName>Humphry Jackson</persName></p>

<p>you will pleas in struct how to act in all cases   I expect a part of
the property will be claimed by <persName>capt. Allin</persName> as I have heard he did
will enclose an <placeName>advertisement </placeName>to you if you think it best I will have
a part of the property brought to this place   I have kept two young
men on board to gard and take care of the schooner and cargo they
the <persName>captain </persName>have ruin some flour and whiskey and other property
since the attachment has been served and sold it    [Instruct me]
whether it is lawfull for me to keep [a guard if ?] I delay the sale
longer than is needed [the reason for ?] giving so short a time was
to save ex[pense the sale is ?] at this place because there is a gra[te
many of people com- ?]ing and I knew if I sold on board [there
would be very few  ?] <persName>biders </persName>to bring it here would so of caused
[some trouble  ?] tobacco and flour and whiskey and whole bo [at
. . .]   might be brought without much  expense . . . [answer]   it
and forward it to me as soon as possible</p>

<p>your obedient servant                               </p>
<p><persName>R. M. Cartwright</persName></p>

<p><persName>Debity Constable</persName> [appointed by ?]</p>

<p><persName>Humphrey Jackson</persName></p>




        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
