<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB2111">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Mateo Ahumada, 09-10-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-26">12-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mateo Ahumada
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1197-1198
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-09-10">09-10-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning plan of procedure against Comanches and their allies. Austin's desire to maintain neutrality.   Karankawa hostilities resumed.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>I received, <date when="1825-09-09">yesterday</date>, your two communications of the <date when="1825-08-21">21st </date>and
<date when="1825-08-26">26th of August last</date>; the first, instructing me to gather the <persName>largest
force possible</persName> and to march immediately and chastise the <persName>Tahuacanos</persName>
and <persName>Tahuiases </persName><placeName>in their villages</placeName>; the second countermanding that
order in consequence of a report received by you, to the effect that
the <persName>hostile Commanches</persName> were in those <placeName>villages</placeName>, and might encounter
us in considerable number, were we to attack them at present. I
had received a similar report from some <persName>hunters</persName>, and was also 
apprized that the <persName>Commanches</persName>, <persName>Tahuacanos</persName>, <persName>Tahuiases </persName>and <persName>Cherokees</persName>
have made a treaty of peace and close alliance. I cannot say whether
this last report deserves credit, but it seems to me very probable,<pb n="1198"/>
considering the antecedents which I have communicated to <persName>His
Lordship, the Political Chief of the Department</persName>.</p>

<p>Some <persName>Americans </persName>recently arrived from the <placeName>Tahuacano villages</placeName>,
told me, that the <persName>Chiefs of that tribe</persName> assured them it was not their
intention to be hostile with the <persName>Americans</persName>, that the last 
depredations were committed by some <persName>Tahuiases </persName>of <placeName>a village situated far
up on Red River</placeName>, that they, (The <persName>Tahuacanos</persName>) wished to make a
treaty of peace with the <persName>Americans</persName>.</p>

<p>If the proposal I have made to the <persName>Political Chief of the 
Department</persName>, in my communication of the <date when="1825-09-08">8th Instant</date>, is approved, I expect
there will be no difficulty in preserving these <persName>settlers </persName>from <persName>Indian</persName>
hostilities, if we avail ourselves of the friendly disposition of these
<persName>Indians </persName>towards the <persName>Americans</persName>. However, in this, as in any other
case, we shall remain at the disposal of the <persName>government</persName>, ready to obey
and execute its orders; nothing but the critical circumstances in
which we are placed, could induce me to think of a proposal of the
kind. I request you to favor me with as early an answer on this
subject as is possible, to enable me to take, without loss of time, the
necessary steps either for war, or for neutrality with the <persName>Indians</persName>.
It is not possible, at present, to raise a sufficient force to attack the
<placeName>Indian villages</placeName>, owing to the number of our <persName>sick men</persName>, and, in 
<date n="10-xx-1825">October</date>, the <persName>Indians </persName>will leave their <placeName>villages </placeName>to go buffalo hunting; so
that if war, or peace is determined upon, it will be necessary to start
before the <date when="1825-10-15">15th of October</date>.</p>

<p>In consequence of the continuous hostilities of the <persName>Carancahuase
Indians</persName>, and considering the conditions of the treaty of peace we
made with them at <placeName>La Bahia</placeName>, in <date n="09-xx-1824">September last</date>; which was broken
by them without any cause whatever, and <persName>one of their parties</persName> having
lately shown themselves between the <placeName>Colorado </placeName>and <placeName>Brazos</placeName>, and in
the <placeName>vicinity of some of the settlements</placeName> making hostile manifestations,
I have been compelled in view of the security of our people, to give
positive orders to the <persName>Lieutenant of Militia</persName> <placeName>in that section</placeName>, to pursue
and kill all those <persName>Indians </persName>wherever they are found, with the 
exception of <persName>Prudencia's party</persName>, provided said <persName>Prudencia </persName>remains <placeName>West
of Buffalo Bayou</placeName>, because it would be impossible to make a 
distinction between <persName>his people and the others</persName>, if they continue mixed 
together in <placeName>our vicinity</placeName>. Which I communicate to you in order that
you may be pleased to approve this measure, or to give me such
orders and instructions as you deem proper, and which shall be
strictly obeyed.</p>

<p>God and Liberty.                                            <persName>Estevan F. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName>, <date when="1825-09-10">September 10th, 1825</date>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
