<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB2064">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Jared D Groce to Hyde and Merit, 07-19-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Jared D Groce</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-22">12-22-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Hyde 
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Merit
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brasos, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1151-1152
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-07-19">07-19-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-22" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Dr. Imla Keep has abused his confidence, deceived Hyde and Groce, buying goods on credit and charging same to Groce.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Brassos <hi rend="italic">Texas </hi></placeName><date when="1825-07-19">July 19th 1825</date></p>
<p><persName>Messrs. Hyde &amp; Merit</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>Doctor Imla Keep</persName> has just arrived from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> with some
goods&#8212;and let me have the greatest part of them for which I paid
him&#8212;by crediting him for money that I placed in his hands to purchase 
some Articles for me. I likewise gave him Authority
to receive for me a considerable Amount of money&#8212;which he 
received, and made use of and has not returned me one cent after
buying the goods of the <persName>Doctor </persName>and paying for them as above stated
I found out he had not paid money for the goods&#8212;but got them on
a credit, and made use of my <hi rend="italic">name</hi> in getting them he was not
authorized to do so&#8212;and he is a man that never will have it in his
power to use my name in that way&#8212; And I was much surprised to
see you had allowed him the liberty of acting so with you&#8212;for he had
not my name on paper&#8212;except he wrote it or got some one to do it.
neither was he authorized either verbally or in any other manner
whatever to use my name&#8212; it is true, about twelve months since I
promised to give him a birth as an <persName>overseer </persName>on one of my <placeName>plantations</placeName>,
on conditions&#8212;he would perform certain acts and come out <date n="Winter - 1824">last
winter</date>&#8212;but he has disappointed me in every case, and not come
untill now, and now, without my money. If he had complied I
would have employed him, and was to give him one tenth of the
profits of sd <placeName>plantation </placeName>after all expenses were paid, he is now 
insisting on me to employ him, for he says he is anxious to make
money to pay you and myself.</p>

<p>I have a right to find fait of all the confidence, I placed in him,
but was more displeased when I found out he was tempering with<pb n="1152"/>
my name, than any thing else. I have given him no employment as
yet, and am so much displeased&#8212;I do not know whither I will or
not, the <hi rend="italic"><persName>doctor </persName></hi>appears to be very desirous to get in some business&#8212;
to make money to pay you and myself, it is a duty I owe my 
feelings to notify you of this immediately&#8212; I have no credit in
<placeName>Orleans</placeName>, for I sent my <persName>son </persName>there to purchase a few articles&#8212; he got
a letter from<persName> Mr. James Brown</persName> of <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>, and had the goods
charged to him&#8212;and I have to pay <persName>Brown</persName>; Why did I do this?
because <persName>Keep</persName>&#8212;as I heard, had made way with my money&#8212;and
could not get the articles I wrote for but in <placeName>Orleans </placeName>he informed
my <persName>son </persName>he could get such and such articles&#8212; And then applied to
my <persName>son</persName>, to go his security&#8212;and he could get what he pleased it
made my <persName>son </persName>very angry for if I wanted a credit I did not want
any assistance with his credit for the last time I saw <persName>Keep</persName>, untill
now, he affirmed if I would send in my <persName>son</persName>&#8212;he would raise my
money at <placeName>Alexandria</placeName>&#8212;and go in company with my <persName>son </persName>to <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName>, and purchase the articles I wanted, and then he, <persName>Keep</persName>,
would come round by water with them, and my <persName>son </persName>by land&#8212;and
bring my money, that is, the overplus&#8212;that <persName>Keep </persName>had after buying
the goods, he advanced my son ten Dollars out of thousands that I
had placed in his hands&#8212;and said that was half what he had.</p>

<p><persName>Jared E. Groce</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Messrs. Hyde and Merit</persName>.&#8212;<placeName>New Orleans</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
