<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB2093">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Richard R Royall to Stephen F Austin, 08-23-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Richard R Royall</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-26">12-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Tuscumbia, Alabama</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Department of Texas, United Mexican States</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1183-1185
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-08-23">08-23-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">His report of Texas has caused great excitement and men of character and large estates are considering emigration. Asks particularly about status of slavery and religious freedom. False reports circulating about conditions in Texas.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>United States of America</placeName></p>
<p>Town of <placeName>Tuscumbia</placeName>.    <placeName>State of Alabama</placeName>.</p>

<p><date when="1825-08-23">Augt 23rd 1825</date></p>
<p>Hon. Sir</p>

<p>After a slow and tedious travel of two months I arrived at home
on the <date when="1825-07-19">19th July</date> haveing been unwell on the Road my Return and
report of the <placeName>country </placeName>caused considerable excitement for emigration
which has renewed vigourously since the arrival of <persName>Majr Morgan A
Heard</persName> who passed lately and remained about a week with me and
in the <placeName>neighbourhood </placeName>many <persName>gentlemen possessing Large Estates
and of high character</persName> speak with much interest of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and 
several have determined to visit your <placeName>Colony </placeName>before <date n="Spring-1826">spring </date>I think
probably the <persName>Hon. E. Ellis</persName>, and my <persName>Father-in-Law</persName>- will be of the
latter number a letter from you to me (as frequent inquiries are
made of me about the <placeName>country</placeName>) relative to a few particulars that
make the most important objections to the country with the <persName>public</persName>,
would I have no doubt tend much to their removal as many of
them exist only in name and others arise from false Rumour&#8212;It is
the natural disposition of human nature to strive to appear wise and
when persons return from a distant <placeName>country </placeName>have seen a little and
acquired but an imperfect knowledge of the <placeName>country</placeName>, as there is no
person commonly to contradict; they undertake to explain every
enquiry that is made of them which lead to many errors and false
rumours relative to the <placeName>country</placeName>; as I passed through <placeName>Arkansas </placeName>I saw
the report of a <persName>travellor </persName>through <placeName>Texas </placeName>(published in a <placeName>Paper </placeName>printed
at <placeName>Little Rock</placeName>) which stated that the <placeName>Colorado </placeName>had overflowed its
<placeName>Banks </placeName>totally this <date n="Spring-1825">last spring</date> and the corn <placeName>on that River</placeName> being all lost
and game very scarce the <persName>settlers </persName>must leave the <placeName>country </placeName>or continue
as formerly to resort to the disagreeable necessity of living on the
flesh of wild horses. The most Interesting subjects to the people
here appear to be that of Slavery and Religion the latter being a
constitutional matter I have no expectation of as early a change
But would like to know what is the present state or prospect relative
to the admission of slavery and If any law has been passed on the
subject would thank you to favor me with an extract and for myself
I would be glad to hear if the <date n="Fall-1825">fall season</date> has been healthy, has the<pb n="1184"/>
drought done any Injury this <date n="Fall-1825">fall </date>to crops, has there been any change
in the colonization sistem, what <placeName>parts of the country</placeName> are granted or
contracted for, has any permission been given within the <placeName>ten leagues
of the coast of the Gulf</placeName> and <placeName>twenty of the U States</placeName> as prohibited in
the law of <persName>congress</persName>, is there any <placeName>Cotton gins</placeName> erected in the <placeName>Colony</placeName>,
has any arrangement been made at <placeName>Orleans </placeName>for a draw Back for
Cotton reshipped from that place, and has there been much increase
of emigration and what in your opinion the <placeName>good lands of the colony</placeName>
can be bought second handed for in money down and the price of
corn this season as many fears exist here about provisions in settling
that <placeName>country</placeName>.</p>

<p>In my route home I passed through <placeName>Arkansas </placeName>and arrested the
<persName>four negroes</persName> sold by <persName>Col. Pettus</persName> to <persName>Boatright </persName>and they are now
pending in law at <placeName>little Rock</placeName> and I expect there in the hands of
the <persName>sheriff </persName>In doing this I acted more from motives of duty than
Interest as I never expected to be fully paid for all the trouble
and expense I have been and must necessarily be at in the matter
I have assured <persName>Judge Ellis</persName> of the security and certainty of the mules
contracted for and the land and <persName>negroes </persName>as is recorded in your office
he appeared somewhat disapointed but satisfied with the compromise
he said he had no disposition to consume <persName>Col. Pettus</persName> though he
has suffered very much and as for myself I would be more than glad
to know that he will meet the contract an[d] afterwards do well
as he treated me with gentlemanly hospitality while at his <placeName>house</placeName>
I should be glad to hear from you as soon as possible relative to my
various enquiries and name also the <persName>Col. Pettus</persName>' prospects of 
meeting his contract and If any thing has taken place that may in any
wise effect my land Claims in <placeName>Texas </placeName>I would like to lift one or both
and locate them anew but I expect I would not be suffered. I will
see you in the course of the <date n="xx-xx-1826">next year</date> I hope before <date n="Summer-1826">summer </date>and
have no other calculations but to reside in your <placeName>Colony </placeName>or <placeName>on the
Banks or Chicholite River</placeName> offer my respects to <persName>Mr. Saml. Williams</persName>
your <persName>Brother </persName>and tend my thanks to <persName>Capt Gray</persName> for his friendly
disposition to me while in the <placeName>country </placeName>I would like to write to <persName>Capt
Gray</persName> but have nothing to write of much interest. I hope the horse
I let him have is doing well, I left one of mine <placeName>on the Route</placeName> and
the other died since my arrival at home tell him I would be more
than glad to hear from him and as the route is long and uncertain
please answer this immediately and then I will think long of the
time before it can Reach me, on the great length of time I was from
home I wrote many times yet only two letters Reached my <placeName>family</placeName>
crops of Cotton here are short Haveing suffered very much from
Drought and the Rust, the price is said to have fallen a little yet it
bears a fine price.   Many <persName>families </persName>here would join a <persName>company </persName>to go<pb n="1185"/>
to that <placeName>country </placeName>but the <persName>higher class of men</persName> generally prefer to go
and act for themselves as the cost of the travel is no object to them
and the fatigue bears no comparative weight to the certainty of
Being suited.</p>

<p><persName>R. R. Royall.  </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:]<persName> Hon. Stephen F. Austin</persName>. <placeName>Department of Texas of
The United Mexican States</placeName>&#8212;</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
