<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3080">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James E. B. Austin to Emily M. Perry, 02-28-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James E. B. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="CLS">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Cameron L. Sinclair</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-16">07-16-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Emily M. Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Potosi, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1268-1269
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-02-28">02-28-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Biographical. Rapid immigration.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1826-02-28">Feby 28th 1826</date></p>
<p>My Dear <persName>Sister</persName></p>

<p>I improve an opportunity which offers itself by a gentleman of
sending this into the <placeName>United States</placeName>, and I hope you will receive it
in due time.</p>

<p>A short time since I returned to this place; from which I
have been absent two or three months on a place down on this <placeName>river</placeName>
where I am opening a <persName>farm </persName>and building a <hi rend="italic">Cotton Gin</hi>, I shall remain here no longer than the absence of <persName>Stephen</persName> compels me he is
absent on a topographical tour to <placeName>Galveston</placeName> to exicute a comission
given him by the <persName>Government</persName>.    I expect him in<date when="1826-03-02"> one or two days</date>&#8212;</p>

<p>On my return to this <placeName>place </placeName>I found letters from you which gave
me much pleasure and satisfaction. I hope you will not attribute
my long silence to any thing but the remote distance and insolated
state that I have been in for the last two or three months&#8212;Nothing
would distress me more my Dr <persName>Emily</persName> than for me to imagine that
you should entertain the smallest doubt that I had abated my
affection for you in the least or that I did not take and feel the
deepest interest for your happiness, What has this world to endear
me to it but my <persName>Sister</persName> and her lovely <persName>family</persName>? altho debared the
inexpressible pleasure and satisfaction of enjoying her society (and
the <hi rend="italic">sweet prattle</hi> of her little ones) I sincerely hope and flatter myself
that the period is not far distant when we shall all be reunited, (if
not under the same roof) so near that we can form a social circle
and " far from the scenes of strife <hi rend="italic">pass the innocent</hi> jest, and
chaunt the merry glee"&#8212;then we can remind each other of "<hi rend="italic">Auld
Lang Syne</hi> " and congratulate ourselves that not withstanding the
many visissitudes and difficulties we have encountered (and the
great and heartfelt satisfaction afforded to the <persName>Enemies of our house
</persName>by its downfall) <hi rend="italic">we have proved to the <placeName>world</placeName></hi> that <hi rend="italic">regardless</hi> of
them all&#8212;We <hi rend="italic">have</hi> accomplished an enterprize that will perpetuate
our name and place it with honor on the page of history It will
then be our turn to triumph&#8212;shall we do so ? I can see a sentiment
of just Resentment pervades your Breast&#8212;but I also see a generous
principle a <hi rend="italic">something</hi> so noble rising still above that&#8212;checking the
first impulse of anger&#8212;and appealing to reason to treat the past <pb n="1269"/>
with silent contempt&#8212;Our old <persName>Enemies </persName>will in a few years more
dwindle into insignificance and would lick the dust from our shoes
to gain a favor&#8212;It will then be a satisfaction a "heavenly satisfaction ["] for me to assist them&#8212;That is the revenge which will be
sweet to me&#8212;</p>

<p>I was truly shocked to hear of the murder committed on the person
of <persName>Wm M Perry</persName> I receivd the letter of <persName>Saml Perry</persName> to my <persName>brother</persName>
informing him of the circumstance and containing an advertisement,
you may assure him that every exertion in our power will be made
to apprehend the <persName>Villian</persName> that he may receive the punishment he so
justly merits.</p>

<p>We have nothing new the <placeName>Colony</placeName> wears a more flourishing aspect
at this time than it ever has before, there is a prospect of an overflowing Emigration this <date n="Spring - 1826">spring </date>and next <date n="Fall- 1826">fall </date>of some of the most
respectable men in the <placeName>United States</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Mr. Andrews</persName> has arrived safe I have not seen him yet&#8212;his <persName>family</persName>
is well and much pleased with the <placeName>Country</placeName>.</p>

<p>I wish you to inform <persName>Mr Perry</persName> that by a <persName>Mr Benjamin Milam</persName>
(Brother of <persName>Milam</persName> at the <placeName>Mines</placeName>) who lately arrived from the <placeName>city
of Mexico</placeName>&#8212;I learned that <persName>Dr Baldwin</persName> has accumulated a handsome
fortune in that <placeName>Country</placeName>; he has purchased a <placeName>coffee plantation </placeName>on the
<placeName>River Guazicualco</placeName> on the <placeName>Pacific Ocean</placeName> where he now [is?] and has
gained the confidence and esteem of all who know him. Also <persName>Cousin
Henry Austin</persName> lives in the <placeName>city of Jalapa</placeName> (between <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and <placeName>Vera
Cruz</placeName>) engaged in the <persName>commission </persName>business&#8212;</p>

<p>Remember me to all my <persName>friends </persName>and <persName>acquaintances</persName>&#8212;write me often
my Dr <persName>Sister</persName>&#8212;you must know that anything from the pen of my
<persName>sister</persName> to me is interesting, kiss all the <persName>little ones</persName> for me, tell <persName>Joel</persName>
and <persName>Austin</persName> their <persName>uncles</persName> are much pleased with their improvement in
writing we shall soon Expect to secure a specimen of their writing
in the form of a letter.</p>

<p>Remember me particularly to <persName>Mr. Perry</persName> This letter must be
my excuse for not writing to him.</p>

<p><persName>Jas E B Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mrs Emily M. Perry</persName> <placeName>Potosi. Missouri</placeName></p>

<p>P. S.   I am not married yet nor is <hi rend="italic">there</hi> any <hi rend="italic">likelihood at present</hi>.</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
