<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3105">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Kerr to Stephen F. Austin, 11-11-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Kerr</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-14">08-14-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Lavaca, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1501-1502
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-11-11">11-11-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Troubles of DeWitt's colonists with Martin De Leon.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Labaca</placeName> <date when="1826-11-11">11. Nov. 1826</date> 2 O'clock p. m.&#8212;
Dear <persName>Colo</persName></p>

<p>I have just Rd and read your of the <date when="1826-11-08">8th</date> Inst by <persName>Mr. Brackin</persName>.
I am confined to my Pallet, and have been for several Days given
out by the <persName>spectators</persName>&#8212;I am now on the mend and by being proped up
etc. I have undertaken to write, I have 6 large blisters all raw and
runing yellow matter etc.</p>

<p>I came here with my Cart, <persName>black man</persName> and <persName>two <hi rend="italic">white</hi> strange Gent</persName>,
who overtook me on the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>, on the evenig of&#8212;<date when="1826-11-01">1st</date>&#8212;found all
well, and in good spirits&#8212;In a few minutes a man by the name of
<persName>Smith</persName> came under whip, from the <placeName>Guadaloupe</placeName> who stated that
<persName>Delion</persName>, and <persName>son</persName> were a Coming with the <persName>indians</persName> to cut of the <persName>white
people</persName> as far as the <placeName>Colorado</placeName>&#8212;It would far exceed the limits of a
letter to detail all he said in relation to <persName>Delion</persName>s threats and those of
his son <persName>fernander</persName>. in fact they were alarming as a <persName>person</persName> (Unknown
to me tho said to be respectable) has as I am informed by the <persName>Alcalde</persName>
here made Oath that <persName>Delion</persName> had lured the <persName>Indians</persName> to come and Kill
all the <persName>Americans</persName> here, and <persName>Mrs. Trudeau</persName> has told me that she
hirself will swear that she several times heard <persName>Delion</persName> aver that he
would have <persName>Dewitt</persName>s head and that he would take it tied to his saddle
to the <persName>Guadaloupe</persName>&#8212;The many threats; the manner in which they
came here; and the <persName>persons </persName>who made Those threats Gave alarme to
the <persName>new settlers</persName> here and altho I myself are not easily alarmed yet
I confess that I scarcely new what to be about;&#8212;There was no order
made to fire from our <placeName>station </placeName>untill we were first fired on.</p>

<p>About this time I went to <persName>Smith</persName> and asked him many questions etc.    he then told me that <persName>Moncholes</persName> of <placeName>Labihia</placeName> and his <persName>troops</persName><pb n="1502"/>
were coming on with <persName>Delion</persName>,&#8212;I then told the <persName>Colo</persName> and all the <persName>people</persName>
that would hear me that there was no danger, and that I knew that no
<persName>Indians</persName> were coming and that I felt confident the <persName>commendant</persName> had
orders from <persName>Govt </persName>etc but the people were still alarmed. <persName>Dewitt</persName>
Often told them they must not oppose Govt and that all orders
coming from Govt must and should be obeyed, for fear some
accident might happen I took a <persName>few men</persName> in the night and went Some
Distance along the road in order to meet the <persName>Commendant</persName> and to
inform him the news that we had, heard, and that the <persName>people </persName>here
were afraid he was coming to put them to death without mercy etc
When the evening Star Disappeared I came back and again told the
<persName>men</persName> there was no danger and for them to be at rest, that I knew <persName>Mr.
Moncholes</persName> to be an <persName>officer, of the Govt</persName> and a Gent, and I then went
to sleep for the ballance of the night. In the <date when="1826-11-02">morning </date>the order
again was given by the <persName>Colo</persName> for no man to fire on or offer to fire,
without we were first fired on. I and the <persName>Colo</persName> went down the <placeName>river</placeName>
to select a place for my <placeName>camp</placeName>&#8212;when we had got a short distance, a
<persName>boy</persName> came on horse back and told us the <persName>indians</persName> were coming&#8212;we
returned on the way to the <placeName>house </placeName>when the <persName>Colo</persName> Asked me to go and
meet the <persName>Commendant</persName> and having my gun, I set it down by a tree
and went on foot as fast as I could to meet the <persName>troop</persName> (<persName>Several men</persName>
from the <placeName>Station </placeName>followed me with their ares [arms?]who layed
them down and wished I would let them to go with me) which I
refused to do and told them as they were <persName>strangers </persName>etc to go back;
that the <persName>Commendant</persName> and all knew me, and that I was not afraid to
go by my self&#8212;I did so and meet them some distance from the <placeName>house</placeName>
and shook hands with several; I told the <persName>Commendant</persName> that the
<persName>people </persName>here were afraid he had come to kill etc&#8212;he told me no that
he had Orders from the <persName>Chief</persName> etc to <persName>Dewitt</persName>, he road on to the <placeName>house</placeName>
and demanded the guns to be put away etc, the <persName>Colo</persName> before I got to
the <placeName>house </placeName>had meet them, and altho he repeatedly told the <persName>men</persName> to
put away the guns, the <persName>men</persName> were in such confusion that it was for
some time before they could be made to know that they would not
be Instantly put to death, the armes were Laid away and on (I
believe the<date when="1826-11-03"> next day)</date> they were taken by <persName>Delion</persName> and put under
guard and have since been sent away to await the order of the <persName>Chief</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>Commendant</persName> told me that he expect the arms would all be sent
back in a few days etc that he would leave some <persName>troops </persName>here to guard
us untill the thing would be Determined. He took <persName>Dewitt</persName> of with
him <persName>5 or 6 others</persName>&#8212;Some times <persName>Dewitt</persName> was told that he was a <persName>prisoner</persName>,
and at other times that he was free etc. my strength failes and I am
obliged to lie down, my head is like a whirl wind and my friend
adiew.</p>

<p><persName>James Kerr</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Colo S. F. Austin</persName> <placeName>Sn. Felipe De Austin</placeName></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
