<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3009">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>J. Erwin to Stephen F. Austin, 09-30-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>J. Erwin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-05-21">05-21-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Shelbyville, Tennessee</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1213-1216
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-09-30">09-30-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-05-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Character of Jared E. Groce, and the business of Erwin, Groce &amp; Co. in the United States.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><persName>S F Austin Eqr. </persName> <placeName>Shelbyville</placeName> <date when="1825-09-30">Sept. 30 1825</date></p>

<p>Sir Altho I have not the pleasure of your personal acquaintance, I take the liberty of writing you, the object is more to reply
to your letter of <date when="1825-02-18">Feby 18th</date> to my <persName>father</persName>, than to make any explanations of our former business with <persName>Mr. Groce</persName> for whom you express
so lively an interest&#8212;how he has created that feeling I am unable
to say. I am too conversant with your character, too well enformed
of your capacity and descrimination, for a moment to believe that
you can be deceived in the man. Three days of acquaintance to a
man of intelligence, will show, <persName>Groce</persName> to be a vain foolish Gasconading
Bragadocia a man of considerable energy or rather industry, acute
and subtle in small matters, ready to see and take an advantage,
ambitious, and vain, the latter two qualities so predominate as to
expose him readily to an <persName>observer</persName>, he is entirely void of the high
and honorable feelings of a gentleman, destitute of principles, and
without the least pretensions to credit for veracity or integrity of
character, all this can not have escaped your attention, and if so
how can you give attention to Statements made by him affecting the
character and standing of men of Reputation Why hesitate about
the opinions you seem at a loss to form about transactions between
such men and a Renegade like <persName>Groce</persName>&#8212;What evidence have you to
create a doubt&#8212;Whatever <persName>Groce</persName> may tell you to the contrary, I now
tell you I can substantiate by <persName>Groce</persName>'s own hand writing that up to
the last transaction of business that ever took place between us in
any shape whatever, that there was no difficulty or complaint and
that I have his rects in full up to the latest transaction signed
and sealed by him acknowledging that all was satisfactorily settled
from the beginning of the world to that date, it was then and
on that very day&#8212;in order to bring the entire business of <persName>A Erwin Groce and Co</persName> to a close that we agreed to divide amongst us individually the remaining out debts which were all in the hands of
<persName>Col. McKenni</persName> of <placeName>Augusta Geo</placeName>. and amounted to $30,000&#8212;it was
at the earnest intreaty of <persName>Groce</persName>, himself&#8212;that <persName>McKenni</persName> divided
this amt into three equal sums say $10,000&#8212;and took <persName>Groce</persName>'s individual notes for $10,000, my note for $10,000 and my <persName>father</persName>'s note
also for $10,000&#8212;I refused to give my note at first until <persName>Groce</persName> begged
me to do so, urged the object of a final settlement&#8212;his rect in full&#8212;
and finally agreed to assist <hi rend="italic">me</hi> who was then void of means to pay
my note, he gave his note payt at such time as would allow two
crops of cotton to intervene and promised <persName>McKenni</persName> on his Honor, <pb n="1214"/>that his note would be punctually paid&#8212;what was the result, my <persName>father</persName>
paid his note, I paid mine, and <persName>Groce</persName> <hi rend="italic">runaway</hi>&#8212;and Left his endorser to pay that note has fallen in my hands&#8212;the individual
note of <persName>J E Groce</persName>&#8212;2 notes of $5000 each which I did expect to have
collected thro your assistance as I learned you intended to pursue
a course of policy, not calculated to encourage flying renegade debtors who contract debts in this <placeName>country</placeName> and fly to your <placeName>colony</placeName>&#8212;
I had heard that you as <persName>alcalde </persName>would enforce contracts&#8212;and
I accordingly sent my claim to <persName>Maj Thomas</persName> for that purpose&#8212;If
it is contrary to your regulations of course I have no course of
complaint&#8212;If its only justice and truth you wish to arrive at I
have ample Means&#8212;to establish all I wish by testimony that would
outweigh the verbal statements of <persName>Groce</persName>&#8212;The fact is <persName>Groce</persName> and
myself quarrelled But not about our business&#8212;at our last meeting
to his face I gave him the same character, I now give you of him,
which he patiently heard. If I had injured him why not then assert
his wrongs he had acted ungentlemanly and I told him so&#8212;he felt
it&#8212;he left this part of the <placeName>country </placeName>and the next news I heard he had
runaway I remained firm at my post&#8212;I have settled up the old
business of <persName>A E G &amp; Co</persName>&#8212;<persName>Groce</persName> complains of suits&#8212;I have been
sued too But I have successfully defended those suits-&#8212;and so might
<persName>Groce</persName> have done. But he chose to fly his <placeName>country</placeName> as the safest and
most glorious mode of settling matters&#8212;he pretends to you and
to the world that he thot I had an agency in having him sued he
knew better, and now knows better, I have tendered my assistance
in defending&#8212;How could I suffer him made liable without becoming
so&#8212;you say My <persName>Brotherinlaw</persName> was selected as the channel&#8212;that is
also false&#8212;<persName>Mr Crawford< the <persName>partner of my Brotherinlaw</persName> Brot the
suits, he was selected by the other <persName>parties </persName>because he is the most
eminent <persName>Lawyer </persName>in that <placeName>State</placeName>, and better able to conduct a Bad
cause&#8212;If <persName>Groce</persName> had remained at his post he could have easily
defeated as I have done the claim-</p>
<p>But there is one claim he can not defeat that is his individual
notes given to <persName>McKenni</persName>&#8212;Now in the hands of <persName>Thomas</persName>&#8212;those he
must and shall pay&#8212;or remain exiled from his <placeName>native Country</placeName> he
can not pretend to have any offsets against this claim. If my eye
was upon him he could not have the assurance to deny this to you I
know he will tell Some other tale, he will say anything that best
suits his purpose; and I have myself seen him voluntarily Subscribe
to an oath&#8212;which made me shudder&#8212;which I can any day produce&#8212;
these things are only mentioned to give you more particular information of his character and standing while in the <placeName>U States</placeName>&#8212; and
altho you have a much better opportunity of observing his course <pb n="1215"/>in <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;than me, I can not help remarking that even there he
gives you some small cause at least to suspect if all I hear be true,
that he is not very particular in his conduct&#8212;or select in his <persName>associates </persName>and <persName>coadjuters</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>The last remark Brings to my mind his Celebrated letter written
to my <persName>father</persName> <date n="xx-xx-1824">last year</date> by the assistance of his <persName>friend </persName>and <persName>Secty </persName>
<persName>Mr Williams</persName> who acted also as a certificate man and certified that all
<persName>Groce</persName> wrote was true, which he must have been well qualified to do&#8212;
as it related to transactions with men, the fellow&#8212;had never seen&#8212;
But who is <persName>Mr. Williams</persName>&#8212;a Renegade also&#8212;who fled to avoid capital
punishment&#8212;his friend also and the inmate of his House from
<placeName>Missouri</placeName> whose name I do not recollect&#8212;who fled for murder&#8212;<persName>Doct Keep</persName>&#8212;quite as well known&#8212;these are his <persName>associates </persName>his men of business&#8212;what can you expect from such a man&#8212;and is this the same
<persName>Mr Groce</persName>&#8212;who is to be so powerful in a chancery suit&#8212;who is to publish a Book&#8212;and demolish by a stroke of his pen all the <persName>Erwins</persName>&#8212;
Unfortunately for this Hero, who is mightiest when far off&#8212;the word
Renegade, would present itself in large letters in every page and
obliterate all he could say&#8212;to which might be added some equally
strong and true&#8212;I must now Sir&#8212;in justice to my own feelings
apologize to you for the tenor of this letter, and all I can say, is
that I feel I am writing to <persName>J E Groce</persName>, and not to <persName>S F Austin</persName>&#8212;and
I also feel that I am replying to <persName>J E Groce</persName> and not to <persName>S F Austin</persName>&#8212;
Because I have with much pleasure read other productions from you
to my <persName>father</persName> and others and I know that this now in question is not
your own legitimate offspring <persName>Groce</persName> may Borrow what plumage he
will, yet he will be <persName>Groce</persName> still&#8212;I know as well as if I had been at
your elbow&#8212;when you wrote that letter, that you did so by the importunity of <persName>Groce</persName> and that you were reluctantly urged to convey
ideas repugnant to your feelings&#8212;I write this with freedom and
frankness not to offend you, But to let you know I understand the
man, I know his object&#8212;he wants under pretence of settling old
disputes to make friends&#8212;But he can not be depended on, and there
is no use in reciving the acknowlegmt of so low minded a fellow&#8212;I
have only one word for him, that is I want the $10,000 and int&#8212;that
he owes me&#8212;and untill that is paid he may exert all his cunning for
I will reach him before I have done trying&#8212;thro some source or
other, and I should be much obliged by your reply at <placeName>Orleans</placeName>&#8212;saying
whether a just claim can be made under your regulations, that is
due to a <persName>Resident of the <placeName>U States</placeName></persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>If he will pay me this claim I have then done with him, as to any
suits vs. him now in <placeName>alabama</placeName> it only requires atention to set them
aside that are hot against him as one of the firm of <persName>A E Groce[<persName>A. Erwin, Groce &amp; Co.</persName>] and Co</persName> &#8212;I have already sent him word that If
he wants to see me, I am always in the winter to be found in <placeName>N.
Orleans</placeName>&#8212;where I am ready&#8212;to defend a suit in chancery&#8212;render
him personal satisfaction or receive $10,000 due me, and settle matters
and let him alone&#8212;either alternative is always before him&#8212;</p>

<p>From the Friendly intercourse that took place and continued
between you and my <persName>father</persName>, I had hoped soon to have had the pleasure of making your acquaintance&#8212;and that I might have some day
been able to have established an acquaintance with you beneficial to
both, which I yet hope may not be prevented by so unworthy an
object as <persName>Groce</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>J. Erwin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
