<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3041">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Emily M. Perry to Stephen F. Austin, 12-18-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Emily M. Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="CLS">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Cameron L. Sinclair</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-06-22">06-22-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mine a Burton, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1239-1241
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-12-18">12-18-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-06-22" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Biographical.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mine A Burton</placeName> <date when="1825-12-18">December 18th 1825</date>&#8212;</p>
<p>My Dear <persName>Brothers</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>A considerable length of time has elaps'd since we have received
any letters from you. What can be the cause of this long silence,
the last letter which I received was from you my Dear <persName>James</persName> dated
<date when="1825-08-17">August 17th</date> from <placeName>Groces Retreat</placeName> writen shortly after your return
from the <placeName>interior</placeName>.    I received it in<date when="1825-09-17"> a month after it was writen</date>; it <pb n="1240"/>was <hi rend="italic">short</hi> but still it gave me a great deal of pleasure to hear that
you were well, and still thought of your <persName>Sister </persName>and her <hi rend="italic"><persName>Children</persName></hi>. I
have writen Several letter[s] lately boath by Mail, and <persName>privet conveyance</persName>; informing you, of the untimely death of your Old acquantence <persName>William M. Perry</persName>, who was shot by <persName>William Hill</persName>, who
absconded immediately; I sent you a hand bill also a large Packet
of letters, by <persName>Esqr Andrews</persName>, who I expect you will see before this
letter comes to hand; their are a number of <persName>Families</persName> moving to your
<placeName>Colloney</placeName> from this <placeName>State</placeName>, Old <persName>Dr Thompson</persName>, and his Son <persName>Burrell</persName>
have <hi rend="italic">started, and a hopefull gang they are;</hi> but you know their
carrector thierfor, you will know how to deal with them&#8212; Old <persName>Mr
Alley</persName> and his <persName>Son</persName>, will start in a few days, and a number more
taulk of going.</p>

<p>I must now commence and give you a catalogue, of news; I shall
first comenc[e] and inform you of those friend and <persName>acquintences</persName>
that have left this troublesome <placeName>world</placeName>, and I hope have found a
better our old Friend <persName>Mrs Nancy Bates</persName> is no more; <persName>Mrs Horrace
Austin</persName> is also gone, died raven distracted, <persName>Mrs Eitchards</persName> did not
survive her <persName>Daughter</persName> but a short time, <persName>Mary Honey</persName> has all her
<persName>Brothers</persName> and <persName>Sisters</persName>; except <persName>William</persName> and <persName>Charles</persName>,&#8212;<persName>Adeline Lewis</persName>
has a <persName>Daughter</persName>, also <persName>Maria Woodson</persName>&#8212; <persName>John Dennisson</persName> is to be
Married in a short time to <persName>Miss Maria Vensant</persName>, a <hi rend="italic">Dutch Beauty</hi>&#8212;
of Fifteen&#8212; <persName>Miss Isabella McIlvain</persName> was Married on <date when="1825-12-15">Thursday last
</date>to <persName>Mr John McGradey</persName>, and your Old Friend <persName>Dr McGradey</persName> has also
taken a <persName>Wife </persName>to himself; a <persName>Mrs Covington</persName>, <persName>Sister </persName>to <persName>Mrs Fletcher</persName>;
<persName>Esqr Brickey</persName> is also Married, to a <persName>widdow</persName>&#8212;<persName>Miss Isabella Hord</persName> was
not pleased at the <persName>Doctor</persName>s Marring and the poor old Man could not
muster courage to take the News to her, but had to send a Friend to
inform her of it,&#8212;etc. etc.&#8212;</p>

<p><date when="1826-01-08">January 8th 1826</date>&#8212;</p>

<p>after letting my letter lay for some time I have once more taken
pen to close this Scrawl and answer my Dear <persName>Brothers</persName> letters of
<date n="10-xx-1825">October</date>, and <date n="11-xx-1825">November</date>, I am much greaved to learn by <persName>Brown</persName>'s
letter that My Dear <persName>Stephen</persName>, had been so ill, O! that I could have
taken wings and of Flown to your <placeName>Sick bed</placeName>; but Alas I am apprehensive that it is our lot to be separated the remainder of our lives,
I shall be extreamly happy to hear that one or boath of you were
<hi rend="italic">Married</hi>, you must lead a very disagreeable life the way that you live,
I do not like to hear you say <persName>Stephen</persName> that you can not visit <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Missouri</placeName></hi>, I think if you were to come on, that you might find some
<persName>Ladey </persName>that would please you, Your Old Favourite <persName>Miss Courtney
Baylor</persName> is now a <persName>Widdow</persName>, living in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>&#8212;but if My Dear
<persName>Brother</persName>, would only, make a visit to this <placeName>State</placeName> I am sure that he
could meat with a <persName>Ladey </persName>that would be willing to go with you to <pb n="1241"/><placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; I often very often think of you and think of how much
you must of suffered in that <placeName>wilderness </placeName>It appears that our <persName>Family</persName>
were destined to be immured in, and settling of <placeName>New-Countrys</placeName>, I
forgot to mention in my former letters that <persName>Capt. Henry Austin</persName> had
Moved to <placeName>South America</placeName>, some time since, but what part I never
could ascertain;&#8212; I thank you My Dear <persName>Brown</persName> for your advice
respecting my <persName>Sons</persName>, and be assured that they shall be rais'd <persName>men of
buisness</persName>, if it is possible and from present appearances I have every
thing to incourage me <persName>Austin</persName> posseses so much of his <persName>Mother</persName>s
temper and <persName>Grand Father</persName>s Temper that I find him much harder to
manage than the rest, but when he coms to go through the same
<placeName>School</placeName>, I have he will be pretty well humbled, he is a smart Lad
and if propperly managed will make a <persName>man of buisness</persName>,&#8212; I wish you
to write me a full account of your<placeName> new <hi rend="italic">settlement</hi>;</placeName> how you progress,
the situation, how far from <persName>Brother</persName> in short every thing relative to the improvement of the establishments, and of the <placeName>Coloney</placeName>
generally is interesting to us&#8212; I never should be at a loss, if their
for a subject to write on&#8212;for we get very little correct information
respecting that <placeName>Country</placeName>; has or do any vessels ever touch, at the
<placeName>mouth of the Brasses</placeName> etc. etc.&#8212;</p>

<p>Their has been a valuable <placeName>Le[a]d Mines</placeName> discover'd <placeName>with-in <hi rend="italic">ten
miles</hi> of Herculaneum</placeName>, on <placeName>Sandy</placeName>, the Land belongs to <persName>Honey and
Bates</persName>, they are acquiring welth very fast&#8212; I was much grattifyed
not long since to see in a work of <persName>Schoolcraft</persName>, a Biographical sketch
of our Dear <persName>Father</persName>, he speaks of every member of the <persName>Family</persName>, and
of <persName>Father</persName>s early visit to this <placeName>Country</placeName>; I intend to purchase the
work, as soon as I can and send it to you&#8212;by the first opportunity&#8212;
I must close this long Scrawl; <persName>Mr. Perry</persName> joins me in good wishes
for your health and Proesperity; and believe me Dear <persName>Brothers</persName>
always your truly attached <persName>Sister </persName>and Friend</p>

<p><persName>E. M. P.</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>children</persName> are all well, your name sake is a most lovely Child.
<hi rend="italic">Adieu</hi></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Stephen, F, Austin Esqr</persName> <placeName>San Felipe de Austin Rio
Brazos Provence of Texas</placeName>.   Care of <persName>Jared Cable</persName> <placeName>Natchitoches</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
