<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3070">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>D. Crozer to James E. B. Austin, 02-09-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>D. Crozer</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="CLS">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Cameron L. Sinclair</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-14">07-14-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Dr J. Fry
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James E. B. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Jessamine County, Kentucky</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1262-1263
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-02-09">02-09-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">D. Crozer to James E. B. Austin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Jessamine County Ky</placeName> <date when="1826-02-09">9th Feb 1826</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr. James E. B. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir I have not had the pleasure of a communication from
you for about 2 years, nor have I written you during that time, but
from no other cause but the impossibility of a safe conveyance&#8212;I
have now an opportunity by <persName>Dr J. Fry</persName> which I gladly embrace&#8212;</p>

<p>In your last you recommended me to come to your <placeName>Country</placeName> which at
that time I had an idea of doing, but afterwards got into business
here that was tolerably good and for that reason, then declined it.
I have not yet however, changed my determination, should the inducement be sufficient, for I am yet unmarried and ready to start to
any <placeName>Country</placeName> that holds out a sufficient inducement, and shall wait
with anxiety to hear from you on the subject&#8212;</p>

<p>A great many persons are now talking of removing to <placeName>Texas</placeName> and
believe the number will increase, <persName>John M. Henderson</persName> lately started
to <placeName>New. Orleans</placeName>, and it is his intention to go from there to your
<placeName>Brother's settlement</placeName>, you know <persName>John</persName>, and it is needless for me to
say he is deserving of your friendship, and his knowledge of the <pb n="1263"/>
duties of a <persName>Clerk </persName>might possibly be of service to your <persName>Brother</persName> or at
least to assure himself the means of a livelihood&#8212;</p>

<p>Times and <persName>men </persName>have changed in this <placeName>Country</placeName> more than you
would imagine,&#8212;I know not how long it has been since you have heard
from here, but presume it has been some time, under this presumption
I now write, and shall give a summary detail of your old <persName>acquaintances</persName>, but if my presumption is erroneous, and you have lately heard
from some of your <persName>friends </persName>here then the letter or that part of it that
looks anterior to your previous information will be useless&#8212;I will
however proceed,&#8212;<persName>Wm Walker</persName> is living <placeName>in the lower part of this
State</placeName> he is keeping a <placeName>Tavern </placeName>on the <placeName>road between this and Nashville</placeName>, <persName>Georgian</persName> is yet unmarried, I have not seen any of the <persName>family</persName>
for 3 years but am told she is handsome beyond comparison, <persName>Martha</persName>
and <persName>Jane</persName> you have no doubt heard are both married, <persName>John C. Walker</persName>
is living somewhere in <placeName>Tennessee</placeName>. <persName>George</persName> was some time since in
<placeName>Warrington Missippi</placeName>, I know not where <persName>Andrew</persName> is, <persName>Kidder</persName> is
teaching <placeName>school </placeName>I am informed near <placeName>Russellville</placeName> in this <placeName>State</placeName>. I
have not seen him for near 2 years. <persName>Jacob</persName> was, not long since at
<placeName>Mobile, Alabama</placeName>, and <persName>Joseph</persName> is living with <persName>Dr E. Warfield</persName> in his
<placeName>Store </placeName>in <placeName>Lexington</placeName>&#8212;so much for the <persName>Walker family</persName> for which I
presume you feel a deeper interest, than for any other in this <placeName>County</placeName></p>

<p><persName>Major R. Crockett</persName> is living in <placeName>Nashville</placeName> and some time since talked
of going to your <placeName>country</placeName>, but believe he has not yet gone&#8212;It would
be almost an endless task for me to pretend to give you a detail of
the miner events that have transpired since you left us, such as
marriages deaths &amp;c suffice it that I am almost the only man you
knew in the <persName>county</persName> but what has either married or gone off&#8212;<persName>Dr, J.
Fry</persName> called upon me this morning for the letter to you which, with
much pleasure I gave him, believing him to be entirely a gentleman
and worthy of your confidence&#8212;</p>

<p>In that letter I added a Postscript, stating, that if a great press of
business did not prevent, I would write you by him, which he politely
promised to be the <persName>bearer </persName>of&#8212;he also, promised to bear a communication from you on his return which I hope you will send, as it would
give me the greatest pleasure to hear from you,&#8212;</p>

<p>Wishing you health prosperity and happiness</p>

           <p><persName>D. Crozer</persName>    [Rubric] </p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
