<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3100">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Imla Keep, et. al. to Unknown, 03-20-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Imla Keep, et. al.</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="CLS">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Cameron L. Sinclair</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-26">07-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Rapides Parish, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1292-1299
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Depositions</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-03-20">03-20-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Depositions and schedule of debts in the case of the bankruptcy of Dr. Imla Keep</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>1. <persName>Isaac Thomas</persName></p>

<p><placeName>United states of North America</placeName>, and state of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName> <placeName>paresh of
Rapide</placeName>. This <date when="1826-03-20">day </date>appeared before me <persName>Gilbert Legrass a Justice
of the peace in and for said <placeName>parish</placeName></persName> <persName>Isaac Thomas</persName> who being duly
sworn According to the Law of said <placeName>State</placeName>, did depose that he was
acquainted with <persName>Docr Imla Keep</persName> in the years <date n="xx-xx-1822">1822</date>, <date n="xx-xx-1823">1823</date>, and <date n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date>.
That he was his near <persName>neighbour </persName>and had as he believes a pretty
general knowledge of his affairs. During those years he is of opinion,
that <persName>Docr Keep</persName>s practice as a <persName>physician </persName>could not have yielded him
on a fair estimate more than five hundred dollars a year, he also
states that the <persName>Docr</persName>s attention was principally confined to the cultivation of his <placeName>farm</placeName>. The said <persName>Thomas</persName> further states&#8212;That <persName>Docr Keep</persName>
purchased<placeName> part of the Land </placeName>that he once owned in this <placeName>parish </placeName>and
which is now owned by the <persName>deponent </persName>of <persName>Col. Thomas Patterson</persName>&#8212;
Who had purchased it of <persName>Waters and Leonard</persName> who held a Mortgage
for the ballance of the purchase money due by <persName>Patterson</persName>&#8212;to the amt
of about four thousand two hundred dollars. The ballance of the
Land the <persName>Docr</persName> bought of <persName>William Smith</persName>&#8212;who had a priviledge on
it for the payment of the ballance due him. <persName>Keep</persName> by his purchase of
<persName>Patterson</persName> became bound to pay <persName>Waters and Leonard</persName>&#8212;failing in
which they obtained a Judgement against <persName>Patterson</persName> on the Mortgage&#8212;and had the Land sold on a twelve months bond&#8212;when this
bond became due <persName>Keep</persName> was still unable to pay and procured this <persName>deponant </persName><persName>John and L. B. Compton</persName>, <persName>Joseph and William Brown</persName> and
<persName>John L. Lecroix</persName> to purchase up the bond and give him one and two
years to pay it in&#8212; The above <persName>parties </persName>did make that arrangement
reserving their right to have the land sold and bought in by them
for their security of the others. <persName>Keep</persName> paid part of the money due
on the bonds at the time fixed&#8212;and this <persName>deponant </persName>paid the ballance&#8212;
and to secure himself for this and other debts bought the <placeName>Land </placeName>and
took a Conveyance from <persName>J and L B Compton</persName>&#8212; The <placeName>land </placeName>bought of
<persName>smith</persName> was sold to pay the ballance due on it When the <persName>deponant </persName>also
became the <persName>purchaser</persName>.</p>

<p>Sworn to, written in the <persName>deponen</persName>ts own handwriting, and Subscribed before me this <date when="1826-03-20">20th, March 1826</date></p>

<p>(Signed)<persName>I. Thomas</persName></p>

<p><persName>G. Legras Jce Pce</persName> </p>
<p>in and for the <placeName>parish of Rapide</placeName></p>

<p>I certify that I have long been acquainted with <persName>Isaac Thomas Esqr</persName>
an <persName>inhabitant of the <placeName>parish of Rapide</placeName></persName> whose deposition is written<pb n="1293"/>
above, that he is a gentleman of respectability, and that his deposition
is entitled to full credit</p>

<p>Given under my hand and Seal of Office as<persName> Parish Judge</persName> in and
for the <placeName>Paresh of Rapide</placeName> this <date when="1826-03-20">20th March 1826</date></p>

<p><persName>Th C. Scott</persName> Par. Judge</p>

<p>2.  <persName>THOMAS  HOOPER</persName></p>

<p><placeName>United Stats of america</placeName> and State of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName> <placeName>Parish of Rappide</placeName>
this the <date when="1826-03-20">20th day of march 1826</date> this day appeared before me <persName>Gilbert
Legrass a Justice of the peace in and for the said <placeName>Parish</placeName> </persName><persName>Thomas
Hooper</persName> who being duly sworn according to the laws of said state,
did depose that he was acquainted with <persName>Doctor Imla Keep</persName> in the
years <date n="xx-xx-1819">1819</date>, <date n="xx-xx-1820">1820</date>, <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date>, <date n="xx-xx-1822">1822</date>, <date n="xx-xx-1823">1823</date>, <date n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date> That he was his near
<persName>neighbour </persName>and had as he believes a pretty general Knowledge of his
affairs.</p>

<p>During the years of <date n="xx-xx-1819">1819</date> or <date n="xx-xx-1820">1820</date> this <persName>deponent </persName>is not confident
which, <persName>Dr. Keep</persName> had an extensive practice and was for a time a
popular <persName>Physician</persName>, so much so this <persName>deponent </persName>was induced to engage
him for the succeeding year as his <persName>family Physician</persName>, but he proved
so unsuccessful in his practice and became so very unpopular in
those <persName>families </persName>in which he practiced that he considered him so unsafe That altho <persName>Dr. Keep</persName> owed this <persName>deponent </persName>the sum of ninety
dollars, and he agreed to attend the deponents family for said sum
of ninety dollars, he gave up the said debt to <persName>Dr. Keep</persName> and employed other <persName>Physicians </persName>in his place when occasion required, altho
<persName>Dr. Keep</persName> was receiving the pay of said sum for the same. The
<persName>deponent </persName>further states that he verily believes that <persName>Doctor Keeps</persName>
practice after the first year he came in the <placeName>country</placeName> was not worth
five hundred dollars per annum. The <persName>deponent </persName>further states that
during the latter part of the year <date n="xx-xx-1824">one thousand eight hundred and
twenty four</date> the <persName>deponent </persName>started from this <placeName>Parish</placeName> in Company with
<persName>Dr. Keep</persName> and <persName>Colonel Gross's family</persName> and that they arrived at <placeName><persName>Col.
Gross</persName>'s residence</placeName> in the <placeName>Providence [sic] of Texas</placeName> on the <date when="1824-12-24">24th</date> or <date when="1824-12-25">25th
of December</date> the <persName>deponent </persName>is uncertain which and was present when
<persName>Dr. Keep</persName> and <persName>Col. Gross</persName> attempted to make a settlement, that the
deponent understood from the <persName>parties </persName>that <persName>Dr. Keep</persName> upon settlement
fell in debt to <persName>Col. Gross</persName> to a very considerable amount and that
<persName>Col. Gross</persName> gave a bill for goods which <persName>Dr. Keep</persName> was to fill in <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName> for the amount of two or three thousand dollars the <persName>deponent </persName>does not remember which but believes the latter, which
money the <persName>deponent </persName>understood was in the hands of <persName>Dr. Keep</persName> and
belonging to <persName>Col. Gross</persName>.</p>

<p>The <persName>deponent </persName>further understood from the <persName>parties </persName>that a <persName>partnership </persName>was to be entered into after <persName>Dr. Keep</persName>s return from <placeName>New Or<pb n="1294"/>
leans</placeName> between <persName>Dr. Keep</persName> <persName>Col. Gross</persName> and <persName>Wm. White</persName> and that said
<persName>White</persName> and <persName>Keep</persName> were to take possession of the <placeName>lower plantation</placeName></p>

<p>(Signed)            <persName>Thomas Hooper</persName></p>

<p>Sworn to and Subscribed before me this <date when="1826-03-20">20th. March 1826</date></p>

<p><persName>G. Legras Jce Pce</persName></p>
<p>for the <placeName>parish of Rapide</placeName></p>

<p>I certify that I have long been acquainted with <persName>Thomas Hooper
Esq.</persName> an <persName>inhabitant of the <placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName></persName> whose deposition is written above, that he is a gentleman of respectability and that his
deposition is entitled to full credit</p>

<p>Given under my hand and seal of office as <persName>Parish Judge in and for
the <placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName> </persName>this <date when="1826-03-20">20th March 1826</date>.</p>

<p>(Signed)           <persName>Th C Scott Par Judge</persName></p>

<p>3. <persName>NARRISH  WRIGHT</persName></p>

<p>Whereas I <persName>Narrish Wright Sheriff of the <placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName></persName> by
virtue of a writ of firie facias to me directed against the goods and
chattels <placeName>Lands and tenements of <persName>Thomas Patterson</persName> <persName>Imla Keep</persName> and
<persName>Henry Haynes</persName></placeName> at the suit of <persName>William Waters</persName> did seize the following
property to wit all the right title and interest of these <persName>defendants</persName>
or either of them in and to<placeName> ninety Arpens of Land </placeName>and all the rights
priviledges and appurtenances thereto belonging situated lying and
being in the <placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName> on the <placeName>right Bank of the Bayou Rapide</placeName>
in descending<placeName> bounded below by Lands of <persName>Charles Curtis</persName></placeName> and <placeName><placeName>above
by the One hundred and eighty arpens of the same tract purchased
by <persName>John and L B Compton</persName></placeName></placeName> at <persName>Sheriff</persName>s sale and being the <placeName>remainder
of the tract acquired by <persName>Imla Keep</persName> or <persName>Thos Patterson</persName></placeName> and<placeName> a Part
of the same on which the said <persName>Keep</persName> now resides</placeName> and having exposed
the same to public sale according to Law on the <date when="1824-03-04">4th of March 1824</date>
for Cash when <persName>J and L B Camptan</persName> became the <persName>purchaser </persName>thereof
for the price of four hundred dollars which I hereby acknowledge
to have received and endorsed as a credit on the execution bearing
date <date when="1824-03-04">March 4th 1824</date> Now therefore Know all men by these presents
that I the said <persName>Sheriff </persName>do in consideration of the premises and by
virtue of the acts in such case made and provided grant bargain Sell
assign and set over to the said <persName>J and L B Compton</persName> <persName>their heirs</persName> and
assigns all the <placeName>above described peice or parcel of Land</placeName> and all the
right title interest or demand which the said <persName>Thomas Patterson</persName> <persName>Imla
Keep</persName> and <persName>Henry Haynes</persName> on the <date when="1822-06-15">15th day of June 1822</date> as at any time
since had in or to the said property or any part thereof there being
the following special Mortgages on the same as certified by the <persName>Parish Judge of the <placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName> </persName>in his certificate as follows I cer<pb n="1295"/>
tify that a special Mortgage exists on the records of my <placeName>office </placeName>by <persName>Imla
Keep</persName> in favor of <persName>Thomas Patterson</persName> on a <placeName>tract of Land situated in the
Parish of Rapide</placeName> <placeName>on the left Bank of the Bayou Rapide</placeName> in descending  <placeName>having a front on the said Bayou</placeName> of six and three quarters arpens
with the depth of forty arpens to secure the payment of the sum of
Eight thousand dollars besides interest dated <date when="1818-12-23">December 23rd 1818</date>
I also certify that another special Mortgage exists by said <persName>Keep</persName> in
favor of <persName>Edmond L Briggs</persName> on fo<placeName>rty Arpens of Land to be taken
from the lower side of the tract above</placeName> described to secure the payment of the sum of Seven hundred and ninety dollars and fifty Cents
besides interest dated <date when="1821-09-19">September 19th 1821</date> I also certify that another special Mortgage exists by said <persName>Keep</persName> in favor of <persName>Joseph Letchworth</persName> on <placeName>forty arpens of the above described tract of Land and adjoining that last Mentioned</placeName> to Secure the payment of the sum of
twenty dollars besides interest dated <date when="1822-10-10">October 10th 1822</date> and that no
other special Mortgage exists on the records of my <placeName>Office </placeName>in the name
of said <persName>Keep</persName> Given under my hand and seal of Office as Parish Judge
in and for the <placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName> this <date when="1924-03-04">4th day of March 1824</date> (Signed)
<persName>Thomas C Scott Par Judge</persName> To hold the same to the said <persName>J and L B
Compton</persName> <persName>their heirs</persName> and assigns for ever In testimony whereof I
have hereunto set my hand and seal this <date when="1824-03-04">fourth day of March in the
year of Our Lord one thousand eight hundred and twenty four</date> and
in the forty eighth year of the independence of the <placeName>United States</placeName></p>

<p><persName>Narrish Wright</persName></p>
<p><persName>Sheriff of the <placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName></persName></p>
<p>(Signed) sealed and delivered in the presence of</p>

<p><persName>Wm R Leckie</persName></p>

<p><persName>S E Cuny</persName></p>

<p>Done and passed before me</p>

<p><persName>Th. C. Scott Par. Judge</persName></p>

<p>I certify the foregoing to be a true copy from the original on
file and of Record in my <placeName>Office</placeName></p>

<p>Given under my hand and seal of Office as <persName>Parish Judge in and
for the <placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName></persName> this <date when="1826-03-21">21st day of March A D 1826</date></p>

<p><persName>Th. C. Scott Par. Judge</persName> </p>

<p>4.  SCHEDULE OP DEBTS.</p>

<p>Be it remembered, that heretofore to wit; on the <date when="1825-05-04">fourth day of
May Eighteen hundred and twenty five</date> <persName>Imla Keep</persName> filed in the <placeName>Office
of the Clerk of the sixth District Court in and for the Parish of
Rapide</placeName> and State of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName> a Petition, in writing, against His<pb n="1296"/>
<persName>Creditors</persName>, together with a Schedule of his debts, in the words and
figures following, to wit:</p>

<p>To the <persName>Honorable William Murray Judge of the sixth District
Court., <placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName></persName></p>

<p>The petition of <persName>Imla Keep</persName> a <persName>citizen of said <placeName>Parish</placeName></persName>, with respect
states to your <persName>Honor </persName>That notwithstanding he has used the greatest
industry and most rigid economy for years past he finds himself in
consequence of his numerous losses and misfortunes in a Condition
that renders it absolutely impossible for him to discharge his
debts&#8212;Your <persName>petitioner </persName>further states: that the step he is about
to take in making a surrender to his <persName>creditors </persName>has alone been produced by the positive belief that whilst encumbered and shakled
with such a load of increasing debt in consequence of the <placeName>Rapide</placeName>
growth of the amount by accumulating interest and Costs, that he
never could by any rational exertion meet the payment his losses
and the payments heretofore made having divested him of every
useful means of making, save his personal exertions&#8212;Your <persName>petitioner </persName>further states that he has been placed in his present unpleasant situation of inability to pay his <persName>creditors</persName>, by misfortunes
that he could not control and meeting necessary expences&#8212;such as
that of having lost his most valuable <persName>slaves</persName>, after having given a
large price at an unfortunate period for a <placeName>plantation </placeName>to employ them
on, That of having given fourteen thousand dollars for a <placeName>plantation</placeName>&#8212;which was sacrificed for less than a third of the amt at
<persName>Sheriff</persName>s sale. That of supporting my <persName>family</persName>, though not an expensive one&#8212;Yet a losing one&#8212;That of not being able to collect
my debts and incurring their loss,&#8212;that of having at great expense
to attend to an expensive law suit most unjustly Prosecuted against
me in the <placeName>state of Mississippi</placeName> These together with many other
causes not enumerated have produced my inability to pay my debts
and force me to take that disagreeable step of calling a meeting
of my <persName>creditors</persName>&#8212;To which end I have hereto annexed a schedule
of my property and a list of my active and passive debts, as also a
Statement of the debts, due by me, and a Statement of the losses
that I have sustained&#8212;Wherefore your <persName>petitioner </persName>prays to be
allowd to call a meeting of his <persName>creditors</persName> at such time and place as
your <persName>Honor </persName>or the <persName>court </persName>may direct, in order that he may be enabled
to lay before them a statement of his affairs and surrender them
his <persName>Estate</persName>, and that in the mean time all Kind of proceedings
against his Person and property be stayed&#8212;</p>

<p>(Signed)           <persName>Imla Keep</persName><pb n="1297"/></p>



<p><hi rend="italic">A Schedule of debts due by <persName>Imla Keep</persName>, with their amts names of <persName>Creditors</persName>,

and place of residence</hi></p>

<p>Names of <persName>Creditors</persName>&#8212;
	amt
	debt
		place of residence</p>

<p>To <persName>William Smith</persName> about
	$1100
	
		<placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName> </p>
<p>" <persName>Stephen E Cuny</persName>
	
		do            do</p>

	
<p>	..</p>
		
<p>" <persName>G Y Kelso</persName>
	40
	
		do            do</p>

<p>" <persName>Ferguson and Rich</persName>
	300
	
		do            do</p>

<p>" <persName>P B Martin</persName> for notes given to <persName>David Pannile</persName>
	215 13
	(including cost and Int)
		do            do</p>

<p>" <persName>Jesse Hudson</persName>
	167 70
	
		do            do</p>

<p>" <persName>Sexton and Morgan</persName>
	302
	
	"
	do            do</p>

<p>" <persName>Mrs Kimble</persName> about
	600
	
	"
	do  <placeName>Feliciana</placeName></p>

<p>" <persName>King and Beatty</persName>
	600
	
	"
	"   <placeName>Radide</placeName></p>

<p>" <persName>G Greeves</persName>
	700
	
	"
	<placeName>New Orleans</placeName></p>

<p>" <persName>H A Bullard</persName>
	600
	
	"
	<placeName>Par of Rapide</placeName></p>

<p>" <persName>Jno. Casson</persName>
	75
	
	"
	do         do</p>

<p>" <persName>Kimble merchant</persName>
	30
	
	"
	do         do</p>

<p>" <persName>Hynson and Wright</persName>
	15
	
	"
	do         do</p>

<p>" <persName>Mrs Bacon</persName> in the hands of <persName>G Oakley Esqr</persName>
	200
	
	"
	do         do</p>

<p>" <persName>Jos. S. Johnston</persName>   "
	300
	
	"
	do         do</p>

<p>" <persName>Chas. F Scott</persName>
	80
	
	"
	do         do</p>

<p>" <persName>Estate </persName>of <persName>Doct Rippey</persName>
	80
	
	"</p>
	

<p>" <persName>Leckie and Norment</persName>
	114
	
	"
	do         do</p>

<p>" <persName>James Price</persName>
	700
	
	"
	do         do</p>

<p>" <persName>Jno. P landreau</persName>
	20
	
	"
	do         do</p>

<p>" <persName>Buckley and Bailey</persName>   ..
	400
	
	"
	do         do</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Schedule of property and debts belonging to <persName>Imla Keep</persName></hi></p>

<p>Farming Tools, plows, Hames axes etc value------------------------------------      30.&#8212;</p>

<p>six head of Cows&#8212;-------------------------------------------------------------------       50.</p>

<p>1 saddle and Bridle---------------------------------------------------------------      20.</p>

<p>Debts due</p>

<p>Account for protessional services against <persName>Matthew Martin</persName>-------    140</p>

<p>account agt.  <persName>McWaters</persName> for professional services------------------------    40</p>

<p>Notes in the hands of <persName>Christopher Bullard</persName> of <placeName>Winchester Tennessee</placeName> against <persName>Doctr Saml. Holland</persName> decd for-----------------------   1100&#8212;</p>

<p>Account against the <persName>Estate </persName>of <persName>Mrs Manbale</persName> deceased for-----------      80</p>

<p>account agt the <persName>Estate </persName>of <persName>J M Martin</persName> decd-------------------------        300</p>

<p>account agt the <persName>Estate </persName>of <persName>Mrs Spencer</persName> decd----------------------     120</p>

<p>Due Bill against <persName>David Manbale</persName> balance--------------------------------      30.</p>

<p>Statement of Losses incured by <persName>Imla Keep</persName></p>
<p>In the year <date n="xx-xx-1819">1819</date>.&#8212;</p>

<p>Three <persName>negroes</persName> worth (men)---------------------------------   4000</p>

<p>one  <persName>negro   child</persName>  worth--------------------------------    100</p>

<p>In <date n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date>&#8212;<persName>one negro man</persName> worth______________________________    300</p>

<p>By expences incured in supporting <persName>family</persName> per annum $1200 for six
years   ______________________________________________________   7200</p>

<p>By cost, and Expences attending Law Suit--------------------------------------   2000</p>

<p>By Interest on debt, due--------------------------------------------------------------   3000</p>

<p>By fall of property______________________________________________   8000</p>

<p>By losses incured in defending a vexatious law suit brought against me
in the <placeName>state of Mississippi</placeName>--------------------------------------------------------   1000</p>

<p>I <persName>Imla Keep</persName> do solemnly swear that the above and foregoing
schedule contains a correct and faithful statement of all the property
I possess, either in moveables or immovables, or in Other rights, or<pb n="1298"/>
claims, except however the clothes and Linen to my use, and the
instruments indispensable to my profession by which I make my
living, and which the law authorises me to Keep&#8212;and I do further
solemnly swear that the said schedule contains a correct and faithful
statement of my active and passive debts, and of the looses I have
experianced in my affairs, and that I have neither directly or indirectly divested anything of my property to the Injury of my <persName>creditors</persName> So help me God&#8212;</p>

<p>(Signed)           <persName>Imla Keep</persName></p>

<p>Sworn to and Subscribed before me <date when="1825-03-07">7th of March 1825</date></p>

<p><persName>Benj M Stokes J. P.</persName> </p>

<p>On which Petition the <persName>Judge</persName> made the following order To wit;
Ordered that a meeting of the <persName>creditors</persName> of the <persName>Petitioner</persName> be held
before the <persName>Parish Judge</persName> of <placeName>said, Parrish</placeName>, on the <date when="1825-05-09">second monday of
May next</date> to deliberate on the affairs of the <persName>petitioner</persName>, and that in
the mean time all proceedings be stayed against his person and
property, and untill further Order be had thereon <date when="1825-04-09">9th April 1825</date>.</p>

<p>(Signed)           <persName>W. Murray</persName> Judge</p>

<p><placeName>6th District</placeName></p>

<p>I certify that I have this day posted up at the <placeName>Jail Door</placeName> a notice
to the <persName>Creditors</persName> of the said <persName>Imla Keep</persName>, returnable on the <date when="1825-05-09">second
monday of present month</date>, according to Law</p>

<p><date when="1825-05-04">May 4th 1825</date></p>

<p><persName>Wm. R. Leckie Dy Clk</persName></p>

<p>And afterwards, to wit, on the <date when="1825-05-09">9th day of May 1825</date> the <persName>Parish
Judge</persName> gave the following certificate to wit</p>

<p><persName>Imla Keep</persName> vs His <persName>creditors</persName></p>

<p>On this <date when="1825-05-09">9th day of May 1825</date> appeared at my <placeName>office </placeName>the said <persName>Imla
Keep</persName> by <persName>Isaac Thomas</persName> his <persName>attorney</persName>, and the <persName>creditors</persName> of the said
<persName>Keep</persName> failing to appear, and no opposition being made to the surrender of property by said <persName>Keep</persName>, the same is certified to the <placeName>sixth District Court.</placeName> </p>

<p><placeName>Parish of Rapide</placeName>&#8212; Th. <persName>C. Scott Par Judge</persName> </p>

<p><placeName>State of Louisiana Parish of Rapide</placeName></p>

<p>I <persName>William R Leckie clerk of the <placeName>sixth District and Parish Courts
for the Parish and State aforesaid</placeName></persName>&#8212;Do certify the foregoing to
be a true Transcript of the Record, and all the proceedings had in the
case of <persName>Imla Keep</persName> vs His <persName>Creditors</persName> exising in my <placeName>Office</placeName>.</p>

<p>In Testimony whereof I have hereunto Subscribed my name and
affixed the seal of Office This <date when="1826-03-20">20th day of March A D 1826</date></p>

<p>(Signed)           <persName>Wm. R. Leckie Clk</persName><pb n="1299"/></p>



<p>I <persName>William Murraysole Judge of the <placeName>6th District Court for the
Parish of Rapide</placeName></persName> , Do certify that <persName>William R Leckie</persName> who signed
the foregoing certificate is and was at the time of so signing <persName>Clerk
of said Courts</persName>, and that full faith and credit is and Ought to be
given to his proceedings as such&#8212; and the same is in due form of
Law&#8212;</p>

<p>Given under my hand and Seal This <date when="1820-03-22">22nd day of March A. D 1820</date></p>

<p>(Signed)           <persName>W. Murray</persName>,</p>

<p><placeName>6th District</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
