<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3069">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Emily M. Perry, 01-28-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="CLS">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Cameron L. Sinclair</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-14">07-14-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Emily M. Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Potosi, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1260-1262
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-01-28">01-28-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Biographical.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe</placeName> <date when="1826-01-28">January 28 1826</date></p>
<p>Dr Sister:</p>
<p>I this day received your truly welcome letter dated <date when="1825-10-12">12 October</date> and
the packet enclosing a shirt for <persName>James</persName>, Some of my old letters and <pb n="1261"/>
a lock of each of your <persName>children</persName>s hair, and of your own&#8212;My beloved
<persName>Sister</persName> could not have sent me a more acceptable present, your sweet
<persName>children</persName> are your greatest comfort in this world&#8212;they are dear to
their <persName>Mother</persName>, and equally so to their <persName>Uncle</persName>&#8212;I needed nothing to
keep me in mind of them, but, it is, notwithstanding a pleasure to
have something that was once theirs&#8212;some keepsake, to represent
them in their absence. They are a comfort to you now, for they are
all innocence, The vices of human nature have not yet shaded their
original purity, nor soured their native sweetness, and a fond <persName>mother</persName>
in the ardor of her affection may flatter herself with the hope, the
pleasing hope, that they never will, and that they will be the prop
and pride of her declining years. Dreams of future happiness of
this kind are the most natural, the most pleasing and the most excusable of any others, but my <persName>Sister </persName>even these some times prove to
be <hi rend="italic">only dreams</hi>, God grant that they may be realised in this instance
by us both, for I have indulged myself in them probably as much
as you have, I never expect to marry and in that event should adopt
your <persName>orpans</persName> for my own or a part of them, it must be our duty to
watch over them, and fortify them to resist the temptations and
vices of this world by instilling into their youthful minds the love
of virtue, of morality and truth, and prepare them to be useful and
ornamental members of <persName>Society </persName>by giving them as good an education as our means will permit&#8212;with their <persName>mother</persName> they will receive
such impressions as will make them all that either of us could
wish&#8212;if those impressions are not effaced by the allurements of
vice&#8212;I hope that it will be in my power to aid in educating them,
but at this time the prospect is rather distant, a few years will
determine what this <placeName>country</placeName> will come to, and in the meantime the
<persName>children</persName> can be educated with their <persName>mother</persName>, as soon as I can do any
thing for them I will write you tho. I flatter myself with the hope
that you will ere long remove and settle down by the side of your
<persName>brothers</persName>&#8212;I wish <persName>Mr Perry</persName> to come and pay me a visit, tell him to
come <date n="Fall - 1826">next fall</date> and take a good look at the <placeName>Country</placeName>, by that time
things will have taken such a turn as to decide the future prospects of
this <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212;at this time they are as flattering as I could wish&#8212;I
think if he will come and see me that he would move, but he must
not move untill he first looks for himself&#8212;I hope it is not necessary
for me to say that I will do all in my power to aid him in securing
land and getting into business and I think by <date n="Fall - 1826">next fall</date> there will
be a very good opening   he might make the trip in three months</p>

<p><persName>Brother</persName> has commenced below this on the <placeName>river</placeName>&#8212;I hope to see him
married before long, tho, there is no prospect at this time&#8212;</p>

<p>I am going <date n="1-29-1826">to morrow</date> to the <placeName>coast</placeName> to make a partial survey of it
preparitory to the opening of the <placeName>port of entry</placeName>, by <date n="Fall - 1826">next fall</date> the <placeName>port</placeName>
will be opend, and business will take a new start <pb n="1262"/></p>


<p>I have never recd any<placeName> news papers</placeName> from you by any one, but should
be happy to get some from <placeName>Missouri</placeName></p>

<p>It is impossible for me to go to <placeName>Arkansas</placeName> to attend to the <placeName>Little
Rock</placeName> business&#8212;All I can do is to write to some of my <persName>acquaintances</persName>
there and that I will do, tho I have not much faith in effecting any
thing in that way&#8212;</p>

<p>remember me to <persName>Mr Perry</persName>&#8212;tell him that I shall look for him here
in <date n="10-xx-1826">October next</date> without fail he can spare three months to look at
the <placeName>Country</placeName> and then can decide for himself</p>

<p>My love to <persName>Mrs H. Elliott</persName> and her <persName>Uncles family</persName> and to <persName>Mrs John
Perry</persName>, she was always something of a favorite with me, her lively
disposition made her society agreeable and I think she is a warm
<persName>friend </persName>where she is a friend&#8212;</p>

<p>farewell my <persName>Sister</persName> kiss the <persName>children</persName> for me and tell <persName>William</persName> and
<persName>Austin</persName> that in one year more I shall expect a letter from them&#8212;is
<persName>Elizabeth</persName> to be a beauty who does she resemble&#8212;how [large?] is
<persName>William</persName> and <persName>Austin</persName>&#8212;and which of them all appears to learn the
fastest and have the most sprightliness&#8212;you ought to study their
dispositions and shape their future destinies accordingly&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mrs Emily M. Perry</persName> <placeName>Potosi Missouri</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
