<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3085">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to George Orr, 03-10-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-18">07-18-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        George Orr
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1272
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-03-10">03-10-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Advice to avoid conflict with Mexican authorities.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1826-03-10">March 10. 1826</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p><persName>Mr. Chastellier</persName> has drawn off copy of the Colonization law and
takes it with him&#8212;</p>

<p>I very much regret that there should have arisen any discontent
among the <persName>settlers</persName> on the <placeName>Trinity</placeName> in regard to the manner of procuring their lands, every thing of this nature has a tendency to injure
the progress of the <placeName>new Settlements</placeName> generally, and I would with due
respect to those <persName>settlers</persName>, and as their <persName>friend </persName>and the friend of all the
<placeName>new Settlements</placeName>, recommend to them to be extremely cautious not to
do any thing of a violent or disorderly character towards the<persName> persons
intrusted by the Government</persName> with the superintendence of those <placeName>new
Settlements</placeName>&#8212;The utmost harmony should be cultivated&#8212;the <persName>agents
of the Government</persName> should be treated with respect, and if causes of
complaint exist against them, representations should be made to the
<persName>proper authority</persName> in a mild manner and without any thing like passion or abuse. These ideas are respectfully suggested to you in
friendship, they proceed from a sincere desire to see harmony prevail, and not from any disposition or desire on my part to intrude
my advice or censure on any person and I hope you will receive
them in the same spirit of candor and friendship in which they are
offered&#8212;I can have no object in wishing harmony, but the prosperity
of the <placeName>country</placeName>, for my conduct in regard to receiving settlers will not
be regulated, or in any manner influenced, by what the other <persName>Empresarios</persName> may do&#8212;my guide shall be the law and the orders of the
<persName>Government</persName>, and the price which the <persName>Government </persName>may direct me to
exact of the <persName>settlers</persName> to pay the expences on their lands, is what must
be paid: how much that will be, I cannot tell untill instructions are
recd on the subject&#8212;I have applied for them and such instructions
and shall do nothing in regard to the final location of <persName>new Settlers</persName>
untill they arrive.</p>

<p>My <persName>brother</persName> who starts to <placeName>Saltillo</placeName> in a few days will take on a
report of the history and observations made by me at <placeName>Galveston</placeName> preparatory to the opening of the <placeName>port</placeName>, and in all pro[ba]bility some
definitive measures will be adopted by the Govt in regard to the
establishment of a <placeName>port town</placeName>, either at <placeName>Galveston</placeName>, or <placeName> some other
convenient point on thecoast</placeName>, during the ensuing <date n="Summer - 1826">summer </date>or <date n="Fall - 1826">fall</date></p>

<p>I shall at all times be happy to hear from you and of the increasing prosperity of the <persName>settlers</persName> in your <placeName>quarter of the country</placeName></p>

<p>[<persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>]</p>

<p>[To <persName>George Orr</persName>]</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
