<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3081">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Haden Edwards to Stephen F. Austin, 2-28-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Haden Edwards</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="CLS">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Cameron L. Sinclair</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-16">07-16-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Trinity River, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1269-1270
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-02-28">2-28-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Explanation of friction with inhabitants of east Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><persName>Colonl Austin</persName></p>

<p>Having heard of your <persName>expedition </persName>to the <placeName>Isleland</placeName>, I made every
exertion in my power to join you there but failed in procuring a
conveyance untill I heard of your return. I then went to the <placeName>bay</placeName>
by land a very unpleasant trip owing to the weather and rottenness
of the <placeName>perarys [prairies]</placeName>, there again heard you was to leave <persName>Mr <pb n="1270"/>
Scotts</persName> on the day of my arrival there for home. Returning to the
<placeName>trinety</placeName> I heard again that you was to attend a meeting at the
<placeName>Santa Jacinta</placeName> on the <date when="1826-03-04">fourth of March</date> ordered by yourself in order to present a memorial against me to the <persName>Government </persName>for asking my
<persName>colonists</persName> more than the Government tax on the lands propigated here
in my absence by <persName>Mr Rankin</persName>. This I placed no confidence in not
believing that <persName>Colo. Austin</persName> could be capable of using any measures
to the injury of the other <persName>Empresarios</persName> after having set the example
himself and reaped the fruits thereof, not only that; the people
who are to be the <persName>memorialists</persName> have already obtained their lands
from yourself therefore can have no interest in the disposition of
my lands and I have never seen more than two or three of them
all of whom I informed might rest contented that there would be no
difficulty about their titles never calculating there would arise any
between us on the subject. As to my conditions I feel myself perfectly justified by that article of the law securing contracts made
between the <persName>settlers </persName>and <persName>Empresarios </persName>which article was inserted in
consequence of complaints made against yourself for selling the
<placeName>lands </placeName>and I feel myself more than doubly justified in asking what
I do for the good of the <placeName>colony</placeName> and of the government in general,
as you must admit as a candid man that one <persName>colonist </persName>who is willing
and able to pay for the lands as offered is worth fifty of those indolent <persName>Iddlers </persName>who barely live to exist and have no ambition or
enterprise further. If you would do me the pleasure of coming to
see me I will show you that my <persName>families</persName> are already engaged at my
prices and are unwilling that I should permit others to settle upon
less terms being satisfied of the disadvantages arising to the <placeName>Country</placeName>
from such a coarse. The honest industrious already in the <placeName>country</placeName>
are of the same opinion and have complied with the terms already.</p>

<p>I am constantly told by those worthless <persName>Iddlers </persName>that <persName>Judge Austin</persName>
gives lands at <persName>Congress </persName>prices and says we have no right to ask or
receive more. I have never payed any attention to their assertions
believing them to be fabrications only replying to them to get lands
of you. I have no doubt but there are hundreds of lies told you
perhaps in the same way in order as I have understood they have
said if the[y] could get the <persName>Empresarios </persName>at variance they would be
able to reap a benefit. I hope you will give me the earliest information of your discoveries to our advantage in your trip to <placeName>isleland</placeName>
and should you be disturbed at any part of my conduct that you
will be candid enough to state your objections to me before taking
any measures unfriendly I expect to meet <persName>Colo. Leftwitch</persName> on my
return to <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName> and should feel very happy [if] we could
all have a meeting to promote the best interests of the <placeName>country</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Haden Edwards</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p><placeName>Mr Munsons Trinety</placeName> <date when="1826-02-28">February 28th 1826</date></p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
