<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3067">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>R. R. Royall to Stephen F. Austin, 02-21-1826</title>
            <author>
                <persName>R. R. Royall</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-07-15">07-15-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Tuscumbia, Alabama</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Austin's Colony, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1266-1267
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1826-02-21">02-21-1826</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-07-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Dangers of travel. Texan interest in Alabama, Tennessee, and Kentucky.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>United States of America</placeName></p>
<p><placeName>Town of Tuscumbia and State of Alabama</placeName></p>

<p><date when="1826-02-21">21st February 1826</date>&#8212;</p>
<p><persName>Col. Austin
</persName></p>
<p>Esteemed Sir At the solicitation of the <persName>friends of Mr Gillespie</persName>
I write to enquire after the circumstances of his death. <persName>Mrs. Gillespie</persName> says <persName>Mr Gillespie</persName> left <placeName>home </placeName>with five hundred dollars and
had made arrangements, whereby he was to receive as much more
in <placeName>Natches</placeName> making the sum of one thousand dollars Some of his
<persName>friends</persName> are of opinion that he received several hundred dollars on
the way that his <persName>family</persName> knew nothing of. it appears however very
certain that he aught to have had $1000. His fellow <persName>Traveller </persName>and
<persName>confident </persName>(<persName>Capt. Lusk</persName>) writes from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> in a very short
and unexplanatory manner informing <persName>Mrs. Gillespie</persName> of her <persName>Husband</persName>s death stating he had died after some ten or fifteen days
Illness at the <placeName>Fort in your Colony</placeName> (I suppose the <placeName>Fort Settlement</placeName>)
that he <persName>Capt Lusk</persName> had sold <persName>Mr. Gillespie</persName>'s horse to pay his Burial
expenses that himself was then in <placeName>New Orlean</placeName> on his way to the
State of <placeName>Ohio</placeName>. There is nothing in <persName>Capt Lusk</persName>s letter to give us
to understand what disposition was made of the money he (<persName>Mr
Gillespie</persName>) had. There appears to be a mistery in the affair which
makes it due to the <persName>family of Mr Gillespie</persName> and the character of
<persName>Capt. Lusk</persName> that an enquiry should be made as such you would
confer a favour on us by making such enquiries as would account
for the disposition of the money he had with him whether disposed of in the purchase of Land or otherwise and give us as early
information as may comport with your convenience.</p>

<p>Your <placeName>Country</placeName> is much spoken of here and much more in <placeName>Tennessee</placeName> and <placeName>Kentucky</placeName>&#8212;<persName>Judge Ellis</persName> and some other gentlemen will
be to see it this <date n="Spring - 1826">Spring </date>The <persName>judge</persName> will make arrangements for
my coming. I wrote you by <persName>Mr Gillespie</persName> consequently have but
little to say here You will write me on every subject which might
be of any importance as it is seldom we receive the Truth from
<placeName>Texas</placeName>. I expect young <persName>Mr Hughs</persName> will have arrived before you
receive this as he left here some time ago.</p>

<p>I have been told of a Proclamation of <persName>Mr Edwards</persName> requiring the
holders of <placeName>Old Grants </placeName><placeName>Swithin the Limits of his ettlement</placeName> to come
forward I think probably one of my <placeName>grants </placeName>are <placeName>within his district
</placeName>if so you have no doubt made it known.</p>

<p>offer my respects to <persName>Capt Gray</persName> and tell him when he writes me
again to write more fully that I am never tired of receiving information from a <placeName>country</placeName> in which I feel so much interest.   I have <pb n="1267"/>
spoken for a pair of grey Hounds for your <persName>Brother</persName> which If I
succeed in getting will Bring when I come. Believe me to be most
sincerely your Obedient Humble Servt.</p>

<p><persName>R. R. Royall</persName></p>

<p><persName>Hon. S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Hon. Stephen F. Austin</persName>. <placeName>Nachitoches. State of Louisiana</placeName> The <persName>Post master at <placeName>Nachitoches</placeName></persName> will forward this by the
first <persName>safe hand</persName> to <placeName>Austin's colony Department of Texas in the U.
Mexican States</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
