<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB3011">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Benjamin W. Edwards to Stephen F. Austin, 10-01-1825</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Benjamin W. Edwards</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="CLS">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Cameron L. Sinclair</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-05-25">05-25-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">La Bahia Crossing, Brazos River, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1218-1219
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1825-10-01">10-01-1825</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-05-25" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Answering Austin's of September 15. Plans for colonizing his brother's grant. Austin's difficulties clue to ignorance of human nature.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>La Bahia Crossing Brasos River</placeName></p>

<p><date when="1825-10-01">Oct. 1st 1825</date></p>

<p>Dear Sir.</p>

<p>I recd in due time, your very friendly letter [of September 15],
and have been compelled to defer replying to it thus long, in consequence of my continued indisposition, with which I have been
persecuted since I left <placeName>town</placeName>, until a few days past&#8212; Indeed I
am now barely able to grasp my pen; and such is the feble state
of my body and mind both, that I am denied the gratification of
writing you a long and sentimental letter as you request, and as I
should have been pleased to have done.</p>

<p>In replying to your remarks respecting the claim of <persName>Mr Harrison</persName>,
I can say nothing more than I have already said to you in person.
I am sensible of the difficulties that present themselves in this case
and being unacquainted with the laws and policy of this <placeName>country</placeName>
feel myself incompetent to point out any way to you by which his
claim could be obtained, that you could derive any instruction from.
I myself can think of no other policy now, than that of your representing the peculiarity of the case to the <persName>Government</persName>, the merit of
the <persName>individual</persName>, the justice of his claim, and the probability of its
adding to the <placeName>colony</placeName> a worthy and useful <persName>family</persName>&#8212;   Could it be
obtained in this way, it would be much more agreeable to the feelings of his <persName>family </persName>as well as to my own&#8212;    I hope you will not
give yourself any inquietude upon the subject in the mean time from
any apprehension of censure from his <persName>family</persName>&#8212;   I feel confident
they will be satisfied with whatever disposition you may choose to
make of this matter-</p>

<p>In your letter, you are lengthy upon the subject of your difficulties
in settleing this <placeName>Colony</placeName>.   I have long since been sensible of the
causes of your difficulties, and find that you have very correctly
pointed them out.   They are I hope now principally over, and with
a proper degree of forbearance and perseverance, I have no doubt,
that they will all shortly vanish, and leave you to the enjoyment of
those advantages, that you have in the commencement anticipated,
and which must inevitably follow.    As it respects this affair of
<persName>Kinney</persName>, I have barely heard the subject mentioned once or twice
since my return to this quarter; and of late it appears entirely 
forgotten&#8212;   You must expect censure and abuse so long as you remain
in your present station, whether you act right or wrong.   Suppress
your feelings on such occasions and even, if necessary, humor the
prejudices of the people you have to deal with.    Your principal
business is with the Government, and your greatest danger is from <pb n="1219"/>
them. All your energies should be directed to the preserving of a
good understanding with them, while those little bickering and
commotions around you should pass unregarded and occupy but
little of your time&#8212; Your greatest misfortune <persName>Austin</persName>, has been
the want of a proper knowledge of human nature&#8212; It has been the
cause of many difficulties, that you have encountered in the last two
years&#8212; But you have in that short time, I doubt not, learnt more
than in all your former life&#8212; This may be too great a freedom
in me, but in this you read the evidence of friendship, and the only
kind of friendship that can be relied on.</p>

<p>I have just learnt that my <persName>brother</persName> has reached <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName> with
his <persName>family</persName>, and that he will establish his <placeName>office </placeName>at that <placeName>place</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have not yet recd a line from him, and am of course in possession
of no particulars respecting him and his movements. I hope to set
out on my journey in <date when="1825-10-04">two or three days</date>, and shall consequently see
him on my way in to the <placeName>U S.</placeName>&#8212; I shall disclose to him, as I have
done to you, my undigested and limited views respecting this <placeName>country</placeName>,
and shall urge him to commence a correspondence with you as soon
as I see him&#8212;</p>

<p>I am much impressed with the importance of a friendly understanding and a free and open communication between all the <persName>contractors these <placeName>grants</placeName></persName>of , and as it respects my <persName>brother</persName> I feel no hesitation in saying that it will both comport with his feelings and policy.</p>

<p>In looking over the C &#8212;&#8212; law, I find you have overlooked an essential part of its provisions. I discover that each <persName>family</persName>, who moves into
those <placeName>grants </placeName>at their <hi rend="italic">own expence</hi> are entitled to <hi rend="italic">two</hi> Labors instead
of one, which being proclaimed might make in favor of the settlement of the <placeName>country</placeName>. The law seems to contemplate that the <persName>contractors </persName>will in the main bring in the <persName>families </persName>at their expence, being
ignorant of the <persName>American </persName>character altogether.</p>

<p>You wish to know my ideas upon the subject of the <persName>Waco</persName> war.
I feel some delicacy in giving an opinion, as I may not know enough
about the situation and policy of the <placeName>country</placeName> to give a correct opinion&#8212;But since you have desired my views upon the subject, I must
remark, that I am of the opinion I have always been; and which perhaps I ventured to express to you when I was down; and that is "that
it should be the last and only alternative"&#8212;some of my reasons I
think I then gave you. I have no room to say more upon the subject.</p>

<p>I shall in a <date when="1825-10-03">day or two</date> perhaps start on my journey <placeName>home</placeName>, and
should I determine to return to this <placeName>country</placeName>, (which is very likely)
we will I hope often have an opportunity of communicating our views
to each other.   Until then a dieu&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>B. W. Edwards</persName></p>

<p><persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
