<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4179">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Francis W Johnson to Stephen F Austin, 03-21-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Francis W Johnson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-09">09-09-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 623-624
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-03-21">03-21-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Report of proceedings of the ayuntamiento. Militia ineffective, and the ayuntamiento is petitioning for
permission to organize a company of rangers. Judiciary.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Town of Austin</placeName></p>
<p><date when="1831-03-21">21st March 1831</date></p>
<p>Dr. Sir,</p>

<p>I received and have read with pleasure yours of the<date when="1831-01-22"> 22nd. Jany</date> and
<date when="1831-02-05">5 Feby </date>last, and do sincerely wish you may succeed in the <placeName>Circuit
Court and jury system</placeName>.</p>

<p>Owing to the severity of the weather and the distance that the
most of the <persName>members </persName>resides from this place we have not been able
to convene in session but twice, at the first nothing of importance
was done and at the second but little finished, in anticipation, 
however of what will in all probability be done at our next meeting
which will take place on the <date when="1831-04-02">2nd. of next month</date>, I write you as
follows which is the most important so that you may have some
time to think and reflect in the best course to be pursued in relation
to them.</p>

<p>The first is a memorial to the government praying for authority
to rase a <persName>company of rangers</persName> and to make an appropration for the
payment of said <persName>rangers </persName>which will be forwarded to the <persName>Chief of
Department</persName> by this mail.</p>

<p>Second a <persName>committee </persName>was appointed to draft a plan for rasing a
fund to defray the expenses of the <placeName>municipality</placeName>, to pay the debts
due by the same: and also for the building of a <placeName>jail</placeName>, and a <placeName>house</placeName>
sufficient for transacting the business of the <persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>and
<placeName>office </placeName>of the <persName>Alcalda</persName>, and also to form and report a plan of the said
<placeName>buildings</placeName>, and make an estimate of the probable cost of erecting
and completing them, which will be reported and acted upon at the
next meeting and forwarded to the <persName>Chief of Department</persName>. I deem
it unnecessary to say anything on this subject, convinced as I am
that you know the necessity importance and worth of said 
<placeName>buildings</placeName>, and also of some established mode for rasing funds.</p>

<p>At our first meeting in consequence of the frequent outrages 
committed by hostile <persName>Indians </persName><placeName>on the frontiers of the Municipality</placeName>, We
called on the <persName>Lieut Colonel of this Battalion </persName>to rase a <persName>company of
men </persName>by draft or otherwise to serve as <persName>rangers</persName>, which he readily
complied with by issuing an order to the <persName>lst. Adjutant</persName>, who on his
part as readily issued corresponding  orders to  the  commanding<pb n="624"/>
officers of <persName>Companies</persName>, who as on former occasions did not obey the
order for on the day they were to have rendevoused at this place
instead of the required number only ten <persName>men </persName>reported themselves
to the <persName>Adjutant</persName>, nine of whom were from the<persName> 5th Company</persName>. Such
is the situation of the <persName>militia </persName>and I fear the diposition of the 
<persName>Commanding officer</persName>, that all and every call will be attended to in a like
manner, be the necessity what it may, I mention this to show you
that the <persName>Militia </persName>cannot be relied on, and consequently the double
necessity for obtaining an appropration for rasing a <persName>company </persName>by
enlistment for some specific time and price. However until this is
done or the contrary appears, I am determined to remind the 
<persName>commanding officer of the Battalion</persName> of what he ought to have done in
the first case, by orders and fines if any can be imposed under such
circumstances, until he acts as an officer should do.</p>

<p>On the subject of the administration of justice, as respects myself
I can say but little and probably ought not to say any thing but 
believing as I do that whatever concerns the <placeName>Colony </placeName>in any wise is a
matter of interest to you, I feel it a duty to give such information as
the shortness of time that I have acted in the capacity of an <persName>officer</persName>
will allow. As yet if I have not given satisfaction the people have
had courtesy enough not to complain, except the <persName>friends of Ingram
and League</persName>, to whom are united a part of the <persName>friends of H. S. Brown</persName>,
as to the number and respectability I say not. In this case as all
others my acts and conduct as an <persName>officer </persName>are publick, therefore I have
the people to judge and time to prove the propriety of both, and
whether correct or not I have the consolation of knowing that I
have done what I believed to be my duty as an <persName>officer</persName>.</p>

<p>I enclose you a copy of a letter directed to the<persName> Assessor General
</persName>on the subject of Interest and Usury, which if consistent with your
views on the subject, I must beg you will mention to the <persName>Assessor</persName>
and so far as prudence will permit give to it your strength and 
influence.</p>

<p>I take this opportunity of acknowledging the obligation of 
gratitude I feel on account of the interest you have taken in my behalf,
and your advice will be received with due deference.</p>

<p>A word more on the subject of <persName>father Muldoon</persName> and I have done.
From the character of that gentleman he is anxiously wished and
looked for&#8212;Messrs. <persName>Lesassier</persName>, <persName>Williams </persName>and <persName>Williamson </persName>are a 
<persName>committee </persName>to wait on him on his arrival in this place.</p>

<p>I hope you will keep us informed how you get on in the legislature
and excuse me for not writing you sooner.</p>

<p><persName>F. W. Johnson </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
