<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4698">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Henry Austin to James F Perry, 11-14-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Henry Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-14">02-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brazoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 26-29
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-11-14">11-14-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Encloses copy of an address which he drafted.  Thinks unnecessary now to circulate it.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Brazoria </placeName><date when="1834-11-14">14, Nov&#8212;1834</date></p>

<p><persName>Mr J F Perry</persName></p>

<p>My Dear Sir I found your letter at <placeName>home </placeName>on my arrival from <placeName>St. Felipe.</placeName>
I was under great alarm for the course of political matters in this 
<placeName>municipality</placeName>, not daring to hope that so decisive a pronouncement would be
made by the <persName>people of this <placeName>Jurisdiction</placeName></persName> as has been made altho almost
unanimous in the upper one, I therefore coincided with <persName>McKinney </persName>and
yourself that something ought to be done, and as the paper you sent me
was informal and not as I thought sufficiently explicit, I drew the one
enclosed and came to town to consult and arrange with you or <persName>McKinney</persName>
as to the best mode of circulating it for signatures&#8212; I now find that
<persName>McKinney </persName>is gone&#8212; That there can be no doubt of the Elections going
right&#8212;I have seen <persName>Govr Smith</persName> <date when="1834-11-14">this morning</date> and he assured me he had
issued notice to <persName>Waller </persName>as well as to other <persName>Ayuntamientos </persName>to hold the Election and if <persName>Waller </persName>neglected his duty he would order the Polls to be held
at the usual places at the usual time I think this spontanious expression of
public feeling much better than any that could have been brought about<pb n="27"/>
by any open exertions of the <persName>friends of Col A.</persName>&#8212;and as things are in a
fair way to come out right our best policy is to avoid everything that can
produce irritation and look with a single eye to the Elections, with a sound
<persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>legally installed all will go right.</p>

<p>You must not decline the nomination for <persName>first Regidor</persName> it will not give
you much trouble and the ticket your name is on will be carried by a strong
vote which will make us safe&#8212; I am glad to learn <persName>Stephen </persName>is to have
a tryal at last for with anything like fair play and legal decision he will
come off with flying colors</p>

<p><persName>H Austin </persName>[Rubric]</p>

<p>I enclose the paper I drew up to show you I have not been idle.</p>

<p>[Enclosure]</p>
<p>address to the <persName>public</persName></p>
<p>By this Public declaration</p>
<p>Be it Known</p>

<p>That we the undersigned <persName>Citizens of the <placeName>Mexican Republic</placeName></persName>, and of the
<placeName>State of Coahuilla and Texas</placeName>; <persName>Resident in the <placeName>Municipality of Columbia</placeName>,
(heretofore called <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>)</persName> being seriously alarmed by the late 
unauthorised call of an Election of members to a <persName>Revolutionary Congress</persName>; 
Jeopardizing as we believe the security of our <persName>families </persName>and our dearest rights and
interests, and tending, if acquiesced in by the <persName>people </persName>to the utter ruin of
all our hopes in <placeName>Texas</placeName>; Feel it incumbent upon us to make this our Public
Protest against, and declaration of disent to, the unauthorized doings of a
few ambitious <hi rend="italic"><persName>agitators </persName>of revolutionary measures.</hi></p>

<p>As <persName>Republicans</persName>, we hold to the immutable republican principle, that in
a republican community, no measure involving the peace, security and
happiness of the <persName>people</persName>, should be adopted without the assent of a majority
of the <persName>people</persName>, fairly called for and distinctly expressed&#8212;</p>

<p>Yet we have seen as we conceive our most sacred rights and privileges
usurped, and sentiments expressed upon our responsibility, which we do
not, nor ever have, subscribed to;</p>

<p>We therefore deem it our duty to ourselves and to our <persName>fellow Citizens</persName> of
the other <placeName>municipalities of Texas</placeName>, to permit no longer by our Silence, a
few aspiring ambitious men&#8212;Zealous to promote their own elevation and
individual advantage, but reckless of consequences to the great body of the
people; to use our names or assume the right of thinking for, or dictating
to us the Political course we shall pursue, without our knowledge or 
consent;&#8212;<pb n="28"/></p>

<p>We distinctly avow our decided disapprobation of the attempt, made by
the <persName>political chief</persName>, to obtain an election of <persName>members </persName>to a <persName>revolutionary
Congress</persName>&#8212;without calling for the sense of the people, or even consulting
the <persName>Central Committee</persName>, appointed by a convention to warn the People of
political dangers&#8212;</p>

<p>Because we view the measure as an unwarantable assumption of authority
TO DICTATE to the people</p>

<p>Because we deem the measure to be fraught with the most ruinous 
consequences to the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>; as directly at variance with the true
interests of our <placeName>adopted country</placeName>, tending to confirm all the unfounded
suspicions (which have been created by evil minded persons,) of our
revolutionary and rebellious dispositions, and destructive of all confidence,
both at <placeName>home </placeName>and <placeName>abroad</placeName>, in the stability and security of political rights
and in the rights of person and property in <placeName>Texas</placeName>; Which we Consider to
be the basis of all public and private prosperity&#8212;</p>

<p>Because we conceive that the <persName>Genl Govt</persName>. by the repeal of the 11 art. of
the obnoxious <date when="1830-04-06">6 April</date> law&#8212;and leaving us until this late period exempt&#8212;
from the payment of imposts [and] duties, paid by the <persName>people </persName>of all <placeName>other
parts of the republic</placeName>, has shown a most paternal regard for our 
prosperity&#8212;</p>

<p>Because we believe that the <persName>State Congress</persName> has given us all the Elements
of good government order and Security under the law, by enacting laws
establishing a system of Jurisprudence adapted to our situation with tryal
by <persName>jury</persName>, which if carried out according to the provisions of the law and
sustained by the people, would place Justice within the reach of every
Citizen, ACCORDING TO THE JUDGEMENT OF HIS <persName>PEERS</persName>; HIS
OWN <persName>NEIGHBORS </persName>OR <persName>EQUALS</persName>:</p>

<p>Because we believe that the arrest and cruel imprisonment of our envoy
to the <persName>Genl Govt&#8212;(Col Austin)</persName> has been occasioned not by any hostile
feeling on the part of the <persName>members of Govt</persName> but by false and malicious
charges, made by evil minded, <persName>malignant persons</persName>, resident in <placeName>Texas </placeName>and
laid before the Govt in such a shape that it became its imperious duty to
take notice of them</p>

<p>Because we are convinced that however desirable a <persName>state Gov</persName>t may be
<hi rend="italic">if obtainable by moral force</hi> (constitutional and legal means) that it has
become less necessary to our prosperity since the establishment of a system
of Jurisprudence which is calculated to give us most of the benefits without
the enormous expense of sustaining a state govt</p>

<p>Because we conscientiously believe, that the frequent agitations of 
political revolutionary measures in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, tends not only to bring us into
collision with the state and <persName>genl Govts</persName> without a chance of success in a
Contest in arms; but by passing to the <placeName>United States of the north</placeName> with
exaggeration destroys all confidence there in the security of property in<pb n="29"/>
<placeName>Texas</placeName>, prevents the immigration of <persName>men of Capital</persName> and force, renders 
property valueless, and blights forever the hopes we have entertained of seeing
<hi rend="italic">"The Wilderness blossom as The rose"</hi></p>

<p>Therefore we feel it to be a duty from which we can no longer abstain
to take this method of making known our disapprobation of any and all
revolutionary measures and our dissatisfaction with <hi rend="italic">"the Choice Spirits"</hi>
who arrogate to themselves the right of thinking and acting for us; 
Sincerely hoping that hereafter they will have the modesty to leave it to the
people to discover their virtues and talents and to wait for a call upon
them, whenever their aid or Counsel may be required</p>

<p>And to the end that this expression of Sentiment may not be taken to be
that of a small number of Citizens, We have adopted this mode of defining
the public feeling by Circulating this decalaration that every mans name
may stand in evidence of his views and wishes</p>

<p>Dated in <placeName>Columbia </placeName>this________________day of <date n="11-xx-1834">November 1834</date></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
