<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4993">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>R R Royall to Stephen F Austin, 10-27-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>R R Royall</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-07">06-07-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Head Quarters, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 215-216
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-10-27">10-27-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-07" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Assistance from United States. Activities of the Permanent Council</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1835-10-27">Octr. 27th 1835</date></p>
<p><persName>Genl. S. F. Austin</persName></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>By <persName>Mr Hufman</persName> a <persName>member from <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></persName> I write you the particulars
of Information before us at this time mostly contained in a Letter from the
<persName>Committee of <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></persName>, a copy of which I forward you by this 
conveyance together with Resolutions (you will find in our last Paper) of
<persName>Citizens of <placeName>Nachitoches</placeName></persName>, at a Genl <persName>Public </persName>meeting in which you will see a
very Liberal Sentiment prevails in the <placeName>U. States </placeName>toward us&#8212;Our Coreo
[mail] from <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>says the <persName>People of the <placeName>Red Lands</placeName></persName> Intend to send
on more help still and <persName>60 men</persName> have also been expected from <placeName>Bevil 
Settlement</placeName> other <persName>Reinforcements </persName>may also be expected from <placeName>other Quarters</placeName>, and
from all you will Readyly see you will have nothing to Loose by 
remaining Secure in your Present Position, untill other <persName>Reinforcements</persName>, shall 
arrive and on the contrary every thing favourable to our cause may be 
expected by waiting untill we can make a secure attact confidently believing
that for the next 3 months the longer we delay the easier the conquest on
act. of the Genl. Increase of Numbers on our side.</p>

<p>We have answered the <persName>Citizens of <placeName>Nachitoches</placeName></persName> through their <persName>Chairman</persName>
in a very respectfull maner and Earnestly solicited that Immediate aid so
nobly offered we have also through the same chanels address'd a feeling
and exciting appeal to the <persName>Citizens of the <placeName>U. States</placeName></persName> Generally we have
had Copies, of <persName>Mr Dimitt</persName>s Letter Printed with Suitable urgent solicitations
on the <persName>People of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> to turn out and Repair to <placeName>Camp at head Quarters</placeName>,
and an earnest call upon those who have been misguided by the designing
to remain inactive Informing them that while the Convention is rewarding
those who so Bravely defend our cause they will not fail to Impose upon
those who refuse the reward due their crime We have also taken the 
Responsability of appointing <persName>Mr T. F. McKinney</persName> as <persName>General Agent</persName> to repair<pb n="216"/>
to <placeName>N Orleans</placeName> and negotiate (under instructions) for the Loan of $100 000
We have our fears of the success as we find in <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName>, Bee and the 
Resolutions of the meeting at <placeName>Nachitoches </placeName>urging our declaration of 
Independence as a necessary step to the procuring of aid from the <persName>Citizens of the
<placeName>U. States</placeName></persName>. <persName>Mr McKinney</persName>s Instructions, are to learn the probable success
before his Buisiness is declared or made public. I hope <persName>Mr McKinney</persName> will
Accept and If he fails in negotiating a loan he will no doubt be able to
Raise considerable by Contributions as Well as have a tendency to Raise
<persName>Volunteers </persName>at that Place a man has gone below to forward the Large
Cannon, Ball and Powder I sincerely hope he will succeed. <persName>Mr W S. Hall</persName>
is on the <placeName>Guadaloupe </placeName>Raising Beaves, and getting meal. <persName>Mr Baird</persName> is here
collecting as many as 100 If he can in this <placeName>Quarter</placeName>. You will properly
communicate with <persName>Mr Hall</persName> as <persName>Contractor at <placeName>Gonzales</placeName></persName> on the subject of
Meal and Beef for the <persName>Army</persName>&#8212;We do not know how the <persName>convention </persName>will
look upon this step of ours to Borrow Money to So Large an amt. but I
would ask what will we do shall be wait until we are destitute and have
not a dollar to pay an <persName>Express </persName>and suffer defeat for fear of Creating 
Responsibilities or should we assume the authority to do all and every thing
necessary to carry the designs of our friend in the field in to Effect to Give
them Bread Meat Arms, amunition clothing and <persName>Reinforcements from
<placeName>abroad</placeName></persName> we have been already accused of transcending our Powers If we
have we have the Conscientious Convictions of having but one Aim to save
<placeName>texas </placeName>and Protect our <persName>Wives </persName>and <persName>children </persName>complaints from the <placeName>East </placeName>made
through their <placeName>delegates </placeName>state that <persName>Persons </persName>are engaged in taking up choice
lands to the Prejudice of those in the field. I have had nothing to say in
the matter myself as an Individual, yet I on reflection approve of the 
Resolution to suspend all land entries till the meeting of the <persName>consultation </persName>when
as we Give assurances in Our resolutions, those who serve in the <persName>Army </persName>shall
be provided for on terms perfectly satisfactorily to their wishes. We have
written to them to come down here. They are friendly We are told that
<persName>Roag [Rueg] the Political [chief] at <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></persName> has ordered out the
<persName>Mexicans in that <placeName>Quarter</placeName></persName> in behalf of the Constitution.</p>

<p>[Addressed:]<persName> Genl. S. F. Austin Commander in Chief</persName> <placeName>Head Quarters</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
