<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4620">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Ayuntamiento of San Felipe, 01-17-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-02">12-02-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Ayuntamiento of San Felipe
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monterrey, Nuevo Leon</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1039-1041
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-01-17">01-17-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-02" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Announcing arrest and advising tranquillity.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Monterey</placeName>, <date when="1834-01-17">Jan. 17, 1834</date></p>
<p>To the <persName>Ayuntamiento of <placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName></persName>:</p>

<p>I have been arrested by an order from the <persName>minister of war</persName>, and
leave soon for <placeName>Mexico </placeName>to answer to a charge made against me, as I
understand, for writing an officio to the <persName>Ayuntamiento[s] of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>,
dated <date when="1833-10-02">2d October</date> last, advising, or rather recommending that they
should consult amongst themselves for the purpose of organizing a
<persName>local government</persName> for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, in the event that no remedies could be
obtained for the evils that threatened that country with ruin.</p>

<p>I do not in any manner blame the <persName>government </persName>for arresting me,
and I particularly request that there may be no excitement about it.</p>

<p>I give the advice to the <persName>people </persName>there that I have always given, keep
quiet, discountenance all revolutionary measures or men, obey the
<persName>state authorities</persName> and laws so long as you are attached to <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>,
have no more conventions, petition through the legal channels, that
is through the <persName>ayuntamiento </persName>and <persName>chief of department</persName>, harmonize
fully with the <persName>people of <placeName>Bexar </placeName>and <placeName>Goliad</placeName>,</persName> and act with them.</p>

<p>The <persName>general government</persName> are disposed to do everything for <placeName>Texas</placeName>
that can be done to promote its prosperity and welfare that is
consistent with the constitution and laws, and I have no doubt the
<persName>state government</persName> will do the same if they are applied to in a proper
manner.</p>

<p>It will be remembered that I went to <persName>Mexico </persName>as a <persName>public agent</persName>
with specific instructions, and as such, that it was my duty to be
governed by them, and by the general wish of the people as expressed
to me.   Also, that when I left in <date n="04-xx-1833">April</date>, the general wish did express<pb n="1040"/>
itself for the separation from <placeName>Coahuila </placeName>and the forming of <placeName>Texas</placeName>
into a <placeName>state of this confederation</placeName>. Also, that there was a 
determination to organize a <persName>local government</persName> at all hazards, if no remedy
could be obtained.</p>

<p>I have in all my acts conformed to this public wish of the people,
so far as I was informed of it, and when I despaired of obtaining
any remedy, as I did the beginning of <date n="10-xx-1833">October</date>, I deemed it to be
my duty as an <persName>agent </persName>to inform the people so; and believing as I
did, that they would organize, I also considered that it would be
much better to do so, by a harmonious consultation of the 
<persName>Ayuntamiento[s]</persName> than by a popular commotion. These were my reasons
for the recommendation given in that officio; also, the result of
the civil war was thought to be doubtful.</p>

<p>I understand, and I rejoice to hear it, that public opinion has
settled down on a more reasonable basis, and that the most of the
<persName>Ayuntamientos of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> have expressed their wish to proceed in
a legal manner to seek redress. I ought to have been informed of
this change, but I was not, and knew nothing of it to a certainty,
untill the <date when="1833-11-05">5th of November</date>, so that up to that time I acted under
the impressions I had when I left <placeName>Texas </placeName>in <date n="04-xx-1833">April</date>. Since then I
have not moved the state question.</p>

<p>The past events in <placeName>Texas </placeName>necessarily grew out of the revolution
of <placeName>Jalappa</placeName>, which overturned the constitution and produced the
counter revolution of <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, which extended over the whole
country, and involved <placeName>Texas </placeName>with the rest. It is well known that
it was my wish to keep <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and particularly the <placeName>colony</placeName>, out of
all revolution, and I tried to do so, but the flame broke out in my
absence from <placeName>Texas</placeName>, in <date n="06-xx-1832">June 1832</date>, and since then all has been 
completely disjointed. A current was set in motion by the general events
of the civil war all over the <placeName>nation</placeName>, and under the circumstances,
<placeName>Texas </placeName>could not avoid being agitated by it. No one can be blamed
in any manner for what has happened since <date n="06-xx-1832">June, 1832</date>, in <placeName>Texas</placeName>-
it was inevitable&#8212;neither was it possible for me to avoid being
drawn into the whirlpool. It was my duty to serve the country as
an <persName>agent </persName>if requested to do so; and as an <persName>agent </persName>it was my duty
to obey my instructions as expressed to me.</p>

<p>I have long since informed the <persName>Ayuntamientos of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> of the
repeal of the law of<date when="1830-04-06"> April, 1830</date>, and of the favorable and friendly
disposition of the government, and by this, I of course rescinded, or
annulled, the recommendation of <date when="1833-10-02">2d October</date>, for that was predicated
on the belief that nothing would be done, and that the result of the
civil war then pending was even doubtful, since then all has changed
for the better, and public opinion in <placeName>Texas </placeName>has become sound, and<pb n="1041"/>
shaken off the excitement that necessarily grew out of the past
agitations.</p>

<p>Under these circumstances the prospects of <placeName>Texas </placeName>are better than
they ever have been. The national revolution is ended, a 
constitutional government exists, the <persName>people </persName>are obedient to the <persName>government</persName>
and laws, everywhere. Be the same in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and have no more 
excitements, tolerate no more violent measures, and you will prosper
and obtain from the <persName>government </persName>all that reasonable men ought to
ask for.</p>

<p>The last year has been one of calamities for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, floods, 
pestilence, and commotions, I hope the present year will be more 
favorable. I request that you will have this letter published for general
information, and also the enclosed copy of the answer given to me
by his Excellency the minister of relations. You will see by this
answer the very favorable and friendly disposition of the <persName>general
government</persName> to make a state or a territory of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and do 
everything else within its constitutional powers for the good of that
<placeName>country</placeName>.</p>

<p>I consider my agency for <placeName>Texas </placeName>as terminated, but this will not
prevent me from doing all I can for the good of that <placeName>country</placeName>, on my
own individual responsibility.</p>

<p>Respectfully your most ob't sert.,</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
