<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4471">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John P Sheldon to Stephen F Austin, 11-12-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John P Sheldon</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-03">11-03-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Detroit, Michigan</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 885-887
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-11-12">11-12-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-03" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Introducing Le Roy and Comstock, who are the advance guard of an "emigrating party" of 15 or 20 families who will go to Texas next season.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Detroit</placeName>, <date when="1832-11-12">Nov. 12,1832,</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>I have the satisfaction of introducing to your acquaintance <persName>Mr.
Robert Le Roy</persName>, (a connexion of mine) and <persName>Mr. E. Comstock</persName>. They
are young men of the strictest "probity, of the most exemplary habits,
and possessing enterprise and industry so as to render them an 
acquisition to your <placeName>colony</placeName>, and to ensure to themselves an enviable
independence. They are but the <persName>pioneers of several families </persName>who
will leave this part of the <placeName>U. States</placeName> <date n="xx-xx-1833">next season</date> for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and they
wish to find a place which will justify them in erecting a <placeName>saw mill
</placeName>and other <placeName>works</placeName>, and which will warrant the formation of a 
<placeName>neighborhood </placeName>of fifteen or twenty <persName>families</persName>. With the <persName>families</persName>, (which
will be formed into an <persName>emigrating company</persName>) it is my intention to be<pb n="886"/>
numbered&#8212;indeed, it is from my advice and representations, that
the plan has been adopted&#8212;consequently, you must be aware of my
solicitude respecting the location of the contemplated <placeName>settlement</placeName>. I
was much delighted with the district of <placeName>country in the vicinity of
<persName>Brookfield</persName>'s</placeName>, but am not certain that water power of sufficient 
magnitude can be had without it is found some <placeName>10 or 15 miles from him</placeName>,
in some of the <placeName>bends of the Colorado</placeName>. A water power and timber
would be desirable. The former, I was told, is abundant in the 
<placeName>interior far as your most northern grant</placeName>as &#8212;please direct the young
<persName>men </persName>to those parts where they will be most likely to find what they
desire, and also tell them what the advantages are for industrious
<persName>agriculturists </persName>and <persName>stock raisers</persName>. These young men are a sample of
those that will emigrate <date n="xx-xx-1833">next season</date>; and are such as will do, each
of them, more actual labor, either as <persName>merchanics </persName>or <persName>agriculturists</persName>,
than three or four men, <persName>black </persName>or <persName>white</persName>, that have been reared with
southern habits&#8212;they are just such as I know you wish to see
<placeName>Texas </placeName>filled with&#8212;and just such as your glorious country deserves.
I am more and more impressed with the correctness of your views,
as expressed to me, relative to the destinies of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and the proper
policy to be pursued.</p>

<p><persName>Mr. Le Roy</persName> and <persName>Mr. Comstock</persName> will inform you of the extent of
the desire to emigrate to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, among the <persName>people of the <placeName>county</placeName></persName> in
which they live&#8212;the feeling is spread far even in this <placeName>new country</placeName>,
from even the slight information which has been diseminated among
them. What then could not be done in the <placeName>eastern and northern
states</placeName>, in the way of forming <persName>emigrating companies</persName>, if proper
measures were adopted ?</p>

<p>I feel, sir, that I have embarked in an important business, (the
arrangement and formation of an <persName>emigrating party</persName>) and it would
always be a source of regret to me, to be instrumental in deceiving
the hopes or just expectations of any one: for this reason, sir, I feel
that every particle of information from <placeName>Texas</placeName>, at all affecting the
interests and well-being of the <persName>settlers</persName>, will be of high importance,
I assure, you, sir, that those who emigrate with me shall not have it
to say that I withheld or misstated any thing in my power to 
communicate, and important for them to know.</p>

<p>By the latest information which has reached me from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, I
perceive that <persName>Santa Anna </persName>has met a reverse in the defeat of 
<persName>Moctezuma</persName>&#8212;and that he himself is in somewhat a critical situation. Tell
me, sir, should those against whom <persName>Santa Anna</persName> took up arms, 
prevail against him, will they dare attempt to be avenged on those of
<placeName>Texas </placeName>who have declared in his favor? Or will they dare attempt
to narrow the privileges of your <persName>colonists</persName>, from the disposition
which they have manifested to abrogate the abominable law to pre-<pb n="887"/>
vent emigration, and the desire which they have expressed to be a
sovereign state of the <placeName>Republic</placeName>? For myself, I am certain that, let
the civil commotion terminate as it may, the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> need
not, from that result, be subjected to any loss, or have their prospects
of rapid advancement in wealth and importance, much impeded&#8212;so
sure am I that the <persName>dominant party in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>,</persName> must be aware of the
strength, the spirit, and the resources of the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>. At
all events, you would oblige me much by letting me know your views,
so that I can have it in my power to reassure those who may feel
fearful about the peace of the <persName>Settlers</persName>.</p>

<p>You may rest assured, sir, that the <persName>families </persName>who will compose the
<persName>emigrating party</persName> to <placeName>Texas </placeName>will be just such as you will rejoice to
see&#8212;respectable, intelligent, and industrious such as you find always
among the <persName>most valuable citizens of our villages in <placeName>N. York</placeName> or 
<placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName></persName>: for they will for the most part be people from the states
who have removed here, and find the winters too rigorous. All our
<persName>farmers </persName>indeed, appear to be sighing for your genial climate and
rich meadows and soil.</p>

<p>Should you happen to see <persName>Doctr N. Labadie, of <placeName>Anahuac</placeName></persName>, please
inform him that his <persName>mother </persName>and <persName>connexions </persName>are well, and wish very
much to receive a letter from him.</p>

<p>Give my best wishes to <persName>Mr Williams</persName> and other gentlemen of my
acquaintance and beleive me, sir,</p>

<p><persName>Col S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p><persName>Jno P Sheldon</persName> [Rubric]</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
