<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4671">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 09-07-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-10">12-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Prison of the Acordada, Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1087-1088
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-09-07">09-07-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Account of his imprisonment. Advises Williams to keep out of politics. Robertson colony.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1834-09-07">Sept 7 1834</date>, <placeName>Prison of the Acordada</placeName>.</p>
<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p>My case has been travelling about from one <persName>tribunal </persName>to another
up to the present time at first a <persName>military tribunal</persName>, then a juez de
letras, then to a <persName>district judge</persName>&#8212;thence to the <persName>Supreme Court</persName>. All
the <persName>inferior courts</persName> decided that they had no jurisdiction over it,
and it was sent to the <persName>Supreme Court</persName> for the purpose of ascertaining
what <persName>tribunal </persName>ought to try it. I have [now] been informed that
the <persName>Supreme Court</persName> has decided that it must be tryed by the <persName>district
judge of the <placeName>Federal district</placeName></persName>, so that I presume I shall now get on a
little faster. I have in eight months ascertained what court is to
try the matter.</p>

<p>I am of the opinion that my affairs will terminate favourably, and
without much more delay. I think I shall be able to get my liberty
by giving bail or [security] not to leave this city.</p>

<p>I wrote to my brother in law <persName>James F. Perry</persName> [on the]<date when="1834-08-25"> 25 of last
month.</date> I refer you and my friends to that letter. I have nothing
more to add to it, except to repeat the opinion that <placeName>Texas </placeName>ought to
keep out [of] all kind of political excitements, and act in strict
conformity with the motto&#8212;<hi rend="italic">Fidelity to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and opposition to
violent men or measures</hi>. Also all kind of personalities, ought to be
forgotten and buried. I have been more [injured] by them, than
any other, and I will be the first to forget them and meet my
<persName>enemies </persName>in harmony on the basis of the motto above stated.</p>

<p><date when="1834-09-06">Yesterday </date>I recd your letter dated <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date when="1834-07-31">31 July</date>. I
expect I shall have to draw on <persName>Beers St John and Co</persName> for another
thousand dollars, to pay <persName>lawyer</persName>s fees etc, you write me in the above
letter that I can draw on them. I sent <persName>Perry </persName>a power of attorney
to sell any of my property he thought proper, and I rely on you
and him to save my property from the wreck that seems to have
been intended by some persons, for me.</p>

<p>I approve of your determination to devote yourself to commerce.
Your <persName>family </persName>and <persName>friends </persName>in the <placeName>United States</placeName> are well known and
have a standing in the com[mercial] world, that enables them to
afford you great facilities and advantages as a <persName>merchant</persName>, and besides
this, in that business you can reasonably expect some tranquility
and happi[ness] which you, nor no other man, need ever look for
in public affairs [or] politics. Let them alone for the rest of your
life if you wish for peace and [pros]perity.</p>

<p>Send this to <persName>Mr Perry</persName>. I am in tolerable health, but have
suffered a good deal from rheumatism. The State Govt, have
[been] imposed upon and deceived. My <persName>friends </persName>in <placeName>Texas </placeName>might
undeceive them if they were disposed to do so.   But "out of<pb n="1088"/>
sight out of mind " perhaps applies to me. I know not whether
I have friends there out of my own family. It is reported in
this city that I have none and as a proof of it, it is said that a 
<placeName>newspaper </placeName>is bountifully supported in the colony by the great mass of Ihe
people for the express purpose of abusing me. This I do not
believe nor half of the reports about the efforts of individuals to
calumniate and ruin me. I cannot, as yet, have so bad an opinion
of human nature. I care nothing about the <placeName>upper colony</placeName> except
to show that all my conduct in regard to it has been correct, as
it has been. I certainly do rely upon my <persName>friends </persName>in the <placeName>colony</placeName>
to make some efforts to place the truth of all these matters before
the Govt. They ought to remember that I am in a distant <placeName>prison</placeName>
unable, [by my] situation, to repel calumny, or defend [my] self&#8212;
and that I am in this prison for having performed what I believed
was my duty to my constituents; as a public <persName>agent</persName>. It ought to be
remembered that the duties of <persName>constituents</persName>, towards their <persName>public
agents</persName>, is not less sacred and [man]datory, than that of the <persName>agent</persName>
to his <persName>constituents</persName>.</p>

<p>I think you ought to go to <placeName>Menclova</placeName>, [and] lay a statement of
facts before the <persName>state [govern]ment</persName></p>

<p>[Re]member me to <persName>Sarah</persName>, to <persName>Mr Scotts[fam]ily</persName> , and to all my
old <persName>companions </persName>and <persName>friends</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>[A letter dated] <placeName>Brazoria </placeName><date when="1834-05-04">May 4</date> was published in the <placeName>New Orleans
Bulletin</placeName> which has in[jured me]. I prefer that my name should
be [kept] out of the <placeName>news papers</placeName>. All is perfectly quiet <placeName>in this
quarter </placeName>and I believe <placeName>all over the nation</placeName>. The elections are going
on in harmony every where.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>I send this by <persName>Mr Comber</persName>, a respectable young gentleman of some
capital, who thinks of settling somewhere in that <placeName>country</placeName>, I 
recommend him to all my <persName>friends</persName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. A.</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
