<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4475">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Ramon Musquiz, 11-15-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-03">11-03-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Ramon Musquiz
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 888-889
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-11-15">11-15-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-03" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Thinks it impolitic to publish Musquiz's address to Ayuntamiento of San Felipe concerning the convention. Thinks convention has done some good in quieting excitement. Outlook for Mexico dark.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe</placeName>: <date when="1832-11-15">November 15th 1832</date></p>
<p>Most Esteemed <persName>Friend</persName>. I agree with the sentiments expressed in
your appreciable letter of the <date when="1832-11-08">8th inst</date>. just received: "He is to be
pitied who has the misfortune to be at the head of public affairs,
in revolutionary times;" Indeed, be [he] a righteous man, or an
angel, he cannot escape the attacks of some party or individuals&#8212;
A rule we should always follow, is to do our duty, without 
minding what may be said: I on my part have always wished to follow
this rule, and my conscience is at rest: I found myself on several
occasions in rather a critical situation, but the polar star that has
always guided me, was to promote the true interests of the <placeName>Nation</placeName>
and <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and I can say that as far as I was able, I complied with<pb n="889"/>
my duty. With regard to the meeting, it did not originate with
me, but I believe some good will result from its action; the <persName>public</persName>
is satisfied, and we have enjoyed more quiet than heretofore.</p>

<p>As to your communication to the <persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>in relation to the
meeting, I believe that it would have been better, not to have written
it, <hi rend="italic">"Revolutionary times are not like peaceable times."</hi> Colonel
<persName>Bradburn </persName>could with the least prudence, have avoided all these
evils: I tell you candidly that in my opinion, it would be very
impolitic to translate, and print your communication, I shall not
do so. The <persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>may do as they please: In times like the
present, any measure is bad, that tends to irritate, and produce
excitement,&#8212;any measure is good that tends to soothe, and to 
preserve order and peace.</p>

<p>I have but little hope of obtaining anything from the 
<persName>Government of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>; there is little probability that we may have a stable
and peaceable <persName>government</persName>, for some time yet, and I believe that
<placeName>Texas </placeName>is lost if she takes no measure of her own for her welfare.
I incline to the opinion, that it is your duty as <persName>first Magistrate</persName>, to
call a general meeting to take into consideration the situation of
the <placeName>Country</placeName>. I do not know how the <placeName>State</placeName>, or <persName>General Government</persName>
can presume to say that the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> have violated the 
Constitution, when the acts of both <persName>Governments </persName>have killed the 
Constitution, and when the confederation itself has hardly any life left.
I cannot approve the principle, that the <persName>people </persName>have not the right
to assemble peaceably and honorably to represent their wants. In
short, the condition of <placeName>Texas </placeName>is bad, but we may fear to see it
still worse.</p>

<p>I am settling up all my business and in <date n="04-xx-1833">April </date>I will go to the
<placeName>North </placeName>for six months or one year. There is little to be hoped for
in <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I wish you would let me hear the news, and tell me if
the Constitution is dead, or alive, if an election for <persName>President </persName>shall
take place, and what hope there is for a peacable settlement of the
affairs. In the meanwhile please to give your orders to your 
affectionate friend</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
