<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4171">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William S Parrott to Stephen F Austin, 03-16-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William S Parrott</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-08">09-08-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 616-617
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-03-16">03-16-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Personal misfortunes; betrayal of trust by Stephen J. Wilson; politics.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1831-03-16">March 16th 1831</date></p>
<p><persName>Stephen P. Austin Esqr</persName></p>

<p><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Saltillo</placeName></hi></p>
<p>My Dear Sir</p>

<p>I have before me your regarded favour of the <date when="1831-03-27">27th ult°</date> and 
continuation of <date when="1831-03-28">28th </date>by which I am advised that my two letters of
the <date when="1831-03-09">9th</date> and <date when="1831-03-16">16th ult°</date> had reached you Our old friend <persName>Grande </persName>was
in the <placeName>counting House</placeName> when I received your letter; and was much
delighted to hear from you, and requested me particularly to 
remember him to you He is one of <date n="xx-xx-1822">1822</date> and few now remain in the
<placeName>City </placeName>or even in the <placeName>country </placeName>of our <persName>acquaintes </persName>[sic] and 
<persName>countrymen </persName>of that memorable Epoch; I am the only <persName>American </persName>that has
weathered the changes and vicissitudes consequent; of a continual
succession of revolution and <persName>rulers</persName>, most of the others have for
want of perseverance or moral virtue, been obliged to return to
their <placeName>homes </placeName>and others have passed off in the storm of intemperance
and folly to<placeName> another world</placeName>; For my part I have had a full share
of misfortunes; amidst; the smiles of prosperity. In <date n="xx-xx-1828">1828</date>, when
I had gained as much of this world's trash as satisfied my ambition,
I left here for the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> on a tour of pleasure, leaving the whole
under the management of <persName>Stephen J Wilson</persName>, whom I had interested
in my concerns, with a view to better his condition and leave him
eventually with the entire controul of the mercantile relations I
had formed for some preceding years; I was upon the point of
Embarking for <placeName>Europe </placeName>when I received letters from a friend here
advising me to return forthwith or my <placeName>House </placeName>would be in a state
of insolvency from the bad management observed in its operations;
Though I could scarcely believe it, I returned immediately and to
accelerate my steps travelled post from <placeName>Baltimore </placeName>to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
finding no vessel for either <placeName>Tampico </placeName>or <placeName>Vera Cruz </placeName>I freighted and
chartered a brig; on my arrival in <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> in <date n="01-xx-1829">January of 1829
</date>I learned the change in <persName>rulers </persName>and <hi rend="italic"><persName>saqueo </persName></hi>of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>by which latter
I supposed I was ruined as I was told my <placeName>House </placeName>did not escape
pillage; which proved in one sense correct for on arriving at <placeName>Puebla</placeName>
with my family I recd an express advising that <persName>Wilson </persName>had fled
and that the <persName>officers of justice</persName> were about to seize upon all they
could find supposing <persName>Wilson </persName>an <persName>accomplice </persName>in a Duel fought be-<pb n="617"/>
tween <persName>W. Wilcocks</persName> and <persName>George Follin </persName>I again took post, and in
9 hours arrived in the <placeName>city </placeName>when to my great astonishment, I found
the surmise of my friend but too true; Bad management during
my absence; and all the available means carried off by <persName>Wilson</persName>,
to the amt of 30.000$ and upwards; leaving debts to the amt of
near 50.000$ more; since which I have had to struggle hard to
organize every thing again; not having in the mean time been
able to obtain one cent from my <hi rend="italic"><persName>worthy partner</persName></hi>; all is going on
well again; I have been thus tedious to give you a full statement
of facts which may in part serve you; as I am told <persName>Wilson </persName>is in
<placeName>your section of the country</placeName>.</p>

<p>I am well aware of the fatigue and perplexities you must have
necessarily undergone since our separation; for which I agree with
you, there can be no compensation; but the calm consciousness of
having done your duty not only in regard to your contract with the
Govt but towards your <persName>colonists</persName>; which will be better appreciated
hereafter, than during your life time; I thank you for the 
information in relation to my solicitude in favor of the <persName>Widow Ross</persName> and
<persName>heirs</persName>, I have no personal interest in it other than a desire to serve the
<persName>widow </persName>and <persName>orphan </persName>of a man whose maintainance was at my charge
during his stay in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>without having received as yet any 
renumeration whatever; nor do I look for any, as his <persName>estate </persName>is insolvent
and the <persName>company at Nashville</persName> refuses to pay me near 1000$ given
to him to keep him from starving while, in the prosecution of their
designs and his success in a great measure was owing to my friendly
interference in his behalf</p>

<p>I have written to the <persName>Company in Nashville </persName>advising of the result
of my solicitude, I was not informed of the location of the <placeName>grant</placeName>
made to him even. In my opinion, however, the suspension of the
colonization <date when="1830-04-06">[law of 6] April</date> last will result to the benefit of all
con[cerned] in it who had not began at that period [mutilated]
for [that] law cannot nor does not annul the titles granted, and it
will afford them ample time to carry into effect their plans, Should
ever a change take place, less pregnant with groundless prejudices,
and unfounded suspicions of a <persName>neighbour </persName>than actually exists and
I am much in hopes to see a change ere long; when we will not be
regarded as an ambitious <persName>neighbour</persName>, but as one willing to give aid
in time of need; and if allowed to judge from words <hi rend="italic">not deeds</hi> the
work of reform has already begun, tho we have a strong tide of
<persName>English </persName>influence arming against us, which in the nature of things
must have its ebbs and flows.</p>

<p>With the hope of hearing from you whenever you have leisure,</p>

<p><persName>W. S. Parrott  </persName> [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
