<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4243">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to N A Ware, 07-24-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-12">09-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        N A Ware
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 681-682
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-07-24">07-24-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Advantages offered by Texas for establishment of cotton mill. Production now 1,000 pounds a year, and will increase. Government will foster colonies already established.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felepe de Austin, Texas,</placeName><date when="1831-07-24"> July 24. 1831</date></p>
<p>Mr. <persName>Nat. A Ware,</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir, A few days before my departure from <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>I received a
letter from <persName>Cap. Henry Austin</persName> informing me of your wish to establish
a <placeName>Cotton Manfactury</placeName> in this <placeName>colony</placeName>. I should have written to you
immediately but was on the eve of departing for this place, and 
concluded that it would be best to defer writing untill I arrived here,</p>

<p>On my arrival at home I found <persName>Cap. Henry Austin</persName> quite sick,
which has caused a delay up to this time.</p>

<p>With respect to the probable success and profits of a <placeName>Cotton 
Manufactory,</placeName> I have no hesitation in saying that I believe there is no
mode in which capital can be employed to greater advantage.</p>

<p>This <placeName>colony</placeName>, and <placeName>Texas </placeName>in general is in a state of secure and 
progressive improvement. The natural resources, and capacities of this
<placeName>country </placeName>to become populous and wealthy, are superior to any portion
of <placeName>north America</placeName> which I have seen or have any knowledge of. It
affords all the elements necessary for the establishment and support
of extensive <placeName>manufacturies</placeName>, except one, <persName>hands</persName>, which at first must be
introduced from other <placeName>countries</placeName>. It no doubt is the settled policy of
the government to encourage <placeName>manufactories </placeName>of cotton, and I think
that the large capital which has been invested in this branch, by the
Government itself, affords a very secure guarantee that the present
policy will not be departed from. This being the case, it needs no
other assurance to insure great profits from the business</p>

<p>The stock of cotton now raised in this <placeName>colony </placeName>may be rated at one
thousand bales of 400 pounds, This amount will increase of course
every year, so that there is no scarcity of the raw material. 
Provisions are getting very abundant and cheap, and will also increase in
quantity at a rapid ratio, with the exception of wheat flour, which is
not yet produced in the <placeName>country</placeName>, but will become a secure and 
profitable staple, from the <placeName>interior parts of Texas </placeName><placeName>high up on the Brazos
and Colorado rivers</placeName>.</p>

<p>This <placeName>colony </placeName>affords many eligible situations for <placeName>cotton factories</placeName>,
but I should recommend the Steam power, in preference to water-
as to the location of the <placeName>factory</placeName>, I think it ought to be a matter for<pb n="682"/>
your detirmination after examining the country, which I presume
you would do before you made an investment of so much importance.</p>

<p>The <placeName>forks of Buffalo bayou at the head of tide water 
navigation six miles above Harrisburgh</placeName>, where <persName>John Austin</persName> has offered a
tract&#8212;or at this place&#8212;or <placeName>on the Colorado river west of this</placeName>-&#8212;or
a <placeName>point on Galveston bay&#8212;</placeName>or at the <placeName>town of Brazoria</placeName>&#8212;are all
eligible situations, and there are many others. I think that land can
be procured by means of a direct <placeName>grant </placeName>from govt, but if it cannot
capital will easily procure as much as could be desired</p>

<p>I will give every aid in my power in this respect, and in every
other particular. I advise you to visit this <placeName>colony </placeName>this <date n="Fall-1831">fall </date>or as
soon as you can, and examine the <placeName>country </placeName>and judge for yourself if
however your mind is fully satisfied as to the advantages of the
business, you would save time by bringing out the machinery at
once. <persName>Cap Henry Austin </persName>will settle himself for the present <placeName>about
15 miles above Brazoria on tide water navigation of the Brazos
river</placeName>. If you should come into this river which is the best place to
land be particular to get a vessel that does not draw more than
five feet water or 5% at most&#8212;on account of <placeName>the bar off the mouth
of the river</placeName></p>

<p>The policy of the <persName>mexican govt</persName>, as to the <placeName>colonies </placeName>which have been
legally established, is clearly developed and frankly manifested
which is to foster and protect them by every possible means. My
<placeName>colony </placeName>in particular has uniformly recd the fullest support and 
protection of the Govt, and I have the most substantial reasons for 
believing that they will prosper during the next year more than at
any former period.</p>

<p>Those who have acted in good faith in their colonizing 
opperations in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and who have adherd to the law and to their 
contracts, have uniformly been protected and there is no cause nor
the shadow of just cause to distrust the good faith of this govt. I
should and do consider property as secure in this <placeName>colony </placeName>as in the
<placeName>U. S.</placeName> or any where else.</p>

<p>I shall be happy to give you any information in my power at any
time. I expect to leave here in <date when="1831-12-01">Dec 1 </date>for <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>and shall 
necessarily be absent six or seven months indeed it is rather probable
I shall visit the <placeName>city of Mexico</placeName> in which event my absence will be
longer.</p>

<p><persName>Step F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>If you visit this <placeName>country </placeName>do not fail to get a passport from the
<persName>Mexican consul</persName>.          </p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
