<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4346">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 05-08-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-22">09-22-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Saltillo, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 770-772
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-05-08">05-08-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-22" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Instructions for locating three tracts of land, including present city of Austin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Saltillo</placeName>, <date when="1832-05-08">May 8th 1832</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>The last mail brought me yours of <date when="1832-04-03">3 </date>and <date when="1832-04-17">17 April,</date> am truly 
gratified to hear that peace and prosperity prevail. I shall leave in a
few days for <placeName>Victoria </placeName>in company with <persName>Mason </persName>and <persName>Greaves</persName>, where
we expect to see <persName>Genl Teran</persName>. I have very friendly letters from
<persName>Teran</persName>, <persName>Alaman </persName>and the <persName>Vice President</persName> (see my letter to the 
<persName>Ayuntamiento</persName>). I have every confidence that the law of <date when="1832-04-06">6th A[pril]</date>
will be modified, I also have full confidence in <persName>Ter[an</persName> <hi rend="italic">Poli]tical
matters will probably soon take a favourable, and p[robably an]
unexpected change.</hi> Peace and harmony in <placeName>Texas </placeName>are [more] 
important now than ever. I cannot give you all the reasons I have for
this opinion, but they are many and very weighty.   Make what use<pb n="771"/>
you deem prudent of these remarks, always avoiding <hi rend="italic">talkers </hi>and
<hi rend="italic">news paper paragraphs.</hi></p>

<p>Aparte&#8212;I send you all the necessary papers and powers to perfect
the titles for the <placeName>grants </placeName>mentioned in them of <persName>Aguirre </persName>and <persName>Vega</persName>.
The concessions are in my <placeName>trunk </placeName>of which you have the key get
them out. I think they are in a bundle rolled up in a news paper.
This <placeName>land </placeName>has cost me $1000 and will cost much more besides the
expenses and the govt dues, settlement, etc.</p>

<p>You will want a sufficiency to take <placeName>the front on the Colorado river
from the upper line of <persName>Tannihill</persName>'s league in the upper colony,</placeName> to <placeName>500
varas</placeName> at least <placeName>above the big springs at the foot of the mountain</placeName>, also
the <placeName>fourth of a league on the mountain on the west side of the 
colorado opposite the said big springs the falls to lie in the center of
the front of said fourth league</placeName>. To make the matter more clear I
give a sketch of the land as near as I can recollect, <placeName>ten sitios which
you will locate on the west side of Colorado, bounding on onion
creek (Burro, or Garrapatas) on the lower or south east, and on
the Colorado river on the eastward&#8212;thus.</placeName> [A sketch map is here
omitted.] These three locations I wish you to be particular about.
The <placeName>Burro or onion creek</placeName> I believe runs more parallel with the river
than I have marked it which of necessity will extend the front up
the <placeName>river</placeName>. The<placeName> 1/4 sitio at the falls is all high mountain</placeName> &#8212;has some
timber and plenty of rock, no land, but I want the <placeName>falls </placeName>for a very
special object and therefore wish them to lie <placeName>in the center of this
tract on the river&#8212;to say&#8212;7 or 8 sitios above Tannihill east side&#8212;
1/4 at falls W. side&#8212;10 sitios in forks of river and onion creek</placeName>.</p>

<p>You will also locate the <placeName>4th league above Bastrop (cedar league)
</placeName>The balance of the land to nil the three concessions you will locate
on the <placeName>Sanjacinto W. Side above the Tuscasite road</placeName>, or <placeName>up the
Brazos or between this river and navisoto</placeName>, or <placeName>on the yeagua</placeName>&#8212;<hi rend="italic">en fin</hi>,
I want the best land that can be had and prefer taking it all <placeName>below
the upper road within the boundaries of my old contracts</placeName>, out of the
ten league reserve. I shall fix a place on the <placeName>colorado </placeName><placeName>at [the] foot
of the mountains </placeName>to live, and wish for those location [s for] my own
use and not to sell. The balance is for m[mutilated] or for sale. I
must request you to attend to this matter [promptly] and have it
all concluded as soon as practicable. [Present] a pe[ti]tion to the
<persName>Alcalde </persName>for the <placeName>two tracts west of colorado </placeName>with [out] any delay, not
one day, for there are various applications for that <placeName>colony of <persName>Milam</persName>s
</placeName>and also for <placeName>DeWitts</placeName>.</p>

<p>As soon as the titles for the <placeName>colorado tracts</placeName> are finished execute
the deed for sale of them to me, the balance you can let alone for
the present, I mean the deed of sale.</p>

<p>As regards what you say about <persName>Dexter</persName>, I never made him any
promise at all of any kind whatever.    <persName>Nixon </persName>I think is so reasonable<pb n="772"/>
that his wishes might be complied with, especially as he is about to
marry and settle permanently, tell the <persName>widow </persName>that she had better
yield than have the LAW put in force against her, as I laid it down
and left you to execute. As regards others who wish to locate <placeName>above
the road</placeName> you can do as you please<hi rend="italic"> con plena poder</hi>&#8212;but keep them
<placeName>away from the limits of my old colonies</placeName>, be particular as to this.
As regards <persName>Bowie </persName>do as you think right I have never objected to his
having a reasonable portion, and he has no cause to find any fault
with me. As regards the subject proposed by <persName>Madero </persName>and <persName>others</persName>
do as you think proper, always keeping above the road, <persName>Navarro </persName>is
appointed in place of <persName>Madero</persName>. For your government in the general,
I have to say that I have recd very favorable offers to settle our 
contract, but shall not [mutilated] until I see the <persName>GENERAL</persName>. Also,
I shall in futu[re have] nothing to do with the <hi rend="italic">home details </hi>of the
busin[ess you] will have to do it all and if you start badly 
[mutilated] to cause any entanglements it will give you trouble in the end.
The sistem of surveying must be changed immediately&#8212;the price is
too much. Stop this at once in the old and the <placeName>new colony</placeName>&#8212;except
the work already done, but have no more done on the same terms,
make <hi rend="italic">special </hi>contracts for the surveying of my lands.</p>

<p>I shall get <persName>Arciniega </persName>appointed <persName>comr of the<placeName> new colony</placeName></persName>, it will
probably be done next week. <persName>Mr. Greaves an english gentleman
</persName>will go to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, he is<persName> applicant for <placeName>Milams colony</placeName>,</persName> he will make
a good <persName>secretary for the Brazoria Ayto</persName> being a very good <persName>Spanish</persName>
scholar, an educated and very moral man and much of a gentleman.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
