<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4046">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>H H League to Stephen F Austin, 10-10-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>H H League</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-29">08-29-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 505
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-10-10">10-10-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-29" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asking Austin's assistance in disposing of land to meet debts.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Town of Austin</placeName> <date when="1830-10-10">Oct&#8212; 10th&#8212; 1830</date>&#8212;</p>
<p><persName>Col Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dear Sir, among the Evils that result to me from my 
Confinement, toy pecuniary affairs are by no means the least, I have not the
power to prosecute my rights or to repel their invasion; I am 
Compelled to submit to whatever terms are offered me; and to neglect
intirely the prossecution of Every effort or Exertion by which I
could bring in my means to my releaf; in this state of affares my
ruin is inevitable unless I can dispose of so much of my property as
will pay off all demands against me be them Just or unjust, and
Trust to Collecting my debts when I have an opportunity of 
attending to them, and when it will opperate less against me than at the
presant time; I wish to dispose of such property as I can pest [best]
spare, or such as is not indispensible to the support of my <persName>family</persName>; I
wish to Sell property to the amount of Three thousand Dollars one
half to be paid in Eighteen months and the Other half to be paid to
the discharge of my debts as they may be Called for, Some of which
is now due and all will be due shortly, for this object I would be
willing to sell my <placeName>League of land at Jennings Camp</placeName>, my <placeName>Eighth of
a League in the Matagorda tract</placeName> <placeName>one forth of a League in John 
McFarlands Tract</placeName> my <placeName>League of land on Clear Creek</placeName>, and my <placeName>Town
property in San Felipe</placeName> or so much as shall be sufficient to raise the
amount above mentioned the object of this communication is to 
propose a sale of the property to you; if you can purchase the <placeName>property</placeName><pb n="506"/>
it will accommodate me Very much, it is true that were it not for
the presant difficulties that seround me and over which I can have
no Controll, I should never have thought of Selling my landed
property, but some of my property has to go, and I can better part
with that than any thing Else; and when I again Get my liberty if
Ever I do I can Acq'uire Other <placeName>lands</placeName>, I am willing to Sell the 
property for a price that will warrant a Speculation to the <persName>purchaser</persName>;
this arrangement will releave me; but unless I can succeed with you
or Some Other person, I must be ruined in my personal property,
and See my <persName>family </persName>come to want, thare was a verbal agreement
between<persName> Joseph white</persName> and myself that he should have <placeName>half of the
Clear Creek League of land</placeName>, I have always been ready on my part
to Comply with the conditions spoken of between him and myself
when Ever he had performed his promises, for it intirely depended
on his own performances whether it should become an Established
contract or not he has never Complied as I shall be Very able to
prove, and his death renders a Compliance impossible, yet neither
him nor his <persName>Estate </persName>has lost nor Can they loose one Cent by his 
failing to Comply, should I make a Deed to that or any Other lands to
him it would be intirely a Donation, for by our last <placeName>Settlement </placeName>it
will be seen that after Crediting him with the horse he let you have
and all other accounts that he had against me, he was left my <persName>debtor</persName>
to the amount of 70 or 80 Dollars this <placeName>settlement </placeName>was made at his
own request and in the manner pointed out by himself, though he did
not say at the time that he abandoned the land arrangement but
rather that he intended to Comply if possible, he has not the least
particle of interest in the land in any way which I shall be able to
Establish to the satisfaction of the world&#8212;you will pleas to let me
here from you as soon as possible as it is necessary that I should
arrange my affares without delay</p>

<p><persName>H. H. League</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
