<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4335">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 03-21-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-22">09-22-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Bexar, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 758
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-03-21">03-21-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-22" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Politics. Mexican attitude toward the colonies. Bowie. Authorities interested in the two cannon at Brazoria. Must avoid imprudence there. Union with Mexico the best course for Texas. Retail law. Land.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p><placeName>Bexar </placeName><date when="1832-03-21">March 21 1832</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p>I leave tomorrow for <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>. There is nothing very important
here from the interior. The <hi rend="italic"><persName>Sabios </persName></hi>of this place are very doubtfull
that <persName>Santana </persName>will fail, except <hi rend="italic">one</hi>, he thinks he will succeed&#8212;this
one is <persName>Erasmo [Seguin],</persName> who expresses the same decided republican
principles now, that he did many years ago, and I believe is the <hi rend="italic">same</hi>
warm friend to colonization and to <placeName>Texas </placeName>that he was at first.</p>

<p>Personal feelings are more violent here now, than ever, I mean
amongst each other. I am told that the <persName>Ayto</persName>. here will support the
memorial, but they think that they ought to have been consulted
first and that even now if they do anything, it ought to bear a date
anterior to the memorial from there, so as to make it appear that
<placeName>Bexar </placeName>was the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Movil</placeName></hi>, and then the other <persName>Aytos</persName>. should follow in its
wake.</p>

<p>I have agreed to this idea and assured them that nothing should
be said about it, you will therefore keep this part of the letter 
entirely to yourself.<pb n="759"/></p>

<p>A great deal of pains has been taken by <hi rend="italic">some one</hi> to foment 
discord between <persName>Bowie </persName>and his connections and me, one of them has
told me who he thinks it is&#8212;he thinks him to be an aspiring man,
an <persName>enemy </persName>at least to both <persName>Bowie </persName>and myself&#8212; I care not much
about such matters. I shall soon be clear of all this stuff and of
public matters I hope.</p>

<p>An order has gone on to inquire how the two cannon came to be
at <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>etc. This thing should be managed very prudently.
The facts as to how they came into the country should be clearly
stated, that is&#8212;The Steam boat Ariel had them on board on the
<placeName>rio grande</placeName>. This boat started from that river for <placeName>Orleans </placeName>and put
into the <placeName>Brazos river</placeName> for wood, and after taking in the wood it was
found necessary to lighten her as much as possible to get over the
bar again, and those two guns and other things were left for that
purpose; that, notwithstanding this, the boat stuck on a bar and
was damaged so much that she was finally lost in<placeName> Galveston bay
</placeName>etc. etc.</p>

<p>It would be best to sell those two guns to <persName>Bradburn </persName>as he 
requested&#8212;they will do more harm than good in their present 
situation&#8212;or they might be delivered to the <persName>custom house officer</persName> that
has gone to <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>.</p>

<p>The best <persName>friends</persName> we have in this place are alarmed lest there
should be some imprudent act committed at <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>, which will
put the <persName>colonists </persName>in the wrong, and afford a pretext to harrass them,
and also defeat the memorial. They think that if any such 
imprudence is committed, it will turn the <persName>Santana party</persName> against the
colonizing system and make them <persName>enemies</persName>&#8212;but if no imprudence
is committed they think the memorial will succeed, even with the
<persName>present administration</persName>, and <hi rend="italic">certain </hi>if <persName>Santana </persName>gets up. This is
also my opinion. There is over 1000 <persName>troops </persName>in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and over
700 in <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>, and a large <persName>garrison </persName>in <placeName>Tampico</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">This </hi>force
can all be thrown into <placeName>Texas </placeName>by <placeName>water</placeName>, in a few days, besides the
<persName>militia </persName>of the<placeName> adjoining states</placeName>.</p>

<p>If things can be kept quiet in the <placeName>colony </placeName>all will end right and
prosperously, of this I have no doubt&#8212;what is needed there is a
<hi rend="italic">dead calm</hi>. All reflecting <persName>men </persName>will become convinced that the true
interest of <placeName>Texas </placeName>is never to separate from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and that it is
the true interest of this <placeName>nation </placeName>to encourage the population of <placeName>Texas</placeName>,
and make a <placeName>state </placeName>of it. This being the case the <persName>govt</persName>, will remove
the restrictions and the <placeName>country </placeName>will prosper.</p>

<p>We have already seen what a check, even the <hi rend="italic">rumor </hi>of difficulties
in <placeName>Texas </placeName>has given to emigration. If difficulties should arise in
reality, there would be no emigration at all, and many would leave
the <placeName>country</placeName>, and the <persName>indians </persName>would take possession of it.<pb n="760"/></p>


<p>The news from <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>says that the retail law has put all in 
confusion there&#8212; it had not passed, but was still pending&#8212; the <persName>Govr</persName>.
had refused to sanction it on the ground that it was unconstitutional-&#8212;
he is <hi rend="italic">right</hi>. XXX[Image of hand pointing did not transfer, substituted with XXX- DML] I understand that the <persName>officers </persName>sent on from 
<placeName>Matamoros </placeName><persName>prisoners</persName>, are to be sent to <persName>Tenoxticlan</persName>, should they come into
the <placeName>colony</placeName>, they will be treated <hi rend="italic">kindly </hi>and with <hi rend="italic">hospitality</hi>, of
course&#8212;very <hi rend="italic">kindly</hi>&#8212;also the <persName>officers </persName>from the <placeName>La Baca Station</placeName>. I
saw them at <placeName>La Bahia&#8212;</placeName><persName>Chovel </persName>is <persName>Teran </persName>in full&#8212;the others have no
confidence in <persName>Chovel</persName>, as I suspect. I wrote you by the last mail
from <placeName>La Bahia</placeName> which I hope you received.</p>

<p><persName>Navarro </persName>has mil congojas about the<placeName> land sold to <persName>Royall</persName></placeName>&#8212;he first
petitioned to take it in my <placeName>colony</placeName>, then wrote to the govr for authority
to take it in <placeName><persName>Dewitt</persName>s</placeName>, and that the <persName>Alcalde </persName>should be authorized to
give the possession. He now says that he cannot request the <persName>Govr </persName>to
appoint a new <persName>comr </persName>to put him in possession on the<placeName> west of the 
colorado</placeName>, for it will make him appear ridiculous in the eyes of the govt.
to be changing about so often. My advise to <persName>Royall </persName>and <persName>Caldwell </persName>is
to take it in <placeName>Dewitts Colony </placeName>and finish the thing at once-&#8212;or if any
place can be found in my <placeName>colony </placeName>that will not interfere, let him take
it there, and finish the matter at once. They must recollect that this
purchase is in the eyes of the law totally void and of no effect untill
they are in a situation to hold land by purchase legally in their own
names, and untill the possession is legally given, and a transfer from
<persName>Navarro</persName>&#8212;and for this reason they run the risk of loosing all by delay
and by being too particular&#8212;the best plan is to take it in <placeName><persName>De Witt</persName>s
Colony</placeName> as was at first intended.</p>

<p>There is a project before the <persName>legislature</persName>, as I am told, to reform
the colonization law, so that no time is to be lost in closing the titles
as soon as possible. I have not seen the plan, but it is said to be
almost a total change. Keep this matter in view so as to be ready
for it&#8212;but say nothing about it for the report toay not be true.
<persName>John Brown's widow</persName> spoke to me here about the <placeName>land </placeName>granted to
her <persName>husband </persName><placeName>on the West side of Carankawy.</placeName> He settled on it
and has a considerable improvement which is now in cultivation. I
believe the title is finished but the copy not delivered. See to this
and finish it.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p><persName>D. Gaspar</persName> sends mil memorias and says I must write to you in
conjunction with him that you must not " por ningún motivo 
separarse de sus destinos." <persName>Arciniega </persName>will return early in <date n="04-xx-832">April</date>&#8212;be
ready to go above and finish that <placeName>colony</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Mrs. Brown</persName>, the <persName>widow of John Brown </persName>will send for the deed of
the league on <placeName>Carancahua bayou</placeName>, send it to her by a safe conveyance.<pb n="761"/>
She leaves here <date when="1832-03-21">today </date>for <placeName>Gonzales</placeName>, where she will remain for the
present&#8212;her stock is on the <placeName>league</placeName>&#8212;it is the <placeName>first below the two
quarters below <placeName><persName>Coleman</persName>'s</placeName></placeName>.</p>

<p>Tell <persName>sister Emily</persName> that <persName>Austin </persName>is very well and pleased with his
journey.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. A</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:]<persName> Mr. Samuel M. Williams </persName>  <persName>Mr. Mitchel </persName>  <placeName>Austin</placeName></p>

<p>K B. Send <persName>Padilla</persName>'s Solicitud by first mail&#8212;I forgot it&#8212;it is for
a lot in <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>&#8212;it is with the power of attorney.</p>

<p>otra&#8212;<persName>Powers </persName>will go on now with his <placeName>colony</placeName>, all difficulties are
removed&#8212;he will settle it rapidly and add very much to the 
population of <placeName>Texas</placeName>.   There is no doubt of this.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
