<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4406">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Ramon Musquiz, 08-15-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-10-01">10-01-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Ramon Musquiz
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 838-841
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-08-15">08-15-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-10-01" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reciting events which have prevented him from going to Saltillo to attend the Legislature. Texans have
defended themselves from military abuses, but do not desire separation from Mexico.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>The resolutions of the <persName>Ayuntamiento of this <placeName>Municipality</placeName></persName> passed
on the <date when="1832-07-26">26th</date> and <date when="1832-07-27">27th ult°</date> have already acquainted your <persName>Lordship </persName>with
the formal and unanimous adhesion of this <placeName>Colony</placeName>, to the 
"Pronunciamunto " of <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, and the true and only motives of the
movements against the <placeName>ports of Anahuac and Velasco</placeName>.</p>

<p>That the <persName>Government </persName>may know circumstantially the cause of my
journey from <placeName>Matamoras </placeName>to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, when I was about to proceed to
<placeName>Saltillo</placeName>, to take my seat in the <placeName>Legislature of the State</placeName>, I accompany<pb n="839"/>
to your <persName>Lordship </persName>copies of my correspondence with <persName>Colonels Don-
Mariano Guerra, principal Commander of Matamoras</persName>, and <persName>Don José
Antonio Mexia, 2nd in command of the Division of the Liberating
Army,</persName> by which your <persName>Lordship </persName>will perceive that I returned to
<placeName>Texas</placeName>, in compliance with the invitation and instances of these
<placeName>officers</placeName>.</p>

<p>Peace having been entirely restored in this <placeName>Colony </placeName>I was preparing
to take my departure for <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>on the <date when="1832-08-14">14th inst</date>, but I received
from the<persName> Alcalde of this <placeName>Municipality</placeName></persName> the annexed copy of a 
communication he had received from the <persName>Alcalde of <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></persName>, 
informing him that <persName>Colonel Piedras</persName>, threatened to gather up the 
<persName>Indians </persName>against the <persName>inhabitants</persName>; thus kindling a war of extermination.
Under such circumstances, and considering, that the security and
peace of the people, is the first duty of the Government, its <persName>officers</persName>,
or <persName>public agents</persName>, I felt under the necessity of postponing my journey,
and directing my attention to the organization of the <persName>civil militia
</persName>under my command, as <persName>Colonel of the Battalion of Bexar</persName>, in order
to be enabled to contribute to common defence, at the same time that
I tried to open a correspondence with <persName>Colonel Piedras</persName>. For this
purpose, I sent to him by an <persName>express</persName>, a communication, a copy of
which, goes herein enclosed. The <persName>express </persName>returned, after having
met on the <placeName>road </placeName>a <persName>courier from <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></persName>, bearing the news of
<persName>Piedra</persName>s defeat, and of the complete restoration of peace, and 
constitutional order, in the <placeName>State of Coahuila and Texas</placeName>. That <persName>Courier</persName>
gave us positive information, that the <persName>inhabitants of <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></persName>,
called by the <persName>Ayuntamiento</persName>, and led by the <persName>Alcalde</persName>, <persName>Don 
Encarnación Chirino</persName>, pronounced themselves in favor of the plan of <placeName>Vera
Cruz</placeName>, and on the <date when="1832-08-02">2nd inst</date>: attacked and completely routed, <persName>Colonel
Piedras</persName>, after a hot contest of 7 hours, in which the <persName>Alcalde </persName>was
killed. <persName>Col: Piedras' troops</persName> withdrew, during the night, to the
<persName>Angelina</persName>, and there pronounced themselves in favor of the plan of
<persName>Santa Anna</persName>, and arrested their <persName>Colonel</persName>.</p>

<p>These occurrences have so delayed my departure, that it would be
impossible for me to arrive in time for the opening of the session,
on the <date n="09-01-182">1st of September </date>and therefore I beg that your <persName>Lordship </persName>will
be pleased to inform His<persName> Excellency the Governor of the State</persName>, of all
these incidents, and to transmit the same to the<persName> Honorable Congress
</persName>hoping that my attendance to the session of <date n="09-xx-1832">September </date>will not be
required. My position is rather delicate: however, none of our
actual difficulties can be charged upon me; it was the 
unconstitutional and imprudent proceedings of some<persName> military men</persName>, and not,
by any means, the wishes of the <persName>Colonists </persName>that hurried the affairs
to their present state: Just as may be the motives that dictated the
steps made by this people, or the principles and objects of the
"Pronunciamiento" of <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, to which they have adhered, I<pb n="840"/>
am well aware, that the <persName>enemies </persName>of <placeName>Texas </placeName>and her prosperity, will
attribute to them, intentions against the integrity of the <placeName>Mexican
Territory</placeName>. This allegation has been necessary and very useful 
indeed, to deceive the <persName>Mexicans</persName>, and justify certain measures taken by
the General Government in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, since the year <date n="xx-xx-1830">1830</date>. There has
never been, and there is no foundation in truth for such an 
allegation, nor is there any foundation to be found in reason or the nature
of conditions, for it neither is nor can be the interest of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to
secede from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, even if there were no obstacles to this course.
I can assure to your <persName>Lordship</persName>, that if the ties that unite <placeName>Texas </placeName>to
the Federacy, are ever broken asunder, the stroke shall come from
the Government itself, and not from the<persName> people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>. These
inhabitants have with their toil and labor redeemed the <placeName>Country</placeName>
from a state of <placeName>wilderness</placeName>, without one dollar of expense to the
<placeName>Nation</placeName>, and they expect in return to be governed agreeably to the
spirit of the Constitution and Federal system and in a manner
adequate to the necessities of the <placeName>Country</placeName>, and their own interest.
The object of the republican institutions adopted by <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, is to
secure the happiness and prosperity of the people, and to provide
for common defense. Can this object be obtained in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, by
following the restrictive system adopted since the year <date n="xx-xx-1830">1830</date>? Is it
possible to provide for common defense, by weakening the whole
<placeName>northern frontier</placeName>, with obstacles opposed to immigration, thus 
leaving it exposed to the incursions of the <persName>Indians</persName>, instead of promoting
an increase of civilized population so as to inhance the physical
strength and resources of the <placeName>Nation </placeName>?</p>

<p>Man seeks hapiness in the improvement of his condition&#8212;this is
a natural and invariable law&#8212;a law that will bind <placeName>Texas </placeName>to
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>with stronger ties, than the force of large <persName>armies</persName>. With
a due regard to this law, and the true spirit of the system of 
government that rules the <placeName>Nation</placeName>, no one would harbor in his bosom, a 
suspicion that <placeName>Texas </placeName>will ever attempt to secede: Let on the contrary
measures be taken for an increase of its population, so as to qualify
it to be admitted as one of the<placeName> Statets of the Mexican Union</placeName>,
and this step will be as favorable to <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>, as to the whole <placeName>Nation</placeName>,
because the whole <placeName>northern frontier of the Republic </placeName>would be 
protected and the effective strength of the <placeName>Nation </placeName>considerably increased,
I believe that these people will not recede from their 
"pronunciamiento ", now that they have made that step under the dictate of
reason and principle: They are firmly convinced that the 
Constitution and the most sacred rights of the people have been violated
since the citizen who, in the election of <date n="09-xx-1828">September 1828</date>, obtained
a constitutional majority of the votes for the Presidency, was 
forcibly expelled from the chair and <placeName>country</placeName>: They understood that the
present effort is to do, in good faith what was promised, by the<pb n="841"/>
plan of <placeName>Jalapa</placeName>, and was not done:&#8212;to restore public affairs on
their constitutional basis, without distinction of persons, parties,
or names. My first duty is to preserve as far as I am able, public
security and peace and to watch over the observation of the 
Constitution and Laws: in these terms, I trust that my conduct shall
meet the approbation of the <persName>Superior Authority</persName>. I avail myself
of this occasion, to offer to your <persName>Lordship </persName>the assurance of my 
consideration and respect.</p>
<p>God and Liberty&#8212;Town of <placeName>Austin </placeName><date when="1832-09-15">August 15th 1832</date>.</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p>P. S. I have just been apprised that the <persName>Tahaucanos</persName>, or <persName>Keechai
Indians</persName>, have killed a man named <persName>M. R. Read</persName> on the <placeName>frontier of
this Colony, near the Bexar road on the Brazos</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
