<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4521">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Emily M Perry, 01-26-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-11">11-11-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Emily M Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 921-923
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-01-26">01-26-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Payment of old debts. His estimate of his work: "The settlers of this colony will never forget me nor be long ungrateful to me."</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1833-01-26">Jany 26 1833</date></p>
<p>Dr Sister,</p>

<p>I recd yours of <date when="1833-01-20">20</date>&#8212; I scarcely know what to do as to the <placeName>Little
rock</placeName> business. The whole truth as it and other matters [stand] is as
follows&#8212; I bought a large amt of <placeName>new madrid claims</placeName> of <persName>G. Tennelle
</persName>for which I gave him my notes&#8212;one of those claims was laid on <placeName>Little
Rock</placeName> in company with <persName>O'Hara</persName>&#8212; I sold all the <placeName>claims </placeName>to <persName>Bryan</persName>
and gave him a deed&#8212; I took an instrument from him by which he
agreed to pay <persName>Tennelle</persName>&#8212;that paper I left in his desk at <placeName>long Prairie</placeName><pb n="922"/>
as I had no safe place to keep it, and it disappeared so that I never
saw it again&#8212; he transfered the <placeName>claims </placeName>to <persName>H. Elliott</persName> and there is
nothing to show that there was any agreement between them&#8212; <persName>Ashly</persName>
no doubt knows all about it and if he is an honest man will settle the
business right&#8212;-if he is not, it will be difficult to do anything with
it. I have paid <persName>Tennell </persName>over seven thousand dollars, I think,&#8212;also
I have paid <persName>Butler </persName>about six thousand dolls, all within two years
or nearly all&#8212; It will take about $4000 more to clear me of debt&#8212;
I have directed <persName>John Austin</persName> to sell land for what it will bring to
raise $1600 for <persName>Hunter </persName>balance due on what was paid <persName>Tennelle </persName>out of
the <placeName>store</placeName>&#8212; I did not wish to sacrifice land for I wanted to give a
large tract to each of your <persName>children</persName>&#8212;but it is all a folly I am only
worrying myself to death</p>

<p>I certainly thought and now think that your removal to <placeName>Texas </placeName>will
make your <persName>children </persName>all independent which they would never have
been in <placeName>Missouri</placeName>&#8212; * * * I have been offered 5 dolls an acre
for <placeName>1000 acres joining <persName>Perry</persName></placeName> and I could get 8 by giving a credit on
a part&#8212;but I wished to go there and live <placeName>along side of you</placeName>. If
however you are always holding up the dark side of the picture to
me, I fear that all my prospects of comfort will be ideal. * * *
The <placeName>tracts you now live on</placeName> will make as good a <placeName>farm </placeName>or <placeName>plantation</placeName>
as any in <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; It has a good situation on the river also&#8212;is in a
good <placeName>neighborhood</placeName>&#8212;convenient to the <placeName>sea</placeName>, to the <placeName>river</placeName>, to <placeName>market</placeName>
will do for stock and planting&#8212;takes in part of <placeName>jones Creek</placeName>&#8212;has
plenty of timber and <placeName>prairie </placeName>I always wanted <persName>Mr Perry </persName>to settle
there, but could not get him to go and look at it&#8212; The place on
<placeName>Chocolate </placeName>will always be a good <placeName>stock farm</placeName> and may be kept up I
do not see that you have had more trouble [or] even as much as
most of the <persName>settlers in <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>&#8212;A new <placeName>country </placeName>cannot be settled
without trouble</p>

<p>As to the <persName>settlers </persName>being ungrateful etc. which you speak of&#8212;all that
is nothing&#8212; They are always in a fret about something&#8212;it is so all
over the world&#8212;one day they curse and the next they praise. In
the end they will be just and if I merit a reward from them, they will
give it&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>settlers of this <placeName>colony</placeName></persName> will never forget me nor be long 
ungrateful to me. Of this you need not have any doubt. A man who
has no <persName>enemies </persName>is a contemptable being, for he is not of sufficient
consequence to excite envy or jealousy so that you may set your mind
at rest as to that matter&#8212; These <persName>settlers </persName>will never forget the man
or the <persName>family </persName>who has made their fortunes.<persName> Cousin Henry</persName> ought
never to have moved to <placeName>Texas </placeName>and I hope never to see another <persName>city
raised family</persName> coming to this <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;he has the foundation of a
future laid, but I fear it will do him no good,<pb n="923"/>
I am surprised to hear you say that we shall never live to realize
anything from my labors&#8212; Is it nothing to have paid off nearly all
the old debts&#8212;to have given a credit to the name of my <persName>family </persName>by
settling this <placeName>colony </placeName>that will be permanent and honorable for ages
to come&#8212; Is it nothing that you are now permanently settled with
the certainty that your <persName>children </persName>will not enter the world penniless&#8212;
Is 5 dollars an acre for land nothing&#8212; a tract was sold a few days
since <placeName>near <persName>Perry</persName>s league west of the Bernard</placeName> for 1.25 for acre, and
not better land than his&#8212; you let trifles have too much influence
on you&#8212; a punchin hut, or an indian camp is nothing, a mere
trifle, when it is to be only a stepping place to get into a comfortable
<placeName>home </placeName>and <placeName>farm </placeName>for life&#8212; If I had the power of a magician to build
Palaces I would not do it, * * * but when I have done all I
can, you ought to have more consideration for my feelings, when
you know they are more sensative than they ought to be to get
through this rough world&#8212;  your <persName>brother</persName></p>

<p><persName>Stephen</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
