<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4558">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 04-20-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-21">11-21-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 956-958
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Memoranda</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-04-20">04-20-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Memoranda. Eleven-league grants. Historic tomahawk. Hopes for State government.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1833-04-20">April 20. 1833.</date></p>
<p><persName>J. F. Perry</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Of the <placeName>three eleven league tracts</placeName> I mentioned one is located <placeName>on
the east side of Colorado at the foot of the mountains above 
<persName>Tannehill</persName></placeName> it was surveyed by<persName> S. P. Brown</persName>-&#8212;has a good deal of rich land,
and fine <placeName>pasture </placeName>for sheep and horses and is well watered with<pb n="957"/>
springs, very healthy&#8212;it takes some <placeName>rough mountain land</placeName>, wild
scenery etc. I intended to keep this place permanently and make a
mountain retreat and a large sheep farm of it. There is sign of
minerals on it.</p>

<p><placeName>Ten leagues of one of the other tracts</placeName> is <placeName>on the west of Colorado
opposite to the above</placeName>, and runs <placeName>from Union [Onion] Creek up&#8212;
</placeName>surveyed by <persName>T. H. Borden</persName>. The other <placeName>11 League tract</placeName> is to be, or
has been located by <persName>Frank Jackson [Johnson?]</persName> in the <placeName>upper colony.</placeName></p>

<p>I make these memorandums for you in case I never return. As to
the notes due by the <persName>settlers</persName>, if I can raise enough out of them
to clear off all my debts and pay my expenses so as not to sell any
land for those purposes it is as much as I ever expected. The land
that <persName>Williams </persName>and <persName>Henry Austin</persName> and<persName> H. Chrisman</persName> have cleared out
is not any of it to be collected from them, that is, none of that part
of the payments that is coming to me. If anything is left out of
those notes I intended it for a <placeName>school </placeName><placeName>on my league in <persName>Coles</persName> 
settlement</placeName> on the plan of an <placeName>academy</placeName>. I have a settlement to make at
<placeName>Bexar </placeName>with the <persName>executor of Saucedo</persName> on a/c of fees of the <persName>Baron de
Bastrop as commissnr</persName> and shall owe him considerable on that business I expect.</p>

<p>The <persName>Hawkins</persName> business is all settled and finally done with.</p>

<p>I made an arrangement with <persName>John Austin</persName> and <persName>Williams </persName>as to the
<placeName>upper colony above the San Antonio road</placeName>, and what is made out of
that <placeName>colony </placeName>is to be equally divided between <persName>us three</persName>. <persName>Williams </persName>is
to attend to the business but nothing is to be done contrary to law
or to the true interests of the <placeName>country</placeName>. That is, there is to be no
kind of wild speculation. My object in this is more to have the
business attended to and that <placeName>wilderness country</placeName> settled than to make
a speculation.</p>

<p>I think I shall get back in about four months, and I hope sooner.
And I shall then close all my affairs and settle myself and get a
<persName>wife </persName>and be a <persName>farmer</persName>. I should like to save and realize enough to
found an <placeName>academy </placeName>up in <placeName>Coles settlement</placeName> and intend to do so if I can,
but unless land sells high I shall not have the means. My expenses
are so much more than anyone thinks they are and there is so great
a sacrifice in the most of the payments that I get from the <persName>settlers</persName>
that I am always hard run and without money or means that can
be used.</p>

<p>I wish you to spare no pains or care in having little <persName>Stephen
my brother's son</persName> well educated. There will be enough out [of] my
property to educate him and <persName>Guy </persName>in the best manner possible. I
wish them to have a finished education and to study law so as to take
care of the future interests of the <persName>family</persName>. There are so many 
<persName>sharpers </persName>in this <placeName>world </placeName>that every large <persName>family </persName>who have much property<pb n="958"/>
ought to have at least one <persName>lawyer</persName>. They must learn Spanish and
french and send all the <persName>children </persName>to <placeName>dancing school</placeName>. <persName>Joel </persName>ought to be
brought up for a <persName>planter</persName>, and <persName>Austin </persName>for a <persName>merchant</persName>. Your <persName>Stephen</persName>
and <persName>Henry </persName>are too young yet to say what they are best calculated
for. All this is in case I never return, for I calculate to attend to
all these things myself in person.</p>

<p>I shall owe <persName>H. Chriesman</persName> for surveying and I wish you to settle
his claim on account of what he owes on the <placeName>Books of <persName>Perry and
Hunter</persName></placeName>. He is to select and survey a five league tract for me up
<placeName>on the waters of the Yeagua</placeName>. <placeName>Coles settlement</placeName> is now the most
populous in the <placeName>colony </placeName>and land is rising very fast and will be
worth as much there as in any part of the <placeName>Colony</placeName>, for that <placeName>Country</placeName>
will be thicker settled than any I know of. Your two leagues
there are very superior in point of soil, timber and water, and salt
in quantities can be made <placeName>on the back part of your mound league
and the adjoining tracts north of the Yeagua</placeName>. You have no idea
of the value of that land of yours up there, and if we get a <persName>state
government</persName> as I have no doubt we shall this <date n="Fall-1833">fall</date>, land will rise
at once very high. Land at the rates it can be had now is better
property than debts scattered over the country. It has taken all
I can raise for my expenses to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and I cannot arrange to
settle <persName>Chriesman </persName>surveying account in any other way than in 
payment of the debt he owes you. I will pay it to you in land that
will yield a better interest than the money would. I have also
agreed to aid <persName>H. Austin</persName> in paying his surveying a/c to <persName>Chriesman</persName>.
<persName>Henry </persName>is in distress and needs aid. A few years, or I think one
year more will set everything right, and give value to our lands
so that we can put everything easy and settle ourselves on <placeName>farms</placeName>
without having much to do with the bustle of business.</p>

<p>I have the <hi rend="italic">Tomahawk </hi>that <persName>Father </persName>had with him in his first trip
to <persName>Texas </persName>in my trunk. I wish it preserved and its history not
forgotten. It <hi rend="italic">blased </hi>the way for <persName>North Americans</persName> to <placeName>Texas</placeName>. When
<persName>Stephen F. Austin </persName>is of age I wish it given to him with an 
explanation. I have also carried it in most of my exploring trips in this
<placeName>country </placeName>in early times. The recollections connected with it are
very interesting to me.</p>

<p><persName>Chambers </persName>has agreed to pay the within order to you. He ought
to do it as it is money lent.</p>

<p>I have just heard of of the Colera <placeName>at the mouth of the river</placeName> and
that there have been 5 deaths&#8212;dreadfull indeed&#8212;how I tremble for
you all&#8212;pray be carefull and use all possible precautions&#8212;if you
were over <placeName>on the bayou</placeName> you would be safer I think&#8212; I have my
<hi rend="italic">will </hi>in my writing desk.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
