<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4607">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 11-05-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-30">11-30-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1013-1015
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-11-05">11-05-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Law of April 6, 1830, amended. Santa Anna favorable to Texas. Quarrel with Farias. Danger that Texas will be organized as a territory. Willingness to sacrifice self for Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1833-11-05">Novr. 5&#8212;-1833</date></p>

<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>A number of cases occurred here during the Cholera of persons
who died, were taken to the grave and then came to life again&#8212;one
<persName>man</persName>, rolled up in a blanket was thrown into a pit with many others,
lime was first spread over them. It operated on this man so as to
stimulate him to life again&#8212;he got up and walked home. His 
appearance there could not have caused a more sudden and agreable
surprise, than the sight of your letter of <date when="1833-09-17">17 sept</date>, did to me. <persName>Col
B. [Butler]</persName> recd letters from <persName>C. [Coles?]</persName> and <persName>W. [Whiteside]</persName> stating
in the positive that you and <persName>Cap Martin</persName> were dead.<persName> Doctor Rivers
</persName>wrote the same from <placeName>Monclova </placeName>so that I had no doubt of it. I really
congratulate you and <persName>Sarah </persName>that they were mistaken.<pb n="1014"/></p>

<p>The law repealing the 11 article of <date when="1830-04-06">6 april 1830</date> passed both houses
ten days since, and I understand has been approved by the <persName>president</persName>
but it is not published yet&#8212;presume it will be in two or three days.</p>

<p>I think that all the <placeName>Texas </placeName>matters will be satisfactorily arranged
in a short time. I shall remain here as long as anything is undone,-&#8212;
if there is a prospect of doing any good by it. I think something
will be effected in the mail and <placeName>customhouse </placeName>arrangements. It is
said that <persName>Zavala </persName>is to be <persName>minister of State</persName>, and some speak of <persName>Genl
Mejia</persName> for the <placeName>war department</placeName>, I believe there will be a change of
<persName>ministers </persName>in a few days.</p>

<p>I have had two interviews with the <persName>President Santana</persName>. He
speaks very friendly about <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I am of opinion that if you all
keep quiet and obey the state laws that the <hi rend="italic">substance </hi>of all Texas
wants will be granted. The appearance of things is much better
than it was a <date n="10-xx-1833">month </date>or even two weeks ago.</p>

<p><persName>Bustamante</persName>, <persName>Arista </persName>and a large number of the <persName>banished</persName>, about
300 left here a few days since for <placeName>vera cruz</placeName> to embark&#8212;they were
banished for life.</p>

<p><persName>Congress </persName>have repealed all laws that gave power to <persName>judges </persName>or <persName>civil
authority</persName> to enforce the collection of <hi rend="italic">diezmos</hi>, or to compel <persName>nuns</persName>
or <persName>monkes </persName>to remain in <placeName>convents </placeName>contrary to their will&#8212;so that it
is now a mere matter of <hi rend="italic">conscience </hi>to pay tythes or stay in a convent,
several <persName>nuns </persName>are out already&#8212; the whole system as it existed is
undergoing a change desean tumbar lo gótico, y fabricar conforme
a lo moderno.</p>

<p>No <placeName>11 league grants</placeName> can be had now for any price within reason&#8212;
<hi rend="italic">not one</hi>.</p>

<p>I wish you to reflect on the awkward situation your affairs as well
as mine would have been left, if you had actually died&#8212;and try and
close them all so as to run no more risks for the future. <persName>Luke </persName>writes
that all will be content with sending the State question to the <placeName>States</placeName>.
This remark of his displays more common sense than was in the
fashion when I left. I got a letter from <persName>Coles </persName>the <date when="1833-11-30">last of September
</date>of an opposite character which had a very bad effect. It has taken
almost ever since to remedy the evils proclaimed by it. what I mean
to say is that it irritated me and I <hi rend="italic">acted </hi>under that influence&#8212;but
all is smooth again.</p>

<p><persName>Dn Victor Blanco</persName> is a good <persName>friend</persName>&#8212;he rejoices much that you are
not a ghost, and wishes you to be very attentive to finish <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the titles
for which you are agent which I hope you will do and write to him.</p>

<p>I doubt whether I shall return now I will stay as long as 
anything is to be done for the good of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. The sacrifice <persName>Luke </persName>speaks of (as a main thing) is with me a secondary affair.   I would sacri-<pb n="1015"/>
fice my property and life to serve <placeName>Texas </placeName>and the substantial <placeName>settlers</placeName>,
the <placeName>farmers </placeName>and <placeName>working men</placeName>&#8212;but I would not willingly do that
much for men who would cut me, if they could. I have drawn on
<placeName>N. O </placeName>(<persName>Beers</persName>, <persName>St John</persName> and co) for one thousand dollars on the letters
of credit you sent me.   I think I shall not need any more.</p>

<p>Get the titles from <persName>Padilla </persName>(3 leagues) and make the transfers of
the <placeName><persName>Aguirrie </persName>tract </placeName>for as they now stand your death would loose
them, as you will see by examining the subject. The <placeName>tract that
<persName>Brown </persName>surveyed east of colorado</placeName> I wish to keep and will not part
from at present. Also close the <persName>Cole </persName>business and in fact all other
matters and be ready for <hi rend="italic">anything </hi>that may happen.</p>

<p>My present opinion is that all will result fortunately (that is if
you all keep quiet at home) but in these ticklish times, almost every
day brings in unexpected change of some kind.</p>

<p>I fear much difficulty about the <placeName>state </placeName>from <hi rend="italic">one </hi>quarter, and I have
just been told that an effort would be made from <hi rend="italic">that </hi>source to make
it a <placeName>territory </placeName>under the plan of the <placeName>territories in the U. S.</placeName> I replyed
that I should protest against it, and told the <persName>President </persName>so or rather
showed him my instructions on that point&#8212;besides this, there is no
constitutional power in <persName>congress </persName>to make it a <placeName>territory</placeName>. To be more
plain I am just now informed that <persName>Za. [Zavala]</persName> is in favor of a
<placeName>territory </placeName>tho he told me the reverse not two days since. I told him
I should protest against it. Since then he has not said anything to
me about it.</p>

<p>[Stephen F. Austin.]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
