<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4422">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Frost Thorn to Stephen F Austin, 08-28-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Frost Thorn</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-10-02">10-02-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nacogdoches, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 851
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-08-28">08-28-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-10-02" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Describing futile efforts to induce Piedras to declare for Santa Anna. Tranquilizing, the Cherokee.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName><date when="1832-08-28">28 August 1832</date>.</p>
<p>Dear Sir.</p>

<p>Your letter of <date when="1832-08-12">12th. inst</date>. was <date when="1832-08-27">yesterday </date>handed to me,   it affords
me as well as my <persName>friends </persName>pleasure to see that yr views so completely
agree with the course adopted in the late difficulty with <persName>Col Piedras</persName></p>

<p>Perhaps a greater Interest never was taken to accomidate matters
than was taken in this case, day after day and time after time, the
<persName>citizens </persName>of this <placeName>village </placeName>called on him for that object. I myself urged
the case so strongly and so repeatedly that I was fearfull he would
arrest me if I persisted.-&#8212;and as a stronger argument I showed him
a letter I had received from <persName>Mr. S. M. Wms </persName>noting the arrivel of
yourself and <persName>Coln. Mehir</persName> and that 1000 <persName>colonists </persName>would assist <persName>Coln.
M.</persName> if needed etc. etc.&#8212;his replies I will not pretend to state to you,
but they were all full of fight, and If in Justification to the cause,
and to counteract any false representation that might be made, you
should wish to be made acquainted with the efforts the <persName>Citisens </persName>used
to prevent the effusion of Blood, a Note from you to the <persName>Alcalde of
this district </persName>to take evidence, will be immediately attended to&#8212;and
It will appear that there was the utmost courtesy on the one side and
the most determined obstinacy on the other.&#8212;<persName>Coln. P.</persName> complains of
the unceremonious note of <persName>Coln Bullock </persName>to him</p>

<p>It merely stated that at a meeting of the <persName>officers </persName>under his 
command, it was resolved to support the constitution and the plan of
<persName>San Anna</persName>, demanding of him to surrender to some <persName>officer </persName>friendly
to that cause he (<persName>Bullock</persName>) reserving to himself the priviledge of
apptg. that <persName>officer </persName>and that <persName>Piedras </persName>should surrender as a <persName>prissoner
of War.</persName> pled[g]ing to him Protection. Suitable attentn etc. etc.
Allowing him 4 Hours for an ans. the note was answered and you are
acquainted with the result.</p>

<p>The <persName>Indians </persName>doubtless were employed as <persName>auxeliaries </persName>and it 
required much explanation to counteract his influence over the 
<persName>cherikees</persName>. but I am induced to believe that these feelings at this time are
encirely changed, and that we have but little to fear from them.</p>

<p>However I shall proceed <date when="1832-08-29">tomorrow </date>in company with <persName>Juan Durst
</persName>to see <persName>Bowls </persName>when so much of yr letters to us, will be explained to
them, as relates to them. This course we deem important, as a party
of <persName>Americans </persName>are now assembling to attack the <persName>Kechise </persName>(in conse-<pb n="852"/>
quence of a murder it is supposed they committed on an <persName>american</persName>
near <placeName>Tenoxtitlan</placeName>) In order to explain to <persName>Bowls </persName>that the Hostility (if
the party proceeds) is only against that party of <persName>Indians </persName>and to
entirely neutralise the <persName>cherekes </persName>etc. etc.</p>

<p><persName>Coln Bullock</persName> is taking an Inventory of the public property a copy
of which will be forwarded to you. The <placeName>country </placeName>is now in a state
of perfect tranquility&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>F. Thorn </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Coln S. F. Austin.</persName>
</p>

        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
