<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4455">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John P Sheldon to Stephen F Austin, 10-22-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John P Sheldon</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-10-29">10-29-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Detroit, Michigan</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 878-880
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-10-22">10-22-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-10-29" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Comment on Texan affairs. Delay in emigration.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Detroit, Oct. 22d. 1832.</p>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>I beg leave to introduce to your acquaintance, <persName>Mr. Saml D. Colt Jr.</persName>,
 a young gentleman of <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName>. He has spent some months
in this <placeName>Territory</placeName>, and finding his health poor, and business here not
answering his expectations, he determined on going to the 
delightful <placeName>region </placeName>which I constantly praise and often dream of&#8212;-Texas,<pb n="879"/>
I regret to say, that after all my exertions and arrangements I 
cannot get ready to remove my <persName>family </persName>this<date n="Fall - 1832"> fall</date>. It was more 
difficult than I anticipated to arrange numerous accounts, which had
been accumulating for more than twelve years, and to change my
little property into money&#8212;and I found that I could not depart
for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, with enough in my pocket to render me independent of
contingencies that were very probable. However, I do not doubt
that I shall be in a condition to undertake the enterprise next season.</p>

<p>Since my return I have conducted a <placeName>weekly journal</placeName> in this <placeName>city</placeName>,
and have occasion [ally] published articles relative to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, which
have been well received and copied into other <placeName>papers</placeName>. During the
<date n="Winter - 1832">coming winter</date> I propose to myself to write and publish several
numbers upon the same subject.</p>

<p>The <placeName>pamphlet</placeName>, containing the interesting proceedings of the <date n="SUmmer - 1832">past
summer</date>, reached me some weeks since. It has been in great demand
among my reading and enterprising <persName>acquaintance</persName>, and will effect
much good for <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>Believe me, my dear sir, there has been no disappointment in my
worldly affairs, which has caused me more regret, than my inability
to carry into effect my intention to remove to <placeName>Texas </placeName><date n="Fall - 1832">this fall</date>. I
feel that I shall not rest contented until I am settled for life in that
genial climate and delightful <placeName>country</placeName>; and every month that I
am withheld from the gratification of the predominant desire, I
consider as a great and absolute loss.</p>

<p>You will see several gentlemen in your <placeName>colony </placeName>in the course of
the <date n="Winter - 1832">winter</date>, coming from <placeName>this portion of the Union</placeName>; and I should
not be suprised if the fame of <persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName>, and interest which
<placeName>Texas </placeName>has excited, will soon cause you more trouble (by increasing
your <persName>visitors</persName>) than you are prepared to encounter.</p>

<p>I should be very glad to receive letters from you often; and rest
assured, that any suggestion of yours will receive that attention
which my sincere desire for the welfare of <placeName>Texas </placeName>and your intimate
acquaintance with her interests, cannot fail to secure. I beg, sir,
you will, at least, <hi rend="italic">think </hi>me willing and able to do a little for the
good of <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Gen. Mason</persName> left his <placeName>home </placeName>in this city a <date when="1832-10-19">few days since</date>, for <placeName>N.
York</placeName>, whence he will go to <placeName>Washington</placeName>. Before setting out for
<placeName>Texas </placeName>he will return to this <placeName>place</placeName>; and in all probability he will
not see you until <date n="02-xx-1833">February </date>or <date n="03-xx-1833">March nex</date>t.</p>

<p>I perceive by a <placeName>Nashville paper</placeName> that the <persName>Tenesee company</persName> are
about sending an <persName>agent </persName>to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, in order to arrange their claims.
I also learn, by a <persName>gentleman </persName>just returned to this place from <placeName>N. York</placeName>,
that a <persName>Mr. Jamieson</persName> had been engaged to survey lands for the <persName>N. Y.
compy</persName> <placeName>in the grants bordering the Trinity</placeName>, etc.<pb n="880"/></p>

<p>If <persName>Mrs. Holly</persName> is in <placeName>Texas </placeName>please give her my respects and best
wishes for her happiness. Remember me also to <persName>Mr. Williams</persName> and
other gentlemen who have not forgotten me,</p>

<p><persName>John P. Sheldon </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>Col. S. F Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
