<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4167">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 03-12-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-08">09-8-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Saltillo, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 611-613
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-03-12">03-12-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Colonists must not participate in the conflict between Madero and Bradburn over land titles. Feeling in legislature strong against foreigners.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p>[Saltillo] <date when="1831-03-12">March 12, 1831</date></p>

<p>This days mail brought me yours of <date when="1831-02-08">Feb. 8</date> and <date when="1831-02-22">22</date>. The course
adopted as to the <placeName>Trinity </placeName>business accords with my views as you
have seen by my letter of <date when="1831-02-19">19 Feb.</date> I then foresaw all this. You
say in the letter of<date when="1831-02-08"> 8th</date> that you are going to <placeName>Trinity</placeName>, but as 
nothing is said on the subject in the one of <date when="1831-02-22">22d.</date> I presume you did not go.
I should have regretted such a visit. No good could have resulted,
and some harm might, besides it would have been deviating from
the <hi rend="italic">spirit </hi>of the policy which has preserved us so far, that is to have
nothing to do with <hi rend="italic">extranious </hi>affairs, unless ordered especially by
Govt. If anything is said by my <placeName>colony </placeName>in favor of one side, or the
other, it will be taken hold of to class us as belonging to one <persName>party</persName>,
or the other. This will do an injury&#8212;we belong to the <hi rend="italic">law </hi>and to
the Govt and will obey when officially called on to do so.</p>

<p>I have understood that <persName>Jorge [Fisher]</persName> is publishing or has 
published a book, against me. He is a second <persName>Dayton </persName>and believes
that nothing was wanting but a <persName>leader </persName>among the <persName>settlers </persName>to turn
them all against <hi rend="italic">me</hi>. I fear the main object is to try and create
<hi rend="italic"><persName>parties </persName></hi>in the <placeName>colony </placeName>and by that means ruin us all. I have 
frequently said that, that <placeName>colony </placeName>had not an <persName>enemy </persName>to fear except <hi rend="italic">itself</hi>,
if it remains united, and firm to me, NOTHING can touch it.</p>

<p>I have written every mail since I have been here. The prospect
of another revolution in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>is said to be getting more probable
every day. God preserve this unhappy and distracted <placeName>nation</placeName>. I
know not what is to become of them. If you keep united and 
harmonious in the <placeName>colony</placeName>, you are better off and have more <hi rend="italic">Solid </hi>
guarantees for your rights, than any other part of this vast <placeName>republic</placeName>, your
fate is in your own hands.</p>

<p>Nothing need be expected from this <persName>Legislature</persName>&#8212;our <hi rend="italic">iniciativa</hi>
relative to the <placeName>ports of Matagorda and Galveston</placeName> was approved, and
afterwards hung up, by manoeuver, of a strange character. The 
feeling against <persName>foreigners </persName>here is overwhelming, all I calculate on is to
pass away the time <hi rend="italic">quietly </hi>and of course silently and get back as
soon as I can.</p>

<p>Remember that one of my contracts expires on <date when="1831-06-04">4 of June</date>&#8212;have
all finished by <persName>Arciniega </persName>before then, for I assure you that nothing<pb n="612"/>
can or will be done afterwards and perhaps a stopper will be applied
sooner owing to the hubbub between <persName><hi rend="italic">B</hi>. [Bradburn]</persName> and <persName><hi rend="italic">M</hi>. [Madero]
</persName>push this business if everything else is neglected.</p>

<p>Keep a dead silence as to politics and <persName>public men</persName>&#8212;read over my
letters by the two last mails more is meant there than is plainly 
expressed&#8212;also the one to <persName>Luke</persName>. Don't form opinions about others
hastily by <hi rend="italic">appearances</hi>. I approve highly of what you said to
<persName><hi rend="italic">B</hi>[radburn?]</persName> and<persName> <hi rend="italic">P</hi>[iedras?]</persName>. Report says that <persName>Genl Teran</persName> goes to
<placeName>Bejar </placeName>in all <date n="03-xx-1831">this month</date>, it is also reported that his <persName>family </persName>is on the
way from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>to acompany him. I know nothing of the truth of
these rumors. About 300 <persName>recruits </persName>passed here last week for <placeName>Bejar</placeName>,
and more are expected</p>

<p>(Send this paragraph in confidence to <persName>Judge Williams</persName> with my
respects)&#8212;What the <persName>people on <placeName>Trinity</placeName></persName> ought to say, is that they
cannot and ought not to take any part in any quarrel between
any two <persName>officers </persName>or <persName>authorities</persName>, unless officially called on to do so
by the competent <persName>superior authorities</persName>. If they take sides, they
will in the end be kicked by <hi rend="italic">both sides</hi> as a person who intermeddles
in a quarrel between man and wife.</p>

<p>I shall leave <persName>[George] Fisher</persName> to the <placeName>colony</placeName>, if the people there do not think that I merit their support, I will submit, for it will 
convince me that justice, honor, and gratitude, have abandoned the
earth.</p>

<p>Don't neglect the <placeName>reserves of land</placeName> I requested you in my last letter
to make.</p>

<p>Request <persName>Arciniega </persName>not to name the <placeName>town on colorado</placeName> untill I get
home.</p>

<p>I send the <placeName>grants </placeName>that are made, I do not know whether any are
missing, but think that <persName><hi rend="italic">Goves </hi>[Jones?]</persName> is, tho I am not certain if it
was sent for I have no list&#8212;you can say to those that are missing
if any, that they are not granted, and will not be, for the present
<persName>Govr </persName>will not grant any augmentations. I will try and get the
<persName>Mexican Domingues </persName>through but the others are <hi rend="italic">hopeless </hi>and you can
say so at once to the interested persons, so that they need not blame
me.</p>

<p>We have had a very cold winter&#8212;three snows of 4 to 6 inches,
I have a bad cold and am in bad health. I fear that <persName>Chambers </persName>will
fail and if so he talks of not returning, I shall try to remove this
idea&#8212;he is a man who has many, very many good and valuable
qualities. I am more and more pleased with him every day, and hope
he will not abandon <placeName>Tejas </placeName>as he sometimes talks of doing&#8212;he has
taken up an erronious opinion about his standing there&#8212;he thinks
that the most of you in <placeName>San Felipe</placeName> are his <persName>enemies</persName>, and are jealous
of him,   I have told him that there is nothing of the kind now&#8212;he<pb n="613"/>
complains that <persName>Luke </persName>did not answer his letters etc&#8212;he was milled
on his first arrival by the gabble of past years, and any stranger
would have been.</p>

<p>On reflection I think it safest to send the <placeName>grants </placeName>by mail, I 
enclose the list of them I send this letter by <persName>Dn Fernando Rodrigues
</persName>and at first intended to have sent the <placeName>grants </placeName>by him, but he would
mail them in <placeName>Bexar </placeName>and the postage would be the same</p>

<p><persName>S. F. A. </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>Let nothing be said in the <placeName>paper </placeName>about <persName>Arciniegas </persName>commission or
the issuing of titles&#8212;<persName>M's [Madero's] </persName>advertisement blew him up.
Remember me to <persName>Col Bradburn </persName><hi rend="italic">very </hi>particularly, say what you think
best in my name.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
