<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4785">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James F. Perry to Stephen F Austin, 05-05-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James F. Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-23">02-23-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Peach Point, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 71-72
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-05-05">05-05-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">General conditions in Texas. William's land speculations at Monclova</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Peach Point</placeName> <date when="1835-05-05">May 5th 1835</date></p>

<p>Dear <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>We received your letters of the <date when="1835-03-04">4th</date> and <date when="1835-03-10">10th March</date> We are verry much
disapointed to learn that you are still detained in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>; when <persName>Mr.
Grason</persName> returned we had no doubt but you would have been in <placeName>Monclova</placeName>
long since but it apears we are still disapointed and now we can make
no further calculation on anything We have [rejoiced?] beleaving you
ware on your road <placeName>home </placeName>but for the future we will beleave nothing untill
we see you, such procastination and disapointments are truely vexatious
distressing&#8212; if we knew what to do for your releaf it would be don but
we know not. I recd- a letter from <persName>Mr. Williams</persName> from <placeName>Montclova </placeName>stating
he had solisited the <persName>Governor </persName>and the <persName>Congress [of the state]</persName> to interfer
for your releaf which he had no doubt would be don, all of which I hope
has been forwarded, write to us what can be don for your spedy 
discharge if money will answer any purpose we will leave nothing undon
to obtain it, although our faith is verry much shaken still we hope ear
this reaches <placeName>Mexico </placeName>you will be on your way home. I shewed your letter
to <persName>Mr. Grason</persName> he is now in this <placeName>neighbourhood</placeName> and is quit well <persName>Jack</persName>
has recovered his health he is in <placeName>San Filepe</placeName> <persName>Emily</persName> and myself have
just returned from a trip <placeName>up the country</placeName> which I think has been of benefit
to her health although she has not entirely recovered. I have made
arrangements to settle our <placeName>Dickison</placeName> and <placeName>clear Creek lands</placeName> and within the
course of the <date n="Summer-1835">summer</date> have the others settled We have about <placeName>65 or 70
acres</placeName> in cotton this year but the [season] since the <date when="1835-03-01">1st Mar</date> has been so
dry that prospects for crops are bad so far, I spoke to <persName>Whitesides </persName>about his
power to collect <persName>Butler</persName>s debt he shewed me a paper which I presume
you have seen which I think would be sufitient authority to him he also
told me he had letters from him which was more particular on that subject
so that I think there will be no difficulty on that score provided <persName>Butler</persName>
has to come here to collect his money. I have never been able to make
any collections of any consequence on your notes. <persName>Mr. Williams</persName> and
<persName>Mr W H Jack</persName> both thought it was not best to commence suits on them.
I intend to try some of them now and have little doubt of recovering,
what is the state of your acct with <persName>John Austin</persName> and <persName>Austin </persName>and <persName>McKinstrey</persName>
they have transfered several of notes belonging to you and are endeavouring
to collect others. <persName>Williams </persName>and myself thought best to have all we could
stoped and have taken steps to stop one on <persName>Westall </persName>and'one on <persName>Mrs Jno
Hall</persName>. <persName>Mrs. Austin</persName> says that <persName>Jno Austin</persName> Held an note of yours for 1100$
and with that you will be indebted to <persName>Jno['s] Estate</persName> about 3000$ if your
return still remains uncertain you had better inform me or <persName>Williams </persName>of
the situation of your business with that <persName>Estate</persName>. there was only 100$<pb n="72"/>
paid on your order on <persName>Austin </persName>and <persName>McKinstrey </persName>for $475 in fv of <persName>Hunter</persName>
the balance still remains unpaid. I have not offered any of your lands
for sale not knowing any necessity for so doing as I have heard of no
claims against you except one small one which <persName>Williams </persName>told me he had
arranged he also told me that there was no necessity for selling any
for the purpose of paying the drafts you have drew from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;that
he had made arrangements to Meet them, in what way he has never 
informed me.</p>

<p><persName>Mr Williams</persName> will or has I have no doubt wrote to you what has been don
in the <placeName>upper collony</placeName> business. <persName>Ben Smith</persName> leaves in the vessel that carries
this pr <placeName>New Orleans </placeName>in rather a bad humer with <persName>W.</persName> about some land speculations at <placeName>Monclova</placeName>. <persName>McKinny </persName>is now absent at <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>&#8212;is lookd
for daily</p>

<p>We still have <persName>Mr. Pilgram</persName> here <persName>S. F. Austin</persName> and all our <persName>children</persName>
are going to <placeName>school </placeName>and improving well <persName>M. A. Bryan</persName> is studying the
spanish with <persName>Mr. Pegram Joel</persName> is attending to the <placeName>farm </placeName>and I think will
make a good <persName>Farmer</persName>. I saw many of your <persName>old friends </persName>when <placeName>up the
country</placeName>. They all enquired after you kindly, and all feel verry anxious
for your return they are all much pleased with your exertions for the
benefit of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, but are more anxious for your return than anything you
can do for them</p>

<p>[James F. Perry.]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
