<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4619">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 01-16-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-02">12-02-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Mr. Powell
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monterrey, Nuevo Leon</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1037-1039
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-01-16">01-16-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-02" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Remain quiet and "let me perish if such is to be my fate." Government would grant territorial organization to Texas if the ayuntamientos asked for it, but there should be no more conventions.  General instructions for management of Austin's affairs.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Monterrey </placeName><date when="1834-01-16">Jany 16 1834</date></p>
<p>Dr <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>I wrote on the <date when="1834-01-14">14</date> by mail and sent some seeds of the <persName>Mexican</persName>
cipres pronounced seepres. I now send some more. Sow them
in a bed like red pepper seed&#8212;raise it so that the water will not
lay on it. Water it in dry weather. Take care of the plants,
they will do to transplant in two years.</p>

<p>The last year has been one of calamities for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, overflow
pestilence and conventions.   I hope this year may be more favour-<pb n="1038"/>
able and that the <persName>people </persName>will have no more excitements, and all
harmonize amongst themselves, and with the <persName>people and 
authorities of <placeName>Bexar</placeName></persName>. Without this, they will not prosper&#8212;on the 
contrary they will ruin themselves.</p>

<p>In a moment of irritation and impatience I wrote an 
imprudent letter to the <persName>Ayuntam of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> in <date n="10-xx-1833">October last</date> for which
I have been arrested and ordered back to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>for which place
I leave soon as a <persName>prisoner</persName>. I do not blame the <persName>govt </persName>at all for this&#8212;
nry treatment has been very good since my arrest in this place, this
matter will cost me some months delay and perhaps a year before
I can return to make one of your <persName>family </persName>as I intend to do if I live
to get back. I have written to <persName>Williams </persName>by mail to furnish me
with the means of living in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. I can sell drafts on <placeName>Orleans</placeName>
[at] . . . [per cent] premium-&#8212; Write to me under cover to
<persName>W[S. Parr]ott, merchant <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>,</p>

<p>The <persName>Genl [Govt</persName> is dis]posed to do everything for <placeName>Texas </placeName>that
can be done and are friendly and wish the <placeName>country </placeName>to prosper,
They are willing to make it a <placeName>State </placeName>or a <placeName>territory </placeName>organized like
<placeName>Arkansas </placeName>and would do so if it was asked for unanimously by the
<persName>Ayuntamientos</persName>&#8212;but no more conventions.</p>

<p>All the <persName>people </persName>have to do is to remain quiet and let <placeName>Bexar </placeName>take
the lead in everything.</p>

<p>I hope there will be no excitement on account of my arrest, it
will do me harm and great harm to <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;keep quiet and let
me perish if such is to be my fate. I have suffered myself to be
drawn into the whirlpool by the excited men and by the party spirit
of the time in <placeName>Texas</placeName>. Men whose fortunes I have labored to make
have been my worst <persName>enemies</persName>. They can now rejoice and triumph
at my difficulties, but no good man will envy them their joy, nor
participate in it.</p>

<p>My advice to <placeName>Texas </placeName>is, what it always has been remain quiet-
populate the <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;improve your <placeName>farms</placeName>&#8212;and discountenance all
kind of revolutionary men or principles. If this advice is followed
that country will prosper. So long as you belong to <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>, obey
the laws and the authorities of that State.</p>

<p>I wish all the people well, even my <persName>enemies</persName>. I have given no
just cause for any one to be my <persName>enemy </persName>but no man can expect to go
through with so great an enterprise as the settling of a <placeName>wilderness</placeName>,
under the circumstances I did, without exposing himself to the
attacks of envy jealousy and malignity.</p>

<p>Collect all the stock you can on claims due me and put them in
your brand on the <placeName>Chocolate Bayou</placeName> place&#8212;keep yourself clean of
party and of politics and seek happiness within the limits of your
<placeName>farm </placeName>and the circle of your <persName>family </persName>and personal <persName>friends</persName>. I will
join [you] in that circle as soon as I can, [and never] leave it.<pb n="1039"/></p>

<p>Remember me to the <persName>ch[ildren]</persName> to your <persName>neighbours </persName>and to <persName>Henry</persName>
and <persName>family</persName>&#8212;to <persName>Phillips </persName>and <persName>Eliza </persName>and dont let <persName>little Stephen</persName> 
forget me.</p>

<p>Your <persName>brother</persName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName>    [Rubric]</p>

<p>[J. F.] <persName>Perry</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr. James F. Perry</persName> care of <persName>S. M. Williams </persName>  <placeName>San
Felipe de Austin Texas</placeName></p>
<p>By <persName>Mr. Powel</persName></p>

<p>I send my two miniatures by <persName>Mr. Powel</persName> for <persName>Emily </persName>and hope
they may arrive safely. Wet will ruin them as they are painted on
ivory in water colors.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
