<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4280">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Mary Austin Holley, 11-17-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-16">09-16-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mary Austin Holley
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 704-706
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-11-17">11-17-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Methods and motives and difficulties in settling Texas. Confidence in justice of Mexican Government. Wishes now to advertise Texas and settle Irish, Scotch, German, Swiss, and French immigrants.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1831-11-17">Nov: 17,1831</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Cousin</persName>,</p>

<p>I wrote you a scrawl some days since, (I do not recollect the date)
when I was quite debilitated, and with rather a feverish brain, and
really have no clear recollection of the contents of my letter, but<pb n="705"/>
doubt whether I answered all the inquiries contained in yours of <date when="1831-11-02">2nd
November</date>.</p>

<p>I am pleased with the idea of some publication that will make
the world acquainted with <placeName>Texas</placeName>, as <placeName>Texas </placeName>and its <persName>inhabitants </persName>
deserve.</p>

<p>When I explored this <placeName>country </placeName>in <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date>, it was a wild, howling,
interminable solitude <placeName>from Sabine to Bexar</placeName>. The <persName>civilized 
population</persName> had not extended <placeName>beyond the margins of the Sabine</placeName> in that
quarter; and was confined, on the <placeName>west </placeName>to the towns or villages of <placeName>Bexar</placeName>
and <placeName>La Bahia </placeName>(the latter is now called <placeName>Goliad</placeName>) which were <placeName>isolated
military posts</placeName>. I found the <placeName>country </placeName>so much more valuable than
I expected that the idea of contributing to fill it with a civilized
and industrious population filled my soul with enthusiasm. I can
with truth, and with a clear conscience, say, that none of the sordid
and selfish motives which influence the mass of <persName>adventure[r]s</persName> had
any weight in determining me to attack this <placeName>wilderness</placeName>. I 
commenced on the solid basis of sound and philanthropic intentions,
and of undeviating integrity. I asked the <hi rend="italic">favor </hi>of the new 
government of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;that is, <hi rend="italic">permission </hi>to settle this <placeName>country</placeName>, and 
become one of its <persName>citizens</persName>. What I asked was granted. I became
a <persName>Mexican Citizen</persName>. From that moment, honor, the sanctity of an
oath, gratitude&#8212;all bound me to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and her interests. Never
have I for one moment, deviated from the line of duty which those
obligations imposed on me. And, I attribute my success (for I may
say with pride I have been successful) to this circumstance. Should
this <persName>Government </persName>ever attempt to trample upon us, however, honor,
duty, justice, the approbation of all good people of all good <placeName>Nations</placeName>,
will point out the course for us to adopt. But, I have no fears&#8212;
not the most distant of such an unhappy event. But few of my
<persName>native countrymen</persName> understand me, my character, motives, or 
principles. An earnest desire to benefit <hi rend="italic">all</hi>; in short, more good will,
and confidence in mankind than [was] deserved, have often led
me into mistakes verging on weakness, and exposed me to the 
impositions of the crafty and designing.</p>

<p>A thorough knowledge of the <persName>Mexican </persName>character, the policy of
the Government and the feelings of the <persName>mass of the people </persName>towards
<persName>foreigners </persName>convinced me at an early day that <placeName>Texas </placeName>must be settled
<hi rend="italic">silently</hi>, or not at all. Hence it is that I was progressing here for
years, and rearing a flourishing settlement in this <placeName>country</placeName>, and it
was unknown even in parts of <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>, the adjoining State, that
such a thing existed. The circumstances are now changed, and it
is time to bring out my <hi rend="italic">ward </hi>and introduce her to the world.</p>

<p>The emigration of <persName>North Americans</persName> is now <hi rend="italic">totally prohibited.</hi> I
wish to start an emigration of <persName>English</persName>, <persName>Irish</persName>, <persName>Scotish</persName>, <persName>German</persName>, <persName>Swiss</persName>,
<persName>French</persName>, any <persName>civilized people</persName>; the three first are the best from the<pb n="706"/>
unity of languages, similarity of character etc: A work on <placeName>Texas</placeName>
would do much good in <placeName>Europe </placeName>especially in <placeName>Great Britan</placeName> I think
a little exertion would set in motion an <persName>English </persName>emigration of 
respectability, and as I am authoiized, in company with another, to
introduce eight hundred <persName>families</persName>, <persName>Europeans</persName>, besides my former
contracts, I feel a great interest on this subject- I have no <hi rend="italic"><persName>North
American</persName> prejudice</hi> against the <persName>English</persName>, on the contrary I only 
remember that <hi rend="italic">our <persName>ancestors </persName>were <persName>English</persName></hi>.</p>

<p>There is a <persName>gentleman </persName>here from <placeName>Virginia </placeName><persName>Doctor Branch T Archer
of Richmond</persName>, a <persName>relation of the Congress [man] Archer</persName>, with whose
character you are no doubt acquainted. He arrived in <date n="07-xx-1831">July</date>, and
talks of writing a history of us, and has been to <placeName>Bexar </placeName>collecting
materials relating to the <placeName>country </placeName>generally.</p>

<p>As soon as I can I will try to spend some time with you at <placeName>Bolivar</placeName>,
and will give you all the information I can. After I have seen <persName>Gen :
Terran</persName> I can form a more certain opinion of the future policy of
the Government, and shall be better able to answer the proposed
queries of the " <persName>British Geographical society"</persName> &#8212;certainly with more
satisfaction than at present.</p>

<p>I shall not leave for <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>until I am fully restored in strength,
which will not probably be sooner than <date when="1832-02-01">1st February.</date> This will
give me a week to spend with you for this reason I omit many
things I have to say until then. I rode out <date when="1831-11-16">yesterday </date>in a carriage
the first time I have left my room. In a week I hope to be at
<placeName>Anahuac</placeName>, and if I can hire a boat will go thence to <placeName>Chocolate </placeName>and
then to <placeName>Bolivar</placeName></p>

<p>I am a houseless <persName>bachelor </persName>and have no accomodations to offer
you, but my <persName>sister </persName>can furnish you a room in a <placeName><hi rend="italic">Texas Cabin</hi></placeName>&#8212;with
<placeName>Texas </placeName>fare&#8212;and an affectionate welcome. Hope promises better
things for next year, though as for <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, a tree, or a tent, with 
blankets and plenty of fat wild meat&#8212;, I am satisfied.</p>

<p>I congratulate <persName>Henry </persName>on the near prospect of seeing his <persName>family</persName>.
We have been scattered before the four winds of Heaven. <placeName>Texas</placeName>
will bring our dispersed <persName>family </persName>together, and afford us competence,
and&#8212;a<placeName> <hi rend="italic">home</hi></placeName>.   To me the idea is truly grateful.</p>

<p><persName>S F Austin</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
