<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4340">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 04-12-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-22">09-22-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Saltillo, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 764-765
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-04-12">04-12-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-22" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Anthony Butler going to Texas. Austin's debt to Mm. Moderation, patience, and fidelity to Mexico the proper course for Texas. Tariff.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p><placeName>Saltillo </placeName><date when="1832-04-12">12 April 1832</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p>I wrote you on the <date when="1832-04-09">9th</date>, since then <persName>Col Butler</persName> arrived here and
proceeds to <placeName>San Felipe</placeName> to settle his private business with <persName>Whitesides</persName>
and <persName>others</persName>.</p>

<p>I have nothing particular to add to my letter of the <date when="1832-04-09">9th</date>. Peace
and harmony in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and especially in the <placeName>Colony </placeName>is all important,
and I hope no event will transpire to interrupt the individual or
public tranquility of the <persName>inhabitants</persName>. Nothing more is known of
the State of things in <placeName>mexico </placeName>than what I communicated in my
last&#8212; you will see by the Registro, that <placeName>Texas </placeName>is reported to be in
a revolutionary situation. I have contradicted this false report in
a letter to<persName> Mr. Alaman,</persName> and everything will end well and 
prosperously if prudence and moderation are used by the <persName>colonists</persName>, but they
must be prudent and quiet.</p>

<p>I wish you would make out the items of my account with <persName>Butler</persName>
and calculate the interest, one of my notes to him is paid&#8212;take that
up and arrange what has been paid on the others as you and him
may think right.</p>

<p><persName>[John T.] Mason</persName> I presume will go to the <placeName>Colony </placeName>and in that
event I shall return <placeName>home </placeName>in <date n="05-xx-1832">May</date>, for he is authorised to settle the
<persName>Hawkins</persName> business&#8212;my anxiety to have that matter finally closed will
probably take me <placeName>home </placeName>instead of going to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. If any money
can be had to make a payment to <persName>Butler</persName>, or if you can make any
contract with him to finish the improvements on his house I wish
you would do so&#8212;at least so far as to take up the note that was
due in <date n="01-xx-1832">Jany last</date>. I am anxious to have that dept [sic] paid, so as
to avoid the accumulation of interest.</p>

<p>The consulta relative to the <persName>families </persName>who came in <date n="04-xx-1832  -  06-xx-1832">between April
and June </date>is favorably dispatched and will go by next mail to 
<persName>Arciniega </persName>so that you can now push all the business and bring it to a
speedy close.</p>

<p>Remember my <placeName>reserve on the Colorado above the road, and above
Tannihill</placeName> I do not wish that interfered with by any means.    The<pb n="765"/>
land is poor, but I think the situation will be healthy which is my
object in wishing to fix a <placeName>residence </placeName>there at some time when I can,
so as to have a retreat from the fevers, mosquitoes and insects of the
<placeName>low country near the coast.</placeName></p>

<p>Keep peace and quietness in the <placeName>colony </placeName>at all hazards. The 
<persName>settlers </persName>ought to have full confidence in me. I say that they must bear
a <hi rend="italic">great deal</hi> from military oppresion and still remain quiet and
patient. I refer you and the <persName>Ayto </persName>particularly to my letter of the
<date when="1832-04-09">9th instant</date> and to the advice it contains on this subject.</p>

<p>As regards the <persName>captains of vessells</persName> who behave imprudently, as
the <persName>captain of the Boston packet</persName> did, I hope the <persName>colonists </persName>will 
unanimously set their faces against them and against such conduct. I
expect that some schooners will have to be sunk, before they will
come to their senses, but that is <hi rend="italic">their </hi>affair&#8212; if they are in the
wrong I will not protect or countenance them and I hope none of
the <persName>colonists </persName>will&#8212; if they are wrongfully sunk, or ill treated let
them appeal to their own govt for redress and not to the <persName>colonists</persName>
who have nothing to do with the matter.</p>

<p>Prudence and a <hi rend="italic">dead calm</hi> in the <placeName>Colony </placeName>will insure a favorable
answer to the memorial&#8212;imprudence and rashness, even if just
cause is given, will totally defeat everything and ruin all.</p>

<p>My standing motto&#8212;<hi rend="italic">" Fidelity to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>"</hi>&#8212;ought to be in every
man's mouth and repeated, instead of <hi rend="italic">many </hi>other things that are
said, <hi rend="italic">over cups</hi> and in moments of heat&#8212; it is a good toast and
ought to be used as a standing toast in the grog shops&#8212; try and
have it so.</p>

<p>Remember me kindly to all</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p><persName>S. M. Williams</persName></p>

<p>I sent my motto in <date n="12-xx-1831">Decr last</date> to <persName>John Austin</persName> to be generally spread
amongst them at <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>, but I never heard of his having 
mentioned it to any one&#8212;   ask him if he did.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. A.</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
