<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4957">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>R R Royall to Stephen F Austin, 10-16-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>R R Royall</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-04-04">04-04-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 187-188
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-10-16">10-16-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-04-04" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Members elected to consultation are hard to hold. Want to return home. Advises meeting as soon as possible. Indian policy </add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe</placeName> <date when="1835-10-16">16th October 1835</date></p>
<p><persName>Genl Austin</persName>.</p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>The <persName>Prisioners </persName>arrived <date when="1835-10-16">This evening</date><persName> Mr Jack </persName>says he cannot take them
he thinks you didnot reflect on his unprepared situation to accommodate
them and his time being entirely taken up with the Buisiness of the <placeName>Land
office</placeName>, as such I must prepare them a Room, one being Liberated to go
<placeName>home </placeName>on Parole as you request. <persName>Governor Zavala</persName> will direct the 
Treatment of the others I am told that this Very <persName>colonel </persName>had <persName>Zavala </persName>a <persName>prisioner</persName>
once and Tantalized him how far this may Influence his feelings towards
them I dont know but he will no doubt be willing to make them 
comfortable&#8212;The <persName>troops from <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></persName> etc are expected to pass <placeName>Washington</placeName>
soon you can have it as I have it from the representations given by <persName>Genl.
Houston</persName> and others so far as they know I hope the force will be
respectable</p>

<p>I must say something to you and to <persName>absent members of the Convention
</persName>of Vital Importance to Texas&#8212;The <persName>members </persName>here are like <persName>Volunteers in
<placeName>Camp</placeName></persName> (Very Restless) and much is said about going <placeName>home </placeName>one by one
each Plead their necesities some from the <placeName>frontier </placeName>are afraid of <persName>Indians on
the <placeName>Brazos</placeName></persName> others to the <placeName>Eastward </placeName>are not fully into the spirit of our times
and are yet wanting some explanition I am proud to find only a few think
that way but from what I learn their <persName>constituents </persName>are far behind in correct<pb n="188"/>
Information as to every thing, as for Instance to relative strength the Cause
etc etc. the Land speculation subject is not yet satisfactory settled <placeName>abroad</placeName>
as the <persName>Delegates </persName>say also that our Proceedings have not had general 
Circulation all these circumstances render it necessary If not Indispensable to
so arrange that the <persName>members </persName>Return to Hold the Convention as Speedily as
possible I think we can detain all but a few till about the <date when="1835-11-01">1st. Novr.</date>
after that it will require positive assurances of a meeting and that in a few
days to stop them Is my belief, several <persName>persons </persName>Present urge me to be more
Pressing on this subject believing that the confusion that would inevitably
follow by a failure of the <persName>Present Convention</persName> would be the distruction of
all our Hopes of Order and Certainty&#8212; Several <persName>Persons </persName>Remaining here
will urge and will do everything in our Power but be assured it is all
important to attend to it I think I would like to have you consult those
who leave here <date when="1835-10-17">tomorrow </date>and have their Ideas on this subject.</p>

<p>The <persName>Indian Chiefs </persName>will I suppose be here soon I would like you to
converse with <persName>Genl Houston</persName> on the subject and If you or you and the 
<persName>members </persName>out in service can Give any assurances to them to do so, I will as far
as the <persName>Council </persName>has authority and will also Provide them comforts. <persName>Col.
Pettus</persName>, will write you and send a Bill of Articles sent by the two wagons
to leave in the <date when="1835-10-17">morning </date>I hope the Wagons from <placeName>Columbia </placeName>are <placeName>on the
Road</placeName> before now.</p>

<p>We look for <persName>Capt Wm Hall</persName> who is authorised to contract for meal etc
what he has done I dont know but suppose he has filled the Order&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>R. R. Royal President of Council</persName></p>

<p>the Cannon from <placeName>Harrisburg </placeName>has been badly managed and will be about
<date when="1835-10-18">two more days</date> before it passes here from <placeName>Columbia </placeName>I learn two only have
cariages&#8212;This <date when="1835-10-16">morning </date>the <persName>minority of the consultation</persName> met and 
adjourned till <date when="1835-11-01">1st Novr</date>. or till a <persName>quorum </persName>to do buisiness Those who remain
is to be joined with the <persName>Council</persName>	<persName>R R R</persName></p>

<p><date when="1835-10-17">17th</date> 6 oclock A. M.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
