<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4519">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>D. W. Anthony to Stephen F Austin, 01-25-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>D. W. Anthony</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-11">11-11-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brazoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 919-921
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-01-25">01-25-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Explaining his editorial policy.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Brazoria</placeName>, <date when="1833-01-25">Jany 25th 1833</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir&#8212;</p>

<p>Your favr of the <date when="1833-01-22">22nd inst</date>. by <persName>Maj. Reynolds</persName> was handed to me
<date when="1833-01-24">last evening</date>, and I have a convenient opportunity to reply. I
must thank you for the hints, that that as well as the one previous,
contained; and assure you I have valued your counsel in all instances
very highly, and have never disregarded it if it did not correspond
fully with my own judgment for I have been able to allow your
knowledge and Experience their proper weight in matters where
they render you more competent to decide than I could for a moment
presume myself&#8212;and I have never been made to doubt the 
correctness of your motives. I must,therefore insist that you let no occasion
pass to afford me the benefits of your advice, for if I do not strictly
adhere to it, rest assured it will be always a guide. I have a task
of much difficulty and great responsibility to perform, and am<pb n="920"/>
destitute of aid or counsel but that I receive from you. The politics
of the <placeName>country</placeName>, as you justly remark, are in rather a tangled 
condition, and that very circumstance makes my track more difficult to
discern; for how to preserve consistency with some settled system oí
opinions, when there is not a standard by which those who are
actually managing the machinery, are guided, is a source which
furnishes matter to Exercise the ingenuity even of an Experienced
diplomatist, rather than to Employ the raw and unskilful hand that
is literally compelled to wield it alone.</p>

<p>For the sake of appearing united, and by that very means 
producing union, I have Endeavoured to give to Every measure broached
and acted upon in a way that it might have an influence on the main
current of our affairs, such a face as would not disgrace us by 
Exposing our situation, agitated with dissention, and rendered 
contemptible by division and inconsistency. It has been my leading wish, to
Keep up a belief of unanimity on all important points, and to bring
as large a volume of the <persName>public </persName>mind to the support of whatever
course the <persName>Central Committee</persName> should adopt, as it would be possible
to do. This idea is very material abroad, and is the only foundation
of confidence intertained of the redemption of the <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;if 
smothered or rendered doubtful, the population of the country will be
checked, and all its hopes darkened. You say the tone of my <placeName>paper</placeName>
has been rather anti <persName>Mexican</persName>, and that I ought to change it. I do
not think I have said any thing that should wound them as a
people&#8212;on the contrary I have when speaking of the <persName>liberal party
</persName>always puffed them. To be sure I have not said much about them,
for I know too little to Enable me [to] say any thing in their favour,
that would not be inconsistent with our own acts and declarations.
As to the mere tone of the <placeName>paper</placeName>, it is not so Easy to change without
the detection of inconsistency as might be thought. The tone of the
<placeName>paper </placeName>has been caught from, and formed by the events that have
occured, and the circumstances and necessary feelings which surround
us&#8212;and some occurence or new event must serve as a hinge upon
which to turn even the tone of <hi rend="italic">my </hi>remarks from the general tenor
of our conduct. If <hi rend="italic">communications </hi>were introduced not too much
varying in substance from the drift of the public feeling, or the 
expectation, or rather belief of what that is, abroad, invested with such
a glossy colouring of true and loyal Mexicanism as to answer the
purpose you desire, I could yield better to that, than to no obvious
cause, in departing from what has at least appeared to Chime with
the united feelings of the people. I dropt you a few hasty remarks
a day or two since, in reply to your letter by <persName>Bradly </persName>which with these,
will inform you how I feel disposed on the subject of our politics.
Without consistency we have no influence-&#8212;Without influence we
can do no good.<pb n="921"/></p>

<p><persName>Grayson </persName>has not yet come, but I have reason to expect him every
week. <persName>Dr. Archer</persName> is <placeName>at the mouth of the river </placeName>on a health 
expedition. I hope they "may be of some use to us in the work we have
before us, as you suggest.</p>

<p>In relation to the correction of the proof sheets of the 
Remonstrance, I have to answer that you will either have to come down
for that purpose, or leave it to me and <persName>Cotton</persName>, for <persName>Eckle </persName>is sick.
The translation cannot be well made here, and I shall therefore
expect the one you made. Wherefore do you wish it copied? your
hand writing is very plain.</p>

<p>When shall I come up on the subject of land ? or will it be 
necessary at all. I shall send my <persName>brother </persName>up before the <persName>Commissioner</persName>
leaves&#8212;I have two here just from the <placeName>College walls</placeName>, and will make
useful Citizens of them by learning them to print a little&#8212;You must
give them a piece of land, for that was the promise upon which they
came. On the subject of <persName>P Green</persName>, he wishes to know, if a petition
could not be sent down to him to sign which would answer the 
purpose without his presence?</p>

<p><persName>DW Anthony</persName>.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Col. S F Austin </persName>  <placeName>San Felipe</placeName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
