<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4733">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to James F. Perry, 03-04-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-17">02-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F. Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 45-46
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-03-04">03-04-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Improvements for Texas mail routes and roads. Officials friendly. Social amusements</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1835-03-04">March 4 1835</date></p>

<p>Dr <persName>Brother</persName>,</p>

<p>I expected to have been on my way <placeName>home </placeName>before this, but my affairs
are not yet concluded so that I can leave I hope however that I shall not
be detained longer than all this month.</p>

<p>The affairs of <placeName>Texas </placeName>are in a much better train for that <placeName>country </placeName>to become
a <placeName>state</placeName>, than they ever have been. The subject was before the <persName>House of
Representatives</persName> last week, and information was called for by the <persName>house</persName>
from the <persName>executive </persName>which will be given in a few days, and is very favourable
for <placeName>Texas</placeName>. The <persName>people </persName>there must not expect a <placeName>state </placeName>immediately, but the
matter will be put in a train to make it a state within a reasonable and
even short time&#8212; There will be an exemption of duties on cotton bagging
iron steel and some other articles I have also recommended that a <hi rend="italic">premium</hi>
be given on <placeName>Texas </placeName>cotton shipped to <placeName>Tampico </placeName>and <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> also that 2
<persName>companies </persName>of <persName>mounted riflemen</persName> be raised in <placeName>Texas </placeName>to be stationed <placeName>high up
on the Colorado and Brazos</placeName>, for the purpose of defense and of opening
the <placeName>road to Chihuahua</placeName>&#8212;also <placeName>new mail routes</placeName>&#8212;one from <placeName>Goliad </placeName>by <placeName>LaBaca</placeName>,
<placeName>Matagorda</placeName>, <placeName>Brazoria</placeName> to <placeName>San Felipe</placeName>, and thence to <placeName>Harrisburg </placeName><placeName>Liberty </placeName>and
<placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>, and several other things of interest to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, all of which
are now under consideration by the <persName>Govt</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>Col Almonte</persName> is the true and active <persName>friend </persName>of <placeName>Texas </placeName>in all these matters&#8212;
The <persName>present minister of relations, Gutierrez Estrada</persName>, is a very enlightened
and good man&#8212; As to myself, I have more <persName>friends </persName>here than I ever had
before, and so has <placeName>Texas</placeName></p>

<p><persName>Almonte </persName>has in the press a statistical notice of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, it will be out
in a few days. I have not seen it or any part of it, but he says it gives
a favourable view of that <persName>country </persName>and its <persName>inhabitants</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I hope that my friend <persName>Grayson </persName>will be with you by the time you get
this&#8212; I can never sufficiently express my thankfulness to him and <persName>Jack</persName>&#8212;
They are truly sterling men Tell <persName>Grayson </persName>that <persName>Butler </persName>told a man the other
day, that the letters which he, <persName>Butler</persName>, wrote to <placeName>Texas </placeName>in my favor was what
induced the <persName>people </persName>there to interest themselves for me so far as to send
on <persName>Grayson </persName>and <persName>Jack</persName>&#8212; <persName>Butler</persName>, I suppose made this statement to try and
injure me with the person he was talking to, for I do not visit nor even
speak to him, and he wishes no doubt to make it appear that he tryed to
serve me, so as to induce others to believe that I am ungratefull&#8212;so far
from trying to serve me, I have reason to believe that he and <persName>Mason</persName><pb n="46"/>
and <persName>Mexia</persName>, would have kept me in a <placeName>dungeon </placeName>for years if they could and
all because I obeyed the instructions of my <persName>constituents </persName>in opposing a
<placeName>territory </placeName>for <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>There has been a "<hi rend="italic">fuss</hi>" at <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>&#8212;the <persName>soldiers in the <placeName>castle </placeName></persName> mutinied
and tied their <persName>officers </persName>etc. etc. have still possession of the <placeName>castle</placeName>&#8212; some
think it is the beginning of another revolution, but I do not believe it is
anything more than a mutiny of the <persName>Garrison</persName>, and that it will have no
political result whatever&#8212; The <placeName>country </placeName>is perfectly tranquil in all parts,
and things are going on well</p>

<p>I think the <placeName>Chihuahua road</placeName> very important and have no doubt the
<persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> will all unite to open it&#8212; I think the <persName>Genl </persName>and <persName>state
Govts</persName>- will aid and so will the <placeName>state of Chihuahua</placeName>, I have spoken to all
the <persName>influential men</persName> here from that state about it, and they have written
home in favor of the project&#8212; If the <persName>rifle companies</persName> are raised they will
open the way in a few months and the <persName>Govt </persName>at present are in favor of
recommending to <persName>congress </persName>that they should be raised&#8212; Calm, a dead calm,
and close attention to farming, and no excitements nor party divisions,
are all that <placeName>Texas </placeName>needs at present&#8212;</p>

<p>Love to <persName>Sister </persName>and all the <persName>children</persName>&#8212; I hope to see you all some time,
but really I have ceased making calculations when it will be
We have had some extra amusements here lately&#8212;the ascension of 
<persName>Robertson </persName>in a <placeName>balloon </placeName>a Grand Ball given by a select party of <persName>gentlemen </persName>with
the <persName>British minister</persName> at their head. I was at it&#8212;there was quite a display&#8212;
also some masquerades new operas etc.&#8212; But these things cannot divert
my thoughts from <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and <placeName>home</placeName>, and I will try before I leave to have
things put in a favourable train for that <placeName>country </placeName>to be a <placeName>state </placeName>before long&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S. [F. Austin]</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
