<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4190">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 04-02-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-10">09-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Leona Vicario, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 636-639
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-04-02">04-02-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Interest in passage of a general law for the government of territories. Slavery. Hold aloof from conflict between Madero and Bradburn. "In these matters say little or nothing, and nothing definite." Law excluding foreigners from retail trade.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p><placeName>L[eona]. Viacario </placeName><date when="1831-04-02">April 2. 1831</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>I have nothing of much interest to communicate. I refer you
and <persName>Luke </persName>to my letters to <persName>Johnson </persName>and <persName>Williamson</persName>. I kept no
copy of either of them, and may need the one to <persName>Johnson </persName>after
my return, for which reason I wish you would request him not to
let it be destroyed.</p>

<p>There is nothing new from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>of a political nature&#8212;<persName>Mexia</persName>
has arrived there from <placeName>New York</placeName> and will be here in all this month,
on the subject of the <persName>land company</persName> formed in <placeName>New York</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Genl Teran</persName> writes on <date when="1831-03-21">21 ult.</date> that he agrees with me in opinion
that <persName>Bradburn</persName> has misconstrued the law as to tonnage duty&#8212;that
he will examine into it and give an order to have all but the first
refunded to<persName> S Rhoads [Fisher]</persName> and I have no doubt it will be done-
he says that he probably will be here this <date n="04-xx-1831">month </date>on his way to
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>where he goes to visit his <persName>family</persName>.<pb n="637"/></p>

<p>I wish you to take the copy of the oficio that <persName>Jorge [Fisher]
</persName>wrote about the <persName>free negroes</persName>, and burn it, that is I mean the copy
that was signed by me, in case I ever signed any which I do this
recollect to have done, and carefully keep the copy and letter on
that subject which is in his hand writing don't neglect to do this
before you forget it, and send him no papers of any sort&#8212;you did
very right in not sending those he wrote for.</p>

<p><persName>Padre Muldoon </persName>was still in <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>on the <date when="1831-03-21">21 March</date>, but
anxious to get on. I presume he will wait untill the <persName>Genl </persName>decides
whether he goes to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>or to <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>This is holy week, of course nothing done in the Legislature, tho
we have had any quantity of processions etc&#8212;the one last night
which began at 8 and ended at 11&#8212;was beautifull&#8212;about 800
<persName>females </persName>walked in two lines each with a wax candle&#8212;the night
was calm and dark&#8212;the lights made a fine display in these <placeName>streets</placeName>,
some of which assend near 200 feet in half a mile.</p>

<p>We are at a law to prevent <persName>foreigners </persName>from retailing&#8212;at first I
thought it would pass&#8212;I now think it will not. I shall oppose it
in its present shape.</p>

<p>I am promised an officio to <persName>Arciniega </persName>by next mail in answer to
the <persName>consulta </persName>about the restriction&#8212;he may go on and put them all
in possession, without any fears. I shall have no difficulty of any
sort with <persName><hi rend="italic">Boss </hi>[Teran?]</persName>. Close all the <date when="1831-06-04">4 of June</date> <placeName>Colony </placeName>as fast
as possible. I ought to go to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>with <persName>Teran </persName>if he goes, but how
can I, without money, and required at home. I am undecided as
yet as to this point, and rather think that if I had 500 dollars I
would go on. Much depends on the organic law for the <placeName>territories</placeName>.
I have written many sheets on this subject and on slavery to 
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>but there is nothing like being personally present. Let me know
by return of mail (if time will permit) what <persName>Luke </persName>and <persName>Johnson</persName>
and others think of my views about a <placeName>territory </placeName>and the manner
of managing the <persName>slave </persName>question&#8212;don't fail in this, there will be
time for it [to] get here by<date when="1831-05-01"> 1 of May</date>. As to the <placeName>Trinity </placeName>business
<persName>Madero </persName>has the right side of the question&#8212;of that there is no
doubt&#8212;and in the end he will come out, if he is prudent. I am
compelled to touch that matter cautiously for the <placeName>colony </placeName>has much
at stake&#8212;too much to be embarked in the cause of another. It is
a hard and unpleasant situation to be placed in. Some use may
be made of the big <hi rend="italic">colonizing business</hi> of <placeName>New York</placeName>, but that
must also be touched prudently. In these matters say little or 
nothing, <hi rend="italic">and nothing deffinite</hi>, as many smooth words without meaning as
you please. By <persName>Rodrigues </persName>I sent forty titles, on which I have
paid forty dollars cash which you must collect. Send out the
<persName>Gonzales </persName>titles without delay get <persName>Pettus </persName>to attend to it.<pb n="638"/></p>

<p>Tell <persName>Arciniega </persName>that I have recd his letter of <date when="1831-03-08">8 March</date> and will
attend to all his requests. I fear that <persName>Hunter</persName>s application is 
hopeless, on the subject of augmentations this Govt, will not yield.
<placeName>Matamoros </placeName>is in a hubbub about its <placeName>port</placeName>. I shall try another
iniciative on <date when="1831-04-05">Tuesday </date>(<date when="1831-04-04">Monday </date>is post day) for <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>and
<placeName>Matagorda</placeName>. I have written direct to the <persName>Vice President</persName> and 
<persName>minister </persName>as to <placeName>Galveston </placeName>and <placeName>Matagorda </placeName>some time ago, also to others
in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;Poca importa&#8212;they cannot build a wall across them
all, as I told the good folks here which they took very ill,
for they say the law ought to be a wall&#8212;I answered so it is, but
the law of nature has a just right to break down all walls that
are violent and notorious public nuisances.</p>

<p>The act of the <persName>Ayto</persName>, which you sent me would have been very
important if anything could have been done with the <persName>judiciary</persName>, but
it is impossible. Shew <persName>Johnson </persName>and <persName>Williamson </persName>the article of the
constitution about <hi rend="italic">Jueces Arbitros</hi>, and remind <persName>Luke </persName>of my 
recommendation to him on that subject.</p>

<p>All harmony is at an end in the <persName>legislature</persName>, the Menudeo [retail]
law has split us into three or four odd sort of lumps.</p>

<p>Remember me to <persName>Sarah </persName>and <persName>Eliza </persName>and my <persName>nephew Austin</persName> and
<persName>Mr Hunter.</persName> I recd <persName>Austin</persName>s letter and am much pleased with it,
would have written by this mail but have not time&#8212;will try and
bring him the poney and rigging he writes me for.</p>

<p>The <persName>Govr </persName>has issued an order as I am told, to the <persName>Chief of 
Department</persName> to report what <placeName>colonies </placeName>are commenced and how many
<persName>families </persName>are recd in each. Be very particular as to this, and make
out a corrected list, for the one on the old book is very incorrect-
one fourth of them have left the <placeName>colony </placeName>and ought not to be counted.
The certificates ought to be numbered differently, for otherwise 
mistaken ideas will arise&#8212;by examining the Genl law of <date when="1828-04-14">14 April 1828</date>
you will see the importance of keeping a regular and correct list
of the <persName>colonists </persName>and it will be still more important if the Menudeo
law passes.</p>

<p>This paragraph to yourself only</p>

<p>I expect <persName>Henry Austin</persName> is in the <placeName>colony </placeName>by this time&#8212;-tell him
to select his <placeName>land </placeName>without delay&#8212;he had the promise of<placeName> tracts in
the 10 League East of Brazos</placeName> and must have the preference, but
the best way is to give out the idea that all that <placeName>land </placeName>is hung up
untill I return. I also want a good tract for<persName> Mrs Holly, widow</persName>
of the late<persName> Doctor Holly,</persName> who will remove to the <placeName>Colony </placeName><date n="Fall-1831">next fall</date>
certain, and be the most valuable acquisition we have ever yet 
received, in the <persName>female </persName>line, or probably will receive.   I shall get<pb n="639"/>
home the <date when="1831-04-30">last of this month</date>. I am glad to hear that <persName>Bowie </persName>is
married.</p>

<p>P. S. Since writing the above I have had a long conversation
with the <persName>Govr </persName>relative to <placeName>Texas</placeName>. [He] is a very just man, and
will not consent to an unjust act, if he knows it. I am fully 
satisfied that the rights of the <persName>people east of my <placeName>colony</placeName></persName> will be fully
respected in the end provided they do not attempt in any way
to seek redress by force or violence&#8212;that will totally ruin them,
and they had better submit to temporary evils than bring greater
ones on themselves. I am much better pleased with the <persName>Govr </persName>than
I ever expected to be. During the session various causes and 
considerations prevented me from being as intimate with him as I
have been since&#8212;also the statements of others misled me as to a
part of his character.</p>

<p>I hope my ideas as to a <placeName>territory </placeName>are not misunderstood. I think
I stated distinctly in my letter of <date when="1831-03-31">31 March</date>, that the <persName>people of
<placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> ought not to move that question at present. I wish the Genl
govt, to move it, we shall then have the advantage of making terms&#8212;
that is we will agree if it suits us, and if not refuse, just as it may
be <hi rend="italic">expedient</hi>. I have more confidence in the present 
administration than I had&#8212;my faith in<persName><hi rend="italic"> Boss </hi>[Teran?]</persName> is unimpaired and all
will be right in the end. If the official publication is made in the
<placeName>U. S. papers</placeName> stating that my <placeName>colony </placeName>is not included in the 11 Article
of the law of<date when="1830-04-06"> 6 April</date>, have it published in the <placeName>Mexican [papers.]
</placeName></p>

<p>If no notice has been taken of the retail law, let it pass off in
silence.</p>

<p>Take care that the <persName>Ayto</persName>. do not entangle themselves by raising
arbitri[os] not authorized by law, as I see they are about to do&#8212;
the resolutions adopted as published in the paper of<date when="1831-04-14"> 14 April</date> are
illegal&#8212;the <persName>Ayto</persName>. can collect half the Taxes authorized by the 8
chapter of the ordinance as you will see by the law that was passed
the last day of the session but you cannot tax anything not 
mentioned in that chapter. Be very cautious on this point. I 
proposed to give the <persName>Ayto</persName>. power to raise 8000 dolls, and assess the Tax
as they might deem proper&#8212;it was objected to on the ground that
no such discretionary power can be given, and I was compelled to
accept of the law as it is or fail in toto                       </p>
<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Shew this letter to <persName>Johnson </persName>or such parts as you please.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
