<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4828">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Asa Brigham to J. A. Wharton et Al., 07-19-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Asa Brigham</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-28">02-28-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J. A. Wharton et Al.
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Columbia, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 92-93
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-07-19">07-19-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-28" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Strong for federal form of government but wants no war with Mexico.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Columbia </placeName><date when="1835-07-19">July 19th 1835</date></p>

<p>To the <persName>Committee from the <placeName>Jurisdiction of Columbia</placeName></persName></p>

<p><persName>Gentlemen</persName>,</p>
<p>I have the pleasure to acknowledge the receipt of your esteemed favor
of the <date when="1835-07-15">15th Inst</date>, together, with the important documents annexed; They
have been published and circulated in this <placeName>jurisdiction</placeName>, the copies 
required will be forwarded to you to day by<persName> Mr. Eaton</persName>; They are printed
in hand bill form, with a part of the late proceedings of the <persName>Ayuntamiento
of Columbia</persName> annexed, the circular which was addressed to different
<persName>Ayuntos of the <placeName>Deptmt of Brazos</placeName></persName> was through mistake omited.</p>

<p>I am highly Gratified to learn that the minds of the <persName>citizens </persName>and public
Meeting at <placeName>San Filipe</placeName>, so completely accord with the resolutions of this
<placeName>Jurisdiction</placeName>, in fact my most sanguine expectations have been more than
realized</p>

<p>I discover the <persName>Planters </persName>are again in good cheer, when informed that the
present prospect is good for them to gether their present crops, and enjoy
the rewards of their Labour, in place of taking up arms, and marching
against the <persName>mexican Troops</persName>, for the only purpose of protecting a few 
unprincipled <persName>Land speculators</persName>, and resqueing, one of the most depraved
<persName>State Legislatures</persName>, that ever assembled on the <placeName>continent of North America</placeName>.&#8212;</p>

<p>Gentlemen, You are now placed upon the watch Tower, dont be caught
naping in time of calm, I hope your zeal and determination will not
abate in effecting if possible our first projected plan, that of calling the
<persName>delegation </persName>we will want advice in <persName>General Council</persName>, ere long important
maters will arrise between <placeName>Texas </placeName>and the <persName>Centeral Government</persName>, which will
require all the intellectual faculties of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to be concentrated, in order
to be prepared to assert our rites as <persName>freemen </persName>with a full determination to
defend them.</p>

<p>In my humble opinion, there is questions nearly ripe, and will soon be
agitated; when once commenced, will flud in upon us in rapied succession,
do let us be prepared to answer them promptly and wisely without 
hesitation,</p>

<p>The first may be, will <placeName>Texas </placeName>pay duties, I am under the impresion the
<persName>planter </persName>cannot be found among us, but would say that he would sooner pay
40 pr. ct. higher for his goods than to take up arms, and run the risque of
embarking in a seven years war with the <placeName>Mexican Nation</placeName>; perhaps the next<pb n="93"/>
will be with others whether <placeName>Texas </placeName>will submit to any form of Government
other than that of Republican, let us be prepared to take a firm stand,
and never degrade those principals which we inherited from our 
<persName>forefathers</persName>,&#8212;</p>

<p>Is the <persName>Political Chieff</persName> doing anything towards effecting our grand 
objects?&#8212; I would suggest to you the propriety of placing the<placeName> post office
</placeName>in hands that can be relied on as soon as practicable; you will please keep
a copy of all (if any) official communications that, in the name of this body
should issue from you, that they can be filed in the <placeName>archives of this
<persName>Ayuntamiento</persName>.</placeName></p>

<p>I have no news that will either be interesting or beneficial to you to
communicate. I am in hopes of hearing from you again soon.&#8212; Rumor
says that <persName>Judge Andrews</persName> received a letter from <placeName>N. Y.</placeName> which informs that
<persName>Col. Morgan</persName> has conversed with <persName>Col. Butler</persName> who says that <persName>San Anna
</persName>intends to put <placeName>Texas </placeName>under a <persName>military Government</persName>, and will appoint <persName>D. G.
Burnet</persName> <persName>Governor</persName>;&#8212; rumord further more that <persName>Genl Coss</persName> has issued another
proclamation the purport of it amounts to the information received from
<persName>Griton [Gritten]</persName>, also the 600 Barl of Flour has been reduced to 4 wagon
loads;&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>A. Brigham</persName></p>

<p>Messrs <persName>J. A. Wharton</persName>, <persName>J. F Perry</persName>, <persName>J H Bell</persName>, <persName>Sterlng McNeel</persName>, <persName>Jas. Knight</persName>,
<persName>Committee</persName>, <placeName>San Felipe</placeName>.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] To the <persName>Hon. Committee from the <placeName>Jurisdiction of 
Columbia</placeName> </persName><hi rend="italic">San. Felipe</hi></p>

<p>Politeness of <persName>Mr. Eaton</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
