<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4109">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Anthony Dey and George Curtis to Stephen F Austin, 12-16-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Anthony Dey and George Curtis</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-02">09-02-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 559-560
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-12-16">12-16-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-02" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Plans of the Galveston Bay &amp; Texas Land Co.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New York</placeName> <date when="1830-12-16">16th. December 1830</date></p>
<p><persName>Col. Stephen F. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p>Sir/ It is perhaps a duty we owe to you to communicate the 
inteligence contained in this letter, lest from reports that are <placeName>abroad </placeName>you
should be impressed with an idea in relation to our business, 
unfriendly towards us, which we think you will not indulge when the
business is fully and fairly understood We have no doubt that you
are aware of the Contracts made by <persName>Government of <placeName>Mexico </placeName></persName>and the
<placeName>State of Coahuila and Texas</placeName> with <persName>Govr Lorenzo de Zavala</persName>, <persName>Joseph
Vehlein</persName> and <persName>David G. Burnet</persName> as <persName>Empresarios </persName>in relation to certain
<placeName>Lands lying East of you and bordering on the United States.</placeName> The
<placeName>land comprehended within the boundaries of the four grants</placeName> made
to those gentlemen is estimated to contain about<placeName> 15 millions of Acres</placeName>.
One condition among others is to put on in all 1200 <persName>families </persName>of 
various <placeName>Nations </placeName>These <placeName>Grants </placeName>have been formed and combined into one
<persName>company </persName>and conveyed to <persName>Anthony Dey</persName> and<persName> George Curtis of <placeName>New
York</placeName></persName> and <persName>William H. Sumner of <placeName>Boston </placeName></persName>as <persName>Trustees </persName>and <persName>Attornies</persName>
of the <persName>Empresarios </persName>to fulfil their engagement, and one great effort
is about to be made to colonize those <placeName>grants </placeName>according to the laws of
<placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212; For that purpose <persName>Mr. Zavala</persName> sails for <placeName>France </placeName>in a few
days to procure <persName>settlers </persName>from <placeName>Germany</placeName>, <placeName>France </placeName>and <placeName>Switzerland</placeName>&#8212;
other efforts are making by other <persName>Gentlemen </persName>to bring <persName>colonizers </persName>from
<placeName>England</placeName>, <placeName>Ireland </placeName>and <placeName>Scotland</placeName>&#8212; A vessel will sail from this <placeName>City</placeName>
in a few days with <persName>Swiss </persName>and <persName>Germans</persName>, with a few <persName>agents </persName>of the
<persName>Company</persName>&#8212;these are intended as a pioneer party, to prepare <placeName>huts,
shantees and other temporary accommodation</placeName> for the <persName>settlers </persName>as they
arrive from <placeName>Europe </placeName>or elsewhere and to prepare for them bread stuff
on which to subsist, until the <persName>settlers </persName>can make their locations and
build <placeName>houses </placeName>for themselves&#8212; The combined interest in these <placeName>grants</placeName>
is great and the pains taking to diffuse knowledge and information
in relation to <placeName>Texas </placeName>will we think have the tendency to direct the
attention of many persons towards that <placeName>country </placeName>and your <placeName>colony</placeName>
must of course considering it[s] advanced state of cultivation have
an advantage over any other We are making a publication which
we will take pleasure in forwarding to you in a few days which
developes our whole plan of operations and we expect to send <persName>Col.
Mexia</persName> to see you, with an <persName>agent </persName>very shortly to propose to you 
certain arrangements which we think will tend much to your advantage
in relation to the future settlement of your <placeName>colony </placeName>and for 
consideration of such other matters as may be considered for the joint benefit
of all the <persName>Empresarios </persName>in <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;<pb n="560"/></p>

<p><persName>Govr Zavala</persName><persName> Mr. Vehlein</persName> and <persName>Mr. Burnet</persName> each retain large 
interests in the <persName>Company </persName>and will use their best endeavours for the
promotion of its interests.&#8212;</p>

<p>We cannot however but express a wish, that there was a toleration
as regards religion in that <placeName>Country</placeName>, many of the best <persName>farmers</persName>, who
are not <persName>Roman Catholics</persName> would remove to it, were it not for the
fact that they must become <persName>Romanists </persName>in their religion, and we hope
soon to see a more benign feeling in the Government towards <persName>North
Americans</persName>&#8212; The Government must be satisfied by this time that
the <placeName>United States</placeName> have not had any disposition to take the <placeName>Country</placeName>
by force of arms.</p>

<p>The class of <persName>men </persName>that would improve the face of that <placeName>country</placeName>
more than any others would be the <persName>hardy yeomanry of the<placeName> New
England states</placeName></persName>. We now contemplate to send in their place 
<placeName>Europeans </placeName>to comply with the Contracts but we hope the time is not
far distant when a more friendly relation will exist between our
<persName>governments</persName>&#8212; We shall be glad to hear from you any suggestion
that will tend to our individual and mutual benefit&#8212; Our 
<persName>Co-Trustee Mr. Sumner </persName>is at <placeName>Boston </placeName>at present, and we avail ourselves
of the present opportunity by <persName>Mr. Treat</persName> to make this 
Communication to you which we trust will be met with a corresponding feeling
on your part, and</p>

<p>remain very respectfully</p>

<p><persName>Anthy Dey</persName></p>
<p><placeName>No. 27 Nassau St</placeName></p>
<p><persName>George Curtis</persName></p>
<p><placeName>No. 17 Hanover Street</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
