<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4773">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Samuel M. Williams to Stephen F Austin, 04-22-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Samuel M. Williams</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-22">02-22-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monclova, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 65-67
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-04-22">04-22-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-22" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Cotton speculation. Application for bank charter. Thinks no fees will be claimed by state on lands in Austin's first colony. Improvements at mouth of Brazos</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Monclova </placeName><date when="1835-04-22">22d April 1835</date></p>

<p>My Dear friend</p>

<p>The mail of <date when="1835-04-21">yesterday </date>presented me your welcome letter of <date when="1835-04-04">4th inst</date>, and
in union with my <persName>Companions </persName>am pleased with the indirect prospect which<pb n="66"/>
it holds out of your being able to leave <placeName>Mexico </placeName>in all this month. I hope
the measures adopted by the <persName>Govt of the <placeName>State</placeName></persName>, will accelerate that matter
if not done.</p>

<p>On the subject of the Contract for 12,000 arrobas of Cotton which you
state is offered to you, and about which you ask my opinion&#8212; I can say
it is fair, although the price of Cotton in <placeName>Europe </placeName>and the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> during the
past season, up to the last accounts which I have, would not authorise an
expectation of realising much from 5$ the arroba, if maintained. <persName>McK</persName>
and <persName>W</persName> [McKinney and Williams] had Cotton sold at 16 1/2C in <placeName>Orleans</placeName>.
Still I cannot believe the present prices can hold on, yet at the same time
I am of opinion that the <placeName>market </placeName>of next season will open not lower than
13c.&#8212; If you feel disposed to make a Contract, and want assistance in it
you may include <persName>McKinney </persName>and <persName>Williams</persName>&#8212;giving us information so that
we may take advantage of the season, by purchasing small crops from needy
<persName>planters</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>The new Schr Brazoria got <placeName>on shore at the mouth of the Brazos</placeName> in <date n="01-xx-1835">Jany
last</date> and was abandoned <persName>McK</persName> bot her for the purpose of having her
naturalised&#8212; We have also bot a steam boat for the navigation of the
<placeName>Brazos</placeName>. I have a letter from <persName>McK </persName>dated <date when="1835-03-23">23d March</date>, he was on the eve
of departure for <placeName>Orleans </placeName>on board the Schoner Sanfelipe, he informed
me that the Steam boat had arrived at <placeName>N. 0 </placeName>from the <placeName>Upper Country</placeName>.
I presume he will return in her. You will hardly recognise the <placeName>mouth of
the River</placeName> when you return. We are making considerable improvements
there, I intend building a <placeName>dwelling </placeName>and moveing my <persName>family </persName>there. <persName>McK</persName>
has been there with his <persName>wife </persName>for a year. It is extremely inconvenient for
me to be at <placeName>Sanfelipfe</placeName>, and our business in <placeName>another quarter</placeName>. One of us is
continually on the wing&#8212;</p>

<p>As we have no <persName>correspondents </persName>yet at <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> nor in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, that know
any thing of our standing&#8212;I must leave to your management, should you
think proper to include <persName>McK </persName>and <persName>W </persName>in the Contract for cotton, the 
regulation of security making use of this letter as authority to obligate
<persName>McKinney </persName>and <persName>Williams </persName>as parties to the Contract. The delivery the
present year, will not probably yield over 10 to 15 per cent but the
prospect for the second year may be rated at from 20 to 25 percent After
deducting freight etc.</p>

<p>I have presented to <persName>Congress </persName>a plan for a <placeName>Bank </placeName>and asked for a charter
for 30 years. I think it will succeed&#8212; Capital 1,000,000$ divided into
10,000 Shares at 100$ each If it be obtained, it will facilitate much the
Commercial and agricultural business of <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>There is nothing in my opinion to apprehend about a claim for fees in
your <placeName>old Colony</placeName>. The <persName>present members</persName> are not of opinion that the <placeName>State</placeName>
has any claim.<pb n="67"/></p>

<p>I hope every thing may go on right and smooth at the fountain head,
yet, I do not like appearances, here I believe the federal system has
every thing to expect, nothing to fear.</p>

<p><persName>Samuel M. Williams</persName> [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:]<persName> Stephen F Austin Esqr</persName> <placeName>Mexico</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
