<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4265">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James F Perry to Israel McGready, 10-01-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James F Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-15">09-15-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Israel McGready
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unnown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 694-695
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-10-01">10-01-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Arrived August 14. Opinion of country. Commissions to arrange business in Missouri.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felepe De Austin</placeName><date when="1831-10-01"> Oct 1st 1831</date></p>
<p>My Dear Sir</p>

<p>I take the oppertunity of a <persName>Gentleman </persName>who leaves here tomorrow
for the<placeName> U. S.</placeName> I wrote to you from the <placeName>Sabine </placeName>and enclosed <persName>David
Imboden</persName>s and <persName>Jno L Robin</persName>s notes which I hope you have recieved
and have put it in train for collection We had a long tedious journey
geting here we arrived on the<date when="1831-08-14"> 14th August</date> all in good health 
without any serious accidents considering the distance and the number
of our <persName>famaly </persName>togather with the Season of the year we came in we
have no reason to complain. Our <persName>famaly </persName>has kept their [health] so
far prety well some of them has been a little sick but not dangerous
<persName>Kenner </persName>has had a brush of the feavour and ague but has got clear
of it for several days and with care I hope will remain so. <persName>Hunter</persName>
has been quit[e] sick but is now on the recovery and able to attend
to business there has been a good deal of sickness here this season<pb n="695"/>
and a number of deaths in this place since we arived here, all of
which ware <persName>strangers </persName>and mostly men and it is thought by many
that most of them might have recovered if they had been properly
attended to in the first stage of the disease but being <persName>strangers </persName>ware
necessaryly compelled to stop at<placeName> public houses</placeName> where they could not
have that attention paid to them which was necessary. I promised
to write to you my oppinion of this <placeName>country </placeName>and the prospects as I
have been here so short a time I can give but verry little more light on
the subject than heretofore my oppinion is about as when I first
visited the <placeName>country </placeName>the soil and climit is here and all that is wanting
is industry and enterprise togathere with a well regulated and
perminent Government to make this <placeName>one of the most desirous parts
of the wourld</placeName> I have ever seen I have made an excursion of two weeks
looking for a situation to fix ourselves on. I was down<placeName> on the coast
</placeName>I now expect to start in a few days to look at <placeName>some of the country
above here</placeName>, before I decide where to reside the <placeName>country </placeName>above here
is verry much extold by those residing there but I am prety much
determined to settle <placeName>near the Coast</placeName> <placeName>within a few miles of the West
end of Galvesten bay</placeName>, and as soon as I determine on the place will
start with all my force to put up some <placeName>cabbins </placeName>to move my <persName>famaly</persName>
to. they will remain at this place until we can get some place for to
live in and in one year after I get to farming I will be better able
to give you my oppinion of the <placeName>country</placeName>, but for the present I would
not advise any of my <persName>friends </persName>or <persName>acquantence </persName>to move to this <placeName>country</placeName>
without first coming to see it and judge for themselves before I left
the <placeName>mines </placeName>I requested you to pay my last years Tax but whether I
gave you any writen memorandon to that effect I dont recollect but
I hope you have and if not I wish you to do so I also wish you to get
me out of<persName> Scotts administrator</persName> as soon as posible and we have several
smalle accts which wish to send you but have had no time as yet to
examine the old books please urge the collection of the claims I left
with you. write to me on the receipt of this and give me all the
news of the place and particularly [how] the<persName> Exeters of S P</persName> are
coming out as you know I am some interested in the management
of that Est. but I have verry little dout but that it will be attended
to strictly and correctly I will get <persName>Bell</persName>s act and rect against <persName>James
Austin</persName> the first time I see him which will [bring] the balance on that
a/c considerably in my fav.
</p>
<p>[James F. Perry.]</p>


<p>[Indorsed:] To <persName>Israel McGrady</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
