<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4512">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Ira Ingram to Stephen F Austin, 01-20-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Ira Ingram</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-09">11-09-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Matagorda, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 915-917
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-01-20">01-20-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Defending a letter which he wrote protesting against abuses in collection of customs.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Matagorda </placeName><date when="1833-01-20">Jan. 20th 1833</date>.</p>
<p><persName>Colo. Stephen F. Austin</persName>,</p>

<p>Sir, Your letter of the <date when="1833-01-14">14th inst</date>., was handed me <hi rend="italic">late</hi>, <date when="1833-01-19">last 
evening</date>. Of the letter which you mention, as having been written from
<placeName>La Bahia</placeName>, I know nothing; never having seen, or heard, of such a
letter, till I perused yours from <placeName>San Felipe</placeName>, of the date above quoted.
As to the letter from <hi rend="italic">this </hi>place, of which you speak, as having seen
at <placeName>La Bahia</placeName>, and which you say you "burnt;" unless it was one
written by myself, signed by me, and <hi rend="italic">no </hi>one else, addressed to Mess.
<persName>Leving</persName>, <persName>Morehouse</persName>, and other <persName>Americans</persName>, resident, as transient, in
that place, I must also remark, that I know nothing. If it was my
letter which you saw, and which you "burnt," as it was addressed
to <hi rend="italic">all </hi>the americans there, it became, as soon as received by them,
their <hi rend="italic">common </hi>property, and if they thought proper to destroy it,
the act of doing so, furnishes no just cause of complaint on <hi rend="italic">my </hi>part.<pb n="916"/></p>

<p>I have only to regret, that, as it may be called in question at a
future day, and that, as the letter <hi rend="italic">itself</hi>, in such event, would be
more <hi rend="italic">true </hi>to the motives of its <persName>author</persName>, better evidence of its tendency
to prevent, or to promote discord, than the confused, or the 
perverted recollection of fallible and mutable man, its preservation,
without doing an injury to <hi rend="italic">any </hi>one, might have served hereafter, as
a shield to the <persName>writer</persName>, against the iliberal and censorious attacks of
more than one man, in times of high excitement.</p>

<p>The letter was ocasioned in part only, by the threat and visitation
of the <persName>pretended collector of <placeName>Goliad</placeName></persName>, to this town, for the avowed
purpose, of collecting duties, searching for, and seizing goods, said
to be deposited in the <placeName>warehouses of this place</placeName>.</p>

<p>It was occasioned <hi rend="italic">principally</hi>, by an occurrence which transpired
previous to the communication of that threat.</p>

<p>The rights of an <persName>American citizen</persName>&#8212;of <hi rend="italic">one </hi>who had violated no
law;&#8212;rights, the protection of which, had been solemnly guarranted
by treaty&#8212;had been invaded, insulted, spit upon, and 
contemptuously trampled in the mud. In doing this, the <hi rend="italic">rites</hi>&#8212;the sacred
rites, of even savage hospitality, had been denied and insultingly
refused. Divested of his arms&#8212;his papers&#8212;travelling apparel; 
forcible possession taken of his horse, and thus deprived, for a time, of
the means of transporting himself to any <placeName>christian habitation</placeName>&#8212;
oppressed by disease; weak, and emaciated, suffering the paroxism
of a fever, he was thus detained for hours in the <placeName>open prairie</placeName>, in a
state of painful suspense which none can know who have not felt it;
and which, it is sincerely hoped, may <hi rend="italic">never never</hi> again be felt, even
by a <persName>barbarian</persName>, in a <hi rend="italic">land </hi>professing Christianity, and calling itself
civilized. Treated as an <persName><hi rend="italic">indian</hi></persName>, and <hi rend="italic">told </hi>that he was <hi rend="italic">one</hi>, put in
charge of beings, far less humane than the <persName>Arab of America</persName>, he was
made to suffer the double torment of present deprivation and Misery,
and a threatening prospect of the future, if possible, still More
alarming.</p>

<p>These are some of the amiable proceedings, these are a <hi rend="italic">part </hi>of the
tantalizing and disgraceful doings of <hi rend="italic">Men</hi>, calling themselves<persName> officers
of the law</persName>, and <persName>guardians of the public interest</persName>.</p>

<p>Oh, liberty! Oh, humanity! Oh, pity!! <hi rend="italic">When</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">why</hi>, did the
thunder sleep? Why was it reserved, why permitted, a "law-
despising," unprincipled, and merciless banditti, thus to outrage, a
pupil, of the school of <persName>Washington </persName>?</p>

<p>But to proceed&#8212;My object in writing to the<persName> Americans in <placeName>Goliad</placeName></persName>,
was, to let <hi rend="italic">them</hi>, and through <hi rend="italic">them</hi>, the selfstyled <persName>authorities of that
place</persName>, <hi rend="italic">know </hi>the determination, the unanimous, the individual, and
the collective <hi rend="italic">determination</hi>, of the people here, in case of an attempt.<pb n="917"/>
by them, to carry their <hi rend="italic">threat </hi>into execution.   I thought, that, by
doing so, the effusion of blood, Might be prevented.</p>

<p>Furthermore&#8212;the convention, considering there was no adequate
power in that body, or <hi rend="italic">elsewhere </hi>in the <placeName>county</placeName>, as we were then
situated, to interfere with the <hi rend="italic">cargo</hi>, consented, and recommended to
tax the flag <hi rend="italic">only</hi>; Not pretending to extend their authority beyond
the collection of the tonage duty.</p>

<p>This was the basis, or foundation of the resolution taken by the
people <hi rend="italic">here</hi>; and if an observance of any part, or portion of the
proceedings of the convention, was either lawful or innocent, then
their proceedings were lawful, were innocent, were patriotic!</p>

<p><persName>Ira Ingram   </persName> [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
