<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4616">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 01-14-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-02">12-02-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monterey, Nuevo Leon</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1033-1036
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-01-14">01-14-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-02" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Announcing arrest, discussing past policies, and advising tranquillity.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Monterey </placeName><date when="1834-01-14">Jany. 14 1834</date></p>
<p>Dr <persName>Brother </persName>and <persName>Sister</persName>,</p>

<p>The affairs of <placeName>Texas </placeName>are likely to cost me much trouble and expense
in addition to what I have already undergone since I left home.
The <persName>state govt</persName>, have made an accusation against me of some kind, to
the <persName>genl Govt</persName>, and I was arrested on the <date when="1834-01-03">3rd inst</date>. at <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>on my
arrival there and shall leave in a few days for <placeName>Mexico </placeName>as a <persName>state
prisoner</persName>. Give yourselves no kind of uneasiness about this matter&#8212;
it can do me no other harm that [than] the delay and expense&#8212;all
I can be accused of is that I have labored most diligently and 
indefatigably to get <placeName>Texas </placeName>made a state separate from <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>, and
that is no crime, nor no dishonor&#8212;it is quite the reverse</p>

<p>I made some <persName>enemies </persName>in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>for opposing a <placeName>territory</placeName>, but I
have many good <persName>friends</persName>, who will see justice done me and amongst
them, the <persName>vice President</persName> himself</p>

<p>It is very likely that I may be hammered and pummeled about for
a year before I get home again, but I think that good will come of it
for <placeName>Texas</placeName>. The <date when="1830-04-06">April </date>law is repealed and before I quit the matter
I hope to see some other remedies. I did not like the manner this
question was started I wanted <placeName>Bexar </placeName>to take the lead&#8212;but so it is&#8212;
you must all now harmonize more with <placeName>Bexar </placeName>and <placeName>Goliad </placeName>and have
union&#8212;and no more <hi rend="italic">party spirit</hi>. I suppose that some of my <persName>enemies
in the <placeName>colony</placeName></persName> will rejoice at what they may think or <hi rend="italic">hope </hi>will be my
ruin&#8212;-no good man will envy them their joy, nor participate in it.</p>

<p>I have been very kindly treated by the <persName>Commandant General Don
Pedro Lemus</persName> and by the <persName>Govr. of this state</persName> and <persName>Col. Ugartechea
</persName>and have no cause to complain on that score. I hope when <persName>Genl
Lemus</persName> visits <placeName>Texas </placeName>my <persName>friends </persName>there will remember that he befriended me very much.</p>

<p>I hope there will be no excitement about my arrest&#8212;-it will do me
harm and no good to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, that is unless I should be unjustly dealt
by, in that case there will be cause for excitement.<pb n="1034"/></p>

<p>I have requested <persName>Williams </persName>to provide me with the means of living
in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, it is likely I may want as much as one thousand dollars,
tho I do not know.</p>

<p>Collect all the stock you can in claims due me and put them <placeName>on
your farm at Chocolate Bayou</placeName>, in your own brand&#8212;call on <persName>Williams</persName>
for the claims and hire some one to collect them.</p>

<p>When I return I wish to make my <placeName>home </placeName>at your <placeName>home </placeName>and hope
you will have a room or cabbin for me.</p>

<p>I send you some seeds of a beautiful tree in shape like a lombardy
poplar, in foliage like a cedar&#8212;sow them&#8212;in a bed like pepper
seed&#8212;raise the bed so that the water will not lay on it&#8212;water them
in dry weather, protect them from frost in the winter when young,
and from the hot sun in the middle of the day, by a bush or mat.
They will do to transplant the second or third year&#8212;take special
care of them. I have many seeds and my miniature taken in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>
by <persName>Wm Howard</persName> who intends to visit <placeName>Texas</placeName>, I recommend him to
you very particularly. I cannot send these things to you now. So
will give away the seeds and take the miniature to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>again.</p>

<p>You have suffered a great affliction since I left in the loss of dear
little <persName>Mary</persName>, and in the sweep made by the cholera&#8212;it is dread full
but without remedy&#8212;my good friends <persName>John Austin</persName>, <persName>Westall</persName>, and
many others are gone. I sympathize sincerely with you all&#8212;poor
<persName>Henry </persName>too has his share and more than a share of affliction&#8212;it is
dreadfull indeed.</p>

<p>Remember me to<persName> Mrs. Westall</persName>&#8212;to the <persName>McNiels</persName>, and <persName>Munson</persName>, to
<persName>Phillips </persName>and <persName>Eliza</persName>, and do not let <persName>little Stephen</persName> and your <persName>children</persName>
forget me, I hope they will some day be benefited by my labors.</p>

<p>remember me to <persName>Henry </persName>particularly&#8212;I have not received a line
from you since I left home</p>

<p>Cotton is worth about 30 cents in <placeName>San Luis Potosí</placeName>&#8212;the freight
from <placeName>Tampico </placeName>is from eight to nine dollars a hundred. If you wish
for information write to <persName>Dall </persName>and <persName>Drege </persName>in <placeName>San Luis Potosi</placeName>&#8212;<persName>Henry</persName>
knows them</p>

<p>God bless you&#8212;farewell&#8212;your <persName>brother</persName></p>

<p><persName>Stephen</persName></p>

<p>It is very rare that a man who labors for the genl good of 
thousands, or for a whole <placeName>country</placeName>, can escape persecution and 
detraction&#8212;no man did more good than <persName><hi rend="italic">DeWitt Clinton</hi></persName> for the state of
<placeName>New York</placeName>, but he did it against a torrent of abuse slander and
opposition. <persName><hi rend="italic">Smith </hi></persName>the father and champion of the infant colony
at <placeName>Jamestown </placeName>in <placeName>Virginia </placeName>was even banished by those whom he had
labor'd for. Party spirit and <hi rend="italic">envy </hi>only see with their own eyes and
for their own ends&#8212;they are everything that is uncharitable 
malignant, selfish, anti moral and anti honest&#8212;the mass of the people,<pb n="1035"/>
the honest laboring class think of their <persName>families </persName>and their domestic
concerns, and are therefore easily mislead by <persName>demagogues </persName>and 
designing or envious men, who only think how to destroy and involve
others to build up themselves. It is well known that I have always
been opposed to violent measures in <placeName>Tejas </placeName>and that I have always
been the friend and a sincere one of the <persName>Mexicans</persName>. <hi rend="italic">Party spirit</hi> has
tryed to make this a crime in me. I wished to smother this spirit
because history shows that the most dangerous enemy to <placeName>new 
colonies</placeName> and <placeName>infant communities</placeName> is division and discord amongst 
themselves, and I resorted to conciliating, yielding and passive means to
keep down party spirit, when perhaps I ought to have adopted the
reverse. Up to <date n="xx-xx-1830">1830 </date>my sistem was not interfered with, and all went
well, but since then, all has been confusion&#8212;and my <persName>enemies </persName>have
succeeded to their utmost wish in involving <hi rend="italic">me </hi>in difficulty&#8212;had I
been as vindictive against <hi rend="italic">them</hi>, as they have against <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, and called
the <persName>old settlers</persName> and sound part of the people to rally a-round me. I
could have easily <hi rend="italic">crushed </hi>my <persName>enemies</persName>&#8212;but they [would] have been
totalty ruined, and I did not wish to ruin even the worst enemy I
had on earth. They have tryed violent measures and gained 
nothing but trouble, let them now try peace and harmony awhile and let
the country advance in population and resourses. The 
favourable reforms and changes are taking place in the<persName> Mexican 
government</persName> and people, and a little time will put all right&#8212;there will be
toleration of religion&#8212;<placeName>Texas </placeName>will be a state and all will go right&#8212;
but above all things the colonists must harmonize with <placeName>Bexar </placeName>and
<placeName>Goliad</placeName>. In the beginning of <date n="10-xx-1833">October </date>I lost patience I recd a letter
then from <placeName>Texas </placeName>that irritated me, also some things occured in
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>that soured and discouraged me, and I wrote to the 
<persName>Ayuntamientos </persName>a letter which is the cause of my arrest&#8212;since then
favourable changes have taken place. There is no sort of doubt of
the <hi rend="italic">right </hi>of the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> to take care of themselves, if there
be no other remedy&#8212;this is very clear&#8212;it is more than a right&#8212;it is a
duty&#8212;but evil may be done by precipitation. The evil in these 
matters is that ambitious and bad men wish for revolution, and they
take advantage of a fevered state of public opinion, to hurry the
people into it, when it is not necessary&#8212;in such cases the <persName><hi rend="italic">actors</hi>
</persName>gain, and the <hi rend="italic">instruments </hi>loose.</p>

<p>As I before said, when I return I will make my home at your
house. I will not have anything more to do with public business if I
can honorably and consistantly avoid it</p>

<p>I am told that <persName>Sterling Robinson</persName> has made charges to the <persName>state
Govt</persName>, against me. I think it unkind that such a man as that should
be made use of as an instrument by others, to try and ruin me&#8212;but
all this is in the regular course of things with envy and party spirit.<pb n="1036"/></p>

<p>Keep yourself totally clear of politics and party and seek 
happiness within the limits of your <placeName>farm </placeName>and the circle of your <persName>family</persName>
and personal <persName>friends</persName>, and I will join that circle as soon as I can, it
is  the  only place  where  I expect  to  find  quiet or  happiness&#8212;
adios</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>the most certain way for letters to reach me is to direct them to
<persName><hi rend="italic">William Parrott, merchant, Mexico</hi></persName>, and send them to <placeName>Tampico</placeName>,
or <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, to be put in the mail there&#8212;if there is no other 
opportunity, send them by way of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, I saw <persName>Baldwin </persName>in
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>and put a letter in the mail here from him to you&#8212;-he has
lost and suffered much.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
