<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4387">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 07-18-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-29">09-29-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brazoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 821-822
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-07-18">07-18-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-29" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">All must now unite in support of Santa Anna and the Liberals. Bradburn precipitated the clash in Texas. Williams must not take to heart popular disapproval of his pacific policy.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p><placeName>Brazoria </placeName><date when="1832-07-19">July 19 1832</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p>I had not time to say much by <persName>Wm. Austin</persName>. Since he left I have
heard of the excitement which some have felt against you owing
to the difference of opinion as to what ought to be done in the
critical situation of the <placeName>country</placeName>. These [are] things to be expected
everywhere and amongst all people under excitement&#8212;they have
their hour and pass away and are forgotten. All that is necessary
for you to do or say is, that you wished to do for the best&#8212;may
have been mistaken as to the means, that nothing but an anxious
desire to serve the common cause of the <placeName>country </placeName>actuated you,
without personal feelings against anyone, that in your moments of
excitement you blamed others who differed in opinion with you, and
that they also had the same right to blame you, for both thought
their course the best etc. Something of this nature and in a good
[hu]mored way, without any display of passion or irritation against
anyone will soon put it all at rest&#8212;some of the <persName>leading men in the
<placeName>U. S</placeName>.</persName> have had the honor of being stuck up in <hi rend="italic">effigy </hi>for political
opinions, so that you need not feel mortified at that. A few persons
here last night had you and two others <persName>Chambers </persName>and <persName>Lewis </persName>up in
effigy&#8212;it will do <hi rend="italic">you </hi>no harm unless you get into a passion about
it&#8212;so keep quite cool and let it all pass away, as it will do of itself.
The fact is that the state of things has been such that, at times none
of us knew or could tell what course was the best&#8212;all had but one
object in view which was to do right as near as they could&#8212;en fin,
vale mas reir qe maldecir.</p>

<p>The <placeName>colony </placeName>and all <placeName>Texas </placeName>have but one course left which is to
unite in the cause of the <persName>Santana party</persName>, and if necessary fight it out
with the <persName>ministerialists</persName>&#8212; I have written to <persName>Musquis </persName>urging him to
make a pronunciamto in <placeName>Bexar</placeName>. <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>will follow as a
matter of course and <persName>Piedras </persName>will acquiess or have to leave the
<placeName>country </placeName>for <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have great need here for<persName> Mr. Greaves </persName>and hope he will come
down&#8212;tho it is now almost too late. I wish the <persName>Ayuntamto </persName>to
make a formal pronunciamto as soon as possible and advise the
<persName>Alcalde </persName>to call an extra meeting as soon as possible so as to give
time for the <persName>members </persName>to attend, this is very important indeed. We
must now all pull at the same end of the rope.<pb n="822"/></p>

<p><persName>Teran </persName>killed himself at <placeName>Padilla </placeName>on the <date when="1832-07-03">3</date>&#8212;he ran his sword through
his heart on the<placeName> very spot where <persName>Iturbide </persName>was shot</placeName>. <persName>Montezuma</persName>
left <placeName>Tampico </placeName>for <placeName>San Luis</placeName> with 1500 <persName>men </persName>soon after <persName>Mexia </persName>sailed
for <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>&#8212;it was a combined movement, ordered by 
<persName>Montezuma</persName>, to [enable] <persName>Mexia </persName>to take <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>by keeping <persName>Teran </persName>
employed elsewhere&#8212;<persName>commissioners </persName>are appointed by <persName>Santana </persName>and
<persName>Bustamte </persName>to meet at the <placeName>Puerto Nacional</placeName> to settle the question,
<persName>Victoria </persName>by <persName>Santana</persName>, <persName>Camacho </persName>by <persName>Bustamte </persName>and I think it probable
the whole matter is settled by this time.</p>

<p><persName>Mexia </persName>and myself have been enthusiastically recd, here&#8212;it was
a joyfull event for the whole <placeName>country</placeName>, for I think it [will] unite
<placeName>Texas </placeName>on the same side, and right or wrong we must all pull together.
I intended to have started up <date when="1832-07-20">tomorrow </date>and if necessary gone from
there with <persName>volunteers </persName>against <placeName>Anahuac </placeName>by the <persName>time Mexia </persName>got round
with the fleet&#8212;but<date when="1832-07-21"> day after tomorrow </date>is a grand Ball, and we must
stay. I think it will be unnecessary for any men to go to <placeName>Anahuac</placeName>
for the <persName>troops </persName>there will no doubt pronounce.</p>

<p>Don't let these matters worry you, what you have done was for
the best. Under the circumstances in which you were placed it
was impossible to say what was for the best-&#8212;all reasonable <persName>men</persName>
will look at the <hi rend="italic">motives </hi>and not at hasty expressions made in a
moment of great excitement. I will write to the <persName>Alcalde </persName>to call a
meeting of the <persName>ayto</persName>.&#8212;it must be as soon as possible for I wish to
return with <persName>Mexia </persName>to <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>so as to be at <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>by the <date when="1832-09-01">1 of
September.</date> He will stay no longer at <placeName>Galveston </placeName>than is necessary
to regulate them at <placeName>Anahuac </placeName>and take <persName>Bradburn </persName>where he will
probably never more hear of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. His cup of disgrace and 
infamy is full, up and over the brim.</p>

<p>Farewell&#8212;remember me to <persName>Sarah </persName>and <persName>Mr. Greaves</persName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Muchissimas memorias a <persName>Arciniega </persName>digale que escribi a <placeName>Bexar </placeName>pa
que se pronuncian por <persName>Santana</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>A</persName></p>
<p><date when="1832-07-20">20th.</date></p>

<p>I have this moment recd, yours by <persName>William Austin</persName>. I am fully
aware of the motives which influenced you.</p>

<p>I have always expressed to you, both verbally and in writing a
wish that the <persName>colonists </persName>should not take part in the civil wars of the
<persName>Mexicans</persName>, unless they should unfortunately reach <placeName>Texas</placeName>, in that
event there would of course be no remidy left but to take a hand.</p>

<p>I had no right or reason to expect that that most consummate of
all fools, <persName>Bradburn</persName>, would have acted as he has done&#8212;he promised
and assured me at <placeName><persName>Lynche</persName>s </placeName>that he would respect the <persName>civil Authority </persName>at<pb n="823"/>
<placeName>Anahuac </placeName>and concilliate the people there, and I believed he would&#8212;
he was too much of a <persName>jack ass</persName> to be governed by reason or 
judgement, or anything else except brutal passion&#8212;I therefore could not
foresee what has happened, and could not give you instructions in
time&#8212; what I feared if the <persName>colonists </persName>took part in the civil wars
was they would get into anarchy and confusion&#8212;but will come right
now and we shall all pull heart and hand at one end of the rope.
See <persName>Chrisman </persName>and have the <persName>Ayto</persName>. convened by <date when="1832-07-25">Wednesday </date>or 
<date when="1832-07-26">thursday </date>at most&#8212;remember me to <persName>Mr. Greaves</persName>. I shall need his aid in
the <persName>Spanish </persName>line of business as soon as I get up. Speak to him on
the subject. I refer you to <persName>Johnson </persName>for particulars as [to] our 
arrival here etc. I wrote from the <placeName>mouth of the river</placeName> the moment I
landed and <persName>Cap John Austin</persName> directed a copy to be sent up, when he
started down to meet us, which was done, but it went <placeName>up the river
on the other side</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Col Mexia </persName>would go up with great pleasure, but his fleet is
anchored off and he is limited as to time,-he starts on <date when="1832-07-23">Monday </date>to
embark for <placeName>Galveston Bay,</placeName> and will only be two days at <placeName>Anahuac</placeName>,
as he last night recd, official information of the pronunciamto of
that place under <persName><hi rend="italic">Col Suveran</hi>.</persName> The report you speak of, that there
had been a saqueo etc is all false. <persName>Suveran </persName>has written to <persName>Cap J.
Austin</persName> and <persName>Lieut. Domingues</persName> is here direct from <placeName>Anahuac</placeName>&#8212; all
goes well over there and <persName>Bradburn </persName>has taken to the brush. If <persName>Piedras</persName>
refuses, we must and will fight him. All <placeName>Texas </placeName>must go together. I
will write to him from <placeName>San felipe</placeName> and to <placeName>Ayish bayou</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>S F A</persName></p>

<p>write to <placeName>Gonzales </placeName>and let them know what they ought to do&#8212;
<hi rend="italic">La constitución y <persName>Santana</persName>.</hi></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
