<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4932">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>George Antonio Nixon to Stephen F Austin, 10-10-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>George Antonio Nixon</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-03-27">03-27-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nacogdoches, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 171-172
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-10-10">10-10-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-03-27" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">East Texas uniting to join you. Money sent to United States for arms and munitions. Efforts to win support of Mexican residents</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName><date when="1835-10-10">oct 10, 1835</date></p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p><date when="1835-10-09">yesterday </date>arived <persName>Col Austin</persName>s Letter giving the account of the Battle at
<placeName>Gonsalles</placeName>, and a Printed hand Bill this semes to unite all <date when="1835-10-07">3 Dayes a Go</date>
we had a meeting at <placeName>my house</placeName> and we Subcribed 2100 Dollars to send in
to Purchas Guns, <persName>8 of us</persName> Subcribed 2000 and <date when="1835-10-09">Last Night</date> the <persName>Comitty </persName>met
at <placeName>my house</placeName> and has Sant on <persName>Capt English</persName> to atland to the Purchas of
arms, he Left hear at 10 oclock at Night and he Bars the <persName>Express </persName>
taining <persName>Austen</persName>s Letters So as, to have the Letters at <placeName>San Auguteen</placeName> by
<date when="1835-10-10">twelve oclock to Day</date>, as thear is to Be a meeting thear, I have had a
Part of the hand Bill translated and will have it Read to the <persName>Maxacans</persName>,
<date when="1835-10-09">yeasterday </date>I had a taulk with with <persName>Col. Bean</persName> and he has promised me to
try and Rase the <persName>Maxacans </persName>and go on with them, I have promised the
<persName>Maxacans </persName>500 Dollar in Cash and all my influance will be yoused to Git
them&#8212;to unite and Joine the arme and at Present from what tauk I have
had I am in Good hopes, to Day <persName>35, or 40 <placeName>San Auguteen</placeName> trupe</persName> Leave<pb n="172"/>
hear for your assistance and about as maney more from <placeName>this Place</placeName> and I
am informed that we may Count on <persName>a hundread more</persName> from <placeName>San Auguteen</placeName>
and that <placeName>Nabourhood</placeName> thear is But one thing wanting hear to unite us all
that is to Convince the <persName>Cheafe </persName>and I hope you will youse your influance
with him and I wall No that all Depends on you and <persName>Gen Zavala</persName> for
<persName>Zavala </persName>Can influance him and then all will Go in togather hart and hand
So you and <persName>Zavala </persName>must Spar No Panes in this mater and the <persName>Cheafe </persName>Sayes
he will Be with you in <date when="1835-10-14">4 Days from this time</date> he also informed me to Day
he will make a Short Stay in <placeName>San Phillipia</placeName>. I Give it as my advise that
If you Can Git him to Joine you in opinion that you will Git him to wright
and Sand his Letter By <persName>Express </persName>thear is a Bout <persName>120 Good maxacans</persName> that
will Joine the Cause when I Commenced these few lines I Entended to Be
sent on to <persName>Dr Richerson</persName> and that he would Present It to you But 
supposing him Gon on to <placeName>Gonzalles </placeName>I wright you</p>

<p><persName>Jorge Anto Nixon Sind[ico]</persName></p>

<p>your <persName>Express </persName>in forming us of your Prospect of <persName>2000</persName> from <placeName>N Orleans</placeName>
has just arrived and in a Bout 20 Minets Somthing like <persName>100 man</persName> will Just
march on hors Back I have Just Been Speaking with <persName>Mr Berrey</persName> and he
for the first time has declard he will Sand an <persName>Express </persName>Back from <placeName>San
Phillipia</placeName>, he Seemes to Be in favour so I hope you will have But Littel
trubil in hast</p>

<p><persName>Jorge Anto Nixon Sind.</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Col. Stephen F. Austin</persName> <placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
