<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4881">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Martin Allen to James F Perry, 09-22-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Martin Allen</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-03-20">03-20-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">8 Mile Point, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Peach Point, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 131-132
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-09-22">09-22-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-03-20" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Suggesting a land settlement. Austin narrowly escaped death by accident</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>8 Mile point</placeName> <date when="1835-09-22">Sept 22nd 1835</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr Pery</persName></p>

<p>Sir I offer my best respects to you and family I congratulate you on
the arrival of our worthy friend <persName>Col. Austin</persName> and hope that his arrival at
this Critical Moment will be the Saving of our <placeName>Country</placeName>. I Saw him 
<date when="1835-09-21">yesterday </date>at <placeName>home </placeName>he is well, at present, but had been very near Ending his
days by accident as he informed me he had sent down to town for a bottle of
Brandy and he had sent to him a bottle of the tincture of corose of 
subliment he informed me that it puked and purged him at the most violent
rate posable. He sayed one teaspoonfull more must have taken his life&#8212;
but he is over it and well and will receive no further injury by it as it
operated in the way it did&#8212; I had some conversation with him relative
to the views I had of fixing my stock on <placeName>Dickersons buyo </placeName>I have been over
lately to that <placeName>buyo </placeName>and examined your <placeName>land </placeName>in order to select a suitable spot
for the purpose&#8212; I have chosen one if you are willing to let me have it
as we have talked of that is for me to have the <placeName>labore </placeName>on which I would<pb n="132"/>
settle. You wrote me once that I must take it in <placeName>one corner of one of your
land.</placeName> this might not suit me attall as the soil is all poor&#8212; the <persName>Colonel</persName>
says he apprehends there will be no objections to my settling on any part
of the land that I may select. And if you are willing to give me a <placeName>labore</placeName>
where I have selected and will write me to that afect, I will go over and
prepare <placeName>cowpens </placeName>and take my stock over as soon as the <placeName>river </placeName>gets low
enough</p>

<p>I think <persName><hi rend="italic">Mr </hi>Perry </persName>that my preposials are not unreasonable as you have
<placeName>two Leagues adjoining each other</placeName> I think the law require that there shall
be put upon <placeName>grasing lands</placeName> 100 heads of horned cattle, and my stock will
amount to at least 200 head will be the settling of <placeName>both leagues</placeName> in the Eye
of the law&#8212; You will please to write to me as soon as posable as the
season is fare advanced to move cattle this <date n="Fall-1835">fall</date>: if the <placeName>river </placeName>gits down in
time to move them this <date n="Fall-1835">fall</date>. I want to do it as soon as posable. And if it
dos not I will go over and make preperations for to move them in the
<date n="Spring-1836">spring </date>I am offered choice of <placeName>lands on the south side of the buyo</placeName> but
the want of timber is a greate objection.</p>

<p>You will please write by the first opportunity
And Olige Your Cincere friend</p>

<p><persName>Martin Allen</persName></p>
<p><persName>Mr J. Perry</persName></p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr James F. Perry</persName> <placeName>Peach point</placeName> politeness of <persName>Capt.
Richardson</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
