<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4945">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William H Jack to Stephen F Austin, 10-13-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William H Jack</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-03-28">03-28-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Goliad, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 177-178
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-10-13">10-13-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-03-28" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Glad of Austin's election to command. Opposes risking battle with odds against us.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Goliad</placeName>, <date when="1835-10-13">13th Oct 1835</date>.</p>

<p>Dr. Sir</p>

<p>You will allow me to congratulate you, on the high command to which
you have been called by the free and unbiased voice of your <persName>fellow-citizens</persName>.
Rely upon it, Sir I conceive this appointment, to be fortunate for <placeName>Texas</placeName>.
Because it will unquestionably have the effect of uniting <persName>all parties</persName>.</p>

<p>You have been truly fortunate in your appointment of an <persName>adjutant Genl</persName>.
for I conceive <persName>Coln Hall</persName>, to be one of the first military men in <placeName>Texas</placeName>; and
I think his incorporation into your <persName>family </persName>will greatly promote the cause.</p>

<p>The orders rec'd here<date when="1835-10-13"> this morning</date> were not agreeable to a <persName>large 
majority of the men</persName>; but they almost unanimously determined to obey without
a murmur.</p>

<p>We are but illy supplied with stores of any kind, but immediate 
arrangements will be made to do the best we can. I flatter myself that the place
will be dearly bought if the <persName>Mexicans </persName>ever regain it.</p>

<p>You will pardon me for expressing my views and opinions to you <hi rend="italic">freely,
fully and frankly</hi>. It seems the <persName>army </persName>has left <placeName>Gonzales </placeName>for <placeName>Bexar</placeName>. I 
understand your <persName>force </persName>does not possibly exceed 400; I cannot conceive that it is
seriously contemplated to attack <placeName>Bexar </placeName>with that number. The fate of
<placeName>Texas </placeName>must not be risked upon one battle; unless the advantages are so
decidedly in our favor, as to place the result beyond a Shadow of doubt.</p>

<p>If the force of <persName>Cos </persName>be such as the statement furnished by <persName>Majr- Smith
</persName>Shews, they will be more than two to one against you; and though I have
the utmost confidence in the firmness and bravery of our <persName>countrymen </persName>yet
it is drawing too heavily on that confidence, to be willing to risk a general
engagement, on which so much depends against such fearful odds.</p>

<p>They have the numerical strength. They have artillery, cavalry, 
muskets, bayonets, lances, against all these you present a band (brave perhaps
to a fault) of <persName>untrained militia</persName>, with such arms only as could be procured
in the immediate emergency.</p>

<p>The case being thus, I give it as my decided opinion, that an engagement
ought not to be risked, unless success is next to certain.<pb n="178"/></p>

<p><persName>Majr- Smith</persName> shewed me yr- post script in which you express a desire to
see me. At this particular crisis it would probably be unadvisable for me
to leave. By your next <persName>express </persName>you can command me as I can then leave
with propriety.</p>

<p>You will be pleased to accept my assurances of highest regard
<persName>WM- H. Jack</persName></p>
<p>[Addressed:]<persName> Stephen F. Austin Commander of <placeName>Texas </placeName>Army</persName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
