<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4181">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Samuel M Williams to Stephen F Austin, 03-22-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Samuel M Williams</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-10">09-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 628-629
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-03-22">03-22-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Conditions in Texas. Newspaper vicissitudes. Austin's difficulties.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Austin </placeName><date when="1831-03-22">22 March 1831</date></p>
<p>My Dear Sir</p>

<p>I do not pretend this scrawl as an answer to your truly 
interesting letter of <date when="1831-02-19">19th ultimo,</date> but as I really feel that your<persName> Texas friends</persName>
have not received your unwearied attentions with that return they
have merited, I determined that you should at least hear from me<pb n="629"/>
in acknowledgement of the receipt of your favours, even tho I be
unable to make mine interesting.</p>

<p>I do most perfectly coincide with you in your opinions respecting
the policy and the probable results of the death of <persName>Guerrero </persName>and
more especially as the<persName> Mexican people</persName> appear fond of change and
novelty.</p>

<p>I cannot account in full for your not having recd any <placeName>papers </placeName>since
<date when="1831-11-13">13th Novr</date> as I have forwarded to you several numbers, nevertheless
a part of the failure has arrisen from a suspension of the paper for
want of materials. You will perceive by the numbers that go by
this mail that a change has been made, and I assure you that it is
an important one. and must prove beneficial to the <placeName>country </placeName>
<persName>Williamson</persName>, partner of <persName>Mr Aiken</persName> is an excellent <persName>workman</persName>, and quite the
gentleman, and they must succeed</p>

<p>Your <persName>friends </persName>here have viewed with great [satisfaction?] the 
management of your bark thro, the storms shoals, and hurricanes under
which you took the helm: for myself I must say I am truly happy
at your perfect success, because had you not succeeded no merit
would have been given you nor, no credit allowed for the truly
unfortunate circumstances that surrounded your station on entering
the discharge of your duties. You will excuse me for enclosing a
<placeName>paper and a half of a paper</placeName> to you with the last numbers, as I do it
to convince you that you are not forgotten, and have <persName>friends </persName>who
are not ashamed to be so considered.</p>

<p><persName>Williamson </persName>was in the <placeName>office </placeName>when I recd your letter, and desired
me when writing to remember him affectionately to you, and 
furthermore say that he would be careful your <placeName>papers </placeName>should be 
forwarded regularly.</p>

<p>Thank God we are getting on harmoniously old <persName>friends </persName>have
cured old grievances, and left the unhappy and restless beings <persName>Ira</persName>
and <persName>Hosea H</persName>. to brood over their own spleen. We are without
news, fine planting season, and I am busily engaged in settling
<persName>families </persName>We have the <persName>commissioner </persName>here. If time permits I will
write you by the next mail and give you my opinions of the 
situation of <placeName>Texas </placeName>in the mean time accept the assurances of my best
feelings, and desires for your success health and happiness</p>

<p><persName>Samuel M Williams </persName>   [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
