<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4293">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Emily F Perry to James F Perry, 12-01-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Emily F Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-16">09-16-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 720-721
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-12-01">12-01-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Discussion of a house plan drawn by Austin</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><date when="1831-12-01">December 1st 1831</date></p>
<p>My Dear <persName>Husband</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I was highly pleased to hear from you by <persName>Joel</persName>, and of your safe
return from your last scrape, I hope to God that you will not
suffer by your being so exposed to the Cold for so many nights,
I am fearfull that it will give you the <hi rend="italic">Fever </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Ague</hi>, you are
not half as carefull of your self as you should be, how, careless
to go out with out your hat, or coat, I am really astonished at you
all the uneasiness that I have now is on your <hi rend="italic">account</hi>, for you are
so careless, of your self, I have to live so very much <hi rend="italic">exposed</hi>, I
shall be miserable if I hear of your being Sick, you must try and
come up, if you should be taken unwell,&#8212; I am very smart, the
<persName>Baby </persName>is not two weeks old, and I have been out into the <placeName>eating
room</placeName> twice, as bad as the weather has been, we have the prospect of
a pleasant day at last, the first for two weeks,&#8212;</p>

<p>I send you a <hi rend="italic">Plan </hi>of a House that <persName>Stephen </persName>sent down for me to
look at, I approve of the Plan very much, it will be a very
convenient, and pleasent <placeName>house</placeName>, altho it is on a pretty large <hi rend="italic">Scale</hi>,
but not two large, if you think your <hi rend="italic">purse </hi>will allow you to venture
so far, if you could git the frame up, and the <hi rend="italic">roof </hi>on and 
<hi rend="italic">weatherboarded</hi>, by having one chimney and three <placeName>rooms </placeName>made habitable
the Balance could remain unfinished until], time, and money ennabled
you to finished it; at all evence you can make some improvement on
your own Plan by comparing it with the one I send you, I would
rather have more room thrown into the <placeName>rooms</placeName>, and not have the
Passage so <hi rend="italic">wide</hi>, I should prefer having the<placeName> Back-Gallery </placeName>much
<hi rend="italic">wider</hi>, than the <placeName>Front Gallery </placeName>as it will always be <hi rend="italic">used </hi>more than
the Other, I approve of <persName>Stephen </persName>Plan as it respects that end of the
house, were the<placeName> Childrens rooms</placeName> are struck of; also by deviding one
of the large rooms,&#8212;; but you can make such alterations as you think
propper, you are a better judge that I am how, large a <placeName>house </placeName>we can
build, and the expence attending it; go according to your own<pb n="721"/>
judgement, if Plank can be had to lay down on the Passage and <placeName>back
Gallery,</placeName> by closing in three rooms, we could move down, (I mean
putting in doors and windows) the rest of the unfinished <placeName>House </placeName>would
do for the boys to Lodge in, through the Summer; I approve of his
Plan in laying off the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Grounds </placeName></hi>very much I wish the <placeName>Back Yard
</placeName>to run down to the <placeName>Creek </placeName>and do not let the Boys cut down any of
the trees that will make a Shade, you know I am a great Friend to
trees and sh[r]ubbery&#8212; come up as soon as possible, for we are
all very anxious, to see you, write by every opportunity, Adieu&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>E. M. P.</persName></p>

<p>Have received letters from <persName>John Perry and Rachel</persName>,   all friends
were well,   nothing perticular in them;</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
