<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4294">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James Hope, 12-05-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-16">09-16-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James Hope
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 721-722
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-12-05">12-05-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Conditions on which English immigrants will be received.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Mr. <persName>James Hope</persName>,</p>

<p>You inform me that you are going to <placeName>England</placeName>, your <placeName>native 
country</placeName>, on a visit, and expect that many enquiries will be made by your
<persName>friends </persName>and <persName>relations </persName>relative to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and as to the encouragement
that is given by this government to <persName>emigrants </persName>and in order that you
may be enabled to answer them correctly you wish me to give you a
memorandum on the subject&#8212;</p>

<p>In complyance with this request I herewith hand you a <placeName>pamphlet</placeName>
which contains translations of the colonization laws now in force&#8212;
you will find the national law on the 40th and 41st pages numbered
20, and the law of the <placeName>State of coahuila and Texas</placeName> on pages 42, to
48&#8212;it is numbered 21, and commences at the bottom of page 41.&#8212;
The State law is the one which prescribes the quantity of <placeName>land </placeName>each
<persName>settler </persName>is to get and the mode of issuing the titles, The instructions
to the <persName>commissioners </persName>on pages 55. 56. 57. and 58. also clearly 
explain the mode of issuing the titles etc&#8212;</p>

<p>It will be seen by examining the state law above mentioned that
a <placeName>league of land</placeName> and a "<hi rend="italic"><placeName>Labor</placeName></hi>" can be granted to each <persName>family</persName>, and
the quarter of that quantity to single men&#8212; A <placeName>Mexican league</placeName> is
equal to <hi rend="italic"><placeName>four thousand four hundred and twenty eight acres</placeName></hi> english
measure&#8212; A <placeName>Labor </placeName>is equal to <placeName>177 acres</placeName>&#8212; The whole cost of a
league of land including surveying, office fees and what has to be
paid to the Government under the 22d article of the state law, will
not exceed about four cents pr acre, and a considerable portion of
this is payable in instalments&#8212;</p>

<p>By a new contract which I have lately made with the 
<persName>Government </persName>in which I have taken <persName>Mr S. M. Williams</persName> in as a <persName>partner</persName>,
We are authorised to introduce <persName>eight hundred European families</persName>,
and settle them on the <placeName>vacant land</placeName> within the limits of and adjoin-<pb n="722"/>
ing my other <placeName>colonies </placeName>which are completed, The new <persName>emigrants</persName>
therefore who now come, will not have to settle in a <placeName>wilderness</placeName>,
destitute of supplies as the first <persName>emigrants </persName>did, but on the contrary,
they come to a <placeName>country </placeName>abounding in provisions, and in all that is
necessary to make them comfortable By the existing laws of the
Mexican Govt. <persName>Europeans </persName>are prefered to <persName>North Americans</persName>, and no
people would be better received than the subjects of<placeName> Great Britain</placeName>,
for no <placeName>nation </placeName>is on more friendly terms with the <persName>Mexican 
Government</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>English farmers</persName>, and <persName>capitalists </persName>would greatly benefit themselves
by a removal to <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; The industrious and economical habits of
the former, would advance their fortunes rapidly by agriculture, and
the capital of the latter invested in <placeName>Manufactories</placeName>, Agriculture, or
commerce would yield them an immense interest&#8212; There certainly
never was such an opening on earth for <persName>european emigrants</persName>, as is
now presented in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, for it will be remembered that they are not
compelled to settle in<placeName> Austin's colony</placeName> unless they chuse to do so, but
can settle in <placeName>other parts of Texas</placeName>&#8212;it will also be rememberd that no
money is required of the <persName>settler</persName>, untill he has actually recd, his title
from the <persName>commissioner </persName>of the Govt, duly appointed for that 
purpose&#8212;no one can get a title without an actual removal of his <persName>family</persName>
to the <placeName>country</placeName>. By the constitution and laws of this nation slavery
is forever prohibited within the<placeName> mexican territory</placeName>, <persName>emigrants </persName>from
<placeName>England </placeName>would therefore do well to bring a number of <persName>laborers </persName>and
<persName>white servants</persName>, bound under written contracts specifying their wages
and the term for which they had engaged&#8212;such contracts will be
binding and enforced in this <placeName>country</placeName>. It would be a good plan to
bring out a number of <persName>Dutch</persName>, <persName>Belgian </persName>or <persName>German</persName> <persName>families </persName>as 
<persName>laborers</persName>. It is thought by some that they would be much more easily
managed and more profitable, than either <persName>english</persName>, <persName>irish</persName>, or <persName>scotch</persName>
<persName>laborers</persName></p>

<p><persName>Emigrants </persName>will be required to produce evidence of their good moral
character, respectable standing, and industrious and sober habits,
from the judicial or <persName>civil authority</persName> of the <placeName>country </placeName>they remove from,
which must be properly authenticated to avoid frauds and 
impositions, without this indispensable requisite, land will not be granted
to them as <persName>settlers</persName>&#8212;.</p>

<p>On their arrival in this <placeName>country</placeName>, those who wish to settle under the
[last] contract of <persName>Austin </persName>and <persName>Williams</persName>, must apply to one of those
persons in this place, and report himself with a list of his <persName>family</persName>
and present his documents of recommendation, and also his passport
from the <persName>mexican consul</persName> of the <placeName>port </placeName>where he saild from</p>

<p>[Stephen F. Austin.]</p>

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1831-12-05">5th December 1831</date></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
