<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4459">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John T. Mason to Stephen F Austin, 10-25-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John T. Mason</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-10-29">10-29-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 881-882
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-10-25">10-25-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-10-29" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Plans of the Galveston Bay &amp; Texas Land Co. Will cooperate fully with Austin. Approves recent movements in Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>City of New York</placeName> <date when="1832-10-25">Octr 25. 1832</date></p>
<p>Mr Dear Sir</p>

<p>I arrived here from <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>on the <date when="1832-07-22">22 July</date> last at the height of
the prevailing epidemic; and found the <placeName>City </placeName>nearly abandoned and
all business virtually suspended. And it is only <date n="10-xx-1832">within this month</date>
that the <persName>inhabitants </persName>have returned to their <placeName>homes </placeName>and things
begin to assume their usual aspect. This information, which has
doubtless been partially anticipated, will account for the apparent
apathy in the <persName>land companies</persName>, for whose progress I had made 
arrangements. I am now here for the first time that an assemblage of
the <persName>company </persName>could be had since the cholera, and in a few days they<pb n="882"/>
will have organised their plans of operation, and go to work to
introduce <persName>settlers</persName>. It is more than probable I shall come on to
<placeName>Texas </placeName>as early as practicable to fix <persName>resident agents</persName> on the <placeName>respective
grants</placeName>, and get the colonization fairly under way. But whether I
undertake this or not, it will not change my determination to visit
your <placeName>country </placeName>this <date n="Winter - 1832">winter</date>; and I hope to see you at <placeName>St. Felipe</placeName> in
<date n="12-xx-1832">December </date>at farthest.</p>

<p>I am fully persuaded the <persName>Galveston company</persName> will go on with
spirit, and you may expect from them a full cooperation in all
your views. Your movements in <placeName>Texas </placeName>I have learnt with no little
interest, and see you have taken the first step for a change in your
<persName>government</persName>,&#8212;declaring in favor of a <placeName>seperate State.</placeName> This 
doubtless can be readily effected so soon as quiet is restored to the <placeName>Republic</placeName>.
The news here is that <persName>Bustamente </persName>has been completely routed by
<persName>Montesuma</persName>, and is a <persName>fugitive</persName>. <persName>Padraza </persName>has returned, at the repeated
solicitation of<persName> Santa Anna</persName>, and by his resuming the Presidency will
end the contest and restore the constitution. We are on the eve of
our Presidential election, and <persName>Jackson </persName>must be reelected by an 
overwhelming <persName>majority</persName>. The goubernatorial elections of <placeName>Ohio</placeName>, <placeName>Keny</placeName>
and <placeName>Pensa</placeName>&#8212;have been <persName>Jackson</persName>&#8212;<placeName>ohio </placeName>by an immense <persName>majority</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I hope to see you when I visit your <placeName>country</placeName>, because I have much
to say to you, and many important subjects to submit to your 
consideration deeply interesting to us both and to the <placeName>country</placeName>. Should
you return to<placeName> Leona Vicario</placeName> before I arrive or be absent leave a 
letter saying what will be your movements.</p>

<p>I think it more than probable you have been induced to forego
your inclination to retire from public life and will be found at the
<persName>Legislature </persName>in <date n="01-xx-1833">January</date>&#8212; much to my disappointment, it is said
that <persName>Bravo </persName>has been chosen <persName>President</persName>&#8212;should our old friend <persName>Graves</persName>
be with you assure him of my cordial remembrance, and accept for
yourself my most friendly regards</p>

<p><persName>John T. Mason</persName></p>

<p>P. S. I sent your letter to <persName>Ed Hawes</persName> on my arrival: but have heard
nothing from him, I have not been in <placeName>Keny</placeName>. I hope the <persName>Governor</persName>
has appointed a <persName>commissioner </persName>for these <placeName>grants</placeName>: if not please have
it done as early as practicable. My expectation was you would 
return to <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>and have this done when there&#8212;-</p>

<p>[Addressed:]<persName> Colonel Stephen F. Austin</persName> <placeName>St. Felipe de Austin Texas</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
