<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4539">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Jose Antonio Mexia to Stephen F Austin, 03-27-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Jose Antonio Mexia</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-11">11-11-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 932-933
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-03-27">03-27-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Informs Austin that he was elected to senate from Mexico and will further the interests of Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1833-03-27">27th. March 1833</date>.</p>
<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin Esqre.</persName></p>

<p>My dear Friend. I take the pen in my hand to direct a few lines
to <placeName>Texas</placeName>: which part of the <placeName>Republic </placeName>I so much cherish and in
which fate I am so much interested.</p>

<p>As I told you in my previous letter, I am in the <placeName>Senat of the
Union</placeName> for which station I was named by two <placeName>States </placeName>though the valid
election has been that of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>by reason ot vicinity. You and the
other <persName>friends in <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> may have no doubt that <persName>Jose Antonio Mexia</persName>
will employ all the influence that he may have, in favor of those
<placeName>Colonies </placeName>as well as to take away and destroy all the hinderances
which were opposed to their improvement and prosperity by the
mean and low of <persName>Bustamente's administration</persName>.</p>

<p>So soon as the ordinary sesions of the <persName>Congress </persName>may begin I 
intend to try how a law of colonization may be issued as liberal as
possible to promote by these means the increase of the population in
<placeName>Texas </placeName>and its future happiness. Perhaps some memoranda that you
should send me, would be useful to get myself perfectly instructed of
such measures as might be adopted for the attainment of our 
desirable object,   You know, better than any other person whatever, what<pb n="933"/>
<placeName>Texas </placeName>wants, and of course you can give me better than any body else
such light as may be necessary to obtain a favourable result.</p>

<p><persName>Padre Moldoon</persName> presented himself to me a few day ago saying
that he came as <persName>Commissioner </persName>from you and the <persName>Colonists</persName>, to ask for
the derogation of the Law of <date when="1830-04-06">6th of April</date>. Perhaps the 
circumstances are not at present the best for him to obtain a good despatch,
nor do I believe indeed, that you have commissioned him for any
thing.</p>

<p>You may consider me, my friend, as interested in the welfare of
<placeName>Texas </placeName>as any of its <persName>inhabitants</persName>, and you may believe that I am very
sorry that my political affairs prevent my going to begin my <placeName>farm
at Atascosito</placeName> or my <placeName>house at Brazoria</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Geo. Fisher</persName> wished with such ardour to go to his destination in
<placeName>Anahuac</placeName>, notwithstanding that I tried to persuade him not to do
such a thing, that at last I had to give him a letter for your. He
is gone, but I think <persName>Filisola </persName>will not let him pass farther than 
<placeName>Matamoras </placeName>because he told me before going that he would not permit him
to enter <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Filisola </persName>is the best <persName>chief </persName>that you could have wished&#8212; Treat him
with the same frankness with which you have treated me, and let
all persons of some consideration in your <placeName>colony </placeName>be his friends.</p>

<p>Our <persName>Santa Anna</persName> has at last been elected <persName>President </persName>by the votes
of <placeName>16 States out of the 20</placeName>, of which the Union is composed. The
<persName>Vice President</persName> is<persName> Don. Valentin Gomez Farias</persName> by the votes of <placeName>U.
States</placeName>. <persName>Santa Anna</persName>, it appears, is determined not to admit the
Presidency but the <persName>Congress </persName>will not admit his resignation and he
will have to come up to the <placeName>Capital </placeName>for his inauguration.</p>

<p>I would wish that a commission might come from <placeName>Texas </placeName>
composed of individuals from all the <placeName>colonies</placeName>, to which I would join
here as <persName>member </persName>should I was named for it, to present to the <persName>General</persName>
the most cordial compliments and good wishes, as well for the 
triumph attained by him against tiranny as for the good election of
the <placeName>Republic </placeName>choicing him for his <persName>first magistrate</persName>.&#8212;You are well
aware that a public testimony of this nature would be of great 
convenience and perhaps useful to all interests. It would be desirable
that you should come with the Commission&#8212;</p>

<p>Pray write me by every opportunity and have the goodness to
give direction to the Inclosures. Do not forget that you promised
me a piece of <placeName>land in your Colony</placeName> and that a promise is a debt.</p>

<p>My compliments to our common friend <persName>Williams </persName>and to <persName>Don.
Juan your Brother</persName>, and consider toe always
Your affectionate friend</p>

<p><persName>José Antonio Mexia </persName>   [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
