<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4603">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James F Perry to Stephen F Austin, 10-26-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James F Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-30">11-30-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Peach Point, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1009-1011
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-10-26">10-26-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Conditions in Texas during Austin's absence&#8212;flood, cholera, malaria.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Peach Point</placeName> <date when="1833-10-26">26th Oct. 1833</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>Your letters of the <date when="1833-07-30">30th of July</date>&#8212;the <date when="1833-09-05">5th </date>and <date when="1833-09-11">11th of Sept</date>. dated
at <placeName>Mexico </placeName>came to hand two days ago it gave us verry great pleasure
to receive them and to hear of your good state of health, as we had
heard through <persName>Williams </persName>that you had wrote him you had at the
time you wrote all the premonetary simptims of the Cholera and as
it had been very fatle here scarsely any who was attaced with it
that recovered. We was very much alarmed for your safety but kind
providence has preserved you to us and to the <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212;Which still
needs your Guardien hand to guid them through.</p>

<p>To give you an account of the over flow Cholara, Fevers and
deaths in the <placeName>colony </placeName>I presume would be unnessary as I expect <persName>Mr
Williams</persName> has given you full acts. We would have wrote you long
since but did not think our Leatters would reach you as When
you left <placeName>Matamoras </placeName>you expected your stay in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>would be very
short we will now give you a short act. of the sickness and deaths
in our emediate <placeName>neighbourhood </placeName>on your return you will find a great
vacuam in <placeName>this part of the country</placeName>, but before we say anything of
the <placeName>neighborhood </placeName>we will give you some account of our own <placeName>famales</placeName>
sickness. Our famely has not been entirely clear of sickness since
<date n="06-xx-1833">June </date>and part of the time scarsely enough well of either <persName>servants </persName>or
<persName>whites </persName>to wait on the sick and at the worst of our sickness there was
not a <persName>Physician </persName>could be had or a <persName>neighbour </persName>to call to see us <persName>Emily</persName>
was verry low indeed I scarsely thought she could recover.   But it<pb n="1010"/>
was the will of providence to save her to her <persName>famaly </persName>and <persName>friends </persName>but
our dear little <persName>Mary</persName> it was her lot to be taken from us. She was sick
only five days. With the fever and was called of very sudenly and
verry unexpectedly. She died on the <date when="1833-08-04">4th august</date>. We feel and regret
her loss much&#8212; the balance of the <persName>famaly </persName>are now generally in 
tolarable health. Some of them have still slight chills and fevers but we
hope they will soon ware off as the weather is getting quit[e] cool on
the <date when="1833-10-21">21st </date>we had a heavy white frost which is considered very early here.</p>

<p>With regard to our crops and improvements we have done verry
little since the <date when="1833-06-15">middle of June </date>as the <persName>Blacks </persName>were all sick as well as
ourselves we made a good crop of corn and pumpkins about 8 or 900
bushels of corn and plenty of pumpkins. We planted 13 acres of
cotton the <date when="1833-06-24">last week in June</date> which bid fair to do pretty well but the
early frost has injured it much as it had not commenced opening we
do not expect much of a crop cotten is now a fine price in <placeName>N. O.</placeName> from
16 to 18 cts. There is fine cropes in this <placeName>neighbourhood </placeName>and I am
told all over the <placeName>coloney </placeName>where the overflow did not injure it the 
season has been very wet at least untile about the <date when="1833-09-15">middle of September
</date>(since prety dry) together with the over flow is the reason, assigned
for sickly season, this <placeName>low country</placeName> has been visited more severely
with sickness and deaths than the <placeName>upper</placeName> but that has not bean 
entirely clear, there has been recently a good deal of sickness at <placeName>San
felepe</placeName> and above and a good many deaths in our <placeName>neighbourhood </placeName>we
have lost old<persName> Mr McNeel</persName> (fever) <persName>Mr. Westall</persName>, <persName>James </persName>and <persName>Emeline</persName>
(cholera) and <persName>Mr Munson</persName> (fever) which leves a very considerable
vackancey here in <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>our friend <persName>John austin</persName> both his <persName>children</persName>
<persName>Mrs Wm austin</persName>&#8212;<persName>Anthony the printer</persName>, <persName>Bradly </persName>and a number of
<persName>negroes </persName>all died at <placeName>Westall </placeName>with the cholara. there was six or seven
corps there at one time before they could be buried as the <persName>neighbours</persName>
were afraid to approach them a great many more of your 
<persName>acquantances </persName>you will find gon among them are <persName>Doctr Cox</persName> and <persName>counsel</persName>,
<persName>counsels wife</persName> and <persName>child</persName>. <persName>Jno Cox</persName> on the <placeName>Bernard </placeName>and a number of
others not recolected it is said there was 80 <persName>persons </persName>died at <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>
in the course of the <date n="Summer-1833">summer </date>and <placeName>Velasco </placeName>was nearly depopulated by
the cholera.</p>

<p>Since you left I wrote to <placeName>Missouri </placeName>for a <persName>Mr Alex Somervill</persName> a man
I have been acquainted with for many years and in whom I have full
confidence he come in may and <persName>Austin </persName>and him have been in
charge of the <placeName>store </placeName>since I gave him an interest as I thought it best.
<persName>Austin </persName>was at <placeName>school </placeName>most of the <date n="SUmmer-1833">summer </date>learning Spanish and says
he has improved a great deal, they have sold a good many goods as
they had the best assortment in <placeName>San Felepe</placeName> <persName>Mr S.</persName> is going in a few
days to <placeName>N O </placeName>to get a few goods to replenish <persName>Joel </persName>and <persName>Beared </persName>are
now gone to collect your cattle as it is the first oppertunity we have
had all <date n="Summer-1833">sumer </date>in concequence of the wet season the heat and the flies,<pb n="1011"/>
<persName>Col Philips</persName> has been laid up all <date n="Summer-1833">summer </date>with his sore leg. fever etc
<persName>Mrs. P.</persName> is well the last acts. "We have <persName>Mr Pilgrim</persName> Teaching here
<persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName> is going to school from his <persName>grand mothers</persName> he is a
smart boy and <persName>Mr. Pilgram</persName> says he will learn well <persName>Guy </persName><persName>Steph </persName>and
<persName>Eliza </persName>are going and as soon as <persName>Joel </persName>gets done writing some accounts I
have him to do, I will send him. <persName>Lavinia </persName>wishes to be kindly 
rememberd to you she leves for the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> in a few days, <persName>Simon </persName>is well and
has been a good boy.                                                     </p>

<p>[J. F. Perry]</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
