<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4058">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Henry Austin to Stephen F Austin, 10-20-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Henry Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-30">08-30-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brasoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 517-519
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-10-20">10-20-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Pessimistic views of Mexican government. Doubts establishment of tranquillity, and until that is done Austin must hold the helm.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Brassoria </placeName><date when="1830-10-20">Octo- 20. 1830</date></p>
<p>My dear Sir   I have recd yours by <persName>John </persName>with the enclosures and
now return the Pedimento signed.</p>

<p>I regret much that affairs have taken so unfavorable a turn at
<placeName>Saltillo </placeName>but I have witnessed so many political squables in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>
the last six years that I set them down as of but little acct, They
usually make a great deal of noise and do nothing&#8212; The result of
<persName>Viesca</persName>'s offer of resignation will probably be a reconciliation 
However I doubt much whether you can permanently hold your ground
as a <persName>member of the Legislature</persName>&#8212; The independent stand which
both your principles and interests would compell you to take would
embroil you with both <persName>parties</persName>&#8212; Still there is no other course left
you to pursue and the novelty of an upright independent public man
pursuing solely the interests of the <placeName>State </placeName>in conformity with the
constitution might make a salutary impression even upon 
<persName>Mexicans</persName>&#8212; If you can steer clear of these political broils I think they
will in the main conduce to the interests of the <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212; They
paralize the <persName>Mexican </persName>arm and put it out of the power of the Govt
to interfere with you by force&#8212; So long therefore as they abstain
from any legislative acts affecting your rights or interests in Gods
name let them wrangle amongst themselves as much as they please</p>

<p>I seriously believe that my prediction, now five years old, that
the want of <hi rend="italic">material </hi>for a stable Govt would ultimately cause the
<placeName>Mexican republic</placeName> to break up into little <placeName>principalities</placeName>, each 
Governed by a <persName>popular Chief</persName> to the extent of his personal influence and
no further, like the<placeName> malay region</placeName>, will one day be realized <persName>Don
Felipe</persName> appears to be aiming at that now and I strongly suspect
<persName>Teran </persName>looks to <placeName>Texas </placeName>for his share, Flatter him in that point and
make him believe the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> look up to him as their 
political Savior and you may do anything with him As to my own
affairs&#8212;I have visited the <placeName>junction of the two creeks</placeName> and find the
land to be good grasing land, the timber small and much of the<pb n="518"/>
<placeName>tract crawfish land</placeName>, still the position is pleasant<placeName> Flores creek</placeName> fresh
and I think the situation would be healthy-&#8212; You appear to be in
error as to the <placeName>league Survey'd for <persName>Clark</persName></placeName> it does not reach <placeName>Flores
creek&#8212;</placeName>the distance from <placeName>oyster creek</placeName> to <placeName>Flores </placeName>is 8 or 10 Miles the
<placeName>island of timber</placeName> in the centre of <placeName><persName>Clark</persName>s league</placeName> is full seven miles
this side of <placeName>Flores Creek</placeName> The land on this side <placeName>Flores Creek</placeName> is
good <placeName>praire </placeName>with a narrow skirt of timber one or two miles down
<placeName>Bastrop creek</placeName> <placeName>below the forks</placeName>.</p>

<p>Should my solicitation be granted I should like to have one league
<placeName>between Clarks survey and Flores Creek</placeName> half a league wide and
running down<placeName> Bastrop creek</placeName> for quantity.</p>

<p>I am told <placeName>Chocolate creek</placeName> comes within one league of <placeName>Austin
creek</placeName> or of <placeName>Bastrop</placeName>s somewhere <placeName>near the junction of Austin
and Flores</placeName>&#8212;and that there is plenty of timber on <placeName>Chocolate </placeName>at
that point, I should like <placeName>one league running through from creek to
creek</placeName> <hi rend="italic">just for a highway to get in timber for my <placeName>buildings </placeName></hi>For
the fourth league I should like to embrace <placeName>St Louis Island,</placeName> the
<placeName>Island </placeName>with trees on it and so much of the point of main land along
the coast as would make up a league  <hi rend="italic"> on joint acct</hi></p>

<p>This will one day be valuable for making salt for a position to
accommodate shipping, as a <placeName>fishing station</placeName> and for pasturage for
cattle which must ultimately be driven there for shipment.</p>

<p>You will say I am reckoning my chickens before they are
hatched&#8212;but I mention these things that in case the concession
should come on you may know what lands I should like to have
reserved if circumstances will permit it&#8212; I see no reason why
<persName>Viesca </persName>should not comply with his declaration to Doct Grant, but
<persName>Smith </persName>under date of<date when="1830-08-29"> August 29th</date>&#8212;says nothing of having received
any papers from <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>&#8212; the amount of his letter is that my
<placeName>buildings </placeName>remain rented at 60$ pr month without a prospect of sale
and <persName>Mr Grant</persName> writes <hi rend="italic">he hopes</hi> to send forward the proceeds of my
bar silver <hi rend="italic">shortly</hi></p>

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName>is truly a land of promise ! ! but it requires a deal of
patience to wait the performance.</p>

<p>As for the future my first object is to free myself from the 
embarassments of the steamboat concern and should my concession be
granted to come here with all the means I can command to make a
permanent location and give my best efforts to the promotion of the
interests of the <placeName>Colony</placeName>&#8212; It would however be folly for me to 
devote the remainder of my life to the occupation of a league of land</p>

<p>I must do something on an extensive scale with prospects of 
ultimate advantages of magnitude or do nothing, you and I may 
indulge our imaginations with the pleasing prospect of passing the
remainder of life in the tranquility which a snug <placeName>stock farm </placeName>appears<pb n="519"/>
to offer but neither you nor I could exist in such a State. It would
be very well to have a good <placeName>stock farm</placeName> but not to be confined to it as
a sole dependance&#8212;</p>

<p>Besides until a stable Govt be established and security for personal
rights and property placed on a firm basis there can be no 
tranquility on a farm of any sort, until this be effected you will be
compelled ex necessitate to direct the helm</p>

<p>on the subject of the <placeName>canal </placeName>project you will please inform me
when you think circumstances favorable to it in the mean time I
will collect what information I can on that subject and as to the
Live oak timber, something may grow out of it hereafter&#8212; I am
in trouble enough this morning&#8212; It was my intention to have
gone to sea to day&#8212;but the beef <persName>Bailey </persName>packd for me has spoiled
and four of my <persName>men </persName>deserted last night, which will detain me until
I can procure provisions and men it is now uncertain when I shall
get away. You will oblige me by leaving word with <persName>Mr Williams</persName>
to send all letters which may come to <placeName>Sn Felipe</placeName> for me to <persName>John
Austin</persName> who will pay the postage</p>

<p>I will write you from <placeName>Orleans </placeName>so soon as I have so arranged my
affairs as to be able to decide upon my future course in the mean
time may god bless you and enable you to bring your troublesome
enterprise to a favorable close</p>

<p>Wherever I may be you can always rely upon me in any matter
in which I can be usefull to you</p>

<p>Most Cordially and sincerely yours</p>

<p><persName>Henry Austin </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p>ps. I enclose a letter for <placeName>matamoros </placeName>which please put in the
mail if no safe private oppertunity offers&#8212;</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
