<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4124">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Asahel Langworthy  to Stephen F Austin, 01-05-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Asahel Langworthy </persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-03">09-03-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 574-576
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-01-05">01-05-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-03" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Galveston Bay &amp; Texas Land Go. Speculative interest in Texan lands. Offers to become
Austin's agent for sales in the United States. Swiss emigration.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin Esq.</persName></p>

<p>Sir, Through the kind offer of your relative <persName>Jno. P. Austin
Esq</persName> of <placeName>New York </placeName>I improve the opportunity of writing you on a<pb n="575"/>
subject, in which, I presume you are much interested, and which, of
late has become a subject of much conversation and no little degree
of excitement, I mean the Colonization of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. A <persName>company </persName>has
recently been formed in the <placeName>City of New York </placeName>to Colonize the
<placeName>grants </placeName>to <persName>Veilin</persName>, <persName>Zavala </persName>and <persName>Burnet</persName>,<placeName> adjoining, as I understood,
your Colony</placeName>&#8212; This <persName>Company</persName>, are composed of <persName>gentlemen </persName>of great
wealth and respectability who are engaged in forwarding <persName>settlers </persName>to
these <placeName>grants</placeName>. One Vessell, has already Sailed, and another will sail
this Week filled with <persName>Emigrants</persName>, principally <hi rend="italic">Swiss</hi>, with provisions,
farming utensials etc, and many other <persName>settlers </persName>will soon follow-
Indeed hundreds I think I may say some thousands <persName>settlers</persName>, would
immediately go out, if they had the means of Conveyance, and a
reasonable prospect of being able to obtain subsistance, until they
could be enabled by Cultivating the earth to procure a Comfortable
subsistence by their own labor. In the Vessell which goes this week,
several competent <persName>surveyors </persName>are going out, in order, in the first
place, to lay off the <placeName>Entire tract</placeName>, and to subdivide it to enable the
<persName>Settlers </persName>to locate themselves, permanently, on their own <placeName>Lands</placeName>, A
principal part of the <persName>Settlers</persName>, that have and are now going out, are
hired, the Conditions, except the sum to be paid, which is Sixty
Dollars pr Annum,) are contained in the printed Sheet which Í
send you. Others pay their passage, and all expences and are 
entitled to receive <placeName>177 Acres</placeName>, subject to reconvey the balance etc. as is
therein stated&#8212;</p>

<p>The price of <placeName>Texas lands</placeName> in Market varies from 5 to 10 Cents
pr Acre by large quantities and almost any amount, might be sold at
from 5. to 10. or Settled on the conditions proposed by this 
<persName>Company</persName>-&#8212; I am myself interested in those <placeName>grants </placeName>to the amount of
<placeName>1,00000 [one hundred thousand] Acres</placeName> and now think of going out,
in the course of a few days for the purpose of making a Selection
of <placeName>Lands </placeName>to locate upon, if so, I intend to Visit your <placeName>settlement </placeName>and
hope to have the pleasure of seeing you there. My particular object
in writing you at this time is to appraise you of the Value of your
Lands in Our market of the course taken by this <persName>Company </persName>and also
to say, that I should be willing to make some arrangement with you
to furnish you with <persName>Settlers</persName>, or to sell your <placeName>Lands</placeName>, as you might find
it most advantageous to you&#8212; Having for 25 years been extensively
employed in the purchase and Sale of Lands, and having formed
many acquaintance, in many of the <placeName>States</placeName>, I believe I could furnish
<persName>Settlers </persName>to almost any extent, or sell your <placeName>Lands </placeName>on as good terms
as any other person, I beg leave to refer to your <persName>relatives </persName>in <placeName>New
York</placeName> for a confirmation of what I have above stated&#8212; I should be
glad to soon hear from you on the subject&#8212;and as I may be at your
place, you will have the goodness to write me in<placeName> New York</placeName>, addressed<pb n="576"/>
to the care of <persName>Mr Austin</persName> and also to your own <placeName>village </placeName>to the care of
your <placeName>agent</placeName>. <persName>Mr Curtis</persName> one concerned in the <placeName>Galveston </placeName>purchase I
understand intends visiting the <placeName>Legislature of Texas and Coahuila
</placeName>this <date n="Winter-1830">winter</date>&#8212;you will probably see him He is a very respectable
worthy young man&#8212; He might feel a degree of Jealousy&#8212;If he
knew the Contents of my Letter, as he is much interested in the 
prosperity of their <placeName>grants</placeName>, and might fear that the sale and Settlement
of their tracts would be impeded by throwing yours into Market,</p>

<p><persName>ASAHEL LANGWORTHY</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
