<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4012">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>S Rhoads Fisher to Stephen F Austin, 08-23-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>S Rhoads Fisher</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-26">08-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Northumberland, Pennsylvania</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination"></placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 469-471
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-08-23">08-23-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Does not agree with Austin's desire to exclude slavery from Texas. The Province must draw its population from the South. Southern men will follow sugar and cotton planting, which demands slaves. Suggests free admission of slaves for five years, then rigid exclusion</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Northumberland [Pennsylvania]</placeName> <date n="008-23-1830">August 23. 1830</date></p>
<p><persName>Colonel S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>My Dear Sir I again address you in consequence of having 
received yours of <date when="1830-06-17">17th June</date>, tho, my opinion on its leading subject
has been anticipated in mine of <date when="1830-08-14">14</date> and <date when="1830-08-23">20th Insts</date>: I mean Slavery,
that you were in favour of a <persName>free population</persName> is no surprise to me,
believing that every reflecting man of equal intelligence must be so;
but I was not prepared to learn that your determination was so
decided as you have expressed it at the <hi rend="italic">present juncture</hi>&#8212; I 
conceive <persName>each member of our little <placeName>democracy</placeName></persName>, however inconspicuous
his standing, has an unquestionable right to a free expression of
opinion, in whatever relates to the policy of the <placeName>State</placeName>, and much
more of the <placeName>colony</placeName>: under this view then, I feel no hesitation in 
saying that I believe the Interests of the <placeName>Colony </placeName>will be essentially 
injured, should the course of policy,&#8212;the non admission of <persName>slaves</persName>-
mentioned in yours of <date when="1830-06-17">17th: June</date> be adopted&#8212; Most of your
<persName>Colonists </persName>are from <placeName>Slave-holding States&#8212;</placeName>they have enrolled 
themselves in your register under the firm conviction that slavery would
be tolerated, and that they would be secure in the ownership of
those brought by them &#8212;-Many others have made arrangements
with you to remove, and with an express understanding that they
could safely bring their <persName>negroes </persName>with them.</p>

<p>From your approximity to the <placeName>Southern States</placeName>, and from the
favorable feeling already pervading her <persName>citizens</persName>, <placeName>Texas </placeName>may fairly
anticipate a <persName>population </persName>from that <placeName>quarter</placeName>, more speedy and more
numerous than from the <placeName>northern </placeName>and <placeName>Eastern</placeName>, and this I conceive
is at present all important: added to which, do you believe that cane
and cotton can be grown to advantage by a sparce <persName>white population</persName>?<pb n="470"/>
or are the <placeName>whole cane and cotton growing districts </placeName>of your delightful
<placeName>country </placeName>to still remain a <placeName>wilderness </placeName>of flowers&#8212;a waste of richness ?
It is impossible! <persName>Men </persName>remove from their <placeName>Homes </placeName>to better their 
situations, they submit to deprivations and encounter difficulties for the
accumulation of wealth; and they will pursue that course of conduct
which they believe will the soonest and the most certainly put them in
possession of it&#8212; they will raise cane and cotton in preference to
wheat and oats, when they live in a country peculiarly calculated
for it, and as they cannot raise these staples without <persName>slave </persName>labour,
they will raise them with it&#8212; there is no <placeName>country </placeName>in the <placeName>world</placeName>
where these articles are grown unless by the assistance of <persName>Slaves</persName>,
or where the population is so dense or so abject as to always place at
the option of the <persName>proprietor </persName>any force commensurate to his wants&#8212;
on this half of the continent thank God I the latter cannot be the
case for centuries; therefore we must either abandon the finest portion
of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to its original uselessness or submit to the acknowledged, but
lesser evil of Slavery&#8212; In mine of <date when="1830-08-14">14th Inst</date> without being made
acquainted with your views, I stated as my opinion the expediency
of <placeName>Texas </placeName>allowing the free admission of <persName>Slaves </persName>for -<hi rend="italic">five </hi>years: this
is a short period of time, but of sufficient length to enable a <persName>Southern
emigration</persName> to introduce as many as would supply the <hi rend="italic">actual </hi>wants
of the <placeName>colony</placeName>&#8212; let the law of permission be then repealed and one
substituted, making their introduction under any pretense <hi rend="italic">highly
penal&#8212;</hi> as soon as this is the case an emigration will rapidly 
commence from the <placeName>South</placeName>, and their time having expired, the <persName>Eastern
people</persName> will in their turn view <placeName>Texas </placeName>as their <placeName>Home</placeName>&#8212; the very 
circumstance of it being measurably settled by <hi rend="italic"><persName>Southerners </persName></hi>which in
their opinions is synonimous with <hi rend="italic">wealth </hi>will act as a strong 
inducement to their coming in among us&#8212; these men will naturally seek
the <placeName>grain-growing districts</placeName>, while those from the <placeName>South </placeName>will as 
certainly settle where they can raise sugar and cotten&#8212;or suppose a
line should be drawn&#8212;say the <placeName>Opelousas road to San Felipe, thence to
Bejar</placeName>&#8212; thence, following the <placeName>Leona Vicario road till it strikes the
river Nueces</placeName> thence <placeName>following its course to the Mouth</placeName>&#8212; let the
<placeName>district of country lying between this Cordon and the gulf</placeName> be 
appropriated to <persName>Slaves</persName>, and the other side be exempted from them&#8212;
all <persName>parties </persName>would thus be suited, and each peculiar soil be brought
into requisition&#8212; But it is not now necessary to discuss the subject
at length; it is one of deep and serious interest, and should be
viewed with great deliberation, and without prejudice&#8212; were we
exclusively a <placeName>grain-growing State</placeName>, I should most strenuously 
cooperate with you in support of the non-<persName>slave </persName>holding principle;
as it is&#8212;I must see you before I decide&#8212;<pb n="471"/></p>

<p>Allow me to thank you for the passports; and here I will mention
a thing which may be all important to me&#8212;I may probably come out
in a vessel drawing full <hi rend="italic">twelve </hi>feet, having understood there was
always at least that water at <placeName>Paso Cavallo</placeName>, and sometimes more, and
that with this dft. one may readily go up to "<placeName> Dog Island</placeName> " even 
without a <persName>pilot</persName>: should my information be incorrect you will greatly
oblige me by employing<persName> Mr. Tone</persName> or some one equally qualified to
keep a look out from the <date when="1830-10-20">20 October&#8212;</date>and board any vessel which
may be standing for the Pass:</p>

<p><persName>S Rhoads Fisher</persName>&#8212;</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
