<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4162">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Amos Edwards to Stephen F Austin, 03-07-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Amos Edwards</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-08">09-08-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Col. Langworthy
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Galveston Bay on Board Schooner Angelia, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Saltillo,Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 607-609
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-03-07">03-07-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">He furnished the money which enabled Leftwich to get the grant for the Nashville Co. Asks Austin to use
influence with the governor to have the grant transferred to him.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Galveston Bay on Board Schooner Angelia</placeName></p>

<p><date when="1831-03-07"> March 7th 1831</date></p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I take this favourable opportunity of writing <persName>By Col. 
Langworthy</persName> a Gentleman of high respectability from <placeName>New York</placeName> who<pb n="608"/>
is now on his way to <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>and possibly may go as far as 
<placeName>Saltillio </placeName>and if he does will hand you this himself, otherwise will
forward it from <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>, as I have but a few minutes to write
before the departure of the vessel, must come to the subject at once
and be brief. I named to you <date n="Fall-1830">last fall </date>that I had expended 
upwards of $12000 in obtaining the <placeName>Grant </placeName>made to the <persName>Nashville 
Company</persName> and my share of the expenses since, and emigrated to this
<placeName>Country </placeName>with my large <persName>family </persName>nearly three years ago for the purpose
of aiding in colonizing sd <placeName>grant </placeName>which has cost me much more
money and as none of the <persName>Company </persName>except myself and <persName>Doctor Heard
</persName>emigrated to this <placeName>country </placeName>and they have done nothing towards 
colonizing but have sold out their shares to <persName>speculators </persName>who will probably
try to get the <placeName>Grant </placeName>for themselves exclusively and leave me to
suffer my losses, although the <placeName>Grant </placeName>never would have been obtained
for the <persName>Company </persName>had I not furnished the man and the funds. I 
advanced <persName>Leftwich </persName>$6500 previous to his departure for <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and
my <persName>brother </persName>furnished him $5000 at <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and <placeName>Saltillio </placeName>on my acct
which I have accounted with him for since, and had it not been for
these funds he could not have succeeded but must have been 
imprisoned for his expenses as the <persName>Company </persName>did not furnish him
with half enough. I therefore think and hope that if the 
<persName>Government </persName>will grant that<placeName> tract of country </placeName>to any person they will give
the preference to me who is the greatest sufferer by the enterprise
and has done everything in my power to get the <placeName>Grant </placeName>colonized,
and I must request the favor of you to be so good as to aid me in
every way in your power in obtaining a <placeName>Grant </placeName>for the <placeName>same 
boundary of land that was granted to <persName>H H. League</persName></placeName> as <persName>Empresario </persName>for
the <persName>Nashville Company</persName>, and I will engage to colonize it with one
thousand <persName>families </persName>within six years one half of whom shall be 
<persName>Europeans</persName>, and I wish the <placeName>Grant </placeName>to be upon the same conditions as
the one named, in every other respect or as near as will be consistent
with the laws of the <placeName>country</placeName>. I hope you will act as my <persName>agent </persName>in
this matter and draught and present a petition for the <placeName>grant </placeName>for
me and in my name and sign my name to it and do such other
things as is necessary in the business relative to obtaining sd grant
and this shall be your authority as fully as if I had made you a
regular power of atto. as I have not time now to make one. I have
no hesitation in saying to you that I feel confident in having the
whole number of <persName>families </persName>on the <placeName>Grant </placeName>within half the time of six
years but it is preferable to have time enough.</p>

<p>It will be of great importance to the <placeName>country </placeName>and great advantage
to your <placeName>colony </placeName>and all the <placeName>lower country</placeName> to have that section of
<placeName>country </placeName>settled as early as possible by agricultural people as they
will soon be able to supply the <placeName>lower country</placeName> with flour etc. which
we are now compelled to import from the<placeName> U. S. Of America </placeName>and it
will also be the means of driving back all the <persName>tribes of hostile Indians</persName><pb n="609"/>
who are now constantly committing some depredations on the 
<placeName>Settlements </placeName>of yours and <placeName>Dewits Colony</placeName>s. You know me personally and
my standing in the <placeName>U. S. of America </placeName>and you have seen the 
testimonials of my character which I obtained from several of the most
disinterested <persName>men </persName>in the<placeName> U. States of A</placeName>. which I would forward with
this but left them with <persName>Col. Bradburn</persName> to have them translated and
cannot now get them in time but will forward them to the <persName>Executive
of this State</persName> as early as possible. A letter from <persName>Col. Nelson Patteson
one of the Directors of the Nashville Company and secretary of the
Directory</persName> addressed to <persName>Majr Hose [a] H League</persName> will accompany this
which you will be so good as to translate and show to the <persName>Executive
and the Honble Congress</persName> which will satisfy them in what 
estimation I was held by the <persName>Directory of the Nashville Company</persName> as it
was written at their meeting just before my departure from thence
and it will prove to them that I disapproved of the conduct of my
<persName>brothers </persName>relative to the revolution at <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>&#8212;and the 
testimonials which I brought from <persName>Judge G. P. M. Bibb</persName> will prove that
I have never been in favour of insurrections which you recollect and
was good enough to translate on the back of it. I hope and trust
that the <persName>Government </persName>will remunerate me for the sum of money I
have expended about that <placeName>Grant </placeName>with the purest intentions of 
becoming serviceable to the <placeName>country </placeName>as well as my <persName>family </persName>by aiding in the
colonizing and improving of it as much as was in my power, and
grant me the <placeName>same tract of country</placeName> and I trust that you will give
me all the aid in your power to effect that object, and your friendship
and attention to the Business will be ever duly appreciated and
gratefully acknowledged by</p>

<p><persName>Amos Edwards</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] The <persName>Honble Estevan F. Austin</persName> <placeName>Saltillio</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
