<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4321">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>S Rhoads Fisher to Stephen F Austin, 02-02-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>S Rhoads Fisher</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-19">09-19-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Matagorda, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 746
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-02-02">02-02-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-19" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Difficulties of getting settled.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Matagorda </placeName><date when="1832-02-02">Feby. 2 1832</date></p>
<p><persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>My dear Sir&#8212;I have just received your favour of <date when="1832-01-28">28 ulto</date>: by <persName>Mr,
Jaques</persName> and hasten to reply to&#8212; <persName>Mr. Lesassier </persName>writes me he has not
been able to make collections, but assigns no other reason than the
indisposition of<persName> Mr. Johnson.</persName> It is to me a most unpleasant thing
to write you on a subject in which you have no interest, as it has
the appearance of importunity; but could you feel the inconvenience
and unpleasant situation in which I am plared for the want of a few
hundred Dollars, you would I am convinced excuse it. Arriving
with a <persName>family </persName>in a new <placeName>country</placeName>, you are aware that it is one 
continued expense, and without some means it is impossible to get along;
in my last settlement with our friend <persName>Lesassier</persName>, in consequence of
his being disappointed in some funds, I consented to his retaining
about $100 after he had collected it, with a full promise he would
amply supply me on my arrival in this <placeName>country</placeName>. I mention this to
you in confidence; not to induce any unfavorable impression on your
mind toward <persName>Lesassier</persName>, but to show you I have been placed in my
present situation not from any neglect or want of foresight on my
part. I am sorry your arrangement for <placeName>land </placeName>has failed; and as I
have yet the privilege of locating one <placeName>league</placeName>, you would oblige me
by permitting the title to be made for <placeName>the one adjoining mine on
Peyton's Creek</placeName> originally taken by <persName>Col: Wallace.</persName></p>

<p>Be good enough to inform me, if there bp any other court of
record in your jurisdiction, than that of <placeName>San Felipe</placeName>, also if I cannot
settle upon my <persName>wife </persName>her furniture which belongs to her and a House
and lot I intend to erect, I want to secure to her at least a <placeName>shelter</placeName>,
and Household utensils. Also the mode of doing so. Your advice
upon these subjects will materially serve me. I send by <persName>Mr: Jaques
</persName>a letter, <placeName>maps </placeName>and a bundle of <placeName>newspapers </placeName>for you. In my last letter
I wrote for a power of attorney to vote on your <placeName>Matagorda property</placeName>
and now remention it, lest the other may not reach you. Nothing
but the utter impracticability of my leaving here prevents me seeing
you; but if it could by any possible means suit you to take <placeName>Matagorda</placeName>
in your way to <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>I need not say how much sincere pleasure it
would give me; for independent of my personal feelings I want to
know something of our political relations. Accept thanks of <persName>Mrs:
Fisher</persName> who I am pleased to say has recovered for your remembrances,
and accept of hers in return. She begs me to say she would be much
pleased to see a <persName>gentleman </persName>of whom she has heard so much in her
<placeName>little cabin</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>S. Rhoads Fisher</persName></p>

<p>Be pleased to tender my best regards to<persName> Mr: Williams and family.</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
