<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4585">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Central Committee, 07-24-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-29">11-29-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Central Committee
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">City of Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 988-991
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-07-24">07-24-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-29" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reporting incidents of journey. Officials friendly and he hopes for success. Advises organization of State government if petition is denied.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>City of Mexico</placeName>, <date when="1833-07-24">July 24, 1833</date>.</p>
<p>To the <persName>Central Committee</persName>:</p>

<p>My letter from <placeName>Vera-Cruz</placeName>, dated <date when="1833-07-03">3d instant</date>, informed you of the
many untoward circumstances that retarded my journey to that
place. When I wrote from <placeName>Matamoras</placeName>, on the <date when="1833-05-30">30th May</date>, I expected
to have reached <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> in Six days, and this place in six or seven
more, I left <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> on the <date when="1833-07-05">5th </date>in the stage, and arrived at
<placeName>Jalapa </placeName>on the <date when="1833-05-06">6th</date>, where I received information of the siege of
<placeName>Puebla </placeName>by <persName>Arista </persName>and <persName>Duran</persName>&#8212;-and that the road was occupied on
both sides of the city of <placeName>Puebla </placeName>by their <persName>troops</persName>, and all 
communication with <placeName>Mexico </placeName>cut off. On the <date when="1833-07-08">8th </date>I was told that the stage was
allowed to pass the lines, though the danger of <persName>robbers </persName>was great&#8212;
and I intended to have proceeded in the stage on the <date when="1833-07-09">9th</date>,   But on<pb n="989"/>
that day a new and unexpected difficulty arose&#8212;my passport was
from the <persName>Commandant General, D. Vincente Filisola</persName>, and it was
therefore necessary to present myself to the <persName>military authorities</persName> <placeName>on
the road.</placeName> At <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> I called twice (on the <date when="1833-07-02">2d</date>, the day I landed,
and on the <date when="1833-07-03">3d</date>) on the <persName>Commandant General</persName> of that place, and
exhibited my passport. He told me verbally I could proceed on my
journey, but did not endorse my passport. Owing to the want of
this formality, I was detained at <placeName>Jalapa </placeName>by the <persName>commandant</persName>, and
could not proceed until I sent to <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, so that I did not reach
this place until the <date when="1833-07-18">18th inst</date>. <placeName>Puebla </placeName>was heroically defended by
<persName>Gen. Guadalupe Victoria</persName>, with the <persName>militia </persName>of the <placeName>city</placeName>, hastily 
collected for the purpose. The <persName>regular troops</persName> had all gone over to the
other side previously, and left <persName>Victoria </persName>without any resources except
the patriotism of the <persName>people of <placeName>Puebla</placeName></persName>. With the <persName>militia </persName>he defeated
<persName>Arista </persName>and <persName>Duran </persName>in their attempt to get possession of the <placeName>city</placeName>; and
they retreated to the vicinity of this <placeName>city</placeName>. They are now <placeName>within
four leagues</placeName>, on the retreat, in the direction of <placeName>Queretaro</placeName>. <persName>Santa
Anna </persName>is in close pursuit of them, and no doubt is entertained of a
speedy termination of the <persName>crusaders </persName>and the final triumph of the
<persName>liberal party</persName>. I presume you have seen the Plan of <persName>Arista and
Duran</persName>&#8212;its basis is Religeon and a large standing <persName>Army</persName>. They will
fail in toto, and the result will be another triumph for <persName>Santa Anna
</persName>and a complete dissolution of the <persName>aristocratic party</persName> and influence.</p>

<p>I called on the <persName>Ministers </persName>on the <date when="1833-07-19">19th</date>, and they appointed the
<date when="1833-07-23">23d </date>(yesterday) to have an interview on the subject of my mission.
I also called on the <persName>Vice-President</persName>; my reception was truly kind
and friendly, particularly in the interview yesterday with the <persName>two
Ministers of Relations and Justice, Garcia and Arispe</persName>. They were
fully informed of the objects of my Mission by my communication
from <placeName>Matamoras </placeName>through the <persName>Commandant Gen</persName>. and had received
the memorial of the Convention which I forwarded from that place.
I explained at large and with some detail the situation of <placeName>Texas</placeName>
and the necessity of erecting it into a <placeName>State</placeName>. The leading points on
which I rested our claims were:</p>

<p>First&#8212;The wish of the <persName>people </persName>and their declaration that they
possessed the necessary elements to sustain a <persName>State Government</persName>.</p>

<p>Second&#8212;The natural right of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to occupy its station alongside
of its sisters, the other <placeName>States of the Confederation</placeName>. It has always
been a distinct <placeName>member of the Mexican family</placeName> and as such fought
for the Independence, etc., and its being for a time under age did
not in any manner weaken its rights now that it was in a situation
to enter upon them, etc.</p>

<p>Third&#8212;The law of the <date when="1824-05-07">7th May, 1824</date>. I positively denied the
right of <placeName>Coahuila </placeName>to approve or disapprove of our separation.<pb n="990"/>
also stated that <placeName>Texas </placeName>did not, and would not, recognize the principle
that it was necessary to apply to the other <placeName>states </placeName>of the 
<placeName>confederation </placeName>for their approbation. We were now entering upon a natural
and imprescriptable right, which belonged to us before the formation
of the Constitution, and one which the provisional union with
<placeName>Coahuila </placeName>did not, and could not, weaken in any manner whatever, etc.</p>

<p>Fourth&#8212;The duty and the interest of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to cement and
strengthen its union with the <placeName>Mexican confederation</placeName>&#8212;the indirect
union as an appendage of <placeName>Coahuila </placeName>being very precarious, and liable
to be broken at any time.</p>

<p>Lastly&#8212;The right and the duty of every <persName>people </persName>to save 
themselves from anarchy and ruin! On this last point I enlarged very
much, as I also did on the 4th. I distinctly stated as my opinion
that self-preservation would compel the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> to organize
a <persName>local government</persName>, with or without the approbation of the <persName>General
Government</persName>&#8212;that this measure would not proceed from any hostle
views to the permanent union of <placeName>Texas </placeName>with <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, but from 
absolute necessity, to save themselves from anarchy and total ruin. How
such a measure would affect the union of <placeName>Texas </placeName>with <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, or
where it would end, were matters worthy of serious reflection.</p>

<p>I will give the answer of the two <persName>Ministers</persName>, <persName>Garcia </persName>and <persName>Arispe</persName>,
as nearly verbatim as I can recollect. I do not pledge myself for
the accuracy of the words, but I do for that of the substance:</p>

<p>This <persName>Government </persName>will examine the pretensions of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to become a <placeName>State
of this Confederation</placeName>, with the most friendly disposition towards the <persName>people
of that <placeName>remote section</placeName></persName>, and in conformity with the broad and liberal 
principles of the federal system, adopted by the <placeName>Mexican Republic</placeName>, We wish to
see every portion of the <placeName>confederation </placeName>governed in accordance with these
principles, and of those of the age in which we live. We admit that <placeName>Texas</placeName>
has just cause to complain of the <persName>Legislature of <placeName>Coahuila</placeName></persName>, The <persName>people of
<placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> may therefore expect that their application will be considered, and
their just requests granted, so far as it is within The Constitutional powers
of the <persName>Government </persName>to grant them.</p>

<p>The interview was long, and frank. I was requested to put my
ideas in writing. They are pretty much all embraced in the
Memorial, but I thought it would be better to condense them under
separate heads or points.</p>

<p>So soon as I get the Constitution translated and a new translation
of the Memorial (the first being defective) I will lay the whole
matter before the <persName>Government</persName>.</p>

<p>I believe that <placeName>Texas </placeName>will be a <placeName>State of this Confederation</placeName> with
the approbation of this <persName>Government </persName>before long. I form this
opinion from the information of many persons of influence, all of
whom confirm the friendly disposition expressed by the <persName>Ministers</persName>.
Should I be incorrect in this conclusion there will be but one course,<pb n="991"/>
one remedy left, and that is for <placeName>Texas </placeName>to adopt the alternative I
informed the <persName>Ministers </persName>self preservation would compel it to adopt.
The <persName>people </persName>therefore must organize without any more applications
or delay.</p>

<p>It is pretty well known in <placeName>Texas </placeName>that I have pursued conciliation
as a system; some think I have adhered to it too long, and too
obstinately. I do not think so, placed under the circumstances I
was. However, this is a mere matter of opinion and is of no 
consequence. My conciliatory course has not compromised any of the
rights of <placeName>Texas</placeName>; on the contrary, it has settled that <placeName>country</placeName>, and in
times past saved it from many evils. Clamors and importunities
could not force me from my old rule. You ought, therefore, to
believe that my judgment is now convinced that <placeName>Texas</placeName>, in this
question of right to become a <placeName>State</placeName>, must be uncompromising. I
am placed in a situation here to form a more correct opinion as to
what course will be best calculated to secure the prosperity of <placeName>Texas</placeName>,
and its permanent union with <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, than I was in that remote
section.</p>

<p>I therefore reiterate the opinion, and I place it on the footing of
a recommendation, that should our application be refused, <placeName>Texas</placeName>
ought to organize a <persName>local government</persName> with as little delay as 
possible&#8212;but always on the basis that it is a part of the <placeName>Mexican
Confederation</placeName>, a younger sister who adopts this mode of entering
upon her rights, now that she is of age, because unnecessary 
embarrassments are interposed which are unconstitutional, unjust,
inexpedient and ruinous.</p>

<p>I also recommend tranquillity and obedience to the laws&#8212;these
are the first duties of a <persName>citizen</persName>. Wait for a definite answer. The
moment I get one, or am convinced that delay is the object, I will
leave here and hasten <placeName>home </placeName>to unite in executing the 
recommendations I have made.</p>

<p>Your Fellow-Citizen and Obedient Servant.</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
