<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4130">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 01-09-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-05">09-05-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monclova, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 581-583
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-01-09">01-09-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-05" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Political news, instructions about locating land for Mexican officials.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Monclova </placeName><date when="1831-01-09">Jany 9 1831</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>I arrived here <date when="1831-01-08">yesterday </date>sin novedad, and shall leave in the 
<date when="1831-01-10">morning</date>. <persName>Dn Victor Blanco</persName> recd me in his <placeName>home </placeName>with great friendship
and attention&#8212;he has truly an amiable and interesting <persName>family</persName>. I
wrote you by <persName>Madero </persName>that <persName>Dn Victor</persName> would appoint you his <persName>agent </persName>to
select his <placeName>land</placeName>&#8212;by this mail he will send you a power of attorney
to act as his <persName>agent</persName>, and also as the <persName>agent </persName>of many <persName>others</persName>. I most
particularly request that you will try and make good selections for<pb n="582"/>
<persName>Dn Victor</persName>, lie wants the most of his <placeName>land on the Trinity</placeName> low down
or on <placeName>San Jacinto</placeName>. This <persName>gentleman </persName>is a very warm and sincere
<persName>friend </persName>and I hope you will spare no pains to get good selections
for him</p>

<p>The accounts given to me here by <persName>Dn Victor</persName>, <persName>Tijerina </persName>and <persName>others</persName>,
as to the general aspect of political affairs, amount in substance to
this&#8212;-that the present <persName>administration </persName>have all the effective portion
of the <persName>Army </persName>and all the <persName>Legislatures </persName>and <persName>Governors </persName>of all the <placeName>States</placeName>
in their favor, and most of the Talents and wealth of the nation.
They are of opinion that the present <persName>Govt</persName>, will sustain itself and
that <persName>Guerrero </persName>must soon be put down entirely. <persName>Dn Victor</persName> and <persName>others</persName>
here, think that this <persName>administration </persName>is not hostile to <placeName>North American</placeName>
emigration to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and that the present restrictions will be 
removed before this year concludes. They all say that my <placeName>Colony</placeName>
stands very high with the Govt, both in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and in <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>. The
answer of our <persName>Ayto </persName>to that of <placeName>Leona Vicario</placeName> has given general
satisfaction to all intelligent and reflecting men and has raised our
character more than you have any idea of. The <persName>Senate </persName>has 
approved of <persName>Carrillo</persName>'s credentials as Senator, <hi rend="italic">unanimously </hi>, not one
vote in favor of the Jalapising System proposed by the <persName>Saltilleros</persName>.</p>

<p>In <placeName>Rio Grande</placeName> and in this <placeName>place </placeName>(the only <placeName>towns </placeName>I have passed
through) I have been treated with more attention and respect than
I had any reason to expect. The opinion here is that <persName>Teran </persName>will
not go to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, he that he will proceed to <placeName>Texas </placeName>in a short time.
The <persName>enemies </persName>to <placeName>North American</placeName> emigration are beginning to suspect
that he is more friendly to them than they wish etc. etc. I give
these ideas as I have recd them. You see that they differ very much
from those intertained in <placeName>Bexar</placeName>. When I get to <placeName>headquarters </placeName>I
shall be able to form some certain opinion on these subjects, in the
meantime it is best to pursue a prudent and silent course as to all
matters of politics.</p>

<p>The <placeName>town at the crossing of the upper road on the Colorado</placeName> is yet
to name. I wish you would request <persName>Arciniega </persName>not to name it until
he hears from me on the subject.</p>

<p>My <persName>colleague Padre Murquis</persName> passed here on the <date when="1831-01-08">8d of this month</date>,
I am told he intends to ask leave to resign, but <persName>Dn Victor</persName> thinks that
it was under a belief that I would not come on.</p>

<p>Try and get the<placeName> coast colony</placeName> out of the way, before <persName>Arciniega </persName>gets
there so that you may have nothing to interfere with the other
business.</p>

<p>The <placeName>mountains round this place</placeName> are white with snow and ice and
the weather very cold and wet&#8212;my health is good.    The horses stand<pb n="583"/>
the journey very well&#8212;corn in this place is only 75 cents to a dollar
the fanega I again recommend <placeName><persName>Dn Victor</persName>'s land</placeName> matter to you 
particularly&#8212;that is, his <hi rend="italic">own claims</hi> the others are for his <persName>friends </persName>and
are of secondary consideration in comparison with his, for they want
the <placeName>land </placeName>for speculation&#8212;he wants it for his <persName>family</persName>, he has ten
<persName>children</persName>, and a more promising <persName>family </persName>I have never seen,
remember me to<persName> Mrs. Sweet</persName> and <persName>Sarah</persName></p>

<p><persName>S F Austin </persName>   [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
