<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4509">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>W S Parrott to Stephen F Austin, 01-16-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>W S Parrott</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-09">11-09-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin(
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 914
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-01-16">01-16-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Mexican politics. Interest in remaining restrictions on immigration into Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mexico</placeName>. <date when="1833-01-16">Jany 16th 1833</date>.</p>
<p><persName>S. F Austin Esq</persName>.</p>

<p>My Dear Sir, Your welcome favour of the <date when="1832-11-12">12th Nov.</date> came to
hand last week, it was no doubt delayed owing to the Suspension
and disorder of our mail arrangements; I regret that my time is so
much taken up at this moment as to deprive me of the pleasure I
would have in replying fully to your interesting letter, but as our
correspondence will become more regular in future, I will find
leisure to enter upon details. <persName>Chambers </persName>I consider has treated me
ill not having replied to any of my letters Since he received his
books; nor has he paid even to my <persName>correspondents in <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName></persName> their
value as he promised to do when he gave the order. With the plan
of <placeName>zavaleta</placeName>, hostilities have ceased; but the amalgam I fear will, not
give us a permanent peace; all appears to be quiet but not solid;
Some of the <placeName>States</placeName>, will not Subscribe to the plan, others have;
<persName>Genl. Pedraza</persName> is however of opinion, that all will go right; my
opinion is that the <date when="1833-04-04">4th of april next</date> will not pass by without, a
noise In relation to the 11th Arto, of the law of the <date when="1830-04-06">6th of april
1830</date>; there are thousands here who are interested in its repeal
Strong remonstrances will therefore be made; and the <persName>Executive </persName>is
Strongly indisposed against the Said law, and in order to prepare
the way for its repeal I will manouvre with the <placeName>liberal presses</placeName>, and
if I have time will translate and have published, Some paragraphs
of your letter, as written by a <hi rend="italic">Texano</hi>. I Sometimes dabble in 
politics; but my commercial occupations rarely give me time to think
of any thing else but <hi rend="italic">business </hi>While you remain in the <placeName>country</placeName>,
write me and When in the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> I hope to hear from you; I will
Send you Some of the most interesting Numbers of the Phoenix.
The <placeName><hi rend="italic">Registro </hi></placeName>is dead; The <persName>friends of the constitution</persName> are trying to
revive it.</p>

<p><persName>W. S. Parrott</persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>(P. S.) <persName>Genl Mexia</persName> Sends you his remembrance We will work
together for the repeal of the law in question. <persName>Genl. Filasola</persName> goes
to <placeName>Texas </placeName>as <persName>comandant gral</persName>. he is interested in the peopling of
<placeName>Texas </placeName>He has a <placeName>grant near the red river</placeName> abot which we have had
several conversations He will go to <placeName>Matamoras </placeName>by land from thence
by water to <placeName>Matagorda </placeName>and <placeName>Galveston</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
