<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4458">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John P Austin to Stephen F Austin, 10-25-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John P Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-10-29">10-29-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 880-881
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-10-25">10-25-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-10-29" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Galveston Bay &amp; Texas Land Co.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New York </placeName><date when="1832-10-25">Oct. 25. 1832</date></p>
<p>My dear <persName>Cousin</persName>,</p>

<p>I am in receipt of your kind letters of the <date when="1832-07-04">4th of July</date>&#8212;-from 
<placeName>Matamoras</placeName>&#8212;and <date when="1832-07-29">29th July</date>, via <placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>. The latter when 
confined to my bed by a severe attack, of a derangement of the Liver
and Bowels, from which I trust I have recovered except my Strength,
which is fast returning, It kept me housed several weeks, so that
I may say for <date n="08-xx-1832">two Months past</date> I have been out the way of news.
I have however enclosed<persName> brother Henry </persName>a letter from friend <persName>Treat</persName>,
giving all the news that has transpired for some time past, both in
regard to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and <placeName>Texas</placeName>, thus far very favourable, as we have
every reason to believe the result will be. I have therefore only to
refer you to <placeName>Henry </placeName>who will with pleasure Communicate it to you&#8212;
<persName>Genl. Mason</persName>, whom I am told reports very favorably of his Mission
to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>is now here, and the <persName>Trustees to the Galveston Bay Compy</persName>,<pb n="881"/>
are only waiting the arrival of one of their <persName>members</persName>, <persName>Mr. Sumner</persName>
hourly expected from <placeName>Boston</placeName>, to have a meeting to determine upon
future operations, the result of which, I was in hopes to have 
obtained in time for this letter, but find will have to defer it for my next,
as I find the vessel is to sail in an hours time. From the latest 
advises from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, <persName>Santa Anna</persName>'s success is now looked upon as 
Certain&#8212;by the best informed here, so desirable for your <placeName>Colony </placeName>as
well as all <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and more particularly the former, since the late
movements there, which I was happy to learn terminated so 
fortunately&#8212;I thank you for the <placeName>Pamphlet</placeName>, which reached me from
<placeName>Mobile</placeName>, giving the details and very satisfactory they must be to
all unbiased minds. I hope to get it republished here, in which
Case will have the article put in form agreeably to the ideas 
Suggested in your letter and appended. That part of your letter
from <placeName>Matamoras</placeName>&#8212;which you Suggested, I had published, as you will
have seen by the <placeName>paper </placeName>Sent you at the time. I got a letter <date when="1832-10-18">last week</date>
from <persName>brother Henry</persName> giving the painful news of the affliction of his
<persName>family</persName>, in the death of his <persName>wife</persName>. It is a severe trial for him and I
fear much for his own health, but trust he will bear up under it
with usual fortitude, when he reflects upon the Situation of his
<persName>Children</persName>, and not suffer himself to be unnecessarily exposed. I
know he has a kind <persName>friend </persName>in you and that there will be nothing
wanting on your part to Comfort him&#8212; I am told his location <placeName>on
the river</placeName> is a very unhealthy one, and fear there is too much truth
in it. I send him a file of <placeName>papers</placeName>, which are equally at your Service.
I must Close this Scrawl or be too late It goes pr Schr. Sabine <persName>Capt.
Brown</persName>-&#8212;She has 16 to 18 passengers. I hope soon to be in receipt
of late dates from you&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>J. P. Austin</persName></p>
<p><persName>Col Stephen F. Austin</persName>   <placeName>San Felipe de Austin   Texas</placeName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
