<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4233">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Archibald Austin to Stephen F Austin, 06-30-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Archibald Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-12">09-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 669-671
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-06-30">06-30-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Sending dimensions for sawing live oak for shipbuilders.  Wishes to get land in Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New York </placeName><date when="1831-06-30">30 June 1831</date>.</p>
<p>Dear <persName>Cousin</persName>,</p>

<p>I hope my letter acknowledgeing receipt of yours of <date when="1831-03-17">17 March last</date>
has reached you ere this, in which I inclosed some directions recd
from <persName>Mr Burgh</persName>, one of our <persName>principal Ship Carpenters</persName>, relative to
the proper dimensions in which live Oak should be cut, to answer in
our <placeName>Ship yards</placeName>, for fear that letter may have miscarried, I inclose
a copy of it, as there is I understand<placeName> on the banks of the Brazos</placeName>, a
large quantity of that valuable wood, all the information that can be
obtained from such a man as <persName>Burgh</persName>, must I presume be of 
consequence.</p>

<p>In my letter alluded to above I signified my desire to become a
<persName>landholder </persName>in your <placeName>Colony</placeName>, if it could be done without interfering
with your plans or views, say the usual quantity allowed to a man<pb n="670"/>
with a <persName>family </persName>if practicable, I should like to have it in a healthy
situation, to have some part of it extend to the <placeName>river</placeName>. <persName>Henry </persName>writes
me that he will be situated near <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>that is so near the <placeName>Gulph</placeName>,
that I should think it must be unhealthy, in many other respects I
should consider it preferable, particularly for commercial operations,
perhaps a situation<placeName> on the Border of Galveston Bay</placeName>, may be more
preferable for those purposes being easier I believe of access for 
vessels, and more <placeName>contiguos to the United States</placeName>, but my impression is
that there is a good deal of <placeName>low marshy ground</placeName> in that vicinity, 
besides the <persName>Galveston Bay Company</persName> appear to have arrogated to 
themselves, <placeName>the whole of that Bay</placeName>, which might subject a body to some
restrictions that would not be altogether agreeable&#8212;it puts me in
mind of the <placeName>State of New York</placeName> claiming jurisdiction over all the
<placeName>navigable waters on the Jersey shore</placeName>, <placeName>this side of that state</placeName>.</p>

<p>To have some of that valuable live oak included in my <placeName>farm</placeName>, would
be very desirable as that must become very important sooner or later,
but I presume that is out of the question, for if I mistake not it is all
disposed of in another way. I should like to locate somewhere in
your <placeName>neighborhood</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Henry </persName>writes me from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> that he would inform me,
when an oppy offered in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, by which I might get a living, it
would be strange if that oppy does not soon offer, in a <placeName>Country </placeName>that
was so recently in Embryo, now possessing thousands of <persName>Inhabitants</persName>,
and a rush of population, setting that way unpresidented, of such a
variety of character and diversity of occupations, and represented to
possess so many superior advantages over any part of <placeName>North America</placeName>,
that I cannot but flatter myself, that I may benefit by a removal to it.</p>

<p>I should like some occupation when there, by way of variety and
relief from the toils of the plough, a reasonable proportion of the
time; as not having been in the habit for many years past of wielding
any instrument in the way of labour, more weighty than a Goose
quill, I fear my hands are too tender to follow the plough and hew
timber for a constancy, practice may bring them to a proper 
consistency.</p>

<p>I saw a letter <date when="1831-06-29">last evening</date> from one of the <persName>agents of the G. B. C°</persName>,
dated <date n="04-xx-1831">last April </date>in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, in which he speaks of the <placeName>country </placeName>on the
<placeName>Trinity </placeName>being very fine, but observes that it is superior <placeName>on the border
of the Brazos</placeName>, a good deal for them to allow.</p>

<p>As you calculated to be back in <date n="05-xx-1831">May</date>, I am flatering myself with
the pleasure of a letter soon announcing your safe return, if you
take the <placeName>Leag of Land</placeName> for me, let me know what the amount of 
expenses are as they accrue that I may remit the same, I think the time
is six years before the whole amount becomes due, a pretty long credit
however I suppose that depends on circumstances. I hope to be
with you <date n="xx-xx-1832">within the year from the date</date>, cannot go immediately.<pb n="671"/>
should like to be here when you make your visit this way, but do not
think you will be able to accomplish it, for several years yet.</p>

<p>The <persName>European powers</persName> are striving hard to prevent a general war
on the <placeName>continent</placeName>, and it looks at present as if they wood succeed
but it yet remains doubtful. The <persName>Poles </persName>fight desperately but must
be overpowered and subdued by the <persName>Russians </persName>unless assisted by some
<persName>European </persName>power, of which there appears no indication at present.
The <persName>Genl </persName>who went to <placeName>Spain </placeName>from the<persName> Mexican Government</persName> for the
purpose of forming, or proposing a Treaty between the two 
<placeName>countries </placeName>had had an interview with the <persName>King</persName>, and by the last accounts
taken his passage at <placeName>Bordeaux </placeName>for <placeName>Vera Vruz</placeName>, where it is supposed
he is about this time, with the <persName>King</persName>s answer, and terms, on which
he is willing to accede to, to lay before his <persName>Govt </persName>which are thought to
be so favorable that a Treaty will soon be concluded. I understand
that it is probable one of the<placeName> Ports of Mexico</placeName> will be declared a <placeName>free
port</placeName> ere long. Please remember me particularly to <persName>Mr. and Mrs.
Perry </persName>who I presume are with you. I hope to receive a letter from
you soon telling me you returned safe in <date n="05-xx-1831">May last</date>, and your health
much improved.</p>

<p><persName>Arch Austin</persName>   [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName> Colo S. F. Austin</persName>, <placeName>San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
