<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4622">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Peter and Joseph Powell, 01-22-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-03">12-03-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Peter 
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Joseph Powell
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monterrey, Nuevo Leon</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1043-1044
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-01-22">01-22-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-03" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Discussing his arrest and advising quiet in Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Monterrey</placeName>, <date when="1834-01-18">Jany. 18, 1834.</date></p>
<p>To <persName>Peter Powell</persName> and <persName>Joseph Powell</persName>.</p>

<p>Dr Sirs, <persName>Mr. Allsbury</persName> has informed that you are at <placeName>Pilon</placeName>, and
have heard of my arrest. I am arrested by an order of the <persName>Minister
of War</persName> to answer an accusation made, as I understand, by the <persName>State
Government</persName>, on account of my having written to the <persName>Ayuntamiento
of <placeName>Bexar </placeName></persName>recommending that all the <persName>ayuntamientos of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> should
consult together as to what ought to be done in the event no remedies
could be obtained for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and also in the event that the <persName>Arista</persName>
or <persName>military party</persName> should succeed, it being somewhat doubtful at
that time <date when="1833-10-02">(2nd of October)</date>, how the civil war would terminate.</p>

<p>The <persName>genl. govt</persName>, could do no otherwise than order me back to
<placeName>Mexicon</placeName>, to answer to this accusation, coming as it did from the
<persName>state</persName>, neither could the<persName> state govt</persName>, very well have avoided making
the accusation&#8212;so do not blame either of them in any manner.</p>

<p>It was my duty, as an <persName>agent</persName>, acting under the instructions I had
to write as I did under the circumstances.</p>

<p>The fact is that the revolutions since the plan of <placeName>Jalapa</placeName>, have
kept everything so disjointed and so confused all over the <placeName>nation</placeName>,
that no man who has had anything to do with public business, could
avoid being entangled in some way. It was always my wish, as is
well known in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, to keep the <placeName>colony </placeName>and that whole <placeName>country </placeName>out
of the revolution, but it was impossible. All the measures of the
<persName>Bustamante administration</persName> tended to ruin <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and subject it to a
<persName>military govt</persName>. This irritated the <persName>people </persName>so much that they could
not be restrained. They had sufficient cause to oppose military
usurpation, but I wished them to keep out of that revolution for
it was not absolutely necessary.</p>

<p>The <persName>military </persName>would have gone away of themselves in a short time.
Since then all has been unsettled everywhere and I have been drawn
into the whirlpool, unavoidable.   It could not be helped.</p>

<p>The disposition of the <persName>genl. govt</persName>, toward <placeName>Texas </placeName>is in the highest
degree favorable and friendly and everything will be done for that
country that can be consistent with the constitution and laws. It
would be made a <placeName>state </placeName>or a <placeName>territory </placeName>without delay if it was asked
for by the <persName>ayuntamientos </persName>unanimously, but there must be no more
conventions and no more wild excitements. The <persName>people </persName>must keep
quiet, obey the state <persName>authorities </persName>and law, harmonise fully with <placeName>Bexar</placeName>
and <placeName>Goliad </placeName>and with the <persName>Mexican population</persName>, discountenance all<pb n="1044"/>
<persName>violent men</persName> or measures and speak to the <persName>govt</persName>, through, the legal
channels, that is the <persName>ayuntamientos </persName>and <persName>chief of department</persName>, as they
would speak to a kind and affectionate <persName>father</persName>, and they will then be
listened to and all their reasonable requests will be granted.</p>

<p>I hope there will be no excitement about my arrest, and I 
particularly request that on your return, you will say that I request of
the people there to remain quiet, and not be excited because I am
arrested. No injustice or violence will be done me, I have been
very kindly and respectfully treated since my arrest. It may cost
me some months and perhaps a year delay and great expense but
nothing more, and good will finally come out of it for <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>God knows the <placeName>Colony </placeName>has given me trouble enough. I am wasting
away my years, my strength and my spirit to try and make all your
fortunes. I have no time of my own, it is all yours, and yet many
of you (I speak of the <persName>colonists</persName>) complain&#8212;you lissen to men who
are my <persName>enemies</persName>. If you think I do wrong in anything it is 
unpardonable and magnified, you get perversed and excited and violent
and drag me into difficulties in spite of myself these things however
are all inevitable. Upon the whole my <placeName>Colony </placeName>has suffered much
less from party spirit and division than most <placeName>new settlements</placeName> under
such circumstances, and it is now entirely safe. The <persName>govt</persName>, is in
favor of <placeName>Texas </placeName>and will protect it, and the <persName>people </persName>are beginning to
have too much property and too many comforts at <placeName>home </placeName>to risk
them by any more conventions or excitements. I think things will
now get better and better every day, and that consideration and
reason will have more weight than they heretofore have had. If so
there will be peace, and prosperity. I particularly request that you
will say to the <persName>people </persName>that I advise them to harmonise fully with
the <persName>Mexican part of the population</persName>.   This is very important indeed.</p>

<p>Remember me kindly to everybody. I am as I always have been
and will be a friend to <placeName>Texas </placeName>and to you all.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
