<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4864">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>F. W. Johnson to Stephen F. Austin, 09-05-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>F. W. Johnson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-03-11">03-11-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Mouth of the Brazos, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 114-115
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-09-05">09-05-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-03-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Considers Austin's return opportune. Unity necessary for safety of Texas and Austin alone can, effect it. Invites him to meeting at San Felipe September 12. Note by Gail Borden, Jr</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1835-09-05">5th Sept. 1835</date></p>

<p><persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName>,</p>
<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p>It is with feelings inexpressible that I write you this, Your return has
been long wished for, but little expected at this time, but the God of Nature
seems to have arranged all things better than even men could have desired&#8212;
Your coming would always have been hailed by the <persName>people </persName>as the coming
of a <persName>father</persName>, but your coming at this time is doubly dear to the <persName>people of
all <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>&#8212; Never was there a time in the events of <placeName>Texas </placeName>that so much
required the joint action of the people as the present&#8212; Union of 
sentiment and action is the one thing alone can save the country from the 
impending danger that now hangs over our heads&#8212; Unfortunately for
<placeName>Texas </placeName>at this time as on former occasions the people have been governed
by sectional feeling, they mistake an imaginary for real interest, but I am
proud to say that this interest or feeling only exists in the<placeName> municipality of
Austin.</placeName></p>

<p>I have but a few days since returned to this place from a tour through
the <placeName>department of Nacogdoches</placeName> where the <persName>people </persName>are united and determined
to sustain their constitutional rights against the usurpations attemped by
<persName>Santa Anna and his party</persName>&#8212; Meetings have been held at <placeName>Liberty </placeName><placeName>San
Augustine</placeName> and <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>, at all of which places they have resolved that<pb n="115"/>
a convention of all <placeName>Texas </placeName>by means of <persName>representatives </persName>were necessary to
the security and harmony of the country&#8212; <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>Matagorda</placeName>, <placeName>San
Jacinto</placeName>, <placeName>Lavaca </placeName>and other places of this <persName>department </persName>have sent in their
resolutions in favor of a convention and indeed there is no opposition except
in this <placeName>jurisdiction </placeName>and that I look upon to be of but little consequence
other than the injury that it may do <placeName>abroad</placeName>, it can have no influence in
any part of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, for were I disposed to enter into matters personal I
could satisfy any <persName>rational man</persName> that it has been of service rather than injury,
but at a time like this none should indulge in personal feeling, but on
the contrary use every means to unite and harmonize&#8212; Our interest is a
joint and common one and should be so regarded&#8212; The question as
regards the call of a convention is settled, and all former opposition has
given way except in this place and but for this and the necessity of union
of sentiment and action I would not make the call upon you that I feel
bound under existing circumstances&#8212; I know your policy in such cases
and I acknowledge the propriety of it, therefore I must request you to
attend a called meeting of this jurisdiction on the <date when="1835-09-12">12th- inst</date>. You are aware
of the influence your presence will have, not that it is important to the cause
in any other way than that I have before mentioned of reconciling and
allaying the personal feeling that now exists, and I report again that it
should be the object of all to throw in their mite to effect this great
purpose.&#8212;</p>

<p>We shall have a meeting of the <persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>on <date when="1835-09-07">Monday next</date> and . . .
that body a call for a convention the meeting will probably be adjourned
to the <date when="1835-09-12">12th</date> at which time I hope to have the pleasure of once more seeing
you in the <placeName>first american town in Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>F. W. Johnson</persName> [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName> <placeName>Mouth of Brazos Texas</placeName></p>

<p>[note]</p>

<p>At the time it was known at <placeName>San Felipe</placeName> that <persName>Austin </persName>had arrived on our
shores, both the<persName> war and peace party</persName> hailed the event as one which would
unite the people and produce one course of action whatever that might be&#8212;
They said "if <placeName>Col Austin</placeName> is for peace, we are for peace, if he is for war we
are for <hi rend="italic">War</hi>"</p>

<p><date when="1844-02-06">6th Feby 1844</date>.</p>
<p><persName>G. Borden</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
