<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4814">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Benjamin R. Milam  to Francis W. Johnson, 07-05-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Benjamin R. Milam </persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-25">02-25-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Francis W. Johnson
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Punto Lampasos, Nuevo Leon</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 82-83
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-07-05">07-05-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-25" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Recounting political disturbances in Monclova.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Punto Lampasos</placeName>, <date when="1835-07-05">July 5, 1835</date>.</p>

<p>Dear <persName>Johnson</persName>,</p>

<p>I hope you spent the <date when="1835-07-04">4th July</date> pleasantly with your <persName>friends </persName>who feel
some reverence for the day. As to myself, I can not say I enjoyed it. I
got a bottle of vino muscale and drank to the <hi rend="italic">Federal Constitution in all
parts of <placeName>America</placeName>.</hi> I had no <persName>countrymen </persName>to join me or perhaps I should
have done better.</p>

<p>We left <placeName>Monclova </placeName>on the <date when="1835-05-29">29 of May</date>, and were taken <persName>prisoners </persName>on the <date when="1835-06-05">5th
of June</date>, at night, after we had encamped about <placeName>eight leagues northwest of
San Fernando</placeName>. The <persName>troops </persName>had been viewing our march for the last day,
and knew the only chance we had for water and placed themselves in a
situation to take possession of our horses as soon as it was dusk. In this
situation we were obliged to surrender to <persName>twenty five men</persName>&#8212;or <persName>savages </persName>as
we may more properly call them. <persName>Capt Galan</persName> and <persName>Liut: Roderiguiz 
[Rodriguez]</persName> commanded the party. They will be long remembered by your
humble servant.</p>

<p>We were taken to <placeName>San Fernando</placeName> and kept in close <placeName>confinement </placeName>for one
week&#8212;not permitted to write or speak to any person except in the presence
of an <persName>officer</persName>, and then but in the Spanish language. From there we were
taken to <placeName>Rio Grande</placeName>, where we were treated something better by <persName>Capt
Barigan</persName> from <placeName>Rio Grande</placeName> to this place. At present we are under the
charge of <persName>Col: Altapa</persName>, who is a 
<persName>gentleman </persName>and an <persName>officer</persName>, and gives every
indulgence we ask for. From here we expect to be sent to <placeName>Monterey </placeName>to
stand our trial, and I hope to be set at liberty. But all is uncertainty.
The whole of this part of the state has and will support the <persName>Central
Government</persName>. The <placeName>Interior </placeName>from the last information we have, has fallen
into the Central system, <persName>Santanna </persName>is <persName>Dictator</persName>&#8212;the Constitution is thrown
away and ridiculed by those who used to call themselves <persName>Federal 
Republicans</persName>.</p>

<p>The plan for the dissolution and destruction is laid, and every 
preparation is making for its execution. In the last ten days <persName>two hundred troops</persName>
have left <placeName>this quarter</placeName> for <placeName>San Antonio</placeName>; and from the test information I
can collect <persName>two thousand more</persName> will be on their march in a few weeks.
Their intention is to gain the friendship of the <persName>different tribes of Indians</persName>;<pb n="83"/>
and, if possible to get the <persName>slaves </persName>to revolt. These plans of barbarity and
injustice will make a wilderness of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and beggars of its <persName>inhabitants</persName>,
if they do not unite and act with promptitude and decision. If the Federal
system is lost in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, what will be our situation? worse than that of
the most degraded <persName>slaves</persName>. The hopes of the <persName>Republican party</persName> here are all
on <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I trust they will not be deceived. The <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> will
never submit to a <persName>Dictator</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>B R Milam</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
