<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4727">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to Samuel M. Williams, 02-14-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-16">02-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M. Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Monclova, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 42-44
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-02-14">02-14-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Promoting a road to Chihuahua through Texas. His Exposition has corrected false impressions concerning Texas. Robertson Colony. Opposition to territorial government for Texas made him enemies</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Texas.]</p>

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1835-02-14">Feb. 14. 1835</date></p>

<p><persName>S. M. Williams</persName></p>

<p>My good friend,</p>

<p>I confidently hoped to have met you at <placeName>Monclova </placeName>by the <date when="1835-03-01">1 of March</date>, but
I find that I cannot&#8212; I think I shall be able to leave here in <date when="1835-03-01">about 15<pb n="43"/>
days,</date> tho I cannot say to a certainty&#8212; I have some idea of employing
this interval in trying to get some aid of the <persName>Genl Govt</persName> towards opening
<placeName>a road from Texas to the Paso del norte</placeName>, or in a direct line (or as nearly
so as the country will admit) to <placeName>Chihuahua </placeName>I speak of this interprise in
my exposicion copies of which I have sent to <placeName>Monclova </placeName>and by this mail
I send you one, I sent one to you <date when="1835-02-12">two days ago </date>directed to <placeName>Austin</placeName>&#8212; It
has been very well received here, and has satisfied every reasonable man&#8212;
I believe that <placeName>Texas </placeName>has more <persName>friends </persName>in the Govt and in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>now, than
it ever had before. I can say the same as to myself&#8212;</p>

<p>I cannot believe that such men as <persName>Robertson </persName>and <persName>Chambers </persName>can have
any influence at <placeName>Monclova </placeName>and I confidently expect that the evil they have
done will be remedied&#8212; There was [never] a more outrageous injustice
done to anyone than that committed by <persName>Vidauri</persName> in renewing the contract
for the<placeName> upper colony</placeName> in direct violation of our rights&#8212; you must attend
to that business&#8212; I will be there as soon as I can to aid in putting things
to rights once more.</p>

<p>I have reason to believe that <persName>Mason </persName>and <persName>Mexia </persName>tryed to do me all the
injury they could and to perpetuate my imprisonment as long as they
could&#8212; they never forgave me for opposing their schemes to make a
<placeName>territory </placeName>of <placeName>Texas </placeName>and their monopolies of land etc and I shall be well
satisfied if they will remain my <persName>enemies </persName>for the balance of their lives&#8212;
<hi rend="italic"><persName>Tony </persName></hi>and them are birds of the same feather&#8212;</p>

<p>An effort was made in <date n="01-xx-1835">Jany</date>- to make a <placeName>territory </placeName>of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, but it failed&#8212;
another effort was about to be made when my esposicion came out, which
has also died away.</p>

<p>The last clause of my esposicion was intended to kill this project, and
it has had the effect. A proposicion was made sometime since to renew
the 11 article of the law of <date when="1830-04-06">6 april</date> which I am told will die <hi rend="italic">en 
commission</hi>&#8212;so that upon the whole my personal sufferings will result to the
advantage of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, by removing prejudices and leading to inquiries that
have satisfied everyone&#8212; This is some consolation at least&#8212; It is in fact
a full reward for all my trouble and persecution.<pb n="44"/></p>

<p>My <persName>constituents </persName>at <placeName>home </placeName><hi rend="italic">ought </hi>to be satisfied with me&#8212; I have done my
duty towards them, regardless of my own personal interests or safety&#8212;
I have paid my own expenses and they have been very great indeed.</p>

<p>The <placeName>Chihuahua road</placeName> is a great hobby with me&#8212; I intend to persevere
untill it is completed, and <hi rend="italic">then </hi>I am done with empresas&#8212; I have written
to <placeName>Chihuahua </placeName>on the subject and think the whole influence of that state
can be inlisted in this great enterprise&#8212;it is the <hi rend="italic">last </hi>and <hi rend="italic">only </hi>object of my
ambition&#8212;</p>

<p>Cotton will be in great demand here <date n="xx-xx-1836">next year</date>, it is so now&#8212;</p>

<p>I saw an ascension by <persName>Mr. Robertson</persName> on the <date when="1835-03-12">12 instant</date>&#8212;he descended
<placeName>14 leagues South of this beyond the mountain [s] that surround the valley
of Mexico&#8212;</placeName> he returned to day all well you will see it in <placeName>papers</placeName>&#8212;
<persName>Grayson </persName>left last week for <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> via <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>&#8212; I am going to
the <placeName>Theatre </placeName>so adios</p>

<p><persName>S. F. A.</persName></p>

<p>I am told <persName>Aguirrie </persName>has sold those <placeName>claims </placeName>a second time and perhaps a
dozen times see to it before it is too late&#8212;</p>

<p>Write <placeName>home </placeName>that I am well&#8212; I am waiting for the Amnesty law, for I
am still on bail&#8212;</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <placeName>(Coahuila y Texas)</placeName> Al <persName>sor D. Samuel M. Williams
</persName><placeName>Monclova</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
