<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4526">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William H Skerrett to Stephen F Austin, 02-04-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William H Skerrett</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-11">11-11-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Chillicothe, Ohio</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 925-926
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-02-04">02-04-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asking Austin to assist him in settling business in Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Chillicothe </placeName><date when="1833-02-04">February 4th. 1833</date></p>
<p><persName>Col Stephen F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dear Sir You will be pleased to pardon me for troubling you,
but I have just received an <persName>anonimous </persName>letter dated " <placeName>Mouth of the
Brazos</placeName> <date when="1832-12-22">22d. December 1832</date> " which purports to have been written
by some person who feels interested in my wellfare but they either
designedly or neglectfully sent the letter without signing it&#8212; In
which they inform me that <persName>Capt. J. B. Bailey</persName> is dead and in 
consequence thereof my business left in his hands is in a bad condition&#8212;</p>

<p>Deeming it advisable at all times to apply to the fountain head,
I have taken the liberty of addressing this to you, and hope you will
not think it too much trouble to reply immediately&#8212; I wish to
ascertain if <persName>Bailey </persName>is dead, and if so, would you be pleased to enquire
and inform me the situation in which he left my business&#8212;also
would you be pleased to advise in whose hands I had better place
it, or whether I had better come down myself the latter Í know from
experience would be the better course, but at present it would be
attended with great inconvenience and sacrafice to me, and I would
rather suffer loss there, than here at present, unless the sacrifice
would be too great there, I had hoped to have been down in the
<date n="Spring - 1828">spring of 1828</date> but was prevented by suits&#8212;since when by a 
succession of ill chances I have not been able to get off&#8212; since my return
from <placeName>Texas </placeName>I have lost a <persName>brother-in-law-</persName><persName>Sister-in-law</persName> and <persName>Mother-in-<pb n="926"/>
law</persName> by the death of the former my <persName>family </persName>has been increased 1 boy
and three girls&#8212;and in the same time my <persName>wife </persName>has presented me
with 2 girls and 1 boy&#8212;   So you see when I do come down, I shall
come in considerable force in point of numbers, though not in 
military strength&#8212;and I am determined to come down and settle in
that <placeName>country </placeName>yet, so soon as I can make my arrangements to close all
my business here, which I hope to be enabled to do in all this year
When I do come you I think will find me a different person in
many respects from what I was when you last seen me&#8212;   it has
been a great source of regret to me the manner in which I conducted
myself while there&#8212;   had I attended to my business as I ought to
have done while down I might have left it without any difficulty or
trouble about it at this time&#8212;but the fact is I cared little about the
world or any person in it at that time&#8212;I had been harassed and 
defrauded by some of my <persName>relations</persName>, and by some who ought to have
been my best friends&#8212;and who professed themselves as such&#8212;   I
therefore cared little what become of myself or anything else&#8212;but
I have since thought and learned better things&#8212;   Dear Sir yo[u
see]    I have a large <persName>family </persName>and had hoped that the [land I purchased
in Texas might be beneficial to [them and]    *   *   *   *   to me&#8212;
I therefore do now hope that [it]    *   *    *   may not be wrested
from me&#8212;   I had sen[t] [Bailey]    *   *   *   a full power of Atty.
to do and act as he thought most advisable for me investing him
with all the powers that I myself possessed&#8212;   you perhaps think it
strange that I put my business in his hands&#8212;but I knew that he
felt a very warm friendship for me&#8212;and would make every exertion
in his power to serve me&#8212;   I wrote by <persName>Mr. J. P. Fessenden</persName> <date n="Fall - 1832">last
fall</date> and sent a package by him to <persName>Bailey </persName>containing sundry papers
of value to me,&#8212;<persName>Fessenden </persName>promised to write me immediately on
his arrival since when I have heard nothing of him&#8212;   will you be
so good as to inform me whether he has arrived in the <placeName>colony </placeName>and if
he has taken charge of the packet designed for <persName>Bailey </persName>I had every
confidence in <persName>Bailey</persName>&#8212;and in his letters he states that when I come
down, I will find every thing done that lay in his power for me
and whether he is dead or alive I should find it done for my interest
and benefit and not his&#8212;</p>

<p>Dear Sir by devoting some attention to this business you will 
confer a lasting favour, and possibly it may one day be in my power
to reciprocate-&#8212;                                              </p>
<p><persName>Wm. H. Skerrett</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
