<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4317">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John P Austin to Stephen F Austin, 01-27-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John P Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-19">09-19-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 741-742
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-01-27">01-27-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-19" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Acknowledging letter from Austin concerning Galveston Bay &amp; Texas Land Co.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            


<p><placeName>New York</placeName> <date when="1832-01-27">January 27 1832</date></p>
<p>My dear <persName>Cousin</persName>,</p>

<p>Your Esteemed favor of the <date when="1831-12-27">27th Ulto</date>. is at hand and contents
noted with a lively interest. In answer to your main question, I
will refer you to my letter to <persName>Henry </persName>per <date when="1832-01-26">yesterday</date>s mail, via <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName>, as showing that no time had been lost since the receipt of
your and his letters, that the business is in its proper train
appears to have excited due interest, and as far as could judge did
not think you need fear the result etc, etc, etc., which I requested
him to communicate to you immediately on receipt and would write
further next week. A <persName>friend</persName>, wellknown to <persName>Henry</persName>, in whom, as
he will tell you, the utmost confidence can be placed, takes a deep
interest and will render every aid in his power to accomplish the
object and I know no one better qualified or that has half the weight
with the principal <persName>gentlemen </persName>interested in the <persName>Galveston Bay 
Company </persName>that he has or who is so well informed on the subject generally
or the means of obtaining so correct information either private or
otherwise and further I am well satisfied he will go heart and hand
with us, a true <persName>friend </persName>every wish of him, so that whatever we do
you may rely on secrecy. I could wish however, that you could
see <persName>Mr. M. [John T. Mason?]</persName> as I have good grounds for believing
he would meet your views and wishes fully with ample power to
act. It is possible he may be with you, as he with<persName> Mr. Butler </persName>were
to have left the <placeName>City of Mexico</placeName> for your <placeName>colony</placeName>, the <date n="01-xx-1832">present month,</date><pb n="742"/>
but is to be feared the Counter revolution of which advises were
received here last packet from <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, <persName>majr </persName>detain them both.
I send you and <persName>Henry</persName>, with this, an abridgement of the 
Colonization Laws etc of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, just published by <persName>Col. Langworthy</persName>, who
visited your <placeName>colony </placeName><date n="xx-xx-1831">the last year</date>. Have also sent <persName>Mrs Holley </persName>a copy.
I regret extremely that circumstances should delay your intended
visit, which we have been anticipating with so much pleasure. My
<persName>sister Mary</persName>, appears, from her letters, perfectly delighted with her
visit to your <placeName>colony</placeName>, says there is no mistake or exageration as to
the favourable impression she had previously received that she
wishes all she has was there and that she would not return upon
any account, she mentions her book on <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and was to send the
manuscript per first packet. Also requests me to pay fifty dollars,
for her, on your account, which <persName>Mr. Leaming</persName> has drawn for, and his
Draft duly paid, agreeably to your letter of advise, and the amount
placed to the debit of<persName> Mrs. Holley</persName>. It is to me highly gratifying to
hear you passed your time so agreeably at<placeName><persName>Henry</persName>s</placeName> as well as the high
commendations in which you name<persName> Mrs. H.</persName> She mentions that visit
with rapture and says would have done me good to have seen how
all enjoyed it, and quite made me wish myself and <persName>wife </persName>could have
been of the party, as I know nothing that could give me more
pleasure than to make you a visit, but fear will be some time yet
before circumstances will admit of it which alone keeps me here.
The weather is so intensely cold, it is with difficulty I can direct my
pen (4 Degrees below zero) I beg you will let me hear from you
by every opportunity as I can but feel an intense interest in your
and<placeName> colony</placeName>s welfare.</p>

<p><persName>J. P. Austin</persName></p>

<p>P. S. I would refer you to the enclosed letter recd, per last packet
from <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, as giving some particulars of the movements there.
I also send with this a file of papers for your and <persName>Henry</persName>s perusal,
which will give much interesting matter if not previously received
and to which I would refer. To days mail from <placeName>Washington</placeName>, brings
the news of the rejection of the <persName>Senate </persName>of the nomination of the
<persName>Honbl. Martin Van Buren as minister to <placeName>London</placeName></persName>.</p>

<p><persName>J. P. A.</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
