<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4639">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James F Perry to Stephen F Austin, 05-13-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James F Perry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-03">12-03-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1055-1056
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Lettter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-05-13">05-13-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-03" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Anxiety for Austin, Conditions in Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1834-05-13">13th May 1834</date></p>
<p>My Dear <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>I enclose this to our beloved <persName>Pastor Father Muldoon</persName> through
whose kindness I hope you will receive it knowing your anxiety to
hear from us. <persName>Emily </persName>and myself both wrote to you a short time
since by the way of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> which I hope you have recd. We
have not recd a line from you since you left <placeName>Montary </placeName>nor has there
been any direct information recd of you since shortly after you 
arrived at the <placeName>city of Mexico</placeName>, our anxiety on your act. is very great&#8212;
not through fear of any charges which can be brought against you
as we have too much confidence in the <persName>Justness of the enlightened
officers of the <placeName>Mexican nation</placeName></persName> to think that they would treat you
unjustly and knowing as we do that you have committed no offence,
we fear not a fair exposetion of all your conduct but knowing the
many severe attacks of diseas you have had caused from fatigue and
exposure, we fear for your health but we still hope you are now
on your way home and anticipate the happy moment when we may
once more meet, the hour for the arrival of the mail today was
looked for here In hopes that some intelligence would be recd of
you but to our mortification not a word came, what can be the
cause We cannot conceive. I left home <date when="1834-05-03">ten days since</date> the <persName>family</persName>
were all well <persName>Emily </persName>enjoys tolerable health and all that is wanting
to make her happy is your return once more the weather has been
dry and fair so far and bids fair for a healthy season and good
crops. <persName>Mr Pilgram</persName> still continues with us the <persName>children </persName>are very
well.    <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> is going to school to him and begins to<pb n="1056"/>
learn fast <persName>Col. Philips</persName> is in a very bad health it is doubtful
whether he will recover. <persName>S. M. Williams</persName> left two weeks since for
<placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, everything is going on here smoothly, a fair 
prospect for crops in <placeName>every part of the colony</placeName> and the passage of some
Salutary Laws by the <persName>Congress of the State</persName> encourages us to look
forward to prosperity and happiness.</p>

<p>By the last mail the <persName>Ayuntamiento of the <placeName>Jurisdiction</placeName></persName> forwarded
to the <persName>Genl Government</persName> a petition praying your release and 
informing them that you had done nothing but what you was expected
and instructed to do.</p>

<p>May God bless and protect you and hasten your return to your
<persName>relatives </persName>and <persName>friends </persName>is the sincere prayer of your affectionat
<persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>[James F. Perry.]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
