<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4482">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Ira Ingram to Public, 11-20-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Ira Ingram</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-03">11-03-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Public
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination"></placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 891-893
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Circular</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-11-20">11-20-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-03" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Gail for convention to meet January 14, 1832, to frame criminal code.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Circular</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">To the <persName>Comisario the Precinct</persName>of or the <persName>Sub-Committee of said
District</persName>:</hi></p>

<p>You are hereby requested to hold an Election in your <placeName>Precinct</placeName>,
on the<date when="1832-12-29"> last Saturday </date>and <date when="1832-12-30">Sunday in December next</date>, for the purpose
of Electing <persName>Five Delegates</persName>, to meet in Convention in the Town of
<placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName>, On <date when="1833-01-14">Monday, the 14th day of January next</date></p>

<p>The object of this call, will be sufficiently explained by the 
accompanying Report of the <persName>Committee </persName>appointed by a meeting of the
<persName>People </persName>of this place.<pb n="892"/></p>

<p>Should the <persName>Comisario</persName>, from any cause, be unable to hold the 
Election, any <persName>Member of Your Committee</persName>, together with a <persName>Citizen</persName>, are
competent to hold the Election, The returns to be made as soon
as possible after the Election.</p>

<p>Given under our hands, at the Town of <placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName>
this <date when="1832-11-20">20th day of November, 1832</date>.</p>

<p>At a numerous meeting of <persName>Citizens</persName>, at <placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName>, 
convened for the purpose of expressing their sentiments in relation to
the then pending execution of <hi rend="italic"><persName>Délaney</persName></hi>, <persName>Mr. Ira Ingram</persName> availed 
himself of the opportunity, to introduce a Resolution, which led to the
following Report :</p>

<p><persName>Mr. Chairman</persName>:&#8212;The Committee to whom was referred the resolution 
relative to the " expediency, or inexpediency, of calling a Convention of the <persName>people
of <placeName>Austin's Colony</placeName></persName>, for the purpose of framing a Provisional Code of Criminal
Jurisprudence, and for the further purpose of providing for the correction
of abuses, if any, in Civil proceedings "; having had the subject of reference
under consideration, and having given it all the attention which the short
time allowed for reflection would permit&#8212;Report&#8212;-that they deem the call of
such a Convention not expedient only, but vitally imporant to the protection
of our dearest rights.</p>

<p>Your <persName>Committee </persName>have long witnessed, and have long lamented, in common
with their <persName>Fellow-Citizens of the <placeName>Jurisdiction</placeName></persName>, the tardy and tiresome progress
of criminal proceedings in our <placeName>Courts</placeName>&#8212;they have witnessed the impunity of
the guilty, and the total want of protection for the innocnt. The laws
which ought to be inforced, if any such there be, are locked up in a
language known to a few only, and, therefore, for all practical purposes,
utterly beyond our reach. The <persName>Tribunals</persName>, too, whose duty it is to administer
the law, are, if possible, of still more difficult access.</p>

<p>Superadded to these considerations, which, of themselves, must always
weigh heavily with an intelligent and increasing population, we are at
present involved in the uncertainties of the Civil War now raging in the
<placeName>interior of the country</placeName>. The excitements and political agitations, always
attendant on belligerent operations, necessarily produce delay in all countries,
and in all times; and operate on us, at the present crises, as a total denial
of the administration of justice.</p>

<p>The accurate <persName>observer</persName>, on taking a survey of our situation, must pronounce
the decisive opinion, that we are without <hi rend="italic">remedy </hi>for wrongs; that we are
without <hi rend="italic">redress </hi>for grievances; and that we must remain without them, until
they are provided by the deliberate, and <hi rend="italic">declared will</hi> of a majority of the
people, assembled by <persName>delegation</persName>, in Public Convention.</p>

<p>Your <persName>Committee </persName>are of opinion, therefore, that such Convention should be
called with as little delay as possible, for the purpose of recommending, or
of framing a Criminal Code for trial and final disposal of those charged with
offences, and with crimes; and for the purpose of adopting such measures as
In their wisdom, may be necessary to carry the system into full, complete,
and immediate operation.</p>

<p>Your <persName>Committee </persName>would also recommend, that, such Convention institute a
full and thorough investigation of abuses in the administration of justice in
civil proceedings; and that they apply such remedy, or remedies, as may be<pb n="893"/>
necessary to afford relief for past wrongs, and to prevent, if possible, the 
occurrence of others hereafter.</p>

<p>And they further recommend, that a call be made by the <persName>First and Second
Alcalde</persName>, or by either of them, on the <persName>Comisarios</persName>, or <persName>Sub-Committees of each
<placeName>Precinct</placeName></persName> throughout the <placeName>Colony</placeName>, to hold an election, or cause one to be
held, at as many different places as may be necessary for a full expression
of public sentiment, for the election, of <persName>five Delegates from each <placeName>Precinct</placeName></persName>, on
the <date when="1832-12-29">last Saturday</date> and <date when="1829-12-30">Sunday of December next</date>; to meet in Convention on
<date when="1833-01-14">Monday, the 14th of January, 1833</date>, in the Town of <placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName>.</p>

<p>And your <persName>Committee </persName>recommend also, that a copy of the proceedings of
this meeting, signed by the <persName>Chairman </persName>and certified by the <persName>Secretary</persName>, be
circulated to all the <persName>Comisarios</persName>, or <persName>Sub-Committees;</persName> and that they be
requested to furnish a copy of the same to every <persName>citizen </persName>called by them to
hold a poll.</p>

<p><placeName>San Felipe</placeName>, <date when="1832-01-13">13th November, 1832</date>.</p>

<p><persName>Ira Ingram, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi></persName>,</p>

<p><persName>Luke Lesassier</persName>.</p>
<p><persName>William H. Jack</persName>.</p>

<p>Amendment.&#8212;Moved, seconded and carried&#8212;that this report was adopted
by the meeting with the amendment that the <persName>members of the Ayuntamientos
of the <placeName>Municipalities of Austin </placeName>and <placeName>Brazoria</placeName></persName>, be considered as <persName>members ex
officio of the proposed Convention</persName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
