<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4574">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Wily Martin, 05-30-1831 [1833]</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-26">11-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Wily Martin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Matamoras, Texxas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 977-981
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-05-30">05-30-1831 [1833]</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Many alarming rumors in Mexico concerning intention of Texans to revolt. He has dissipated most
of the uneasiness. Customhouses must be reestablished and Austin has pledged people to support the collector. Has changed attitude toward slavery. Texas must be a slave country. Hopes for State organization with consent of Coahuila.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Matamoras</placeName>,<date n="05-30-18310[1833]"> May 30, 1831 [1833]</date></p>
<p><persName>Capt. Wiley Martin </persName>:                               </p>

<p>On my arrival here, things were rather a bad aspect, but they have
totally changed for the better. It was believed that <placeName>Texas </placeName>had
declared independence, and that <persName>John Austin</persName> was organizing an <persName>army</persName>
to fight the <persName>Mexicans</persName>. I am told there is also some excitement in
<placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and that the <placeName>State </placeName>got all excited, and have sent 
<persName>commissioners </persName>to <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>The <persName>Com. Gen'l Filisola</persName>, is a blunt, honest, candid and prompt
<persName>soldier</persName>. He has been over thirty years in service; has been <persName>Com.
Gen'l.</persName> at various times, with important powers entrusted to him,&#8212;
and what is rather uncommon, he has not made a fortune. His 
principles are liberal and republican, and he wishes that the practice of
all the <persName>authorities </persName>should conform with the true spirit of the 
Constitution and the laws. Says that there is a great want of moral
honesty, and great abuses in the revenue. He is the <persName>friend </persName>of the
farming and agricultural interests&#8212;a decided <persName>enemy </persName>of <persName>smugglers</persName>
and <persName>lawyers</persName>, for he thinks they demoralize the <placeName>community </placeName>by placing
temptations before weak or avaricious persons etc. He will be 
unpopular with all who wish to make money by evading the law. He
thinks well of the idea of making a <placeName>State of Texas</placeName>, and has a good
opinion of the <persName>Colonists </persName>in general, but believes they have more
<persName>enemies </persName>amongst themselves than any where else. The reason he
thinks so is, that he says a quiet and prudent course is the best for
them and a rigid adherence to all the laws, so long as they are in
force, etc. They are gaining yearly, and the republican principle[s]
they have been accustomed to, are also gaining all over the nation,
so that a little patience will place all right without any difficulty etc.<pb n="978"/></p>

<p>He has orders to reestablish the <placeName>custom house</placeName> and <placeName>garrisons</placeName>, and
is compelled to do so. The former will be done, the latter, probably
not until <date n="Fall-1833">fall</date>; and I am of opinion not to the extent then that was
contemplated a month ago.</p>

<p><persName>Geo. Fisher</persName> goes back as <persName>collector</persName>. I assure you that he is now a
new man, it is the interest of the <placeName>country </placeName>to sustain him, and I request
my friend, that you will unite in support of what I recommended on
this, and all other matters in my letter to the <persName>Ayuntamientos</persName>.</p>

<p>The quantity of tobacco that has been smuggled from the <placeName>ports of
Texas</placeName>, has made a great noise all over the <placeName>nation</placeName>, and the violation
of the <placeName>custom house</placeName> laws in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, are made a pretext for similar
violations elsewhere. The <persName>enemies of Santa Anna</persName> are making a
great handle of these <placeName>Texas </placeName>matters, to injure him and destroy his
popularity. They say he has lost <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and is the cause of the 
destruction of the public property there, the ruin of the <placeName>forts</placeName>, and the
insults which it is reported the <persName>Mexicans </persName>have received there, etc.;
and that he is now unwilling or unable or afraid to punish such acts
of outrage, etc.   Much is said by his <persName>enemies </persName>on the subject.</p>

<p>I am told that <persName>Santa Anna</persName> and his <persName>friends </persName>are very much enraged
at the <persName>colonists</persName>, and blames them for the <placeName>Anahuac </placeName>expedition; says
they had some cause to complain, but they went to work in so headlong 
and passionate a manner to get redress, that they placed 
themselves in a worse situation than they were before, because they put
weapons in the hands of their <persName>enemies</persName>, and injured and mortified
their <persName>friends</persName>.</p>

<p>Amongst other things, it is reported that there are a number of
<persName>American Generals in <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, who are inflaming the <persName>people </persName>against
the <persName>Mexicans</persName>, and that the common talk is about independence, 
fighting, and abuse of the <persName>Mexicans</persName>, etc.</p>

<p>It is also reported that the <persName>alcalde </persName>and the <persName>ayuntamientos of <placeName>Austin</placeName></persName>
treat the <persName>State authorities</persName> with contempt, and do not even 
acknowledge the receipt of the official correspondence, and never pretend to
answer it, or comply with the laws. Amongst so many rumors and
lies, it is not to be expected that I should escape. It is reported that
I was the <persName>author </persName>of the <placeName>Anahuac expedition</placeName>, and of all <persName>John Austin</persName>'s
acts. The <persName>Santa Anna party</persName> are irritated at that <persName>expedition </persName>for
they say it put the current in motion and was the cause of all that
passed. I am told I shall be roughly received by <persName>Santa Anna</persName> at
first. This I do not believe, for nothing could be more unjust than
to accuse me of being the <persName>author </persName>of that <persName>expedition</persName>. However, all
this can be corrected and placed on its true basis by a statement of
facts; for I believe the irritation has proceeded more from the handle<pb n="979"/>
or pretext it gives the<persName> enemies of Santa Anna</persName> to abuse him, than
from a belief that there was no cause for complaint.</p>

<p>You could not have a correct idea of how matters stood, unless
you were informed of all these reports and sayings, and for this
reason I have mentioned them.</p>

<p>I think it best to harmonize with the <persName>State commissioners</persName> so far
as it can be done, without yielding the principle of a <persName>State 
Government</persName>.</p>

<p>I am told that <placeName>Coahuila </placeName>would consent to the separation, if the
money now due for land already granted was secured to <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>,
they say that <placeName>Texas</placeName> has paid nothing as yet, to defray the expenses
of the State etc. For my part, so far as I am interested as a <persName>citizen
of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, I am willing to yield this point and to pay to <placeName>Coahuila</placeName> all
that is or may be due for all land where titles are actually issued.
This would not include the <placeName>floating eleven league tracts not located,
nor lands in colonizing contracts not settled</placeName>, but would only embrace
<placeName>all where the possession was actually given</placeName> and the title issued before
the final separation.</p>

<p>That money is a mere trifle compared to getting a <placeName>State</placeName>, and I can
assure you it will be very difficult to get a State without the consent
of <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>, and very easy to get it with her consent.</p>

<p>I merely make the suggestion to you of harmonizing as much as
possible with <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>, for if the <persName>State Government</persName> should apply
to the <persName>General Government</persName>, or to the other <placeName>States </placeName>for aid to inforce
its laws in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, the <persName>General Government</persName> would hardly dare to
refuse it in the present critical state of things.</p>

<p>The <persName>general congress</persName> has adjourned and probably will not meet
again until <date n="01-xx-1834">January next</date>, so that my trip to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>was rendered
measurably useless, and having been very much debilitated by a
dysentery, or Cholarina, that is prevailing here, I had concluded at
one time to postpone my trip for the present and I forwarded the
memorial to the <persName>President </persName>through the <persName>commandant General</persName> by mail,
so as to remove the bad impressions that existed in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. I have
this day heard of a vessel that is unexpectedly to be sent to <placeName>Vera
Cruz</placeName>, the schooner Comet, and I shall embark on board of her and
take the stage from <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. I am illy calculated at
this time to stand the trip by land, and I believe that it would lay
me up in this hot, dry <placeName>country </placeName>perhaps for the whole <date n="Summer-1833">summer</date>.</p>

<p>Nothing definite can be done about the State question, until 
<persName>Congress </persName>meets in <date n="01-xx-1834">January</date>, unless there should be a called session, and
they are always convened for special objects, and by the constitution
nothing can be done in them but the special objects for which they
are convened. So that all I can do is to talk with the <persName>President </persName>and
<persName>Ministers </persName>and correct lies and false reports etc., and pave the way.
I think I shall return in <date n="08-xx-1833">August</date>, but if it appears to be necessary for
me to remain until <date n="01-xx-1834">January</date>, I shall do so.<pb n="980"/></p>

<p>The basis of my policy, so far as I had any thing to do with <placeName>Texas</placeName>
matters, up to last <date n="07-xx-1832">July </date>the time when I returned and found all in
confusion, was this&#8212;never to put the interests of the <persName>settlers </persName>at
hazard, and to rely more upon the regular and natural progress of
things for remedies, than upon efforts to force them prematurely.</p>

<p>The <persName>settlers </persName>have earned what they have got too hard, and by too
many years of hard labor and privation, to jeopardize all hastily&#8212;a
war with the <placeName>nation </placeName>will be ruinous to them, for they will be 
destroyed and overwhelmed, eaten up by those who come from <placeName>abroad</placeName>
to aid them in fighting their battles. They have more to dread from
such <persName>friends</persName>, and from <persName>Indians</persName>, than from the whole <placeName>Mexican nation</placeName>.</p>

<p>Had I been an ambitious<persName> military leader,</persName> the reverse of this would
have been my policy, and I would have aroused and led on the
<persName>settlers</persName>, and inflamed them into a war and then made use of them
(as all <persName>military leaders </persName>do of the <persName>people</persName>) to build up my own fame
as a <persName>chieftain</persName>, success would have deceived the most of them and
made me a great man, nominally. For I think that true greatness
consists in doing the most good, and not in acquiring the most fame-
when I entered <placeName>Texas </placeName>I laid it down as a fixed rule of action, to
conquer that <placeName>country </placeName>with the axe, the plough and the hoe. Silently
and gradually my ambition was to benefit all, and make use of none
as mere instruments to build up myself and a few chosen band of
<persName>leaders</persName>. Every <persName>military leader</persName> must of necessity be surrounded by
a set of <hi rend="italic"><persName>leeches </persName></hi>who must be kept fat, and whose ambition must be
gratified, and whims satisfied. All this is done by using the people
as tools, or rather as food to glut upon.</p>

<p>I am the <persName>friend </persName>of <persName>farmers</persName>. The plough is my favorite weapon
for conquest, and I <hi rend="italic">am not</hi> the <persName>friend </persName>of the <persName>useless dupes</persName> in society.
I look upon the most of <persName>military and professional men</persName> as useless. I
speak in general of the masses as we find them.</p>

<p>Also, I have pursued <hi rend="italic">concilliation </hi>as a system; both in the <placeName>colony</placeName>
and out of it. I did so because a small spark kindles a great flame,
and such flames always injure the <persName>farmers </persName>and <persName>working classes</persName>.
Besides this, a <hi rend="italic"><persName>child </persName></hi>is easier destroyed in a conflict than a full
grown <persName>man</persName>. My policy has displeased the ardent spirits in my
<placeName>colony</placeName>, but I still think it was the correct one; and I see no necessity
for abandoning it and adopting the reverse as a basis. Though, if
it is abandoned, I shall go into the opposite extreme, and adhere to
it as fully, and as obstinately, as I have to the system of concilliation,
and perhaps much more so than some of those who are easily excited,
and talk much about fighting.</p>

<p>Upon the whole, I think we have all got along wonderfully well,
considering all things; and I have the fullest confidence in the most
favorable results.<pb n="981"/></p>

<p>I have been adverse to the principle of slavery in <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I have
now, and for the last six months, changed my views of that matter;
though my ideas are the same as to the abstract principle. <placeName>Texas</placeName>
must he a <placeName><persName>slave </persName>country</placeName>. Circumstances and unavoidable 
necessity compels it. It is the wish of the <persName>people </persName>there, and it is my duty
to do all I can, prudently, in favor of it.   I will do so.</p>

<p>I think the <persName>General </persName>will send on <persName>Fisher </persName>with a few <persName>men </persName>by land.
He is <hi rend="italic">compelled </hi>to re-establish the <placeName>customhouses</placeName>, and I advised
him to rely on the <persName>colonists </persName>to enforce the revenue laws. I am of
opinion decidedly, that if <persName>Fisher</persName>'s reports are favorable, there will
not be any <persName>garrisons </persName>sent to <placeName>Texas </placeName>except on the <placeName>frontiers</placeName>.</p>

<p>It would take a sheet or two of paper to tell you the extent of the
injury that was done to all <placeName>Texas </placeName>by the departure of <persName>Dudor 
[Duclor]</persName> from <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>.   He was a <persName>Santa Anna officer</persName>.</p>

<p>When I look back, I am really mortified at some things. In the
first excitement at <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>, <persName>Samuel Sawyer</persName> was a <persName>leader</persName>, and a
great man&#8212;a <persName>right-hand man</persName> of <persName>J. B. McKinstre</persName>. Also, in 
<placeName>Matagorda bay</placeName>, one <persName>John Colbourne</persName>, who was concerned in the <persName><placeName>Boston</placeName>
packet</persName>, took a part in insulting the <placeName>customhouse</placeName>. Now, this 
<persName>Colbourne </persName>went to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and cheated <persName>Mr. Parrot</persName>, an <persName>American
merchant</persName> out of $3,500, by a forged draft in company with <persName>Girard</persName>.
And yet the <hi rend="italic"><persName>farmers </persName></hi>were ready to fight all <placeName>Mexico </placeName>to favor the
smuggling operations of such miserable <persName>scoundrels</persName>. <persName>Mr. McKinstre</persName>
was the principal cause of <persName>Dudor's [Duclor's]</persName> leaving <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>, and
he has done as much harm to <placeName>Texas </placeName>as any man in it. If the 
<persName>industrious men</persName> of the <placeName>country </placeName>will suffer themselves to be made the
mere tools of <persName>peddling traders</persName> and <persName>hot-brained madmen</persName>, they will
deserve to suffer.</p>

<p><persName>Fisher </persName>ought to be sustained, and I hope all the past will be
totally forgotten. See <persName>John Austin </persName>on this subject. As to <persName>Fisher</persName>,
the fact is there were faults all round, on both sides.   Farewell.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
