<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4606">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Ayuntamiento of Bexar to Stephen F Austin, 10-31-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Ayuntamiento of Bexar</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-30">11-30-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Bexar, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1012-1013
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-10-31">10-31-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Refusing to lead in organizing State government of Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>The honorable <persName>ayuntamiento </persName>of this town, being advised of the
official letter which you directed to it, dated the <date when="1833-09-02">2d of the month
just passed</date>, has seen with the greatest regret and surprise the
exciting plea which you make to them that not a moment be lost
in directing a communication to the rest of the <persName>department </persName>and
treating with them in order that <placeName>Texas </placeName>may separate from <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>
and establish a <persName>local government</persName> for itself, even though the <persName>general
government</persName> refuses its consent. It is certainly very regretable that
you should breathe sentiments so contrary and opposed to those of
every good <persName>Mexican</persName>, whose constitution and laws prohibit in a
positive manner this class of proceedings, as you very well know,
and when the ephemeral support which it is believed to have in
the general law of the <date when="1824-05-07">7th of May, 1824</date>, is entirely apparent to the
most moderate political capacity of the <placeName>country</placeName>. Thus it is that this
corporation neither can nor ought, nor even wishes, to follow your
suggestion, and it begs that you cease writing to it in regard to
this matter, because you know very well what these 
communications render one liable to, considering the laws and orders of the
state which must be obeyed, and which up to the present time
there is no reason to violate in so brusque a manner as you propose&#8212;¦
especially as there is wanting any reasonable ground which could be
sustained, once the enterprise were begun.<pb n="1013"/></p>

<p>Much has already been said in what has been written concerning
the separation of <placeName>Texas </placeName>from <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>, and much more that you
heard here personally, showing you clearly that we have none of
the elemente, physically and morally, for sustaining a <persName>local 
government</persName>. It is beyond all doubt, therefore, that this project neither
can nor ought to be entertained by any <persName>citizen of <placeName>Coahuila and
Texas</placeName></persName> who recognizes the interests of his <placeName>country </placeName>and of himself.</p>

<p>In conclusion, this corporation entreats you, inasmuch as the state
of revolution in which the <placeName>colonies of this department</placeName>, especially
that of which you are <persName>empresario</persName>, have been placed since <date n="xx-xx-1832">last year</date>
seems about to be terminated by the measures of leniency and
prudence which the <persName>supreme government of the state</persName> has lately
decreed, that you bethink yourself and do not provoke a new motive
for disturbance, which, as you will see if you clearly examine it,
must be more injurious to the <persName>colonists </persName>than to any one else, and
particularly to yourself. We desire the progress of this <placeName>country</placeName>,
and with it our own and that of the <placeName>colonists </placeName>established in it,
our <persName>co-laborers</persName> for the attainment of the desired end. But we
desire that this be attained by legal and peaceful measures which
shall not jeopardize the tranquillity of the <persName>department</persName>, and that
we may assure to ourselves and to our children forever the possession
of the properties that we acquire in it; and there is no doubt that
the measure which you propose is exceedingly rash.</p>

<p>God and Liberty.</p>

<p><placeName>Bejar</placeName>, <date when="1833-10-31">Oct. 31, 1833</date>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
