<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4573">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Ayuntamineto of Nacogdoches, 05-30-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-21">11-21-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Ayuntamineto of Nacogdoches
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Matamoras, Tamaulipas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Nacogdoches, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 975-977
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-05-30">05-30-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Conditions in Mexico tranquil and attitude toward Texas considerate. Custom-houses to be reestablished to stop contraband tobacco trade, Austin has assured authorities that people will support the Government.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Matamoras </placeName><date when="1833-05-30">30th May 1833</date></p>
<p>The <persName>public </persName>was very much agitated in this place by false reports
and rumors from <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;but they have been removed by the 
statement of facts which I have laid before his <persName>Excellency the 
Commandant General Don Vicente Fillisola</persName> who assures me of the
paternal intentions of the <persName>Govt </persName>towards the <persName>People of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>.
There never has been any cause for doubt that such are its 
intentions&#8212;all the vague rumours that have been circulated as to the
marching of a large <persName>Army </persName>to <placeName>Tejas </placeName>with hostile views are utterly
false. The <persName>Genl </persName>has ordered the reestablishment of the <placeName>Custom
Houses</placeName> and the <placeName>military Garrisons</placeName>, and will do so for the purpose
of protecting the public Revenue and stopping the scandalous 
contraband that has been carried on in Tobacco from the <placeName>Ports of
Tejas</placeName>. I have assured him that he will receive the support of the
<persName>Colonist </persName>in sustaining the Revenue laws and that they would do
their duty faithfully as <persName>Mexican Citizens</persName>.</p>

<p>I have pledged my honor for the Truth of this declaration and
have full confidence that the <persName>People of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> will not forfeit the
pledge I have made but will by their acts prove its correctness and
that the revenue laws can be enforced without the aid of large 
<placeName>military Garrisons</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Mr. George Fisher</persName> will leave here shortly to enter upon his duties
of <persName>Collector of<placeName> Galveston Bay</placeName></persName> with only sufficient number of <persName>Troops</persName>
for necessary <persName>Guards </persName>etc.<pb n="976"/></p>

<p>Whatever Ideas and opinions may have heretofore existed as to
<persName>Mr Fisher</persName> they should now be consigned to oblivion and forgotten.
He returns as an <persName>officer of the Govt</persName> and as such it is the duty of the
People to respect and sustain him. I will also observe that I have
investigated very minutely all the past transactions in which he was
concerned and have formed the opinion that the excitements which
unfortunately grew out of them were produced by misconception
and suspicion too hastily entertained and not from intention to do
wrong or injure any one. I believe there were misconceptions on
both sides and probably as much on one part as on the other&#8212;<persName>Mr.
Fisher</persName> will make a usefull <persName>collector </persName>his knowledge of the English
language will give more facilities in his intercourse with the people
than could exist with a <persName>collector </persName>who was unacquainted with that
language. I therefore particularly recommend the utmost harmony
and that he be sustained in the discharge of his duties by all, 
regardless of the clamour of a few <persName>Transient Traders</persName> who would involve
the honest <persName>farmers </persName>in difficulty with the <persName>authorities </persName>if they could
increase their own profits thereby.</p>

<p>The political events of the past year necessarily produced a 
temporary and partial disorganization in the <persName>regular administration of
the Govt</persName> all over the <placeName>nation </placeName>which as a matter of course extended to
<placeName>Texas </placeName>everything is now settled down again upon the constitutional
basis and the regular operation of the laws and of all the <persName>legal
authorities</persName> has been restored. The temporary and provisional
measures which the peculiar exigencies of the times may have 
rendered necessary to pursue the public tranquility and protect persons
and property are consequently ceased all over the nation and I have
assured the <persName>Comt. General</persName> that they will also cease as a matter of
course in <placeName>Tejas</placeName>. I therefore particularly recommend that what
ever temporary deviation of the <persName>Militia </persName>or in any other matter
should be corrected without delay and everything restored again to
the legal basis as has been done all over the <placeName>nation</placeName>. The <persName>Genl 
Congress</persName> adjourned on the <date when="1833-05-20">20th of this month</date> and as there will not be
another regular session untill <date n="01-xx-1834">January next</date>&#8212;my Journey to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>
was rendered measurably useless. I have also been very much 
debilitated by Dysentary or <hi rend="italic">Cholorina </hi>which prevails here. These 
considerations determined me to postpone my trip to the <placeName>Capital </placeName>for the
present and I forwarded the memorial of the convention through the
<persName>Comt General</persName>. Since then my health has improved and an 
opportunity haveing very unexpectedly offered of a passage to <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>
by <placeName>sea </placeName>I have concluded to embrace it and shall depart in a few hours.</p>

<p>I will close by assuring you that I have the most unlimited 
confidence in the patrotism liberality and Justice of the <persName>Govt </persName>and I
rely with full confidence upon the <persName>people of <placeName>Tejas</placeName></persName> to sustain firmly all
the <persName>authorities both federal and State</persName> and to obey the laws strictly.<pb n="977"/></p>

<p>By so doing they will procure a <persName>State Govt</persName> and keep away large and
unnecessary <persName>military Garrisons</persName> and obtain everything that a 
reasonable people ought to expect or a just and <persName>liberal Govt</persName> ought to
grant.</p>

<p>I recommend that the <persName>people of <placeName>Tejas</placeName></persName> should be mild calm and
firm in favour of making a <placeName>state of Tejas</placeName> by legal and constitutional
means and by no other.</p>

<p>To the <persName>Aymt of Nacogdoches</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>A true copy of the original.   <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName><date when="1833-07-10">10 July 1833</date></p>

<p><persName>Adolfo Stern</persName>  [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
