<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4360">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Unknown to Unknown, 06-24-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-26">09-26-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 798-799
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Draft</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-06-24">06-24-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-26" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Draft of a law to abolish security for debt.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[June 24, 1832.]</p>
<p>Desirous that the <persName>Colonists of <placeName>Austins Colony</placeName></persName> should prosper in
wealth peace and harmony. From and after the promulgation of this
Law no debt shall be recoverable by law that is contracted between
any <persName>persons in the <placeName>Colony </placeName></persName> but it will be considered when one credits
another [that] it is in faith of the good opinion and confidence he
entertains of him and does it to oblige and not to ruin him and if
the person credited decieve the other he is a base character and
never will be respected and his credit for ever damd. many 
objections may be raised but when both sides of the question are examined
fairly it will appear evident it is very much in favor of the poor, as
it is them generally who want credit&#8212;-then <persName>monied men</persName> prey upon
them&#8212;they will apply for credit and if it is for property and the
<persName>owner </persName>has it to spare he will deniand 50 or 100 per cent more than
he would be willing to take in cash by waiting a year, there is
from 50 to 100 per cent on his property and money is not worth
more than 10 percent, I have known many <persName>widows </persName>and <persName>Orphans</persName>
ruined by the like for the <persName>man </persName>would drink and trade while drunk
and everyone [was then] his <persName>friend</persName>, because he had a little property
and at the same time they are planning to ruin him. let him have
what he wants for he is good and they can make him willing by
law and every advantage is taken of his distress. The <persName>family </persName>is
brought to suffer,   It is generally said that it is hard to pay a<pb n="799"/>
security debt. This [law] prevents any one from giving or asking a
security except in cases where men have confidence and are willing
to pay one another's debts. Men generally do not credit for more
than one Year and their is some one that will oblige him if he is a
good <persName>man </persName>and if not they had better as they have been Obliged to
do in this <placeName>country </placeName>suffer one year than be eternally ruined; For
instance had there been plenty of provisions and clothing brought
here and sold at the Enormous prices that the <persName>settlers </persName>would have
given it would have been their ruin instead of that they have
suffered and now are clear of debt and have plenty of provisions it
may be said if one gets credit and dies the property is lost. It had
better be than ruin a poor family but this can be remidied for every
man intends for some one to manage his Estate when he dies let
him take with him his <persName>friend </persName>and both pass their word and should
one die all will be wright. The <persName>creditor </persName>does it to favor the <persName>debtor</persName>
and not to ruin him. Much could be said on this subject.</p>

<p>Let it be plainly understood that if one of this <placeName>Colony </placeName>Contracts a
debt out of the <placeName>Colony </placeName>where a similar law does not exist the most
speedy remedy at Law must be used for the collection of it and all
debts contracted previously to this shall be collected by Law.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
