<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4384">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John Austin to Jose Antonio Mexia, 07-18-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-29">09-29-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Jose Antonio Mexia
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 881-820
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-07-18">07-18-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-29" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Proceedings of public meeting at Brazoria.  Resolutions declaring adherence to Santa Anna.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[Answer of the Alcalde John Austin to the foregoing official letter]</p>

<p>I have recd, your official letter dated <date when="1832-07-16">16 of the present month</date>, and
in reply have the honor to inform you that a <persName>committee </persName>appointed by
the <persName>inhabitants of this <placeName>town </placeName></persName>will present to you copies of the acts
and resolutions heretofore adopted and the documents as to the past
occurrances, which will explain to you the principles that have 
governed us up to this time&#8212;. These documents contain our true 
sentiments, and will serve as an answer to your official letter to me dated
the <date when="1832-07-16">16 of this month</date></p>

<p>The <persName>enemies of <placeName>Texas</placeName>,</persName> the <persName>enemies </persName>of the enterprising <persName>men </persName>who
have devoted their time and labor to improve a <placeName>country </placeName>that was
never before trod by<persName> civilised man</persName>, have taken pains, and are 
continually doing it, to attribute to us a disposition to separate from
the <placeName>Mexican confederation</placeName>&#8212;   We have never entertaind, and have<pb n="819"/>
not any such intention or desire, We are <persName>Mexicans </persName>by adoption,
we are the same in heart and will so remain</p>

<p>If the laws have granted to us the honorable title of <persName>citizens</persName>, we
wish that that title should be respected, and that the <persName>authorities </persName>
established by the constitution of the <placeName>State</placeName>, shall govern us. We are
<persName>farmers </persName>and not <persName>soldiers </persName>and therefore desire that the <persName>military 
commandants</persName> shall not enterfere with us at all&#8212;</p>

<p>Since <date n="xx-xx-1830">1830 </date>we have been pretty much governed militarily, and
in so despotic a manner, that we were finally driven to arms to 
restrain within their limits the military subalterns of the <persName>general govt</persName>.</p>

<p>We have not insulted the flag of our <placeName>adopted country</placeName>, as has been
falsly stated by our <persName>enemies</persName>, but on the contrary we have defended
and sustained its true dignity and attacked those who have outraged
it by using it as a pretext for their encroachments upon the 
constitution and sovereignty of the <placeName>state of coahuila and Texas</placeName>, and as a
cover for their baseness and personal crimes. The <persName>commandant of
<placeName>fort velasco</placeName></persName> acted under the orders of the <persName>commandant of <placeName>Anahuac</placeName>
Col Juan Davis Bradburn </persName>who was his <persName>superior</persName>. An investigation
into the conduct of this <persName>officer at <placeName>anahuac</placeName></persName> will inform you fully of
the details of many despotic and arbitrary acts&#8212;He refused to
respect the <persName>authorities </persName>or the constitution of the <placeName>state of coahuila and
Texas</placeName>, or to adhere to the plan of<placeName> vera Cruz</placeName> which we had adopted.
He was sustaind by the <persName>commandant of <placeName>Nacogodoches </placeName>Col Piedras</persName>,
y [and] by that of <placeName>fort velasco</placeName> <persName>Lent. Col Ugartechea</persName>, and 
consequently we were compelled to oppose them all. We attacked <placeName>Fort
velasco</placeName> on the<date when="1832-06-27"> 27 of last month</date> with 112 <persName>farmers </persName>hastily collected
without disciplin and badly armd, and after an obstinate and
bloody engagement of 7 hours it capitulated on the terms expressed
in the enclosed copy of the capitulation every article, of which has
been strictly complyed with on our part, besides furnishing him with
the provisions he needed for his <persName>troops</persName>&#8212;I herewith furnish you
with a return of the <persName>killed </persName>and <persName>wounded </persName>on both sides as nearly as
can be ascertained</p>

<p>This sir is what has passed I hope it will be sufficient to convince
you that these <persName>inhabitants </persName>have not manifested any other desire or
intention than to unite with <persName>Genl Santana</persName> to procure the 
establishment of peace in the <placeName>republic </placeName>under the shield of the constitution,
laws, and that soverignty of the <placeName>states </placeName>shall be respected&#8212;</p>

<p>It is a matter of pride and congratulation to me, that you have
come to this place to see with your own eyes the rectitude of our
sentiments, and that it has afford[ed] us the opportunity of 
presenting to you our respects and the assurances of our hearty 
cooperation in the great and glorious cause which is so nobly advocated by<pb n="820"/>
our distinguisd <persName>Commander in chief Genl Santana</persName>&#8212;God and 
Liberty   <placeName>Brazoria </placeName><date when="1832-07-18">18 July 1832</date></p>

<p><persName>John Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
