<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4199">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 04-16-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-10">09-10-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Leaona Vicario, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 645-647
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-04-16">04-16-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-10" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Government attempting to close Texan ports. Territorial organization could be obtained for Texas. Slavery. Colonization law. Law concerning retail trade. Muldoon. Terán.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            
<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>
<p><placeName>Lea Veo [Leona Vicario],</placeName><date when="1831-04-16"> 16 april 1831</date></p>
<p><persName>S. M. Williams</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir. I refer you to my letter to the <persName>Ayto</persName>. and its enclosure,
where you will find as huge a monster as ever appeared in any
Legislative Hall on earth. I have endeavored to do all.I could
for <persName>Madero</persName>, but nothing can be done with the present <persName>Govr</persName>. I will
attend to this matter at <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>[with Terán] where more can
be effected than here. I wish you to write to <persName>Madero </persName>or get 
<persName>Arciniega </persName>to do so and inform him of this.</p>

<p>By the last mail I recd the <placeName>pamphlet </placeName>from <placeName>New York</placeName> which you
sent me, and the other letter. I have given no answer, and shall
give none untill after my visit to <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have a letter dated <date when="1831-04-06">6 April</date> from <persName>Alaman </persName>and one of <date when="1831-04-03">3d. April
</date>from <persName>Teran</persName>, all seems as well as could possibly be wished for.
The excess of tonnage duty paid by <persName>S. Rhoads [Fisher],</persName> will be
refunded&#8212;<placeName>Texas </placeName>will be remembered in regulating the <placeName>ports</placeName>. The
arms of the <persName>Genl Govt</persName>, are <hi rend="italic">wide open</hi> to receive us as a <placeName>territory</placeName>,
(but no basis is stated with the absolute precision which I think
necessary) agreeing in genl terms to the plan of <placeName>Arkansas </placeName>or 
something like it etc. The question of Slavery with the reasons which
I presented (some of which you have seen in my letter to <persName>Johnson</persName>
of <date when="1831-03-31">31 March</date>) has made a very great impression. I sometimes
shudder at the consequences and think that <placeName>a large part [of]
America</placeName> will be<placeName> Santo Domingonized</placeName> in 100, or 200 years. The
wishes of my <persName>colonists </persName>have hurried me into this thing&#8212;but I am
now in for the cuestión and there is no retreat, for my rule is to
go ahead after once coming to a decisive resolution on a matter of
such consequence as this.</p>

<p>My health is not very good, this atmosphere does not agree with
me. I wish for a long life, for if these <persName>devils </persName><hi rend="italic">jalapize </hi>me, I have
a desire to live long enough to <hi rend="italic">Texize </hi>them with full interest.</p>

<p>I have prepared a bill to amend the colonization law in the 
article which prohibits sales untill cultivated in totalidad, but I found
there was a desire that I should move the subject so as to destroy
the whole law and do all the harm possible. <persName>Jesus Grande</persName> is at
the head of all the mischief&#8212;his <persName>brother Mariano</persName> made a 
handsome fortune out [of] the <hi rend="italic">Salary </hi>he recd in a few months as <persName>vista
of the Aduana of <placeName>Matamoros</placeName></persName>, and now no doubt would find it to<pb n="646"/>
be a very comfortable thing to exclude <persName>foreigners </persName>from retailing
here so as to employ his capital to proper and honest advantage.</p>

<p>I could have obtained anything and all I would have asked by
joining in this retail law&#8212;but better nothing than everything on
such terms.   Push the titles as fast as possible.</p>

<p>Remember me very particularly to <persName>Father Muldoon</persName>&#8212;I have no
objection to his seeing all my letters to <persName>Johnson</persName>, particularly that
of <date when="1831-03-31">31 March</date>, and of this date, also what I said to <persName>Williamson </persName>
relative to the evident necessity of never separating from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. I
have confidence in <persName>Father Muldoon</persName> and in <persName>Teran</persName>, tho time will
shew all things. He ought to be consulted as to the policy of
forming a <placeName>territory of Texas</placeName>, and in doing so my letter on that
subject might be shewn to him by <persName>Johnson</persName>, with a request that he
could give his opinion, in as much as it was a subject of great
importance and could involve the genl interests of the <placeName>country </placeName>etc.
Tho do as circumstances may seem to indicate as the best.</p>

<p>I have become responsable for all the fees on all the pe[ti]tions
sent on from <placeName>Bejar</placeName>, <placeName>La Bahia</placeName> and <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>, and shall have to
borrow money, and you must have some ready to send in <placeName>U. S.</placeName> Bills.</p>

<p>Remember [me] to all and particularly to <persName>Eliza </persName>and <persName>Elizabeth</persName>
and <persName>Arciniega</persName>, tell the latter that I have attended to all his requests
read to him my letter to <persName>Johnson </persName>in full.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin  </persName>  [Rubric]</p>

<p>I shall send two seals for the <persName>Jusgado </persName>and <persName>Ayto </persName>by <persName>Powel </persName>and
<persName>Hickoke </persName>who start in a few days</p>

<p>My colleague <persName>[Manuel] Musquis</persName> is in favor of excluding those who
are merely <persName>foreigners </persName>in transit. I would not have opposed that, if
the <persName>legislature </persName>had power to legislate on the subject, but I think that
the 50 Article of the national constitution gives that power 
exclusively to the national congress. <persName>Musquis </persName>is a man of sound principles
and unshaken integrity, he has made a host of bitter <persName>enemies </persName>here
by his vote on the 1 Article and I fear will have an unpleasant time
in the permanent deputation.</p>

<p>I think nothing ought to be said in the paper at present relative to
this law&#8212;or if anything is said, don't fail to compliment <persName>Musquis </persName>on
his vote against the 1 Article&#8212;on reflection I see no harm that can
arise from publishing the dictamen of the committee, and the names
of those who voted for and against&#8212;tho do as may be thought best.
It would be a very good opportunity to make some energetic but
 respectful remarks on the danger of violating the constitution, and on
the sacredness of that instrument etc&#8212;mention the thing to <persName>Wil-<pb n="647"/>
liamson </persName>and <persName>Luke</persName>. I have sent a copy of the law to <persName>Alaman</persName>, and to
<persName>Teran </persName>so that they may not attribute the results which may happen
from its publication in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, to any but to the true cause.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
