<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4348">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Archibald Austin to Stephen F Austin, 05-22-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Archibald Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-24">09-24-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 772-775
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-05-22">05-22-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-24" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Live oak for ship building.  Emigration.  European news.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[New York, May 22, 1831.]</p>
<p>it is only temporary, this of course can be onely conjecture with
him, as it must depend on the political elements of <placeName>Europe</placeName>, whether<pb n="773"/>
tween <placeName>France </placeName>and some of the <placeName>other powers of the Continent</placeName>, and
will probably burst forth ere a great while, the <persName>french Government
</persName>have managed to prolong the time, like throwing water on a fire
you may smother it, yet not extinguish it, it will flash out 
occasionally, and then all is dark again, so they appear to manage,
they are not ready yet, and the probability is that the <persName>government</persName>
would prefer to have a continuance of peace, but the materials are
too combustible, they will have war or another revolution must
be the result&#8212;</p>

<p>My request to <persName>Mr Burgh </persName>was that he would give the particulars
in the way that he would like to receive the oak at his yard, which
he promised to do, and desired me to give him a call when it 
arrived&#8212; He told me they formerly sent moulds, but he prefers
it according to his directions, He sais <persName>men </persName>ought to be employed,
from the <placeName>north </placeName>who are acquainted with the manner of cutting
Timber of this discription&#8212;<persName> Mr. B.</persName> builds most of our <placeName>Havre</placeName>
packets, and many of the <placeName>Liverpool</placeName>, however Hy knows all about
him&#8212; You should be careful he sais not to send cedar, that has
any worm holes in it, as they generally penetrate into the heart of
it, and then it is good for nothing, not even for firewood&#8212; What
you say in regard to the<hi rend="italic"> new concern</hi> is just what I anticipated,
and told <persName>John </persName>long ago that I was confident you would not. I
shall not say anything about it, and have told <persName>John </persName>he must be
particular not to speak of it&#8212; They consider it quite an enigma
that you should be averse to this <persName>Government </persName>obtaining that 
<placeName>Territory </placeName>by negotiation, they think you would be made immencely
rich almost immediately in that event and far more so than if it
remains as it now does, altho' they think in time, you will become
rich under the present <persName>Government</persName>, to be sure it does appear so,
but you ought to be your own <persName>counseller </persName>on that score&#8212; I 
forwarded your letter for <persName>Charles </persName>and wrote <persName>Henrietta </persName>at same time
relative to her <persName>son</persName>, who I believe is now in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>at <placeName>San Louis
de Potosi</placeName>, with his <persName>uncle</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>My <persName>children </persName>have sent me a letter of thanks to you for your kind
remembrances which I inclose&#8212; I am sorry to hear your health
is not reestablished yet, you propose making a trip this way, but
do not say when, your <persName>friends </persName>will be very happy to see you here,
and I think the change would be of great service to you, brace you
up, and hope restore you to perfect health, but you should manage
not to be here during the winter, for they are not only excessively
unplesant, but too tremindously cold, for any thing but an <persName>Esquimaux</persName>,
I fear it would be too much for you, and yet a <persName>West-Indian</persName> or one
that has been accustomed to that climate will come here in a 
debilitated state, and find the climate to agree with him, the cold resusi-<pb n="774"/>
tales him, and he feels like another man&#8212;-    I do not know that this
is [the] case generally, but I know of a few&#8212;</p>

<p>I saw <persName>Perry</persName>s advertisement in the <placeName>Texas paper, </placeName>so I conclud he
is there, just jog his elbow for me, by way of putting him in mind
that he was to write to me on his arrival there, I hope, he, his <persName>wife</persName>
and <persName>family </persName>are well,&#8212; Please remember me affectionately to them,</p>

<p><date when="1831-05-22">22 May</date> In the commercial of <date when="1831-05-17">19 inst</date> you will see something 
relative to the <persName>Galveston Bay and land Comp</persName> which looks very favorable
for them, I am told it is from our <persName>Charge d' affairs-</persName></p>

<p>After all the deprivations, toilsome and anxious life you have
been put to, you may well seek repose, and the oppy offering, I
am not surprised at your proposed arrangements for a quiet life,
ere you are too old to enjoy it&#8212; However I presume your intention
is to keep an eye to the <placeName>Colony</placeName>, you cannot divest yourself of the
pleasure of considering the prosperity of the <placeName>Colony </placeName>the main object,
after all the toil you have passed through, when it is so rappidly
marching on to the Zenith of its Glory, all Eyes are directed that
way with admiration and astonishment at the rise and progress of
it, and consider you as having performed prodigies, I was pleased
the other day to hear a <persName>Gentlemen of learning</persName>, and who holds and
has held many distinguished situations express many high encomiums
on your <placeName>Colony </placeName>and your management, he observed there never had
been any thing of the kind to equal it&#8212; You have unfurled your
colours, let them continue to wave in so noble a cause, you now will
give up the ship&#8212;22d&#8212;</p>

<p>not meeting with a good oppy to send my letter, I have left it
open to add whatever might occur interesting&#8212;</p>

<p>The Packet of the <date when="1831-04-15">15 ult</date>., from <placeName>England </placeName>brought news that the
<persName>Poles </persName>had defeated the <persName>Russians </persName>in which the latter lost 7000, and
some accts say 12000 men, <placeName>Lithuania </placeName>had revolted, <placeName>Sweden </placeName>was
about taking up arms to recover <placeName>Finland</placeName>, the <persName>Turks </persName>rebellouis, and
talking about commencing hostilities against <persName>Russia</persName>, <placeName>Austria </placeName>had
or was about withdrawing her <persName>troops </persName>from <placeName>Italy</placeName>,&#8212;and by another
packet a few hours later there was a report that the <persName>Russian General
Diebitsch</persName> had been taken <persName>prisoner</persName>, and the main body of his <persName>army</persName>
dipersed, such great Achievements by the <persName>Poles</persName>, caused a thril of
delight through this part of the <placeName>Country</placeName>, and a meeting is called
in this <placeName>city</placeName>, to congratulate the <persName>Poles</persName>, in regular form&#8212; <date when="1831-05-22">Yesterday</date>
we had a packet in from <placeName>France</placeName>, a little later, contradicting the
report of <persName>Diebitsch </persName>being taken-&#8212;</p>

<p>In <placeName>France </placeName>the people were very restless, several revolutionary
movements had taken place in <placeName>Paris</placeName>, and dispersed by the <placeName>national
Guards</placeName>&#8212;<pb n="775"/></p>

<p>I see by an extract from an<placeName> English paper </placeName>that hence forward all
the Ships of the<persName> Royal Navy</persName>, are to be built exclusively of English
and American Oak in equal portions&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>Galviston Company</persName> appear to have been for some time past
in Statu quo, The Steps<persName> Colo Bradburn </persName>took on the arrival of the
<persName>Emigrants </persName>sent out by them put them hors de Combat, but they
appear to consider all in a fair train again, I have called Several
times to see one of the concern to make some inquiries, but have not
been able to see him&#8212;</p>

<p>The last accounts from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>say the Treaty between that
<placeName>Country </placeName>and this was already to be signed, and would be dispatched
in the Lavinia now on her passage to this place&#8212;</p>

<p>As I have understood that <persName>Henry </persName>was to return to <placeName>Texas </placeName>late in
<date n="04-xx-1831">April</date>, I presume ere this is there please tell him that I saw a letter
from his <persName>wife </persName>on <date when="1831-05-17">Thursday evening last,</date> saying she and her <persName>family</persName>
were all very comfortably situated in <placeName>New Haven </placeName>and waiting
anxiously for the time for them to embark for <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>tell him also that we have now a Steam Boat plying between this
and<placeName> New Haven</placeName>, that leaves here in the <date when="1832-05-23">morning </date>at 7 O'Clock, and
returns the same day&#8212; remember me to him,&#8212; wishing you
better health,</p>

<p><persName>A A</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>When you write again I should like to hear something about the
live oak, the quantity size situation etc&#8212;that I may be able to
answer some of <persName>Eckford</persName>s and <persName>Burgh</persName>s inquiries about it, from what
I have already heard about it, I should suppose it must be very
valuable&#8212;</p>

<p>[addressed:] <persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName><placeName> Sn Felipe de Austin Texas&#8212;</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
