<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4501">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>D W Anthony to Stephen F Austin, 12-26-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>D W Anthony</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-09">11-09-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 910-911
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-12-26">12-26-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Discussing policy to be followed in seeking reform. His editorial policy.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Austin</placeName>,<date when="1832-12-26"> Decr, 26th [1832]</date></p>
<p>Dear Sir:</p>

<p>I had hoped to find you here, or at least that you would have 
arrived during my stay, as the principal object of my visit was to 
obtain a title to the lands I have selected, etc.&#8212;which it seems could not
be effected without your presence.</p>

<p>If it be beyond the reach of your power and option, to extend the
quantity of land to more than 1/4 of a League, will you have the
goodness to assist me in obtaining a <placeName>grant </placeName>from such authority as is
requisite, if you think an application for that purpose would not be
fruitless. I perceive that either a discretion has been confided to
you, of else by means of petitions etc, great inequality in the 
quantity of <placeName>lands </placeName>granted to different <persName>individuals </persName>has been effected, and
I hope if there be any such capacity, either which you have, or may
be obtained to increase the quantity of land which I may be entitled
to receive, that you will not be reluctant to aid me in its acquisition,</p>

<p>I have had the pleasure of seeing your letter of<date when="1832-12-20"> 20th inst.</date> to the
<persName>Central Committee</persName>, with the contents of which communicating the
result and success of your visit to <placeName>Bexar</placeName>, I am highly delighted, I
sincerely hope you may not be deceived in the constancy and 
firmness of the people with whom you have been in conference.</p>

<p>I am much pleased with the state of feeling prevailing, and the
prospect of effecting the great objects we have proposed for 
ourselves&#8212;but I do not see much harmony in the design of a remon-<pb n="911"/>
strance, which must include the idea of submission on conditions
of redress, and contain the request of the people to govt, to grant
a mitigation and redress of grivances&#8212;and at the same time that
there should be going forward a solm and firm determination of
the same people to form a <persName>separate government</persName> and remedy the
evils of which they complain,&#8212;and without any intention of turning 
back, or giving up that determination. Such I understand to
be the actual state of things. The <persName>Central Comt</persName>. have ordered a
positive and unconditional call of a convention. The people with
whom you have been in communication have remonstrated, and
expect the same thing to be performed by the <persName>people </persName>and 
<persName>Authorities of the whole <placeName>country</placeName></persName>. Should what is complained of be listened
to, and acted upon favourably by the present <persName>state Go[vt]</persName> how will
we stand, or how will we proceed? I hope you, and all of us will
not be unable to solve the dilemma, when it presses itself upon us.
But at present it has not a very seemly, or very sincere appearance.
Let us make the good of our country our motto, and our highest
maxim.</p>

<p>I shall be glad to hear from you, which I should at any rate 
expect, as soon as you return. I look for <persName>Grayson </persName>every day, having
lately heard from him, and with him I expect my <persName>brother</persName>, etc.
Their land affairs too, I hope you will not forget.</p>

<p><persName>D W Anthony</persName>.</p>

<p>[Addressed] <persName>Col. Steven F. Austin</persName>  <placeName> San Felipe</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
