<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4682">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 10-06-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-11">2-11-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Cap. H. J. Offutt
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Prison of the Deputation</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp.  6-8
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-10-06">10-06-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Slow progress of his case. Enemies in Texas and in Mexico, and the causes of their enmity. Loyalty to Mexico and benefits to the people of Texas repaid by ingratitude. Hope of relief in the rise of Santa Anna</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[From the Williams Papers. Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Texas.]</p>
<p>In the <placeName>Prison of the Deputation</placeName> or <placeName>Carcel de Ciudad</placeName></p>
<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date n="10-6-1834">October 6 1834</date></p>

<p><persName>S. M. Williams</persName></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>I wish you to close and finish all my business and affairs in conjunction
with my <persName>brother in law James F. Perry</persName> and give him all the aid you can in
so doing&#8212;deliver to him all notes and accounts due me, my desk trunks
papers etc also copies certified of all my land titles and inform him when
each tract must be settled so as to comply with the law in every particular&#8212;
I rely on you and him to save my property from total ruin and I have
confidence that every honest man in <placeName>Texas </placeName>will aid you both in so doing.</p>

<p>I was removed to this <placeName>prison </placeName>on the <date when="1834-09-19">19 ult.</date> and an investigation of my
case has at last commenced by the district <persName>Judge D. Martinez de Castro.
</persName>I know nothing more than that evidence and circumstances and the say sos
of my <persName>enemies </persName>are collecting by the <persName>Minister Lombardo</persName>, all <hi rend="italic">ex-parte</hi>&#8212;he
expects, as I am told something more from <placeName>Texas </placeName>from <persName>agents </persName>there, and
in the mean time I am languishing here, and when at the end of six months
or a year it is thought that sufficient proof is collected, I shall then be called
on to disprove what is against me and of course shall have to send to <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>In short to sum up a long story in a few words, my <persName>friends </persName>in that <placeName>country</placeName>
may look on me as dead for a long time to come and probably for ever&#8212;
A frank manly, but mild and respectful representation from the <persName>people of<pb n="7"/>
<placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> in my favor would have set me at liberty long since and would do
it now&#8212;The <persName>President Genl Santana</persName> is friendly to me. So is the <persName>Judge</persName>
but what can they do against a host of bitter <persName>enemies </persName>which I made by 
opposing a <placeName>territory</placeName>, and others because I am a <persName>foreigner </persName>and hundreds 
because I have been active and successfull in settling, and others from envy
and others because they think I am wealthy and others because I am in
misfortune, what can the <persName>president </persName>and <persName>judge </persName>do against all this host with
the <persName>Minister Lombardo</persName> at their head, and especially when <placeName>Texas </placeName>is silent
as to me, or worse than silent for I am told that every thing that comes
from there is against me&#8212; My situation is desolate&#8212;almost destitute
of <persName>friends </persName>and money, in a <placeName>prison </placeName>amidst <persName>foes </persName>who are active to destroy me
and forgotten at home by those I have faithfully labored to serve&#8212; I have
been true and faithful to this <persName>Govt</persName>- and <placeName>nation</placeName>&#8212;have served them 
laboriously&#8212;have tried to do all the good I could to <persName>individuals </persName>and to the
<placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;have been a <persName>philanthropist</persName>, and I am now meeting my reward&#8212;
I expect to die in this <placeName>prison</placeName>&#8212; I have no reason to make any other 
calculation&#8212; It is hard and unjust and cruel&#8212;when I am dead justice will be
done me&#8212; I have performed my duty and my conscience is at rest&#8212;
Even the things that my <persName>enemies </persName>say were errors, were evidently intended
to benefit the public interest and advance the <placeName>country </placeName>and not to benefit
myself&#8212; But so be it&#8212; I have been the means of distributing many
millions of acres to make the fortunes of <persName>others</persName>, and I now doubt whether
I shall not have to depend on Charity for six feet of ground to sleep in
at rest&#8212; This is man and mankind&#8212;a picture of human life&#8212;</p>

<p>I send this by <persName>Cap. H. J. Offutt</persName>. I recommend him to you as an honest
man and a <persName>friend </persName>give him what information you can about the <placeName>country</placeName>,
he wishes to settle there&#8212; I again repeat, close all my affairs save my
property for <persName>sisters children</persName> and for my <persName>brothers little boy</persName> This is your
duty as a friend, and I know that you will faithfully comply with it If I
had eight or ten thousand dolls. I might get my liberty I think&#8212;but where
or how can I get that sum&#8212; I shall draw on <persName>Beeres &amp; St John</persName> for another
thousand as you wrote me <date when="1834-07-31">31 July</date> I could do&#8212;you and <persName>Perry </persName>can make
the arrangement to meet it&#8212; <persName>Colonel Butler</persName> has refused to give me up
one of my notes, the last one and the largest one you can see by his
receipt its amount&#8212;he says that <persName>Whitesides </persName>had no authority to draw on
me for the whole amount&#8212; <persName>Whitesides </persName>recept is in my desk, call on him
to pay the deficit or show authority to draw and settle that business.
<persName>Butler </persName>gave me up one note and <persName>Whitesides </persName>gave me up one&#8212;there were
three in all, and <persName>Butler </persName>still has one which he holds me accountable for
altho I have paid it to <persName>Whitesides </persName>Try and settle all my affairs&#8212; I wish<pb n="8"/>
to be square with the world and with mankind tho that is difficult for they
owe me much more than I do them&#8212; When I am dead they will pay&#8212;
they never pay the living</p>

<p>Remember me to <persName>Sarah </persName><persName>Mr. Scott</persName>, and to all others&#8212; My <persName>enemies </persName>are
quite welcome to all the tryumph and all the pleasure which they can
derive from my unfortunate and persecuted situation, one that I have
brought on myself by my honest efforts to serve them as well as every body
else&#8212; The day will come if honesty has not abandoned the earth when
they will meet with their reward from public opinion&#8212; As for me I shall
die, as I expect to do in <placeName>prison </placeName>and under persecution, but with a clear and
quiet conscience&#8212; Remember me to <persName>Ramon Musquis</persName> I shall always
respect him and also <persName>Victor Blanco</persName>&#8212; nothing in my favor need be sent
to <persName>Lombardo the present minister</persName></p>

<p>My only hope now is the expected change of politics, govt. or system, or
something, that all look for in <date n="01-xx-1835">Jany- next</date>&#8212; If that change gives <persName>Santanna</persName>
absolute power or extra facultades I shall be set at liberty&#8212; I think also
that <persName>Alaman </persName>will then come into office and if so I shall be set at liberty&#8212;
he is my friend and he is an honest man as well as an able one&#8212; you
are all prosperous and safe in <placeName>Texas </placeName>because you are far removed from
the convulsions of this distracted <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;you are all far beyond the
reach of harm&#8212;may you be so for ever and rise in prosperity and 
happiness.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p>P. D. remember me to <persName>H. Austin</persName> and show him this, request him to
write to <persName>H. Meigs</persName> and to thank him for his kindness in my favor it 
however has availed me nothing as yet but I hope may when the expected
change takes place in <date n="01-xx-1835">Jany-</date> you must not write to <placeName>this place</placeName> all is 
perverted against me&#8212;everything.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
