<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4668">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to E. W. Gregory, 08-26-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-09">12-09-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        E. W. Gregory
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Brazoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1085-1086
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-08-26">08-26-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-09" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Loyalty to Mexico. Political news. Santa Anna.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1834-08-26">26 August 1834</date></p>
<p><persName>Mr. E. W- Gregory</persName></p>

<p>Dear Sir. I enclose you a letter for my <persName>brother in law Mr.
James F. Perry</persName>, of <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>which I must beg the favour of you
to forward by the first safe opportunity</p>

<p>I am still in confinement but expect a favourable change in my
situation soon</p>

<p>The political affairs of this <placeName>country </placeName>are all quiet I have no doubt
that the political intentions of the <persName>President Gen Santa Ana</persName> are
sound and patriotic, he wishes to get a <persName>general congress</persName> togather
in <date n="01-xx-1835">January next</date>, freely elected by the <persName>people</persName>, with the powers of a
National convention in order to reestablish the Constitution which
has been so dreadfully outraged by all parties that none respect it. I
do not think he has designs to change the system of Government.
At least not in its principal features. He has put a stop to the system
of banishment and imprisonment, and recalled all the banished a
very just humane and necessary measure.</p>

<p>The past events in <placeName>Texas </placeName>have cost me very dear. I was 
precipitated into them by the excitements and circumstances of the times It
is a consolation to me that I am the only one who has suffered by
them and that much good has resulted to <placeName>Texas </placeName>and also to the
<placeName>Mexican republic </placeName>from those events. The evils complained of in
<placeName>Texas </placeName>have been remedied by the <persName>government </persName>on the one hand and
on the other the <persName>people </persName>of the <placeName>country </placeName>have become convinced of the
dangers of political excitements and of listening to political fanatics
and political adventurers they will consequently be on their guard<pb n="1086"/>
against such dangers in future. My motto always has been <hi rend="italic">Fidelity
to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, opposition to <persName>violent men</persName> or measures</hi> it is the only
sound rule for <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I am more convinced of it now than ever, tho
I never doubted it notwithstanding it would seem as tho I had in one
single act and for a moment departed from it, but I never did.</p>

<p>When I left <placeName>Texas </placeName>in <date n="04-xx-1833">April 1833</date> the <persName>people </persName>there were determined
to have a state. As the <persName>agent </persName>for those people it was my duty to
promote that determination but neither the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> nor
myself have ever in the least failed in our duty as <persName>Mexican Citizens
</persName>and there never has been any kind of design or plot to separate <placeName>Texas</placeName>
from the <placeName>Mexican republic</placeName>. All the rumors and reports and 
suspicions that have been circulated about me and about the <persName>people of
<placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> on this subject are uterly false and without the least 
foundation in truth</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>
<p><persName>Mr. S. M. Williams</persName></p>

<p>I annex a copy of a letter received by <persName>Mr. G </persName>about a hour ago <hi rend="italic">in
great haste</hi></p>

<p>Yours <persName>Henry [Austin]</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr. S. M. Williams</persName> <persName>McKinney </persName>&amp; <persName>Williams </persName><placeName>Brazoria
Texas</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
