<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4983">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Philip Dimmitt to Stephen F Austin, 10-25-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Philip Dimmitt</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-05-23">05-23-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Port of Goliad, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Head Quarters, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 207-209
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-10-25">10-25-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-05-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Answering Austin's orders for supplies. Local conditions </add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Port of Goliad</placeName>, <date when="1835-10-25">Oct, 25 '35</date></p>
<p>8 oClock in the evening.</p>
<p>To <persName>Gen Stephen F. Austin,
Com. in ch.</persName> of the <persName>Army of the People</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>Yours of the <date when="1835-10-21">21t. inst</date>., a postscrip to that of <persName>Padillo </persName>of the same date&#8212;
yours also of the <date when="1835-10-22">22d.</date> and <date when="1835-10-23">23d. instants</date>, and recd, at 4 oClock P. M. <date when="1835-10-25">to
day</date>, are duly noted.<pb n="208"/></p>

<p>The supplies which you call for shall be forwarded immediately. The
teams, 5 or 6 in number, and more if they can be procured, shall be put in
motion <date when="1835-10-26">tomorrow evening</date>, or <date when="1835-10-27">early next day morning</date>.</p>

<p>Nothing has transpired relative to our liability to attack at <placeName>this place</placeName>,
since the date of my last by hand of <persName>Mr Bracken</persName>, worthy your attention. At
the date of that communication, I addressed the <persName>people residing <placeName>east of the
Guardeloupe</placeName></persName>, urging the necessity of a reinforcement, and have much 
reason to expect some increase of force from the sections of Country 
mentioned in- yours of the <date when="1835-10-23">23d. inst</date>.</p>

<p>You enquire after <persName>Linn </persName>and <persName>Powers</persName>&#8212;Both, altho' absent at the moment,
have been with me, have acted in concert, and have been very useful to the
service. They will probably return <date when="1835-10-25">to night</date>, or <date when="1835-10-26">tomorrow</date>. <persName>Col. Powers</persName>
became very much alarmed for the safety of his people, (nearly all the men
being here,) occasioned by information received by him from a <persName>confidential
friend at <placeName>San Patricio</placeName></persName>: In consequence of which, steps have been taken to
remove the <persName>women </persName>and <persName>children</persName>,<placeName> beyond the Guardeloupe River</placeName>. Being
informed that this removal is now nearly, or quite accomplished I expect
to see the <persName>Emprisario of <placeName>that Coloney</placeName></persName> here immediately. Supplies for the
poor of these <persName>families</persName>, and for <persName>recruits</persName>, have been forwarded hence to the
<placeName>Town of Guardeloupe Victoria</placeName> This step was recommended too, by the
possibility of our being compelled to fall back on that point&#8212;one of the
most defensible, by a <persName>small force</persName>, of any whatever in <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>For some reason or other the people of<placeName> this place</placeName> have nearly all left
<placeName>town</placeName>. I have done, and have said, every thing which I could do, or say,
to pacify and inspire them with confidence&#8212;But they had seen the brilliant
equipment of <persName>Cos</persName>, his sword, and retinue; and they had listened to his 
flattering and captivating speeches; they had attended his parties, and tasted
his wine: But we have made no such display&#8212;we have no epaulettes, nor
swords&#8212;we have given no dinners, no parties&#8212;and as to wine, we have
none to use in the way he used it.</p>

<p>Immediately after the occupation of this <placeName>fort </placeName>by the <persName>force </persName>then 
commanded by <persName>Capt. Collinsworth</persName>, two <persName>Volunteers</persName>,<persName> John Williams</persName> and <persName>John
Tool</persName>, were dispatched to <placeName>San Patricio</placeName>, <persName>express</persName>, with letters to the <persName>Alcalde
of that jurisdiction</persName>, and to others, soliciting their cooperation. <persName>Tool </persName>and
<persName>Williams </persName>were both surrendered to the <persName>military of Le Panticlan</persName>, put in
irons, and compelled to work on the <placeName>Garrison</placeName>.</p>

<p>We are informed also, that, the population of <placeName>San Patricio</placeName>, have almost
unanimously joined the <persName>military</persName>.</p>

<p>The supplies spoken of above, will be forwarded to the <placeName>Ranche of <persName>Don
Erasmo Seguin</persName></placeName>, about <placeName>10 leagues below Bexar</placeName>, under the safe conduct of
<persName>Maj. George Southerland</persName>, with <persName>20 men</persName>. You can therefore, make such<pb n="209"/>
arrangements for their transportation thence to <placeName>Head Quarters</placeName>, as you shall
deem most advisable. By <persName>Maj. Southerland</persName>, I will write you again.</p>

<p>It will be impossible for us to supply <persName>Don Juan Seguin</persName> with arms&#8212;We
could furnish powder, also small shot, which may be run into bullets&#8212;and
we can send him as much subsistence as he will probably need. <persName>Zentena</persName>
is at <placeName>Le.Panteclan</placeName>, and writes to me, that, he intends establishing the 
<placeName>Custom House</placeName> at that point. I doubt his fidelity.</p>

<p><persName>P. Dimmitt</persName> Comg</p>
<p>[Addressed:] To <persName>Gen. Stephen F. Austin Com. in Chief of The Army of
the people.</persName> <placeName>Head Quarters</placeName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
