<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4070">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Ayuntamiento of San Fellipe, 11-05-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-08-31">08-31-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Ayuntamiento of San Fellipe
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 527-528
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-11-05">11-05-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-08-31" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Assuring it that he will expel certain undesirables from the colony.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            
<p>To the Illustrious <persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>of the <placeName>Municipality of Austin</placeName>,</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of the official 
communication, made to me by that corporation, dated <date when="1830-11-04">yesterday</date>, and
a copy of the resolutions, adopted on the<date when="1830-11-02"> 2nd inst</date>. relative to the
removal from this <placeName>colony </placeName>of certain <persName>persons </persName>therein named, of 
<persName>notorious-infamous character</persName>; and recommending a rigid scrutiny as
to the conduct of certain others, before they are received as <persName>settlers</persName>.</p>

<p>The 5th article of my contract with the <persName>government </persName>for the 
settlement of this <placeName>colony</placeName>, is in these words, "It shall be an obligation
upon him (<persName>Austin</persName>,) not to admit <persName>criminals</persName>, <persName>vagabonds</persName>, or <persName>men of
bad character</persName>, and he shall cause all those of this description who
are found within his limits to leave it, and should it be necessary, he
shall put them out by force of arms."</p>

<p>The 122d article of law No. 37, prescribing duties of the 
<persName>Ayuntamientos</persName>, says: " They shall not permit in their <placeName>jurisdictions</placeName>, 
<persName>vagabonds</persName>, <persName>drunkards</persName>, <persName>gamblers </persName>by profession, nor any other idle or
<persName>vicious people</persName> who have no visible means of subsistence, etc. etc."</p>

<p>The above mentioned 5th article of my contract has imposed a
very heavy and responsible obligation upon me, and one which
from its nature, might necessarily involve much delicacy and ought
to require great prudence in its execution. This has never been
more particularly the case, than at present, for heretofore the ex-<pb n="528"/>
pulsions of bad men ordered by me, have been made, solely on my
own individual responsibility, without the powerful support of a
special recommendation to do so, from <persName>municipal representatives</persName> of
the people.</p>

<p>The situation of this <placeName>country </placeName><placeName>on the borders of a foreign nation
</placeName>certainly exposes it to impositions by criminal <persName>fugitives </persName>and 
<persName>vagabonds</persName>, who are nuisances in all <placeName>countries</placeName>, but more especially so
in a new and thinly settled one like this. The first <persName>settlers </persName>who
have devoted years of hardship to bring it forward, justly deserve
and have a right to expect protection from such <persName>nuisances</persName>. The
<persName>Government </persName>has offered the most liberal inducements to honest
<persName>emigrants</persName>, but nothing to <persName>fugitives </persName>or, <persName>vagabonds</persName>, and it expects
and commands that no such shall be admitted. It is therefore due
to the <persName>people </persName>who are permanently settled&#8212;to the law&#8212;and to
the government, that the 5th article of my contract, and the 122nd
article of law No. 37 which I have quoted, should be rigidly 
executed; always, however keeping in view what is due to justice and
to humanity.</p>

<p>The measures which I have heretofore deemed it my duty to
adopt on this subject, have been promptly executed by the <persName>militia
officers</persName> charged therewith, and they have been sustained by public
opinion, which in this <placeName>colony </placeName>has always been on the side of good
order, and opposed to the admission of<persName> bad men</persName>. But 
notwithstanding this, it is with great satisfaction, that I find the 
<persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>co-operating by the weight of its authority and influence, in
a measure which might be construed by the designing, or the 
everscrupulous, into an act of oppression, or as being too strong for
mistaken ideas of liberty. I have therefore to assure that 
corporation, that the removal of <persName>Peter Whetstone</persName>,<persName> Trammel Pryor</persName>, <persName>John
or Jack House</persName>, and <persName>Brooks Williams</persName>, which is recommended by it,
shall be immediately ordered; and that the course will be adopted
which is indicated, with respect to the other individuals named in
said resolutions.</p>

<p>I embrace this opportunity to present to that illustrious 
corporation the assurances of my consideration and respect; and of my
hearty co-operation in all measures which are calculated to promote
the public good, and to inforce the laws.</p>

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin,</placeName> <date when="1830-11-05">Nov. 5th 1830.</date></p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>,</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
