<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4239">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William H Wharton to Stephen F Austin, 07-14-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William H Wharton</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-12">09-12-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Home</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Brazoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 672-673
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-07-14">07-14-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Wants to buy some land from Austin and to have a general understanding with him.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>At home</placeName> <date when="1831-07-14">July 14th 1831</date>.</p>

<p><persName>Colonel Austin</persName></p>

<p>D Sir. You must excuse me for again troubling you on the 
subject of the <placeName>land I wish to purchase of you.</placeName> I would thank you to
send by My <persName>Brother </persName>your obligation to convey to me so much <placeName>land</placeName><pb n="673"/>
when such a price per Acre is paid. If you have any difficulty about
the quantity to be expressed in the obligation, say <placeName>100 Acres</placeName>, if you
think this too much say enough to cover the emprovements I have
already made which would not exceed <placeName>10 or 15 Acres</placeName>. I cannot
conceive that you would hazard any thing by doing this, and I
should in the event of a transfer or of death be and feel much more
secure. Some future <persName>owner </persName>of the land unaware of what has passed
between us or disregardful of it, might take advantage of the
improvements I have made on the land in question and incommode
me materially by refusing to sell altogether or by asking ten prices.
You doubtless recollect that a short time previous to your departure
for <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>you told me to go on with my building that I should
have the small amount I wanted. I should therefore think that I
ought to get the <placeName>lands </placeName>at the price you would have put upon it
<date n="Fall-1831">last autumn</date>, without regard to its subsequent enhancement. This
would seem to me to be right, should you think differently however
I must acquiesce, not hereby insinuating that I believe you capable
of taking advantage of my situation, Defer not this on account
of haste or occupation or amusement for the penning of the 
obligation will not take up 2 minutes of your time. Were you here
I would show you conclusively that the quantity of <placeName>land </placeName>I want
ought properly to belong to mine and would not diminish the
value of yours, your <placeName>league </placeName>from the <placeName>Brazos </placeName>runs <placeName>across the prairie
</placeName>and takes in about <placeName>30 or 40 Acres of the Oyster Bayou</placeName> timber not
enough timbered land for a <placeName>settlement </placeName><placeName>on the Oyster Bayou side
of the prairie</placeName>, it is out of the question to cart that timber across
the <placeName>prairie</placeName>. But of this when you come down. I am anxious to
see you at my <placeName>house </placeName>not more on account of the land than for other
reasons. Our personal intercourse has always been of an undefined
negative and unconfidential character, which I am sick of and
wish to put an end to for the future. However indifferent I may
feel toward the <hi rend="italic">million </hi>in my likes and dislikes of <persName>gentlemen </persName>with
whom I am brought in contact I have no middle ground. I go in
this case for open war or confiding friendship. If nothing has
occurred on the part of either [of] us to prevent mutual friendship
and esteem, let an ecclairissement place us in that delightful 
relation to each other, if on the contrary there should be found to be
cause for hostitity and enimity let it be avowed and aboveboard.
At all events let us understand each other.</p>

<p>Be so good as to present my regrets to <persName>Mr Wm T Austin</persName> on
account of not being able to comply with his polite invitation, With
the hope of soon seeing you I remain yours Respectfully</p>

<p><persName>Wm H Wharton</persName></p>

<p><persName>Colonel S. F Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Col S. F Austin </persName>  <placeName>Brazoria</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
