<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4725">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to J. F. Perry, 02-06-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-16">02-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Mr Peter W. Grayson
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J. F. Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Brazoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 41-42
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-02-06">02-06-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Publication of his pamphlet has created good feeling. Trouble with Anthony Butler. Plans for the future</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1835-02-06">Feb. 6, 1835</date></p>

<p>Dr. <persName>Brother</persName>,</p>

<p>I send you by <persName>Mr. [Peter W.] Grayson</persName> a copy of the exposition I have
published, defending the<persName> people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, and myself. I wish you to
preserve it, as I find I shall have no copies left. I think I shall leave in
ten or fifteen days for <placeName>Monclova</placeName>. I am waiting for the publication of the
general amnesty law, which it is said will be done <date when="1835-02-07">tomorrow </date>or <date when="1835-02-08">next day</date>,
when I shall be free once more for I am still on bail.</p>

<p><persName>Col Butler</persName> has refused to give me up my last note of 1900 and odd
dollars which I paid to <persName>Whitesides </persName>alleging that <persName>Whitesides </persName>had drawn on
me for more than he was authorised to do. <persName>Whitesides </persName>receipt as <persName>Butlers agent</persName>is in my desk and I wish you to see him, and let him know that if
<persName>Butler </persName>refuses to give up my note I shall hold <persName>Whitesides </persName>responsible.
He must show his authority from <persName>Butler </persName>to draw.</p>

<p>If you can get along without selling land I wish you to do so, as it
will be a sacrifice to sell now. The <placeName>league adjoining and below St. Felipe</placeName>.,
and the one <placeName>on the West Bernard (a prairie league)</placeName> must not be sold for
any price as I may dispose of it otherwise. I send you some seeds. I refer
you to <persName>Mr Grayson</persName> for all the news. I hope that a dead calm will reign
all over <placeName>Texas </placeName>for many years to come&#8212;and that there will be no more
excitements of any kind whatever.</p>

<p>Cotton will be high here <date n="xx-xx-1836">next year</date>. There are a great many <placeName>large factories</placeName>
building in various places by <persName>foreigners</persName>&#8212;the demand for <placeName>Texas </placeName>cotton
will be very great, deliverd at <placeName>Vera Cruz.</placeName></p>

<p>I do not write to my <persName>friends</persName>, because I cannot write to all, and <persName>Grayson</persName>
can tell them all the news.<pb n="42"/></p>

<p>I look forward with the most heartfelt anxiety to the period when I
shall be restored to you all once more, so that I can enjoy your society
and that of my <persName>friends </persName>in a <placeName>log cabbin</placeName>, or a <placeName>camp</placeName>&#8212;far very far from
the intrigues and vilinous intanglements of <placeName>palaces </placeName>and politics.</p>

<p>My opposition to a <placeName>territory </placeName><date n="xx-xxx1834">last year</date> has been the main cause of all my
entanglements&#8212;but I did my duty and under the same circumstances I
would do again just as I did in <date n="xx-xx-1833">1833</date>.</p>

<p>I have more <persName>friends </persName>here now than I ever had, and so has <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;my
exposition has had a good effect&#8212;tho I am told that I shall be attacked in
the <placeName>newspapers</placeName>, or that a reply will be given to it etc. I fear nothing
from such an attack.</p>

<p>Remember me to all your <persName>neighbors </persName>and my <persName>friends </persName>in general when
you see them and to <persName>J. H Bell</persName> and the <persName>Jacks</persName>, <persName>McKinny</persName>, <persName>Miller</persName>, <persName>Martin</persName>,
<persName>Burnett </persName>etc in particular</p>

<p>Love to all the <persName>children</persName>. I hope they are learning fast. Love to <persName>Eliza</persName>
and <persName>Phillips</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>Mr Grayson</persName> has a project to establish a <placeName>cotton factory</placeName> by a <persName>company</persName>
which I am much in favor of and have authorised him to take stock for me.
<placeName>Texas </placeName>has cost me trouble and labor enough, and I hope yet to see some
happy days there. I have seen but few as yet. I presume my friend <persName>S. M.
Williams</persName> is at <placeName>Monclova</placeName>, for which reason I do not write to him. I 
requested you and him to distroy the letters I sent by <placeName>Offutt </placeName>without showing
them to any one, which I hope was done. Calm, a <hi rend="italic">dead calm</hi>, is all that
<placeName>Texas </placeName>needs&#8212;make good crops, and send them to <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, <placeName>Tampico </placeName>etc.
Remember me to <persName>H. Austin</persName> and his <persName>family</persName>. Tell them to keep up good
spirits&#8212;the dark days have passed, if you can only keep good health.
your affectionate <persName>brother</persName></p>

<p><persName>Stephen</persName>.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr. James F. Perry</persName> near <placeName>Brazoria Texas</placeName> <persName>Mr Grayson</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
