<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4974">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>R R Royall to Stephen F Austin, 10-21-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>R R Royall</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-05-23">05-23-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
                <person>
                    <persName type="sender">
                        Ths Barnett Esqr
                    </persName>
                </person>


                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Bexar, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 199-201
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-10-21">10-21-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-05-23" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Pressing problem of finding revenue to meet demands made on permanent council. Zavala advises tariff</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe</placeName> <date when="1835-10-21">21st October 1835</date></p>
<p><persName>Genl. S. F. Austin</persName></p>
<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>In continuation of my correspondence I will explain to you that you will
find in Our <placeName>news Paper</placeName> your Letter from <placeName>Gonzales </placeName>on <date when="1835-10-13">13th </date>couched in
Discouraging terms. I will Inform you that I had no Intention of 
Publishing that Letter and very much disapprove of it <persName>Mr Borden</persName> who has
always heretofore exercised discretionary Powers, over our Public Papers
Borried your letters under promise to examine them and with hold from
the Press such as was Improper for publication when I found it had gone
out in the <placeName>Paper</placeName>, it was too Late to recall it, I will only now cause to be
published in our next the flatering prospects, of the Present time to 
counteract any Effects, of this <placeName>paper</placeName>.</p>

<p>Our <placeName>House </placeName>has Grown a little thin of <persName>members </persName>[There] have several left
within the Last few days, generally with an understanding to return to the
Convention. <persName>Govnr. Zavala</persName>, has still chills and Fevers he joins us 
occasionally and is of opinion that the three <persName>officers </persName>(<persName>Prisoners</persName>,) here are not
to be relied on as, <persName>friends to the Americans</persName> not one of them but still says,
they are <persName>Gentlemen </persName>and may be trusted on Parole he advises, the retaining
of them till <placeName>Bejar </placeName>falls and says further that the return of <persName>Capt. Saviego</persName>
will not benefit us, to use his Term that he will Blacken our name. The
<persName>officers </persName>appear well satisfied at their treatment but want leave to Return
which the <persName>Council </persName>has Unanimously Refused</p>

<p>The <persName>Council </persName>feals Great Solicitude for the Success of the cause in which
we are Engaged and it has now become necessary to adopt some measure
to cash the Drafts Drawn on us by the <persName>contractor </persName>and <persName>Captain of 
Companies</persName>. We have Passed Resolutions authorizing <persName>Comdts. of Companies</persName><pb n="200"/>
to Draw on the <persName>Council </persName>for supplies for <persName>troops <placeName>on the Road to head 
Quarters</placeName></persName> we have also addressed a letter to <persName>Beason </persName>stating that such Drafts&#8212;
would be Honoured and have forwarded copies to <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>, how these
Extensive and Very necessary demands are to be met, the <persName>Council </persName>has 
requested me to make known their wishes to the <persName>members of the Convention
<placeName>in Camp</placeName></persName> for their advise and for their approbation so far as we have gone.</p>

<p>We will <date when="1835-10-21">this morning</date> authorise our <persName>Commissioners </persName>to go to the <placeName>Red
Lands</placeName> to collect all Public dues from the <persName>Authorities </persName>there so far as that
<placeName>Quarter </placeName>has not a use for and to Contract for Loans of money as we are
told Money has been proposed by <persName>men in that <placeName>Quarter</placeName></persName> we will make a
Simular appointment here pledging the Public Faith and Revenue of our
<placeName>Ports </placeName>as security. I am not certain that we can do much here something
has been talked of Loaning but whether they Really will or not is 
uncertain on tomorrow we will make an experiment. <persName>Majr Saml Whiting</persName>
offered me $1000 it will be well for you to receipt for it and forward it
to this Place as I am confident we will need it in a few days a[s] yet all
calls have been Punctually met.</p>

<p><persName>Govnr Zavala</persName> is of opinion that we should proceed to make 
appointments and collect duties according to <placeName>U. States</placeName> tariff the <persName>Council </persName>feals the
necessity approaching, but fears the responsibility of such a proceedure
as the <persName>People of our <placeName>country</placeName></persName> have been looking forward to the acts of the
Convention and would not likely recognise the <persName>Council </persName>in such acts of
Responsibility of this particularly the <persName>council </persName>requests to be instructed by
the <persName>members in <placeName>camp</placeName></persName> provided they cannot return shortly to make a sitting
of the convention. Something will have to be done shortly to replenish our
finances If <placeName>San Antonio</placeName> holds out and as money is the spring of every
thing it will be by no means amiss to have a surplus on hand, It will Give
confidence. The <persName>members in <placeName>camp</placeName></persName> can suggest other plans perhapse, we
are but a few and would like to hear of their views and will do every thing
to forward our comon Cause. It is also in contemplation to Pass a 
resolution requiring all dues for <placeName>Lands </placeName>to the State to be paid in to Persons
appointed by the <persName>Ayuntomientoes of <placeName>each Municipality</placeName></persName> and put a Note in
the <placeName>Paper </placeName>requiring <persName>all persons of <placeName>Austin</placeName></persName> to make payment to <persName>Gail Borden
jnr.</persName> how far this may meet the necessities or whether in time you [know
best?] Our <persName>committee </persName>is now in sitting on the subject of mails I 
believe they will report in favor of two routs being established Immediately
one to the <placeName>Red Lands</placeName> and to the <placeName>Sabine </placeName>the other to <placeName>Liberty </placeName>I have
thought this essential as it has only been for want of Information that
<persName>troops </persName>have not been from the <placeName>Eastward </placeName>some time ago and at this 
juncture it is more Important as all is on the tiptoe of Expectation. There is
great Delicacy manifested in taking steps of Legislation [as] far as we
do but we fear very much the convention cannot meet as soon as proposed<pb n="201"/>
and If so it will be Indispensable for the <persName>members in <placeName>camp</placeName></persName> to Give us their
approbation and recommend further assumption of responsabilities.</p>

<p><persName>R. R. Royall President council</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Genl. S. F. Austin Commander in Chief</persName> <placeName>Head Quarters
Near Bexar</placeName>&#8212;By <persName>Ths Barnett Esqr</persName>&#8212;</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
