<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4527">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Oliver P Jackson to Stephen F Austin, 02-10-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Oliver P Jackson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-11">11-11-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 926-928
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-02-10">02-10-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Asking information about Texas, and prospects for practice of law.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date when="1833-02-10">February. 10th 1833</date></p>

<p>I presume to address you on a subject which has occupied, more
or less my attention for the last two years, viz, a permanent residence<pb n="927"/>
in the <placeName>Texas Country</placeName>. Circumstances have prevented me from 
carrying my wishes into effect thus far, and being now at <placeName>N. Orleans
</placeName>where I have been residing for the <date n="11-xx-1832">last three months</date>, my wishes
strongly combining with the facility of reaching the <placeName>Spanish 
Country</placeName>, prompt me to carry my desire into effect. When I left <placeName>New York</placeName>
where my life thus far has been passed, to visit this place, I was
induced to believe from representations made me, that I should find
a lucrative practice in the profession of the Law in this city. Altho
I may not perhaps have given it fully a fair experiment, yet a strong
desire to live in a climate less fatal, and a country, less expensive, as
my means are limited, induce me to seek <placeName>Texas </placeName>as a country more
congenial in most respects to my wishes, and I flatter myself to my
future prospects in life also. Had I have determined upon settling
in your <placeName>country</placeName>, when I left<placeName> N York</placeName>, I should have brought to you
introductory letters from your <persName>cousin</persName>, I believe, with whom I am
well acquainted, having boarded with him upwards of a year&#8212;I
mean the <persName>Mr. Austin</persName>, who is with a <persName>Mr. Harmony, a Spanish 
Merchant of <placeName>N York</placeName></persName>&#8212; <persName>Mr. A.</persName> has told me that he intended settling
in the <placeName>Texas </placeName>soon himself. <persName>Mr. Meigs</persName> family of <placeName>N York</placeName>, (whom I
have often heard speak of you and <persName>Cap. Austin</persName>,) I am intimately
acquainted&#8212; I presume you were formerly acquainted with my
Father, <persName>Amasa Jackson</persName>, who married the daughter of <persName>Oliver Phelps
of <placeName>Suffield, Connecticut</placeName></persName>. My <persName>Father </persName>was for many years a <persName>Merchant</persName>
in <placeName>New York</placeName>, and became unfortunate a short time before his death
which happened about seven years ago. Should your answer to this
communication be at all favourable, so as to justify my visiting your
<placeName>country</placeName>, I will endeavor to visit it immediately, and will bring with
me from this place such letters as will be satisfactory to you. I have
mentioned the above, thro, fear that you may [receive] many 
applications of this sort, from <persName>worthless persons</persName>, as the idea is somewhat
prevalent that the <placeName>Texas </placeName>is resorted to by those, and those only from
the <placeName>U States,</placeName> who are ruined in property and character. To be 
candid with you Sir, I would say, that I am poor&#8212;, willingly, ardently
willing to engage in any honourable occupation for a livelihood.
Misfortune has hitherto attended my steps, and being yet in the 
meridian of life, I am very solicitous in your new and rising colony, to
lay the foundation for future success and happiness. If you can
afford toe the least gleam of hope, I will embrace it with eagerness
and will endeavour to the extent of my limited ability to promote
the interests of your <placeName>flourishing colony</placeName> in every practicable
manner&#8212;</p>

<p>May I then request you, Sir, to address me at this place as soon as
may be practicable, imparting to me such information in reference
to my locating in your <placeName>country</placeName>, that I may act upon it with due
deliberation.   Naught, but the most serious obstacles will prevent me<pb n="928"/>
from becoming a <persName>resident </persName>of that land, so that I feel myself prepared
to suffer many trying inconveniences. I have attended to my 
profession, which has been that of the Law, tho I have had in the last few
years experience in mercantiling pursuits-&#8212; I am now engaged in
the <persName>profession of Law</persName> in this place. I shall await the recpt. of your
Letter with some impatience, and I must again beg you to excuse
the liberty&#8212;   I have taken in troubling you on this subject.</p>

<p><persName>Oliver P. Jackson</persName></p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Col. Stephen Austin </persName>  <placeName>San Felippe Texas</placeName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
