<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4863">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Wyly Martin et al to Stephen F Austin, 09-05-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Wyly Martin et al</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-03-11">03-11-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Peach Point, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 112-114
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-09-05">09-05-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-03-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Arranging escort of honor to accompany him into San Felipe. Note by Gail Borden on joy of the people at Austin's return </add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe </placeName><date when="1835-09-05">Sept. 5th 1835</date></p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>A meeting of the <persName>people of this place</persName>, with a number of very respectable
<persName>citizens of the <placeName>surrounding country</placeName></persName>, was called this day, to adopt the most
appropriate measures for welcoming you to your <placeName>adopted country</placeName> and to
the bosom of your <persName>friends </persName>and <placeName>country </placeName>for this purpose, the undersigned,
a <persName>committee </persName>appointed by the meeting to carry their wishes into effect;
have dispatched <persName>Mr. J Borden</persName> one of their body to wait upon you, and
request you to have the goodness to inform them, at what time it will suit
your convenience, to meet them at <placeName><persName>Capt Alien</persName>s</placeName>, to the end that they may
have the honor of accompanying you into the town of<placeName> San Felipe</placeName>, where
you will meet many of your long established <persName>friends</persName>, all prepared to receive
you with open arms and with acclamations of Joy.</p>

<p>We tender to you our respect and most exalted consideration.</p>

<p><persName>Wyly Martin</persName></p>
<p><persName>J. H. Money</persName></p>
<p><persName>A. W. Ewing</persName></p>
<p><persName>Geo. Ewing</persName></p>
<p><persName>Joshua Fletcher</persName></p>
<p><persName>Thos. Gay</persName></p>
<p><persName>John P Borden</persName></p>
<p><persName>Col. S. F. Austin</persName><pb n="113"/></p>

<p>[note]</p>

<p>The sentiment of congratulation expressed by the <persName>committee </persName>appointed
by the <persName>citizens of the <placeName>municipality of Austin</placeName></persName> was responded to by all the
<persName>people of whatever party</persName> throughout the <placeName>country</placeName>. This meeting as well
as those held at <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>, <placeName>Columbia </placeName>and other places, can but faintly
express at this day, the feelings of Joy and pleasure on the return of <persName>Austin</persName>.
They looked upon the event as one which would settle all their doubts as
to what should be done, and as one which would, as it proved, unite all
<persName>parties </persName>of which the <persName>committee </persName>was composed.</p>

<p><placeName>Peach Point</placeName> <date when="1844-02-06">6th Feby 1844</date></p>

<p><persName>G. Borden, Jr</persName></p>

<p>[note]</p>

<p>As evidence of the feeling which prevailed, we need only have recourse
to the many congratulatory letters written to him from <placeName>all parts of the
country</placeName> from the <persName>best and most distinguished citizens</persName>. Even his <persName>enemies</persName>
and some who had threatened in his absence to brand him with infamy
were constrained to greet him as the only physician that could correct the
disorganized system and restore a healthy action to the body corporate.</p>

<p>The entire confidence which <persName>all parties</persName> had in <persName>Austin</persName>'s superior 
knowledge in whatever related to the <placeName>country</placeName>, his zeal and untiring perseverance
to promote its interest, and his integrity and virtue were sufficient reasons for
the influence which his return was calculated to produce upon the 
<persName>community</persName>. The question may have occurred to those unacquainted with the
peculiar situation of the country at that time, Why was not <persName>Austin </persName>placed
at the head of the <persName>provisional government</persName>? Because the disorganized and
unsettled condition of the <placeName>country </placeName>required his action in another sphere.
His extensive correspondence and presence among the <persName>people </persName>exerted a far
greater influence than he could have done at the head of a government little
more than nominal. This may be inferred from the earnest and general
solicitation of the <persName>people </persName>that he should take command of the first army.
They said "his presence in the field will inspire a confidence in the 
hazardous enterprize."</p>

<p>Again when it was thought necessary to send <persName>commissioners </persName>to the <placeName>United
States</placeName>, who but <persName>Austin </persName>could better head the mission which, was intended
to lay before that <persName>people </persName>the true grounds of the contest, and thereby,
interest them in our favor? It is unnecessary to speak of the importance
of this mission. <persName>Twenty-five or Thirty thousand people</persName> without any 
preparations for war without resources contending against <persName>Eight millions</persName>.
If a <persName>Frankland [Franklin]</persName> was called upon to interest the <placeName>European nations</placeName>
in behalf of the <placeName>thirteen colonies</placeName>, who in <placeName>Texas </placeName>more suitable than <persName>Austin</persName><pb n="114"/>
to be entrusted with the important mission. The administration of 
government could be intrusted to others. But it must not be supposed that <persName>Austin</persName>
withheld his aid in directing the Executive and legislative operations of the
country: His opinions were asked for and sought by those departments,
and the numerous communications made by him to the <persName>provisional 
government</persName> on every subject touching the welfare of the <placeName>country </placeName>prove how much
the administration of affairs was indebted to his experience judgement
and skill.</p>

<p>Those acquainted with the condition of the <placeName>country </placeName>at the time, knew
and appreciated the influence which he exerted as <persName>Secretary of State</persName> under
the first organization under the constitution, and which office he accepted
at the earnest solicitation of men who were convinced of his preeminent
abilities in negociating a connection with the <placeName>United States</placeName> which was so
much desired at the time. It should be remarked that the <persName>friends of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>
looked upon <persName>Austin </persName>as the man best qualified to bring about the annexation
to the <placeName>United States</placeName>, a measure to which he lent all his energies and which
was the occasion of his death.</p>

<p><persName>G. Borden, Jr</persName>.</p>

<p><placeName>Peach Point</placeName> <date when="1844-02-07">7th Feby 1844</date></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
