<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4120">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Mary Austin Holley to Stephen F Austin, 01-02-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Mary Austin Holley</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="1831-01-02">09-02010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 570-571
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-01-02">01-02-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="1831-01-02" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Biographical.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans,</placeName> <date when="1831-01-02">January 2, 1831</date></p>

<p>My dear <persName>Cousin</persName>,</p>

<p>I am far from having forgotten you or your visit to <placeName>Greenfield</placeName>,
as you suggest in your letter to my <persName>brother John</persName>. Indeed, I often
find myself employed in tracing the progress of the " <persName>puny boy</persName>,"
through the daring career of the<persName> enterprising man</persName>. Little did either
of us, at that time, contemplate the condition in which the present
anniversary finds us. I have been more frequently led to these
reflections since I have been living comparatively near to you&#8212;since<pb n="571"/>
I have been left alone to mark out the future destiny of myself and
my <persName>son</persName>. More particularly with regard to my <persName>son </persName>I have thought
I would write to you and renew our acquaintance, in order to learn,
what prospect <placeName>Texas </placeName>would offer to him, looking some distance a
head: whether it would be an object for me to take any steps with
such views&#8212;securing land&#8212;etc. He is a boy of twelve, has talents
enough, but as yet I can not decide whether they will be marked
by the love of literature of his <persName>Father's family</persName>, or the love of 
enterprise of mine. His education is before him, and occupies all my
cares. I have thought too, if my <persName>brothers </persName>could make it their
interest to remove to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, we could there together build up our
fallen <persName>family </persName>in new hopes and happiness. I am sure my <persName>brother
Henry's family</persName> might be happier there <hi rend="italic">together </hi>than separated as
now. I am happily and usefully situated where I am but I am
<hi rend="italic">alone</hi>, and think&#8212;I am sure&#8212;I should prefer a place of tolerable
comfort, <hi rend="italic">entirely my own,&#8212;a permanent home</hi>, to all this luxury,
with dependence in the least possible sense. Do I deceive myself?
I saw your letters to my <persName>brothers</persName>, and <placeName>pamphlet </placeName>while in<placeName> New York</placeName>.
Are there persons among you who want education and 
accomplishments such as I could give if that would be necessary, after a year
or so? Be so good as to write me on these points, and others 
concerning your self.   Direct <placeName>New Orleans, </placeName>Care of <persName>Michael Fortier Esq</persName>.</p>

<p>I have taken this moment to write from the possibility that my
<persName>brother Henry</persName> may be with you, and he will thereby hear from me,
while a letter directed to him might benefit neither him nor yourself
if he should not be there.</p>

<p>Is your <persName>Sister </persName>and <persName>her family </persName>with you.</p>

<p><persName>Mary Holley</persName></p>

<p>I lately heard from <placeName>N York</placeName> and <placeName>New Haven</placeName> all well. I am
obliged to hurry to send my letter.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] To,<persName> Col: S F Austin</persName> <placeName>St Filippe de Austin Texas
Mexico</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
