<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4615">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to  Rafae Llanos, 01-14-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-02">12-02-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         Rafae Llanos
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monterrey, Nuevo Leon</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1027-1033
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-01-14">01-14-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-02" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Announcing arrest, explaining his purposes in Texas, and showing need of reform.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Monterrey</placeName>, <date when="1834-01-14">January 14, 1834</date>.</p>
<p><persName>Señor Don Rafael Llanos</persName>.</p>

<p>My dear Sir : In times of political disturbances like those of the
past year it is difficult to have any relations whatever with political
affairs without becoming entangled in some way or other, now with
<persName>parties</persName>, now with <persName>individuals</persName>, now with the <persName>authorities</persName>. Thus it is
that I have fallen into the net, and was arrested on the <date when="1834-01-03">3d of this
month</date> by order of the <persName>minister of war</persName>, and depart in a few days for
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>as a <persName>prisoner</persName>.</p>

<p>From what I have said to you in our conversations concerning
<placeName>Texas</placeName>, you will have understood that that <placeName>country </placeName>was exposed to
anarchy for the want of adequate <persName>local government</persName>. During the
<date n="Winter-1833">winter of last year</date> there was strong sentiment, in fact, for an 
organization of the <persName>local government</persName>, always as an integral part of the
<placeName>Mexican federation</placeName>.</p>

<p>The energetic representations of the <persName>ayuntamientos </persName>and towns of
<placeName>Bejar </placeName>and <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>, dated <date when="1832-12-19">December 19, 1832</date>, demonstrate with
sufficient clearness the evils of <placeName>Texas </placeName>and the aroused feeling of those
towns over the torpor of the population and the backwardness of
<placeName>Texas </placeName>through inadequate legislation and the neglect of its best and
dearest interests. The great majority of the people expressed their
opinion in favor of separation from <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>, and their 
determination to so organize if there were no other remedy. The <persName>Convention</persName>
framed the memorial of <date when="1833-04-13">April 13 [1833] </date> to the <persName>general 
government</persName>, asking that <placeName>Texas </placeName>be erected into a state of this federation,
and nominating me to carry it to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. It appears that since
then some <persName>ayuntamientos </persName>have changed their opinion because they
believe that the <persName>people </persName>ought not to have petitioned for erection
into a state under Article 2 of the organic law of the <persName>General 
Constituent Congress</persName> dated <date when="1824-05-07">May 7, 1824</date>, without the previous consent
of the <persName>Legislature of <placeName>Coahuila </placeName>and <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>. But they do not mean
to be understood by this as being content with their situation.   They<pb n="1028"/>
desire radical remedies, and only believe that they have mistaken
the means to obtain them. Concerning this point, it must be said
that at that time (<date n="11-xx-1832">November </date>and <date n="12-xx-1832">December, 1832</date>) <placeName>Texas </placeName>was almost
in a state of nature as to government&#8212;and perhaps one would not
venture much in saying that the whole <placeName>republic </placeName>was in the same
situation,&#8212;so that the wisest were divided in opinion whether or
not we had a legitimate <persName>government</persName>, or whether the Constitution
still existed.</p>

<p>I did not know of this new attitude of the <persName>ayuntamientos </persName>until
<date when="1833-11-05">November 5 [1883]</date> at the conference of <persName>ministers </persName>called by the
<persName>President</persName>, at which you assisted, when <persName>Señor Blanco</persName> brought it out.
I therefore acted in conformity with the instructions given me by
the convention in <date n="04-xx-1832">April</date>.</p>

In <placeName>Mexico </placeName>I did all that I could to obtain the prompt and 
favorable dispatch of the petitions of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, or busied myself to obtain
such things as the repeal of the 11th Article of the law of <date when="1830-04-06">April 6,
1830</date>, exemptions from the tariff, the regulation of the mails, the
payment of the presidial companies; in short, anything to calm
and content the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>.

<p>At the <date n="10-xx-1833">beginning of October</date> I was discouraged and irritated by
an incident or bad news or a mistake which occurred then, and lost
hope and patience, and in that moment wrote to the <persName>ayuntamientos
of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> recommending that they consult among themselves in order
to organize the <persName>local government</persName> in union and harmony, in case the
<persName>General Congress</persName> did nothing to remedy the evils of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I had
also an other reason which influenced me to make this 
recommendation: at that time, the result of the revolution was, in the opinion
of many, doubtful, and I knew very well that the <persName>inhabitants of
<placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> were decided to revolt rather than submit to the domination
of the <persName>Church party</persName>. In such case it would have been much better
for the interest of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, of the <persName>popular party</persName>, and of the <placeName>republic</placeName>
that it be organized in union and harmony, by agreement and 
approbation of the <persName>local authorities</persName> and under their direction than to
proceed by means of a popular uprising without the intervention
of any authority.</p>

<p>Thus my recommendation was entirely conditional, subject to
the developments of the future, a precautionaiy measure and 
nothing more. As soon as <persName>Arista </persName>surrendered and the 11th Article of the
law of <date when="1830-04-06">April 6, 1830</date>, was repealed, I informed the <persName>ayuntamientos</persName>,
and in so doing believed that I had revoked the recommendation
made in my letter of <date n="10-xx-1833">October</date>, because it was made under the 
supposition that nothing would be done.<pb n="1029"/></p>

<p>I understand that I am arrested for having written that letter of
<date n="10-xx-1833">October </date>to the <persName>ayuntamientos</persName>, and that the <persName>governor of the state</persName> is
my <persName>accuser</persName>, but I do not know certainly whether this is true or not.</p>

<p>All that I have done in this matter has been public and without
concealment. I wrote to the <persName>ayuntamientos </persName>officially, and not 
confidentially or privately. I did not leave <placeName>Mexico </placeName>until <date when="1833-12-10">December 10</date>,
more than two months after writing the letter. I took leave of
the <persName>Minister</persName>, of the <persName>Vice President</persName>, and of my <persName>friends</persName>; travelled in
a coach with <persName>Deputy Don Luis de la Rosa</persName> as far as Lagos; and
thence by <placeName>San Luis Potosi</placeName> to <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>, presenting myself at the
moment of my arrival there to the<persName> Commandant General</persName>. I had
started by the most direct road to <placeName>Monclova </placeName>to see if it was possible
to obtain some laws for <placeName>Texas </placeName>in conformity with the 
recommendations of the <persName>general government</persName> on the subject. I believe that if I
had been able to reach <placeName>Monclova </placeName>during the session of the 
<persName>legislature</persName>, as I desired, it would have been possible to regulate the affairs
of <placeName>Texas </placeName>upon a basis satisfactory to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, to the state, and to the
<persName>general government</persName>. It would have been very easy to go to <placeName>Vera
Cruz</placeName> and embark for <placeName>Orleans</placeName>, if I had thought that I had 
committed a crime that deserved punishment. The truth is that the hope
of accomplishing some good for the contentment of <placeName>Texas </placeName>caused
me to go by land, although the trip is much more severe than a
voyage to <placeName>Europe</placeName>.</p>

<p>In so far as there may be crime in having labored thirteen years,
spending a life of weariness, in peopling the <placeName>wilderness of Texas</placeName>;
in having spent my time and my money in a journey to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>to
obtain relief from the evils which afflict <placeName>Texas </placeName>and threaten its ruin
and even its separation from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>; in measures to save that 
country from a violent revolution; in having assisted in establishing the
foundations for the prosperity and security of the <placeName>frontiers of
Coahuila, Nuevo León, and Tamaulipas</placeName> and the advancement of those
states in population, industry, and agriculture&#8212;in so far as there may
be crime in all this, I am a great criminal.</p>

<p>Without population in <placeName>Texas </placeName>the <placeName>frontiers of the Eastern 
Interior Provinces</placeName> are worse than nothing, for they are an abandoned
field where the <persName>Indians </persName>may rob, kill, and destroy to suit their fancy,
without protection for the wretched <persName>people</persName>. It would be an 
enormous expense to maintain <persName>garrisons </persName>and <persName>troops </persName>enough to restrain
the <persName>Indians </persName>even in a small degree in deserts so vast.</p>

<p>I have been accused of having magnificent schemes for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and
I confess that I have had them.</p>

<p>My friend, I am a <persName>Mexican citizen</persName>, and as such I shall speak with
entire frankness: To suppose that the <placeName>Mexican nation</placeName> in its present<pb n="1030"/>
situation, immersed in clouds of prejudice, and backward in 
everything, can advance rapidly of itself alone and reach the level of other
<placeName>nations </placeName>without drawing learning, industry, and population from
abroad is almost the same as to imagine that the <persName>Mexicans </persName>of the
time of <persName>Cortés </persName>could have advanced to where they now are without
knowing any other people or having had communication with any
other nation in the world. The <placeName>United States of the North</placeName> were
much more advanced at the time of their independence than the
<persName>Mexicans</persName>, and yet they needed learning, arts, and population from
abroad. Upon the same policy are based my schemes for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and
for all the <placeName>eastern frontier</placeName>. It is depopulated; I wish to people it.
The population that is there is backward; I wish it to be advanced
and improved by the introduction of industrious agricultural <persName>settlers</persName>,
<persName>liberal republicans</persName>. I want the savage <persName>Indians </persName>subdued; the <placeName>frontier</placeName>
protected; the lands cultivated; <placeName>roads and canals</placeName> opened; river
navigation developed and the <placeName>rivers </placeName>covered with boats and barges
carrying the produce of the <placeName>interior </placeName>to the <placeName>coast </placeName>for export in 
exchange for <placeName>foreign </placeName>products, thereby saving the precious metals
which are now our only medium of exchange; I wish to take from
my<placeName> native land </placeName>and from every other <placeName>country </placeName>the best that they
contain and plant it in my <placeName>adopted land</placeName>&#8212;that is to say, their best
<persName>inhabitants</persName>, their industry, and their enlightenment, so that the
<placeName>eastern frontier</placeName> which is now without population and in its greater
part almost without government, might present an example worthy
of imitation. These are the magnificent, and as it now appears,
visionary, plans which I have held for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and for all this
<placeName>frontier</placeName>; and if there is a <persName>Mexican </persName>who does not wish to see them
realized, I must say that he does not love his <placeName>country</placeName>; neither wants
to see her emerge from the darkness of the fifteenth century nor
shake off the chains of superstition and monastic ignorance which
she is still dragging along.</p>

<p>Very little do they know me who believe that I have sacrificed the
best years of my life in the <placeName>wildnerness of Texas</placeName> to gain a fortune!
I have not gained it, and I could have lived in comfort in a <placeName>settled
country</placeName>. I entered <placeName>Texas </placeName>in <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821 </date>an enthusiastic <persName>philantropist </persName>and
now at the age of forty I find myself on the verge of misanthropy,
tired of men and their affairs, and convinced that I wished to finish
in a few years the work of a century. I have seen the <placeName>United States
of the North</placeName> make every effort to attract population, knowledge, and
capital from <placeName>abroad </placeName>for its development. I have seen a <placeName>wilderness</placeName>
covered with a dense population in a few years, and <placeName>new states</placeName>
erected where at the time of my birth there was not a single civilized
person. I believed that it would be the same with the free and
nascent <placeName>Mexican nation</placeName>.   I see that I was mistaken.   Before <placeName>Mexico</placeName><pb n="1031"/>
can develop in that manner she must pay the price by a moral 
revolution in which shall be overthrown all the customs and the Gothic
politico-religious system set up by <placeName>Rome </placeName>and <placeName>Spain </placeName>to hold the
people in subjection like beasts of burden&#8212;such a revolution she
will have in a century but not in the life time of one man.</p>

<p>You have been my <persName>friend </persName>since <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date>, and I owe you a frank 
expression of my thoughts. In this letter I have told all my desires
and dreams for <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I was not born in a <placeName>wilderness</placeName>, and have
not the patience of the <persName>Bexareños </persName>and other <persName>inhabitants of this
<placeName>frontier</placeName></persName> who are daily enduring the same dangers and annoyances
that their <persName>fathers </persName>and <persName>grandfathers </persName>and perhaps their <persName>great-grand-
fathers</persName> suffered, without advancing a single step or even thinking
of advancing. Death is preferable to such stagnant existence, such
stupid life.</p>

<p>I am very grateful to your <persName>brother, Don Manuel</persName>, I and to the
<persName>Commandant General</persName>, <persName>Don Pedro Lemus</persName>, and to all here for the
kindness which they have shown to me.</p>

<p>Please show this letter to <persName>Don Victor Blanco</persName> and to <persName>Don Teodoro
Rivarol</persName> and tell them that I put their letters for <placeName>Monclova </placeName>in the
mail here.</p>

<p>I remain your very sincere friend, etc.</p>

<p><persName>Estevan F. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p>P. S.&#8212;I wish you would also do me the favor to show this letter
to <persName>Señor Rejón</persName>. I should be sincerely sorry if that patriot and
eloquent defender of liberty and reform should have erroneous
ideas concerning this matter. I understand that the foundation
of the political creed of that gentleman is that we should proceed
firmly and unwaveringly with the system of radical reforms until
the life and habits of the mass of the <persName>Mexican people</persName> are entirely
in harmony with the form of government adopted by the <placeName>nation</placeName>.
This also is the object of my efforts in the little sphere in which
I have worked.</p>

<p>In the <placeName>United States of the North</placeName> the government was adapted
to established practices. In <placeName>Mexico </placeName>the process has been the reverse
of this. Here it is necessary to shape habits and customs to the
system of government; and it is due to this fact that the <placeName>nation</placeName>
has encountered so much difficulty in consolidating itself.</p>

<p>Customs are not changed or corrected by theories nor by oral or
written preaching, no matter how clearly reasoned and eloquent
it may be, without some practical and palpable application to the
life and understanding of the mass of the <persName>people</persName>. I wished to
make this application in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and so, progressively, throughout
the <persName>Rio Grande frontier</persName>; at the same time strengthening the political<pb n="1032"/>
and economic relations of that remote section of the <placeName>Republic </placeName>with,
the other states by direct representation in <persName>Congress</persName>, by improved
roads, and by <placeName>interior </placeName>and <placeName>coasting </placeName>trade.</p>

<p>Taking a general and impartial view of the matter, with the
government settled, it is very evident that it is not to the interest
of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to separate from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>even if she were free to do so.
But on the other hand it is well known that men are influenced more
by petty local annoyances or grievances in the present, even though
temporary, than by the hope of great benefits in the future. One
may call the grievances of <placeName>Texas </placeName>temporary, but they are not petty;
they are very serious. And it is from this that opinions arise that
there is a conflict between the union of that country with <placeName>Mexico</placeName>
and its progress and happiness. This opinion is erroneous, for
nothing is easier than to remove that conflict and remedy the present
local evils in <placeName>Texas </placeName>by an organization of its <persName>local government</persName> in
conformity with the experience and particular needs of that 
country&#8212;that is, to erect it into a state of the <placeName>Mexican Federation</placeName>.
Doing this will fulfill, moreover, the object and the principles of
the federal system, and will carry forward the important work of
reforming the ancient customs of the people which conflict with
the system, because there are none of these customs in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and
it is not possible to conceive that there will ever be any such.</p>

<p>Men of large conceptions are always exposed to attack as 
visionaries, ambitious and selfish <persName>schemers</persName>, deserving of suspicion, or
something else, particularly if their plans look to general and 
philanthropic improvements, because there are few who labor for anything
but their personal interest. In the colonization of <placeName>Texas </placeName>I have
wanted to make a personal provision for myself and for my <persName>family</persName>,
and if he who sows is entitled also to reap the harvest, I deserve it;
but at the same time I have wanted to confer upon my <placeName>adopted
country</placeName> a general benefit by peopling and redeeming from its savage
state an important part of its <placeName>territory</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have labored in good faith, exposing myself to all sorts of 
burdens and responsibilities for the good of my <placeName>country</placeName>; but at the
same time I have duties to the <persName>settlers </persName>who have emigrated to the
<placeName>wilderness </placeName>through my influence; and they owe a duty to themselves
and to their <persName>families</persName>&#8212;the duty and the right of self-preservation.
And if there were no other way to fulfil it but to separate from
<placeName>Mexico </placeName>and join the <placeName>United States of the North</placeName>, or maintain 
independence, it is very clear that it would then be their most sacred
duty to attempt it.</p>

<p>All that has been said by rumor and prejudiced reports about
projects in <placeName>Texas </placeName>for separation from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>is false. There have
not been and are not now any such projects.   What is wanted there<pb n="1033"/>
is an organization of the <persName>interior government</persName> in order to avert 
disorders, disturbances, and divisions which would undoubtedly 
terminate in a revolution.</p>

<p>I have said and I believe that <placeName>Mexico </placeName>should either establish the
<persName>local government of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> or sell it to the <placeName>United States of the
North</placeName>, in order to get some profit from it before losing it, and the
<persName>Mexicans </persName>with whom I have talked and who thoroughly understood
the matter are of the same opinion.</p>

<p><persName>Estevan F. Austin</persName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
