<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4858">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>John R. Jones, Jr to Moses Austin Bryan, 09-01-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>John R. Jones, Jr</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-03-11">03-11-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Moses Austin Bryan
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 109-110
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-09-01">09-01-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-03-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Political gossip and resolutions adopted by a meeting at San Felipe on August 26</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe</placeName> <date when="1835-09-01">Sept 1st 1835</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Friend</persName></p>
<p>I received yours dated the <date when="1835-08-14">14th of August 1835</date> I have been wating
with a great deal of patience, to hear from you. I had given it out, from
ever hearing from you again but to my great surpise, I received a letter
from you, I have been as I concieved it negligent, for not writing you
sooner but I beg to be excused, I have been busy doing some little
business for the <persName>political chief</persName> and attending to other affairs that it was
almost impossible for me to write you, I am in great hopes you will be
more regular in writing to me, than you have been heretofore, and I will
do the same, our <placeName>village </placeName>has been and is yet in such a state of confusion,
that I scarcely once thought of you a few of the <persName>individuals of <placeName>Columbia</placeName>
</persName>have come to this place and held their meeting. It was termed by several
in fact numbers that it was a <placeName>Columbia </placeName>meeting, and not a <placeName>San Felipe</placeName>
meeting there were some three or four that attended it, the rest stood
off and gazed on but said nothing. the principal part of the<persName> people of <placeName>San
Felipe</placeName></persName> are opposed to a convention or any thing resembling it after the
meeting was adjourned there were some 10 or 12 perhaps more talking
about politicks, and amongst the rest <persName>Wharton </persName>spoke very precipitate about
<persName>Capt Bird</persName> although they were perfect <persName>strangers </persName>to each other, our <persName>Capt</persName>
heard him then there were some words passed and <persName>Bird </persName>went immediately
and got his rifle, and came back, and wated for a chance to single him
from the rest to kill him, but was prevented by some of his <persName>friends</persName>. <persName>Bird</persName>
told him he had him in his power and could use him up if he saw proper.
I was informed by several that was present and saw it. give my respects
to the <persName>family </persName><persName>Mother </persName>sends her compliments to the <persName>family </persName>and is very
sorry to inform them that she is very ill and also <persName>Milam</persName></p>

<p><persName>John R Jones jr</persName> [Rubric]</p>

<p>News has arrived a few days since that there were <persName>6 hundred troops at
<placeName>San Antonio</placeName></persName></p>

<p>I send you a copy of the resolutions that were passed at the Town of
<placeName>San Felipe</placeName> held on the <date when="1835-08-27">27th of Aug 1835</date></p>

<p>At a meeting of the <persName>citizens of the town of <placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName></persName> held
on the <date when="1835-08-26">26th Inst</date> at the <placeName>tavern of <persName>Johnson </persName>and <persName>Winburn</persName></placeName>, <persName>Judge Geo Ewing</persName>
was called to the <persName>chair</persName>, and <persName>Spencer H Jack</persName> elected <persName>Secretary</persName>.</p>

<p>After expressing the object of the meeting <persName>Patrick C Jack</persName> submitted to
the following resolutions were adopted.<pb n="109"/></p>

<p>Resolved That in all <placeName>republican countries</placeName> the voices of the <persName>majority</persName>
should prevail.</p>

<p>Resolved That <placeName>Texas </placeName>is now in a state of anarchy and that nothing but
a consultation of the<persName> people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> at large, can restore quiet and 
concerted action and we therefore recommend a consultation.</p>

<p>Resolved That we heartily approve of and adopt the resolutions and
proceedings of the <placeName>Jurisdiction of Columbia.</placeName></p>

<p>Resolved That we solicit and respectfully invite the <persName>citizens </persName>generally
of this <placeName>Jurisdiction </placeName>to meet at this place on the <date when="1835-09-12">12th of Sept</date> to express their
opinions upon the subject embraced in the foregoing resolutions.</p>

<p>Resolved That the <persName>chairman </persName>nominate <persName>five Gentlemen</persName> as a committee
to notify the <persName>citizens of the whole<placeName> Jurisdiction of Austin</placeName></persName> of the meeting
to be held on the<date when="1835-09-12"> 12th of the present month</date> in pursuance of the foregoing
resolutions.</p>

<p>Whereupon Messrs <persName>John H Money</persName>, <persName>H. C Hudson</persName>, <persName>Patrick C. Jack</persName>, <persName>Wm 0.
Huff</persName>, and <persName>John B. Johnson</persName> [were appointed]</p>

<p><persName>Geo Ewing chairman</persName></p>

<p><persName>Spencer H Jack secretary</persName></p>

<p>I will also give you a copy of <persName>Cos </persName>communication in which you will see
it on the other side.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
