<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4856">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title> Horatio Allsberry to Public, 08-28-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName> Horatio Allsberry</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-03-11">03-11-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Public
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Columbia, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 107-108
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-08-28">08-28-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-03-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Mexican designs against Texas.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>To the <persName>People of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>.</p>

<p>Arriving this day from <placeName>Monterray </placeName>the <placeName>capitol of the state of of New
Leon</placeName>, which place I left on the <date when="1835-08-10">10th inst</date>. and being requested by the
<persName>Chairman of the Committee of Safety and Correspondence for the 
jurisdiction of <placeName>Columbia</placeName></persName>, to detail the information which I possess in regard to
the designs of the <persName>Mexican Government</persName> towards the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>,
I make the following communication, for the truth of which I stake my
reputation, and appeal to time to establish every fact herein stated: I left<pb n="108"/>
the <placeName>state of New Leon</placeName> on the <date when="1835-08-10">10th of this month</date> with a request from our
<persName>republican friends</persName> to say to the <persName>citizens of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> that our only hopes of
<hi rend="italic">future liberty and security depended upon our immediately</hi> taking steps
to oppose the <persName>military </persName>in their establishing a <persName>Central Government</persName> or an
arbitrary despotism which is without doubt their intention.</p>

<p>I have been for the last few years a close <persName>observer </persName>of their movements
respecting <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I have frequently conversed with their <persName>principal men,
Civil, Military and Ecclesiastical</persName>.</p>

<p>I may say almost daily for years, and particularly since the downfall of
<placeName>Zaccatecas</placeName>, about their intention toward <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and I can assure you that
this is their intention; first, to move large numbers of <persName>troops</persName>, at least
thousands to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, for the purpose of being at hand when the change of
Government takes place, which change is intended for next month; 2d.
to establish their <placeName>posts </placeName>or <placeName>Custom houses</placeName>; 3d. Using their own language
to burn the <placeName>houses </placeName>and drive from the <placeName>country </placeName>a number of our <persName>principal
citizens</persName> which they have, and have had on a list for a year past, principally
those that were engaged with the <persName>soldiers </persName>three years since; 4th. put their
<persName>slaves </persName>free and let them loose upon their <persName>families</persName>, as they express 
themselves; and 5th- call up the <persName>empresarios </persName>and demand of them their colonizing
contracts with the <persName>Government</persName>, and say to them you are here authorised
to settle so many <persName>hundred families</persName>, instead of which you have settled
thousands of <persName>families</persName>.&#8212;I replied to them that there had been decrees of
Government permitting emigration of <persName>foreigners </persName>and the sale of <placeName>lands</placeName>
to which they say that these decrees emanated alone from the government
from or through the intrigue of <persName>Empresarios </persName>or the all powerful influence
of a few doubloons; and that these <placeName>lands </placeName>must be given up for their own
<persName>natives</persName>.</p>

<p>I have seen <persName>Gentlemen from different parts of the Government</persName>, 
<hi rend="italic"><persName>responsable Gentlemen</persName></hi>, all <persName>foreigners </persName>who passed <persName>troops </persName>on every <placeName>road </placeName>Marching
for <placeName>Texas</placeName>; one Gentleman from <hi rend="italic">Mexico </hi>told me that the complaints from
<placeName>different sections of the Country</placeName> to <persName>Foreign Ministers</persName> have lately been so
loud and numerous, together with a late attempt to rob the <persName>foreigners</persName>&#8212;
and some insults given to a British armed vessel off <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, by the
<persName>officers of the <placeName>Castle</placeName></persName> would, as he was told by the <persName>English Minister Mister
Packingham</persName> bring down a declaration of war upon them by the <persName>British
Government</persName>. These facts with the outrageous conduct of the <persName>Commandant
now at <placeName>San Antonio</placeName> (Col. Condey)</persName> calls loudly for immediate steps to
be taken for our preservation. These facts are stated by request and for
the benefit of the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>. I pledge my life and honor that these
Statements are correct.</p>

<p><persName>Horatio A. Alsberry</persName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
