<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4697">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William H Wharton to Public, 11-09-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William H Wharton</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-14">02-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Public
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Eagle Island, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 25-26
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-11-09">11-09-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">A card denouncing Austin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>a card</p>

<p>A printed letter dated <placeName>PRISON of the Ocordado</placeName>, <placeName>city of Mexico</placeName>, <date when="1834-08-25">August
25th 1834</date>, has this moment met my eye. Among other false and ridiculous
things it contains many grave and damning charges preferred against
myself. When I first saw this letter; I was in common charity disposed
to believe some <persName>enemy of Austin's</persName> had forged it, for the purpose of holding
him up to public derision and scorn, by exhibiting in ludicros contrast his
former and present opinions or rather PROFESSIONS; for I could not
imagine that any man of common sense would append his name to such
a bloated mass of disgusting self conceit&#8212;of arrogant dictation, and of
inconsistent stupidity. My opinion of the forgery was abandoned, however,
when I learned this FAMOUS document issued from the press under the
auspices of his devoted <persName>personal friends</persName> and of the relation to whom it
was addressed.</p>

<p>I <hi rend="italic">had </hi>hoped that my political career and with it my political dissentions
had terminated. At the close of the last convention I deliberately resolved
to withdraw from all public employment whatever, and for the future, to
seek peace and retirement in the bosom of my own family far&#8212;far, and
<hi rend="italic">forever </hi>removed from the bustle and contention&#8212;the hopes and the honors
of political life. This resolution has been, up to this period, strictly 
adhered to; for since that time I have been more secluded from the public
eye, than the <persName>writer </persName>from the <placeName>PRISON of the Ocordado</placeName>; I have confined
myself exclusively to the pursuits of agriculture, and have not been ten
miles from home in the <placeName>colony of Austin</placeName>. This resolution I fondly wished
<hi rend="italic">still </hi>to adhere to, and would never have troubled the public with anything<pb n="6"/>
under my name, except for the wanton manner in which in this letter my
political reputation and domestic happiness have been assailed. But for
<hi rend="italic">this </hi>the follies the errors, and the inconsistencies of <persName>Austin </persName>might FOR ME
have slumbered in forgetfulness&#8212;or been remembered only to be laughed
at. If nothing else a sincere and tender regard for the feelings of many
individuals who are mutual friends would have prevented me from publicly
exposing him; since his unprovoked attack, however, all of these 
considerations go for NOTHING; and although his being a <persName>prisoner </persName>forbids a full
expose of his many misrepresentations at present; yet a high a sacred and
a never-to-be-forgotten duty which I owe to truth, to myself, to my family
and friends forces me to repel such CALUMNIES the moment they meet
my eye. Whether the <persName>calumniator </persName>be in the <placeName>PRISON of Ocordado</placeName>, or even
at the foot of the altar, I therefore pronounce his insinuations and assertions
so far as they charge me with perpetuating his imprisonment, rejoicing
at his sufferings, or attempting his ruin to be false. Yes! wilfully and
maliciously false.&#8212;Thus much for the present.</p>

<p>In conclusion, I pledge myself when this obeyer of instructions this man
of so many personal <persName>friends</persName>, this <persName>disinterested benefactor of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, this
oracular weathercock, this political Proteas this innocent victim, this maker
of mottos, this organizer of parties, this presumptious dictator returns,
to brand him on the forehead with a mark that shall outlast his epitaph.</p>

<p><persName>Wm. H. Wharton</persName>.</p>
<p><placeName>Eagle Island</placeName>, <date when="1834-11-09">Nov. 9, 1834</date>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
