<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4446">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to General William H Ashley, 10-10-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-10-21">10-21-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        General William H Ashley
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 871-874
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-10-10">10-10-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-10-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Describing recent events in Texas. Texas wants to be a state of Mexican confederation. Annexation to United States undesirable unless on terms agreeable to all parties.  Conditions may bring independence.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin (Texas)</placeName></p>

<p><date when="1832-10-10">October 10, 1832</date>.</p>
<p><persName>Genl Wm H. Ashley</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir, It is long since we have seen or heard of each other by
any direct intercourse, but I judge of you by myself when I say
that you have not forgotten your old <persName>townsman </persName>we have spent too
many pleasant hours together in <placeName>Potosi </placeName>for them to have passed
away from your remembrance,</p>

<p><persName>Sam P. Browne </persName>and <persName>John Rice Jones</persName> with their <persName>families </persName>are here
permanently settled, also my <persName>brother-in-law, James F. Perry</persName>, and
several others from <placeName>Washington County</placeName>; from them and other
sources I have heard of your prosperity and success in private and
in public life, which was highly gratifying to me.</p>

<p>My lot has been cast in the <placeName>wilderness</placeName>&#8212;a <persName>pioneer</persName>&#8212;you may
readily imagine that the change was a considerable one for me.
I recollect your taste for bear hunting and that I wondered at it,
for at that time mine did not incline much to such rude sports,
though I also recollect that when you and <persName>R. T. Brown</persName> and myself
were out on the <placeName>Boons Lick road</placeName> as <persName>commissioners </persName>to examine it,
he killed a large bear and I snapped at one and killed a cub, and
I thought it might be very fine sport&#8212;it was very exciting at least.
I am not now a good <persName>hunter</persName>, but I have entered much more into
the spirit of the thing than I then did and no longer wonder at
your fondness for the sport There is a freedom, a wide and wild
and elevated range of thought, as well as of action, in rambling
over the <placeName>verdant prairies</placeName>, and gentle undulations of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, where
every living thing you see gives evidence of equal freedom by
scampering and bounding before and around you, which 
<persName>persons </persName>who have all their lives elbowed their way through <placeName>crowded
streets</placeName>, know nothing about&#8212;I no longer wonder at the attachment<pb n="872"/>
of the savage for his <placeName>native forests</placeName>, or at his despair at seeing
them felled before the desolating sweep of civilization&#8212;desolating
indeed to the happiness, and the home of the <persName>natives</persName>. But so it is&#8212;
Nature has given to the <persName>whites</persName>, and to the<persName> red man</persName> a place on
earth, and habit and education, or superior intelligence, or 
accident, or what you may please seem to have so regulated matters
that their interest should run in opposite directions&#8212;a shock is, of
course, the consequence, and <hi rend="italic">power </hi>settles the affair, whether justly
or not is a question which belongs exclusively to <persName>theorists</persName>, for the
reason that the current of events in this particular can not be
stopped. It has flowed on, and onward it will flow, until the
<persName>Indians </persName>are swept from existence as a people and amalgamated with
civilization.</p>

<p>It is more than eleven years since I entered this <placeName>country</placeName>. It then
was a <placeName>wilderness</placeName>, but it is not so now. We have advanced very 
considerably and far enough to advance rapidly.</p>

<p>The situation of the <placeName>Mexican republic </placeName>at this time is such that in
all human calculations the destiny of <placeName>Texas </placeName>will depend mainly upon
itself. Our political affairs are assuming an aspect of the most 
intense interest. This fair and highly favored <placeName>country</placeName>, in many 
respects, presents an anomoly in the history of <placeName>new settlements</placeName>&#8212;that
it should have remained unpeopled, unexplored, and even unknown
except in name so long&#8212;that it should have been redeemed from a
state of nature and its advantages developed by individual 
enterprise alone&#8212;-that a few <persName>pioneers </persName>should have resisted military 
misrule and removed to the <placeName>west side of the Rio Brazos del Norte</placeName> all
the <placeName>garrisons </placeName>of regular <persName>troops</persName>&#8212;that we now sustain the constitution
and laws of our <placeName>adopted country</placeName> and are true to our duty as <persName>Mexican
citizens</persName>, although the whole <placeName>nation </placeName>is convulsed by <persName>factions </persName>and 
revolution, the social compact virtually dissolved, and the constitution a
mere name, violated as it is from <placeName>one end of the republic to the other</placeName>,
and morally destitute of power to restrain <persName>military </persName>usurpations or
to bind the confederation together, that events may possibly leave
us with the rights of possession to a <placeName>country </placeName>of sufficient extent for
a <placeName>nation</placeName>, and in a situation which will justify our taking care of
ourselves without violating any moral or political obligation 
whatever,&#8212;or that we may be driven to attempt a political revulsion for
causes which justice will sanction. That <placeName>Texas </placeName>should be thus 
suspended, as it were upon the current of events, all taken together
present rather a new, and I think an interesting picture.</p>

<p>The agency which the <persName>first settlers</persName> have had in developing the
resources of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, must always afford to them a gratification of
the highest character. Humble as the honor may be considered by
many who are revelling in the <hi rend="italic">" horse mill round"</hi> of wealth in<pb n="873"/>
populous <placeName>cities</placeName>, I as one of those <persName>settlers</persName>, and as a <persName>leader of <placeName>Texas</placeName>
pioneers</persName>, prise it very highly. This <placeName>country </placeName>is much more valuable
than was ever supposed. I have seen the best part of <placeName>North America
from Boston to the City of Mexico</placeName>, and I have no hesitation in 
saying that <placeName>Texas </placeName>has moie advantages in fertility of soil, climate, and
locality than any <placeName>section of the country</placeName> I have ever seen. I am well
aware that the mere idea of a <placeName>wilderness </placeName>carries with it in the minds
of many, the frightful picture of <persName>savages</persName>,<persName> wild men</persName> and beasts, and
barbarism, but those who associate those ideas with the population
of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, do us an injustice and deceive themselves.</p>

<p>We have just had a convention of all <placeName>Texas</placeName>, <persName>native Mexicans</persName> and
<persName>foreign settlers</persName>&#8212;all united as one man. We have asked for a
<persName>State government</persName> and a repeal of the laws restricting emigration.
What will be the fate of our application I know not. It may be
said that we stre too few for a <placeName>state</placeName>. To this it may be replied,
what cannot or will not determined enterprise effect? In <date n="12-xx-1821">December
1821</date> I arrived on the <placeName>Brazos River</placeName> with about <persName>20 families</persName> in the
<placeName>center of a wilderness</placeName>, surrounded by<persName> hostile indians</persName> and far remote
from all resources. We were then called <persName>madmen </persName>and our total
destruction was predicted. Those<persName> 20</persName> have grown to many <persName>thousands</persName>.
The idea of a <placeName>State </placeName><hi rend="italic">at this time,</hi> is much less bold than was the idea
of success <hi rend="italic">at that time</hi>, with so feeble a beginning.</p>

<p>We have done our duty faithfully as <persName>Mexican citizens</persName>, and will
continue so to do. Whatever may be the view which the <persName>Mexican
government</persName> may take of the past, we can with honest truth say,
that our consciences are clear. Should the future drive us into an
attitude of hostility in defense of what we have so dearly earned,
the public opinion of good men, I think, will acquit us of all wrong&#8212;
we shall <hi rend="italic">then </hi>expect that the sympathies which cheered the struggling
<persName>Greeks </persName>and <persName>Poles</persName>&#8212;that sanctioned the independence of <placeName>Spanish
America</placeName>&#8212;that applaud the liberals of <placeName>France</placeName>, and the reformists of
<placeName>Great Britain</placeName>, will also cheer the humble watch fires of our 
undisciplined militia, and if necessary soon swell their ranks to a
respectable <persName>army</persName>. The <persName>settlers of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> are disciplined in toils and
privations, in hard enterprise and contempt of danger, in 
constitutional principles and in honest industry, but they are untrained in
the art of regular warfare&#8212;they have never been the tools of 
oppression nor the engines of destruction. The <persName>sons of the North</persName> may
be buried in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, but they cannot be driven from it&#8212;neither do
I think such a thing will be attempted&#8212;it would be a blind and
mistaken policy This <placeName>country</placeName>, as a <placeName>state of Mexico</placeName>, would prosper&#8212;
it would be of great service to the <placeName>nation</placeName>, and add much to the<pb n="874"/>
national strength and resources&#8212;it is not our interest to separate
if such a thing can be avoided, <hi rend="italic">unless indeed we should float into
the <placeName>Northern Republic </placeName>with the consent of all <persName>parties </persName>ourselves
included.</hi></p>

<p>Perhaps the <persName>milliners </persName>on one side and the spirit of revolution on
the other, may split matters into fragments and leave us to ourselves
here in the centre.</p>

<p>Whatever may be the fate of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, it must always excite the
interest of those who have seen it, for it is a very favored <placeName>country</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have scribbled you a long letter, with all the careless freedom and
frankness of an <persName>old acquaintance</persName>. I think you must feel some interest 
for this <placeName>country </placeName>and for your <persName>friends </persName>and <persName>countrymen </persName>who
are in [it] and I am certain <hi rend="italic">you will do us all the good</hi> you can.
Write to me on the subject. Has this out-of-the-way section ever
occupied any place in the attention of the <persName>magnates of <placeName>Washington</placeName></persName>?</p>

<p>If you answer this I shall think you are willing to renew our old
acquaintance and will continue to give you the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Texas </placeName>news</hi>.</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin   </persName> [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
