<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4090">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>M B Menard to Stephen F Austin, 11-27-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>M B Menard</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-01">09-01-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Nacogdoches, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 543-544
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-11-27">11-27-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-01" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Colonel Piedras refuses to allow him to act as Austin's agent in Nacogdoches, to give certificates of admission to immigrants.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>.<date when="1830-11-27"> Nov. 27th. 1830</date>.</p>
<p><persName>Col Stephen F Austin</persName></p>

<p><placeName>San philippe</placeName></p>

<p>dear sir I receved this morning by <persName>Mr. Novara</persName> your Letter and
document appointing me your <persName>agent </persName>to give ceriificat to such 
deserving <persName>persons </persName>as should wish to Emigrate to your <placeName>Colony </placeName>I felt
dedisposed to Accept of the apointment for three Reason Ier to oblige
a man who has done the most for the Interest and promotion of
this <placeName>province </placeName>2er to satisfy the desire that I have if I had the power
to promogate the growth and importance of this <placeName>province </placeName>3er to
the Request of <persName>Mr. Mc.Kinney</persName> a man that I have the highest Estime
and Consideration for.</p>

<p>But not wishing to Expose myself being a <persName>Stranger </persName>in the <placeName>Contry</placeName>
I thought proper (aliso in accordance with your Instruction) to
call on <persName>Col Piedras </persName>to give his approbation on the Subject after
due Consideration he said that he did not think he Could give
his assent being Contrary to his Superior order that he had order
to stop any one who Should not have a passport from a <persName>Mexican
Agent</persName> that you had a wright youself to give pasport or Certificat
to such Number or <persName>persons </persName>as by your Contract with 
<persName>Government </persName>you were to settle in your <placeName>Colony </placeName>and no more, that
having the wright youself (to give Certificat) it was surpassing
your faculty to Extend that wright to other and in short that the
power and Instruction you give me were (if Complyed with) in
direct violation of his order and to the 9th: article of the Law of
the <date when="1830-04-06">Sixth of aprill Last</date> for he said by those Instruction you are
impowered to give Certificat to any <persName>men </persName>(if good men) who Should
say that he is Emigrating to <placeName>Austin Colony</placeName> not specifying the
Number while your Contract with Government Specify a Limited
Number and that no one ells ought to be admited in the <placeName>province</placeName>
besides: it is an affair of too much Responsability for him to 
permit it he said if you would furnish him with a List of the names
of those <persName>persons </persName>you have Contracted with which are to settle in
your <placeName>Colony </placeName>or them to have a Certificat of your own Signature he
has no objection to Let him pass, but upon no other term&#8212;Saying
it would be transgressing his order to do the Contrary.&#8212;he 
Requested me to Let him take a Copi of your Instruction to me and
that he would Write to the Govment to know whether they would
allow you to appoint an <persName>agent </persName>for this business not finding it 
objectionable I Let him have the paper and he took a Copie of it I
am no <persName>Lawyer </persName>therfore I do not know whether <persName>Col. Piedras</persName> is
wright or wrong in this affair nor do I wish to have any Contantion<pb n="544"/>
with him on the Subject therfore I wrote you the Subtance of what
he said it is for you to Juge or to do as you plaese about it</p>

<p>Notwithstanding my Willingness to be of Service to you-&#8212;you see
it is imposible for the present But in this or other Case here after
if I Can be of any help or service to you I prey you to Request it
of me and I will if in my power do it with greatest pleasure</p>

<p>With Respect and Consideration I am your Obed. Sert,</p>

<p><persName>Michel B. Menard</persName>    [Rubric]</p>
<p>To. <persName>Col. Stephen F Austin</persName></p>

<p><placeName>Ville de Austin</placeName></p>

<p>Addressed: <persName>Col.   Stephen   F.   Austin.</persName>   <placeName> Villa   de   Austin   Texas</placeName></p>

<p>Per <persName>Mr. Foster</persName></p>

<p>PS. the <persName>Comisionner Novara</persName> Receved order <date when="1830-11-27">to day </date>from the 
<persName>Governor of the State</persName> not to proceed any farther in his business unless
he is sure that<persName> Col. Milam</persName> <persName>Colonist </persName>are not <persName>North American 
Emigrant</persName> that <persName>Col. Milam</persName>s Contract with Govt, his to settle <persName>European
Emigrant</persName> the <persName>Gentlemen </persName>is very much dissapointed I am sorry
for it.</p>

<p><persName>M. B. Menard</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
