<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4734">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F. Austin to James F. Perry, 03-10-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F. Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-17">02-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F. Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas via New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 46-48
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-03-10">03-10-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Still detained by delay in passing amnesty law. Plans for furthering commercial advancement of Texas. Tariff exemption and trade with Chihuahua. Policy for Texas past and future</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1835-03-10">March 10. 1835</date></p>

<p>Dr. <persName>Brother</persName>, I fully expected to have been on my way <placeName>home </placeName>before this.
I am however still on bail and cannot leave until the amnesty law is 
published and when that will be is uncertain. It was sent to the <persName>President </persName>
<date when="1835-03-09">yesterday</date>, and it is said that he will send it back to <persName>congress </persName>to be altered.
If so it may be a month before it finally becomes a law. Inform <persName>Grayson</persName>
of this&#8212;he will be surpised for when he left we both calculated the law
would be published in a few days. This is a measure in which many
<persName>thousands </persName>are deeply interested and one that the <persName>Govt </persName>and three fourths
or more of<persName> both houses</persName> and all the influential men are anxious should
pass, and yet it has to travel the usual snails pace of public matters. This
example ought, of itself, to be a proof to some of those who are so ready
to blame me at home, of the delay and difficulty of effecting anything here.<pb n="47"/>
They know but little of these matters and of the mental torment I have
suffered, to get anything done for <placeName>Texas </placeName>At this time the feeling in favor
of <placeName>Texas </placeName>is much better and more favourable than it ever has been, and
I believe that if the attention of <persName>Govt </persName>and of <persName>congress </persName>was not distracted
by the disjointed state of the times, something material would be done for
<placeName>Texas</placeName>, however it is really not so <hi rend="italic">very </hi>important whether anything is done
or not if a deal calm and union can be preserved in that country, 
migration&#8212;good crops&#8212;no party divisions&#8212;no excitements&#8212;no personalities
should be the political creed of every one in <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>The<placeName> Chihuahua road</placeName> should be opened by some means and must be,
I think the <persName>Genl Govt</persName> will aid&#8212;the <placeName>state of Chihuahua</placeName> will aid I have
heard from there on the subject In this matter, and probably in others
<placeName>Chihuahua </placeName>and <placeName>Texas </placeName>will have the same interest.</p>

<p>The political character of this country, seems to partake of its geological
features&#8212;all is volcanic If there is sound judgment and common sense
in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, the convulsions here will not affect that country The prosperity
of <placeName>Texas </placeName>should flow onward like the silent current of a river&#8212;nothing
from this quarter can, or will, impede its progress. This has always been
my view of the subject, and hence it is that I have uniformly adopted
(when left to my own judgment, or not contrould by circumstances) a
silent, and conciliatory course. That policy has settled <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and if
pursued a few years longer will secure its happiness and prosperity.</p>

<p><placeName>Spain </placeName>I presume will acknowledge the independence of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>very
soon&#8212; the island of <placeName>Cuba </placeName>will then be open to us&#8212; it is the best <placeName>market</placeName>
for beef cattle, oxen, hogs, horses, mules, corn, lard beans, peas etc in
the <placeName>world</placeName>. I am trying to get a premium on <placeName>Texas </placeName>cotton shipped to <placeName>Vera
Cruz </placeName>and <placeName>Tampico</placeName>&#8212;an exemption from duties and many other things in
favor of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. The state question was taken up in the <persName>house of 
representatives</persName> a short time since and information called for from the 
executive&#8212;it is now before the <persName>cabinet</persName>, and gaining friends dayly. My 
opposition has had a most salutary influence, and placed <placeName>Texas </placeName>on high ground.
The project of a <placeName>territory </placeName>is now totally dead, so much so that its <persName>advocates</persName>
are now in favor, of a <placeName>state</placeName>. Even <persName>Bradburn </persName>is now an active and warm
advocate in favor of a state. There has been a great change since <persName>Grayson</persName>
left in favor of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. <persName>Don Lucas Alaman</persName>, and <persName>Gutierrez Estrada the
present minister of relations</persName>, are two of the best friends <placeName>Texas </placeName>has in
<placeName>Mexico</placeName>. They are educated honest and honorable men, and as a matter
of course have many <persName>enemies</persName>. <persName>Almonte </persName>is another friend of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and
an active one. He is printing an account of that country. He says it is
favourable. I have not seen it, nor any part of it.<pb n="48"/></p>

<p>There is a "<hi rend="italic">fuss</hi>" at <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>&#8212;the <persName>garrison of the <placeName>castle</placeName></persName> mutinied tied
their <persName>officers</persName>, and are bombarding the <placeName>city</placeName>. All the rest of the <placeName>country </placeName>is.
quiet. To say how long it will remain so would be the same as to say
when <placeName>Vesuvius </placeName>will or will not explode&#8212;all this is of no consequence
to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, if the people there will keep down party divisions and 
personalities and make good crops. I wish that all the unquiet spirits in <placeName>Texas</placeName>
would organize themselves into a corps and explore a good route for a
<placeName>wagon road to Chihuahua</placeName>&#8212;in <hi rend="italic">that </hi>way they can be usefull to <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;
much more so, than they, or any body else are aware of at present.</p>

<p>The <placeName>Chihuahua road</placeName> is a great object for <placeName>Texas</placeName>, a vast link in its 
prosperity, and no efforts should be left untried to open it as quick as possible&#8212;
its influence will be known <hi rend="italic">after </hi>it is opened, and not before.</p>

<p>I recd a letter from you not long since&#8212;the bad health of <persName>Emily </persName>afflicts
me dreadfully&#8212;we have as yet recd nothing from <placeName>Texas </placeName>but trouble and
suffering, but I still hope that some better times are in store for us&#8212;as ta
my personal <persName>enemies </persName>I disregard them&#8212; I am laboring for <hi rend="italic">their </hi>good, as.
much as for my own&#8212;honest men will say whether they repay me as I
deserve, and to honest men I leave the matter, with a clear conscience.
Tell <persName>Emily </persName>to keep up good spirits and laugh at all the slang of my
<persName>enemies</persName>. They are only injuring themselves.</p>

<p>Love to all the <persName>children</persName>&#8212;keep up the <placeName>school </placeName>and give them a good education. I hope you have not neglected to put a <persName>family </persName>on the <placeName>league west
of the Bernard</placeName>&#8212;attend to this for if you have neglected it it may cost
you very dear, also on all your other land&#8212;do not neglect this as others
have done&#8212;comply rigidly with the law in every particular&#8212;as to 
settlement and payments.</p>

<p>I am in tolerable health and very good spirits&#8212;tho much older in both
respects than when I left home two years ago.</p>

<p>Remember me to your <persName>neighbors </persName>and to <persName>Grayson </persName>and <persName>Jack </persName>and <persName>Bell </persName>and
<persName>McKinney </persName>in particular. Tell <persName>McKinney </persName>that I shall have to draw for a
thousand dollars on <persName>Gregory </persName>on the letter of credit that <persName>Grayson </persName>brought
me. This trip will cost me about $10,000 dead loss besides my 
imprisonment, and after all to be abused and calumniated by some of those I have
been laboring to serve is not quite as agreeable as it might be&#8212;but such
is man and human nature.</p>

<p>Farewell may heaven bless you and prosper <placeName>Texas</placeName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>I send this by <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>. I wrote you on the <date when="1835-03-05">5 </date>and <persName>Burnett </persName>on
the <date when="1835-03-07">7</date> by mail.	</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
