<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4131">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>S Rhoads Fisher to Stephen F Austin, 01-10-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>S Rhoads Fisher</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-05">09-05-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Harrisburgh, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Saltillo, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 583-584
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-01-10">01-10-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-05" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Official demand tonnage duty at every port which his schooner enters. Fears that Government will stop American immigration even into Austin's colony.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Harrisburgh </placeName><date when="1831-01-10">January 10th 1831</date></p>
<p><hi rend="italic">Dios y Libertad</hi></p>
<p>My Dear Sir</p>

<p>My object in coming to this place was to load the Schooner
Champion with lumber or freight for <placeName>Tampico</placeName>, and I intended to
keep her in the coasting trade provided I found it to my Interest,
knowing it was decidedly to the advantage of the <placeName>Colony </placeName>to have
a vessel as well calculated as she is to carry off their produce. But
I have to state to you with regret that unless a different 
construction of the maritime laws shall be made, or the laws themselves
changed, it will be impossible for any vessel to pursue it. I waited
on <persName>Colonel Bradburn</persName> with the letter you honored me with, and
found him as you represented a <persName>Gentleman</persName>. I stated to him that
I had paid in <placeName>Aransaso Bay</placeName> a Tonnage duty on the Schooner, and
all the other Government dues for which I had a receipt from the
<persName>Administrador</persName>; that after leaving there we entered the <placeName>Bay of
Matagorda</placeName> in ballast, and finding no loading had come on to this
for lumber to proceed to <placeName>Tampico</placeName>: he said his instructions were
positive, and that I must pay the tonnage duty here, and that had
there been an <placeName>office at Matagorda</placeName>, the same would have been 
required there; and further, that the same must also be paid in 
<placeName>Tampico </placeName>: this then, amounts upon the Schooner whose tonnage per <placeName>U. S.</placeName>
Register is 65, besides other port charges to $552.50 from which 16
p. c. is to be deducted; no vessel can stand this, and unless a change
be made the Trade must be abandoned. I am not prepared to 
dispute the legality of<persName> Col. Bradburn</persName>'s demand, but <persName>Mr. Hiram</persName>, and
several other gentletmen here say they would not pay it, for <persName>Colonel
Bradburn</persName> has nothing to do with this <placeName>Colony</placeName>, nor has the 
<persName>ayuntamiento </persName>at <placeName>Austin </placeName>ever received any official notice of an <persName>officer </persName>
having been placed at <placeName>Galveston entrance</placeName>. I have no hesitation in
addressing to you, my dissatisfaction, but under the present feeling
between the two people prefer a slight submission (for submission
I consider it to be) to being the means of increasing that feeling.<pb n="584"/>
I understood <persName>Colonel Bradburn</persName> to say his orders were from 
<persName>General Teran</persName>, and that as he conceived no vessel upon having payed
the Tonnage duty in one <placeName>Mexican port</placeName> should be required to pay it
in another, unless her last clearance was from a <placeName>Foreign </placeName>one, he
would write to the <persName>General </persName>upon the subject, requesting him to give
instructions to have the payment made here returned in this case
and not demanded in future; but God help us! as the fable tells us
there are many tracks into the lions den but none out of it&#8212;he
further added that he would write to the <persName>General</persName>, to grant to the
Schooner a coasting licence for six months, now my dear Sir, if you
would back this request by also addressing the <persName>General </persName>it would
oblige me.</p>

<p>In the course of conversation the <persName>Colonel </persName>mentioned that the views
of the <persName>Mexican Government </persName>were such that he had no doubt but all
<placeName>north american</placeName> emigration would be prohibited in the course of a
short time, even to this <placeName>colony</placeName>; should this prove to be the case, I
shall most truly regret it, for my attachment to this my <placeName>adopted
country,</placeName> where I have located all my interests, and whose prosperity
I consider as identified with my own, is such, that I cannot view 
without pain a step of such short-sighted policy. The <persName>Mexican 
Government</persName> have at all times been most liberal towards us <persName>colonists </persName>and
the people we have ever found to be amiable and hospitable; on the
other hand we have been true and faithful <persName>citizens</persName>, ready at all
times to protect the <placeName>country </placeName>from <placeName>Foreign </placeName>invasion, and <persName>Indian</persName>
aggression, as well as to support the execution of the laws, we have
Industry and mechanical and agricultural knowledge wherewith we
can enrich the <placeName>country </placeName>and set a good example to our <persName>Mexican 
brethren</persName>. Any step therefore on the part of the Government which might
check this Industry, and the good feeling existing between the 
<persName>Colonists </persName>and the <persName>native Mexicans</persName> I consider injudicious.</p>

<p>I shall forward this via <placeName>Tampico</placeName>, and return in a day or two to
<placeName>San Felipe</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>S. Rhoads Fisher </persName>   [Rubric]</p>
<p><persName>Colonel Stephan F. Austin</persName>.</p>
<p>[Addressed to Saltillo]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
