<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4495">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Elias R Wightman to Stephen F Austin, 11-17-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Elias R Wightman</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-05">11-05-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Cany</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 902
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-11-17">11-17-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-05" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Surprised at Austin's success in "harmonizing such a heterogeneous mass."</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Cany </placeName><date when="1832-12-17">Dec 17th 1832</date></p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I have omited to write on your first return, thinking you much
harrassed in business of the <placeName>Colony</placeName>, and since thinking to have been
there before this time, and am aware that my interest requires me to
be there; now that all are geting their deeds, I might make some
Collections for I have made my surveying business less profitable
than any other as so Small a portion of them are taken and many
who have gotten their Deeds live at a distance and still are oweing
if You will get any in and retain it in your own hands it will much
oblige me, I requested <persName>Mr Williams</persName> to do so but he neglected it,
I then appointed<persName> Mr Veeder an Agent</persName> to Collect from whom I
have no account, An Accidental fall dislocating my shoulder and
breaking almost all the bones in my body, has prevented me from
being active in my business, and finally left me disabled, But I
intend shortly to be at <placeName>San Felipe </placeName>when I want to get a Copy of all
my deeds, which I have not and Settle with you and <persName>Mr Williams
</persName>and prepare to take my exit, I often am surprised how you get
along with all the <hi rend="italic">troubles </hi>attendant on your <placeName>Colony </placeName>business, <hi rend="italic">not
the official</hi> But the <hi rend="italic">harmonising</hi>, such a heterogenous, mass of which
your <placeName>Colony </placeName>is Composed, You write me to recommend a quarter
for <persName>Mr Thos. Fletcher</persName> I would recommend a number of <placeName>prairie
quarters</placeName> but the <placeName>best with due portion of Timber is that Surveyed
for <persName>John Cronkrite </persName><placeName>on the main branch of Prairie Creek </placeName>adjoining
<persName>L. L. Veeders</persName></placeName>. I surveyed it to suit him and is a good one, there is
<placeName>adjoining <persName>Doct Cronkrites </persName>unsurveyed land on Mestango Creek</placeName>
which would be <placeName>supurb quarters</placeName>, and one <placeName>below <persName>Allsbury</persName>s Survey on
the San Burnardo</placeName> was <placeName>[near] the Mouth another tolerable quarter
unsurveyed,</placeName></p>

<p>I made Choice of several Blocks of the <placeName>Matagorda Town</placeName> for
you which when I see you shall be explained, as they had voted
the <persName>proprietors </persName>to make choice of <placeName>4 Blocks</placeName> to each share while I was
sick and located I expostulated, that it was unfair for any one to
choose all his first to the exclusion of the absent and obtained leave
to select out of <placeName>those Blocks which were locked up in reserve for
future disposition</placeName>, with which I was satisfied as I chose those in
preference to those they had Selected</p>

<p><persName>E R Wightman </persName>   [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
