<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4146">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Ausitn to Samuel M Williams, 02-05-1831</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Ausitn</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-06">09-06-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Leona Vicario, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 594-595
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1831-02-05">02-05-1831</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-06" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Hopes to obtain judiciary reform. Muldoon. Eleven-league grants of land. Politics.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Leona Vicario</placeName> <date when="1831-02-05">Feb. 5, 1831</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir</p>

<p>In my letter to <persName>Johnson </persName>I have said all there is to say, about
public matters&#8212;we get on slowly, but I think I shall succeed on the
main point, which is the Judiciary, I have been fortunate so far,
in keeping a harmonious understanding with all, and shall endeavor
to continue it. The petitions for land will all be dispatched next
week. The <placeName>office </placeName>has been searched for your petition in vain, it 
cannot be found. This morning I told the <persName>secretary </persName>that I would 
present another petition as your <persName>agent</persName>, he said that he would look once
more, and if the other could not be found that I could present a
new one, and the <persName>Govr </persName>has promised that it shall be <hi rend="italic">immediately</hi>
dispatched. So that you may consider the thing as <hi rend="italic">certain</hi>. Those
who asked for large quantities will get what ought to satisfy them,
and if they had confined themselves to reasonable bounds at first
their petitions would have been granted long since.</p>

<p><persName>Father Muldoon</persName> leaves <date when="1831-02-06">tomorrow </date>for <placeName>Monterrey</placeName>, he appears to
be a true <persName><hi rend="italic">Austinian </hi></persName>and I think he is sincere for he has obtained a
large <hi rend="italic">bite </hi>of land from the <persName>Govr </persName>and looks to <placeName>Texas </placeName>as his only
home, and final resting place.</p>

<p>Chambers has been <hi rend="italic">bedevilled </hi>here, by delays of one sort or 
another, and is not yet dispatched by the <persName>tribunal </persName>and probably will
not be for a month to come. The obstacle to his admission as a
<persName>lawyer </persName>now is, the want of his <hi rend="italic">certificate of baptism.</hi> <date when="1831-02-06">Tomorrow</date>
he presents a petition to <persName>Congress </persName>to dispence with that requisite,
and he will then be examd by the <persName>judges</persName>. I think he will be a usefull
man in <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>Matters are doubtfull in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. The <persName>partisans </persName>of <persName>Pedraza </persName>are
begining to make a great noise and you need not be much 
surprised if he should come on by land through <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;if so treat him
with all possible respect and attention for he is justly entitled to it.
It is said that <persName>Teran </persName>is going to <placeName>Texas </placeName>soon. My confidence in him is
still unimpaired, I believe he is the best among them all. A 
number of the <persName>first men</persName> in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>have obtained 11 League Grants in
<placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>There is a rumor here which I do not like, which is that <persName>Zavala </persName>is
on the way to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and <persName>Teran </persName>is going to repel him by force. I
know not where the rumor came from. I hope it is not so for I do
not wish to see the civil war of the <persName>Mexicans </persName>introduced into <placeName>Texas</placeName>.
Say nothing about it, for it is only vague rumor.</p>

<p>I wrote you from <placeName>Monclova</placeName>&#8212;from here by <persName>Jose Luís Carbajal [?]</persName>
by whom I sent the white horse, also the last mail- you have ac-<pb n="595"/>
knowledged the receipt of mine from <placeName>Bexar </placeName>and <placeName>Rio Grande</placeName>, I
mention the others that you may know if any miscarry.</p>

<p>I am happy to hear of the safe arrival of <persName>Mr. Dwyer</persName> and <persName>family</persName>
and others from <placeName>Alabama </placeName>which you inform me of in your last letter,
the plan of sending the certificates by <persName>Grayson </persName>was a very good one,
I wish you to write to him, that I say he has a <placeName>league of land in
Texas</placeName>, and that he must hurry back to improve it, and bring a <persName>wife</persName>
and <hi rend="italic">one hundred good <persName>families </persName>for <persName>neighbors</persName></hi>&#8212;you see by <persName>Tonys
[Anthony Butler]</persName> letter that there are some <persName>snakes in the grass
</persName>round <placeName>San Felipe.</placeName> I have a notion who they are, perhaps I am 
mistaken&#8212;you know that I have been very cautious in shewing his
letters&#8212;others have done it and critisized them and it is all charged
upon me.</p>

<p>Remember me to <persName>Sarah </persName>and <persName>Eliza </persName>and all <persName>friends</persName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p>You say nothing about the progress of the <placeName>store house</placeName></p>

<p>I enclose <persName>Johnson </persName>letter to you lest it should miscarry. You
must make him pay his portion of the postage.</p>

<p>[Addressed:] Al <persName>Ciudno Samuel M. Williams Administrador de
correos en <placeName>Austin</placeName></persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
