<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4557">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Mary Austin Holley, 04-20-1833</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-11-18">11-18-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mary Austin Holley
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 954-956
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1833-04-20">04-20-1833</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-11-18" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Texas petitions for organization as a State. People do not want to separate from Mexico, but anything preferable to present conditions.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[April 20, 1833.]</p>

<p>I do not know that, in the whole course of my life I have so 
sensibly felt the extremes which ardent and sanguine temperaments<pb n="955"/>
are liable to, as during the last eighteen months. When you were
here we permitted our imagination to ramble into futurity with
untiring, and more than full grown wings. The result has been
what calm and calculating judgment would have foreseen&#8212;an 
unnatural flight, and consequent disappointment. Well, so be it. I had
rather at least be capable of being moved by bright visions, never
realized, than to pass through the world without being touched by
the recollection of the past, the events of the present, or the 
anticipations of the future.</p>

<p>The calamity which <persName>Henry </persName>has suffered by the loss of his <persName>wife</persName>,
and by sickness is truly distressing. I am convinced from numerous
examples that persons raised in <placeName>cities </placeName>ought never to remove to a
new and <placeName>thinly settled country</placeName>. It is a total change of <hi rend="italic">element</hi>, and
a corresponding change of habits, ideas, and customs must take
place, or disappointment and discontent will surely follow. The
wild garb of nature may delight and enchant at first, because it
is new; the foliage the vines and the forest are pleasing images to
those who have always looked upon brick walls and paved streets,
but it is the pleasure of novelty and soon vanishes. <persName>Henry</persName>'s health,
and that of his <persName>family </persName>have very much improved, and also his
spirits.   I think, after this <date n="Summer-1833">summer </date>we shall get along much better.</p>

<p>Our political affairs have been somewhat agitated during the <date n="xx-xx-1833">past
year</date>. But their course though often much too wild and rapid, and
too impulsive, has been tending towards the prosperity, and 
permanent tranquility of the <placeName>country</placeName>. Every thing has now settled down
on one fixed basis. <placeName>Texas </placeName>needs a <persName><hi rend="italic">State Government</hi></persName> and is 
<hi rend="italic">determined to have one</hi>. We have lately had a Convention and asked of
the general <persName>Congress </persName>admission into the <placeName>Mexican Confederacy</placeName> as a
<placeName>State </placeName>separate from <placeName>Coahuila</placeName>. This request is accompanied by a
Constitution as an evidence that we wish for nothing contrary to the
National Constitution. I was appointed by the <persName>Convention </persName>to take
on our application for admission as a state; and depart tomorrow
morning on this responsible and important mission. I go by land,
and expect to be in the <placeName>City of Mexico</placeName> in about a month.</p>

<p>I have great confidence of success in procuring the approbation of
<persName>Congress </persName>to the measure. It was originally united to <persName>Coahuila </persName>
provisionally and the law that joined them says,<hi rend="italic"> "So soon as <placeName>Texas </placeName>is
in a situation to figure as a <placeName>State </placeName>she shall inform <persName>Congress </persName>thereof for its resolution."</hi> So that we are acting by authority, and in virtue
of the express mandate of the law, for we only inform <persName>Congress </persName>that
we are in a situation contemplated by said law, as it requires us to do,
and ask for admission as such.</p>

<p>Should this application he refused it will be the greatest error
ever committed by the <persName>Mexican Government</persName>. <placeName>Texas </placeName>is now in the
budding, and impulsive vigor of youth, and a wise direction of its<pb n="956"/>
energies will make it one of the most efficient, faithful, and devoted
states of the <placeName>Union</placeName>. But, under disappointment it will be an 
unmanageable and wayward child. For young as it is in some respects,
it is far advanced in energy of character, and an unbending 
determination of purpose. In short, <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Texas </placeName>is determined to have a <persName>state
Government</persName></hi>.</p>

<p>There is a decided opposition to seperating from the <placeName>Mexican
Confederacy</placeName>. The people do not desire, and would not agree to it,
if they could get a <persName>State Government</persName>, but anything would be better
than to remain as we are, for we have no government that deserves
the name of one.</p>

<p>If I succeed in this mission I intend it shall terminate my 
participation in public matters. I have contributed very much to the
settling of the <placeName>Country</placeName>, and if I am now successful, I shall be 
contented, and think I have done my part. Where, a few years since, the
primitive solitude of nature was undisturbed, a grand Theatre has
been erected. I have no desire to enter upon the stage as an actor.
But, I must confess, I have done calculating for the future.
Before this I fully expected to have been settled on my <placeName>farm </placeName>quite
snug and comfortable. Instead of which I am on the <hi rend="italic">wing </hi>for
twelve hundred miles, on a mules back (not a pegasus) over plains
and mountains, to the <placeName>City of Montezuma</placeName>, farther from all hopes of
farm and home than I ever was.</p>

<p><persName>Henry </persName>informs me that you intend spending the <date n="Summer-1833">summer </date>in 
<placeName>Kentucky</placeName>. I think this a good plan. In the <date n="Fall-1833">fall</date>, or <date n="Winter-1833">winter </date>come and pay
us a visit and look at your league of land so as to keep up your
domicil in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, for you know you are only temporarily absent.
I enclose a certificate that may be of use in case it should ever be
made a question whether you were domiciliated or not.</p>

<p>I hope to be back in <date n="08-xx-1833">four months</date>. It is probable I shall return by
water, and as it is doubtful whether I can get a direct passage from
<placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName> to <placeName>Texas </placeName>I shall have to come by way of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>.
Farewell&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S F Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
