<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4306">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Mary Austin Holley, 01-04-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-19">09-19-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mary Austin Holley(
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 732-733
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-01-04">01-04-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-19" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Trouble at Brazoria carried him beyond himself. Texas must remain united with Mexico as a State with right to legislate for itself.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Austin</placeName>, <date when="1832-01-04">January 4, 1832</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Cousin</persName>,</p>

<p>We are always more or less influenced by the state of the 
atmosphere. While at <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>every thing around me was greatly above
fever heat, and its influence could not but reach me. The rumour of
difficulties has set in motion all the violent passions of the <hi rend="italic">body
politic</hi>, and there will not be wanting persons who will catch at
straws to attack and injure me if they can, and some of those I have
most served will be foremost to raise a clamour against me. How
little they know me!</p>

<p>The true interest of this <placeName>country </placeName>requires that it should remain
united to <placeName>Mexico </placeName><hi rend="italic">as a <placeName>State </placeName></hi>that can legislate for itself in all local<pb n="733"/>
and internal matters.<hi rend="italic"> I must go to the <placeName>interior </placeName>by <date n="02-xx-1832">February</date></hi>. It
will be a fatiguing journey, and [at] tended, perhaps, with difficulties
and dangers. My situation is unpleasant and unnatural. I long
for retirement and quiet, and I much fear that, in spite of myself,
I shall be borne along on the current of events into a stormy and
troubled sea. Such is life!&#8212;<hi rend="italic"> a speck between two eternities,</hi> as has
been aptly said. A speck&#8212;and yet how much of troubles and 
perplexities! But it is our all. The past is but a picture, a shadow
of various hues. The future&#8212;we know not what. Theological and
mythological contradictions and inconsistensies make it everything,
anything, nothing. The mind is lost that seeks for a clear and 
absolute demonstration of doctrinal or sectarian aphorisms, unless it
rests with confidence upon the throne of <hi rend="italic">one, only just and 
omnipotant <persName>God</persName>;</hi>&#8212;the <persName>God </persName>of the eternity past&#8212;the speck&#8212;and the eternity
to come&#8212;uncreated, and undeformed by mythological fancies, or
theological investments&#8212;the self existing, consistent, and bountiful
<persName>Father of Worlds</persName>, of time and of Eternity. From such a throne the
jargon and choas of religious strife may be calmly viewed and 
understood. Yet it is sickening to see the wickedness that is practised
under the most sacred of names, and beneath the garb of religion.</p>

<p>I reached <placeName>home </placeName><date when="1832-01-02">night before last</date> after riding forty seven miles
that day, and found <persName>sister Emily</persName> at a ball, dancing away in fine
spirits. She enjoyed the party, and I joined her, caught the 
excitement, remembered your injunction to " laugh away care," and soon
forgot my forty seven miles ride. <persName>Sister </persName>is quite delighted with the
prospect of your removal here. I write without study or disguise,
confident that you will be an indulgent and candid critic. The
weather has been beautiful and I hope you are this day in <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName>.</p>

<p>Adiós, amiga mia.</p>

<p><persName>ESTEVAN</persName>.</p>

<p>Your<persName> brother Henry</persName> is authorized to chuse a situation for you
out of my <placeName>" Peach Point"</placeName> survey of <placeName>premium land</placeName>&#8212;say two 
hundred acres. I expect to be back soon enough to designate it myself
before it will be necessary to begin building, and should prefer
doing so, but if I am detained too long he can make a selection.
Farewell.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
