<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4661">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Ayuntamiento of Brazoria to Congress, 07-31-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Ayuntamiento of Brazoria</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-12-06">12-06-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Congress
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 1069-1071
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Memorial</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-07-31">07-31-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-12-06" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Memorial in behalf of Austin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>To the <persName>Supreme Govt of the <placeName>United States of Mexico</placeName></persName></p>

<p>The <persName>Ayuntamiento of the Jurisdiction of <placeName>Brazoria</placeName></persName> of the <placeName>State
of Cuahuila and Texas</placeName> approaching the Govt, with that high 
consideration with [which] is due from the subject to the sovereign
would most respectfully represent.</p>

<p>That with feelings of the deepest regret and anxiety they have
learned that their <persName>agent </persName>and fellow citizen <persName>S. F. Austin</persName> has been
for a long time under arrest and in a state of most rigorous 
confinement&#8212; when <persName>A</persName> was first arrested on his return to <placeName>Texas </placeName>he
requested us to express or feel no anxiety on his account. For
relying on the purity of his intentions his established character and
his known devoted adherence to the constitution and laws of his
<placeName>adopted country</placeName> he could not anticipate that his detention would
be more than temporary. From that time until very recently we
have been totaly ignorant of his true situation. Hence we have been
perfectly silent lest in attempting to do good we might possibly do
an injury.</p>

<p>But now when our information is such as can be confidently relied
on we concieve it to be a duty we owe to ourselves to <persName>Austin </persName>and to
<placeName>Texas </placeName>to make a full frank and candid statement of facts with a
view to the removal of impressions unfavorable to the character of
the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, and injurious to <persName>Austin</persName>. The situation of the
<placeName>country </placeName>before the meeting of the convention which adopted the
constitution of which <persName>Austin </persName>was the <persName>bearer </persName>was distressing beyond
description The <persName>Congress of the State</persName> was either ignorant of oar
wants or unable or unwilling to apply the necessary remedy The
administration of justice was a mere mockery the rights of the
<persName>citizens </persName>were trampled on with impunity.   The person, property, or<pb n="1070"/>
liberty of the <persName>subject </persName>unprotected, the <persName>innocent </persName>and <persName>unofending </persName>were
frequently the <persName>victims </persName>of persecution while the <persName>lawless </persName>and <persName>guilty</persName>
often passed unpunished. Living at a distance of <placeName>near 700 miles
from the capital of the state</placeName> having but two <persName>members </persName>from <placeName>Texas</placeName>
in <persName>Congress</persName>, having feelings views, habits and pursuits entirely
different and distinct from the <persName>people of <placeName>Coahuila</placeName></persName> the voice of our
complaints and petition was either unheard or disregarded.</p>

<p>In this state of things it was conceived that unless some remedy
could be applied disorganization and ruin would be the inevitable
consequences these were the reasons which produced a call of that
convention these were the reasons which prompted that convention
to form a plan of constitution and these were the reasons which
induced <persName>Austin </persName>at an immense sacrifice to undertake the discharge
of the duties imposed on him with a confident hope that he would
be able to render effective services to his <persName>countrymen</persName>. That he has
been unsuccessful in his mission is but too true and the consequences
to have been of the most unfortunate character</p>

<p>We know not the charges upon which <persName>A </persName>has been arrested and
hence it is impossible to refute them.   But if it be true as has been
alleged by some that he is suspected of having designs upon the
integrity of the <placeName>Mexican Territory</placeName> we reply that the allegation is a
libel as well upon the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> as upon <persName>Austin</persName>.   These <persName>people</persName>
have never for one single moment entertained such a monstrious idea
and <persName>A </persName>is the last man against whom such a charge could be
successfully made.    His motto has universally been the constituition
Laws federal and state and one some occasions he has even  aroused
the feelings of some of his <persName>countrymen </persName>against him by advising a tame
and humiliating submission to the indignities which have been heaped
upon us.   These are facts too notorious to be question and to doubt
them would be evidence of the weakest incredulity.    Since <persName>A </persName>was
dispatched to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>the most favourable changes have taken place
in the political affairs of <placeName>Texas</placeName>.   The <persName>National Congress</persName> in answer
to our petitions has repealed the obnoxious feature of the Law at
the<date when="1830-04-06"> 6th of Apl 1830</date> and the <persName>Govt, of our state </persName>having come to a
knowledge of our wants and prompted by a spirit of justice and 
liberality with which its later acts have been characterised has 
extended its arm of relief and applied the necessary remedy to our
wrongs.</p>

<p>The administration of the laws is placed upon a firm and 
intelligible basis the trial by <persName>Jury </persName>the bulwark of our liberty is established
and the property and life and liberty of the subject is secured for
all of which distinguished marks of kindness and liberality we take
this public opportunity of tendering our most cordial and heartfelt
gratitude both to the <persName>Federal and State Govts</persName>. In conclusion we
most humbly pray that our friend and fellow citizen<persName> S. F. Austin</persName><pb n="1071"/>
may be immediately discharged and that he be permitted without
further molestation to return to his <placeName>home </placeName>and to his <persName>friends </persName>
assuring the <persName>Govt</persName>, that should an opportunity ever present itself <placeName>Texas</placeName>
will prove that it is ready and willing to spend its blood and treasure
in support of the <persName>Mexican </persName>Constitution, the <persName>Mexican </persName>Laws and the
<placeName>Mexican Territory</placeName></p>
<p>God and Liberty</p>
<p><date when="1834-07-31">July [31?] 1834</date>                                          </p>
<p><persName>Edwin Waller</persName></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><persName>Alcalde</persName></hi></p>

<p><persName>Wm, H. Wharton,</persName></p>
<p><hi rend="italic"><persName>1st. Regidor</persName></hi></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
