<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4701">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Thomas F. McKinney, 12-02-1834</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-14">02-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Thomas F. McKinney
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 30-31
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1834-12-02">12-02-1834</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Advice concerning state politics</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Mexico </placeName><date when="1834-12-02">Dec. 2. 1834 </date>(<placeName>in prison</placeName>)</p>

<p>To <persName>Thos. F. McKinney</persName>,</p>

<p>Dr Sir, <persName>Don Ramos Arispe</persName> and <persName>D. Victor Blanco</persName> visited me <date when="1834-12-02">this day</date>,
and informed me that the difficulties between <placeName>Monclova </placeName>and <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>had
been terminated by the decission of the <persName>President Genl. Santana</persName> to whom
the subject was referred by the treaty between the <persName>contending parties</persName>. By
this decision of the <persName>President </persName>the <placeName>seat of Government of the State</placeName> is to
remain at <placeName>Monclova </placeName>in conformity with the law fixing it there. The acting
<persName>Govr. Algue Sabal [Elguezabal]</persName> is to continue until a <persName>Govr </persName>is elected by the
<persName>people of the <placeName>State</placeName></persName>. A new election is to be ordered for the whole <placeName>state </placeName>for
<persName>Govr vice Govr Councillers</persName>, <persName>members of the legislature</persName> and of <persName>congress</persName>.</p>

<p>I am informed that the <persName>President </persName>considered this last clause to be 
necessary for a final and amicable termination of this entangled business, by
refering it directly to the source and origin of power, the <hi rend="italic">people </hi>so as to
give a voice to the <placeName>department of Saltillo </placeName>which it had not in the <date n="09-xx-1834">September</date>
election.</p>

<p>The object of the <persName>President </persName>is to terminate all the local disputes and give
to <placeName>every part of the State</placeName> an unembarased voice in the election of all the
public functionaries. This is certainly a most important and desirable
object, and the means which have been adopted to attain it are probably
the best if not the only ones that the confused State of the circumstances
will admit.</p>

<p>Under this view I recommend that the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> unanimously
sustain the decission of the <persName>President </persName>and proceed without any hesitation
or doubt to hold new elections in conformity with the orders that are to
be circulated by the <persName>Govr of the State</persName> in conformity with said decission.
It will be an honourable evidence of the disposition of <persName>those people</persName> to 
promote harmony and union with the <placeName>other parts of the state</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have no doubt that the <persName>persons who were elected in <date n="09-xx-1834">September last</date></persName>
will cheerfully acquiesce in this measure, and I for one of them frankly
say that I do so.</p>

<p>It is to be hoped that at the election care will be taken in <placeName>each of the
departments in Texas</placeName> to select as <persName>deputies to the legislature</persName> <persName>men 
personally known to the people</persName>, familiar with their necessities, and closely 
identified with them in property, interest, and <hi rend="italic">actual residence.</hi> There is little
doubt that <persName>representatives </persName>so circumstanced would be more likely to serve
the interests of their <persName>constituents </persName>than wiser men who do not reside among<pb n="31"/>
them. <placeName>Texas </placeName>now has <persName>three members</persName>, but if persons are chosen who do not
reside there, it would seem as tho nothing had been gained by the 
augmentation of <persName>representatives</persName>.</p>

<p>In the selection of the other <persName>public functionaries</persName> the good sence of the
people will of course lead them to choose men of strict probity impartiality
and established character and principles who will attend impartially and
honestly to the genl prosperity of every part of the state.</p>

<p>I expect that my affairs will terminate so as to enable me to reach
<placeName>Monclova </placeName>in <date n="02-xx-1834">February</date>.</p>

<p>I wish you to show this letter to my <persName>friends </persName>and make such use of it as
you think best for the attainment of the object which is harmony and
union between <placeName>all parts of the State</placeName> and union in sustaining the measures
of the <persName>President </persName>as to the new elections</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName> [Rubric]</p>

<p>All is going well. The <persName>President Genl Santana</persName> has solemnly and 
officially declared that he will sustain the <hi rend="italic">federal republican system</hi> as 
established by the constitution of <date n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date> and all <persName>parties </persName>will unite to support him
in this measure. <date n="xx-xx-1833">Last year</date> there was no local <persName>Govt </persName>in <placeName>Texas</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">Now </hi>there
is and your evils are remidied. So that all ought <hi rend="italic">now </hi>to unite in promoting
union and harmony with <placeName>Coahuila </placeName>and <placeName>all parts of the State</placeName>. These are
the opinions of your fellow citizen</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName> [Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
