<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4078">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Alexander Thomson to Stephen F Austin, 11-13-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Alexander Thomson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-01">09-01-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Tenoxtitlan, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 534-535
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-11-13">11-13-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-01" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Informs Austin of the attempt of Piedras to detain his own and four other families at Nacogdoches in obedience to orders from Terán concerning the law of April 6, 1830. Suggests action by Austin.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Tenoxtitlan</placeName><date when="1830-11-18">&#8212;Novr 18th 1830</date></p>

<p>Respected sir,</p>

<p>I am unacquainted with you personally, yet situated as I am, I
think it necessary, to address you, and apprise you of a considerable
difficulity, that now exist in the settlement of your <placeName>colony</placeName>, and the
others also; namely, the order from <persName>General Teran</persName>, to the <persName>Colo at
<placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></persName> to suffer no person to pass, unless, they have a passport,
I was not apprised of that order, and came here, I think on the <date when="1830-10-28">28
ultmo&#8212;</date>, the <persName>Alcalde </persName>informed me when the <persName>families </persName>came into <placeName>town</placeName>
I must collect them all together, and present them, I done so, then
the <persName>Coll</persName>, sent for me, and inform'd me that he had the Saturday
before recd- the above mentioned order and could not consistent with
his order, let me pass, but as we were ignorant of the late Law, and
as we had compleatly complyed with the Colonization Law, having
our certificates Legally arra[n]ged, by the proper <persName>authorities</persName>, he
would venture to give five of us a permit to you, who he said was
authorised to give us passports; but the <persName>families </persName>must remain until
our return, we had traveled better than 8 weeks, had spent a great
deal of money, and was much fatigued, we could not feel willing to
remain in that part of the <placeName>country </placeName>on expences so Long, we therefore
came round, which caus'd us to loose 2 1/2 days travel, we are now at
the <placeName>barracks</placeName>, at <persName>Mr Williams</persName> that is the <persName>families</persName>, We arrived there
<date when="1830-11-12">Last night</date>, <date when="1830-11-13">Today </date>I came up to the <placeName>new garrison</placeName> to see the 
<persName>commander </persName>here he says that he has recd the same order, and advises us
to remain where we are, until he receives further orders in answer
to his letter that he had writen after <persName>Majr Robertson </persName>had inform'd
him that I was on the road, which answer he expected would arrive
in <date when="1830-11-17">four days</date>, mean-while he gave us permission to explore the 
<placeName>country</placeName>, which we intend to do immediately&#8212; <persName>Col. Thorn</persName> has sent you
a letter by me on the subject. We, him and myself think it advisable
for you to have an <persName>agent </persName>appointed in <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName>,   he says he is<pb n="535"/>
willing to act for you if you wish him, but he expected to start in a
day or two for <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> and be absent two months, There ought
to be some person there authorised immediately, for since I left
there I have been informed of two more <persName>families </persName>that have been
stoped, and detain'd,- I have been particular in giving the 
particulars of my detention, to you, in order, that, you may have a clear
view of the impediment, <persName>emigrants </persName>will meet with in comeing to the
<placeName>colonies</placeName>&#8212; So soon as I can, I expect to see you, but can not for a
few days,&#8212; <persName>Majr Robertson</persName> has inform'd you that I am interested
in the settlement of this <placeName>colony</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Alexander Thomson</persName></p>
<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Colo S. F. Austin </persName>  <placeName>San Phillipi De Austin</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
