<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4118">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 12-28-1830</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-03">09-03-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Bexar, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 567-569
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1830-12-28">12-28-1830</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-03" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Political news. Difficulty of avoiding party entanglements. Certificates for admission of colonists according to law of April 6, 1830</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p><placeName>Bexar </placeName><date when="1830-12-28">28 December 1830</date></p>
<p>Dr <persName>Sam</persName>.</p>

<p>I arrived here <date when="1830-12-27">last morning</date>, and shall leave the <date when="1830-12-30">day after 
tomorrow</date> by the <placeName>upper road</placeName>. I get an <persName>escort </persName>from here as far as
<placeName>Rio Grande</placeName>, and another from there to <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>&#8212; <persName>Madero </persName>will leave
in a few days for that place. I wish you to pay him all the
attention you can. Shew him some of the deeds that are finished
and explain the mode of translating the <persName>Surveyors </persName>return etc&#8212;also
the general plots, he is (I have no doubt) as true and warm a
<persName>friend </persName>as the <persName>North Americans</persName> have&#8212; he is a devoted <persName>friend of
Guerrero </persName>and opposed to <persName>Teran </persName>and the <persName>present administration</persName>&#8212;
on subjects of this kind it is best to be <hi rend="italic">silent </hi>unless directly 
questioned, in the latter case you will of course give prudent answers.<pb n="568"/></p>

<p>The people of this place are, in heart, unanimously hostile to the
<persName>present administration</persName>, and they are more friendly to the <persName>North
American</persName> emigration than they ever were. The state of affairs
in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>is, if any thing, more unsettled than ever. <persName>Teran </persName>I 
believe will not go to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and I think it not improbable that he
may turn his course this way&#8212; from what I can learn both
<persName>Piedrass</persName> and the <persName>General </persName>are desirous to have a good standing with
the <persName>settlers</persName>&#8212; we ought to encourage this idea for we may derive
much benefit from it, at least so far as to keep off harsh orders etc.</p>

<p>I send you two hundred signatures, have certificates printed over
them verbatim like the others and fill them up, all except the name&#8212;
give as many to <persName>R. Williamson</persName> as he wants and send some to 
<persName>McGuffin </persName>and some to <persName>Piedrass</persName>, and some to <persName>Col Thorn.</persName> Try and
have them printed at night when no one is present and take care
that none of the blanks get into other hands, let none know anything
of this but <persName>Lesassier </persName>and <persName>Williamson</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>Settlers </persName>can get in with certificates from <persName>De Witt</persName> and he ought
to have about 200 struck off and sent to <placeName>Arkansas </placeName>and <placeName>Natchitoches </placeName>etc.</p>

<p>I presume you have heard all the news from <persName>Pettus </persName>and <persName>Johnson</persName>,
in this place there is Novedad de <persName>indios </persName>[rumor of Indians] every
hour&#8212;a large <persName>party </persName>were discovered <date when="1830-12-27">yesterday </date>on <placeName>Medina near the
road.</placeName></p>

<p><persName>Arciniega </persName>will be on by the<date when="1831-01-15"> 15 of next mon</date>to try and get the
<placeName>coast colony </placeName>out of the way by that time. I will write another letter
by him and one by <persName>Madero </persName>both of a <hi rend="italic">public character</hi>, that is you
can shew them if you think proper, but this one no person must see
except <persName>Lesassier</persName>.</p>

<p>There can scarcely be a more difficult thing than to play a <hi rend="italic">double
game</hi>, it is dangerous, and it is at times, a nice point to draw the
distinction between such a game and dishonor&#8212; we are so situated
that we must keep a good understanding with <persName>Teran </persName>and <persName>Alaman</persName>,&#8212;
but at the same time all our <persName>best friends</persName> at <placeName>Saltillo </placeName>and in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>
are very hostile to both those men. Silence, prudence, and vigilance,
must all be called in requisition. I shall have a dreadful task at
<placeName>Saltillo</placeName>&#8212;if I am compelled to come out and take sides openly, I
must go with the <persName>Viescas </persName>of course, in this event the whole pack with
<persName>Licenciado Aguirre</persName> at the head will open against me. Tho, it is best
not to anticipate trouble, in two weeks after I get there you shall
hear what the prospect is. <persName>Viesca </persName>has returned to the Govt.&#8212;this
is a good sign.    Say nothing for, nor against <persName>Zavala</persName>, very rigid<pb n="569"/>
orders have been issued by <persName>Teran </persName>prohibiting the admission of 
<persName>Zavalas families</persName></p>

<p>Keep peace and union at <placeName>home</placeName>, I shall not idle <placeName>abroad</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have written to <persName>De Witt</persName> to get 200 certificates of the same kind
of mine printed and signed by him and sent in blank to different
places. Aid the <persName>poor fellow</persName> along with it. <persName>Chambers </persName>has not yet
arrived. I cannot concieve what detains him. <persName>Pettus </persName>and myself
parted in such terms as I wish to be with all the <persName>settlers</persName>&#8212;I have
confidence in him now, and I think he has in me. The <persName>chiefs </persName>answer
to <persName>Williamson </persName>will inform you what has been done in his business&#8212;
A <hi rend="italic">consulta </hi>with the <persName>Superioridad </persName>and nothing can be done until an
answer is obtained</p>

<p>Attend to the writing of the certificates (do) take care of <hi rend="italic">my </hi>
signatures, don't put m[e] in the power of the <persName>printer </persName>or his <persName>boys</persName>. I
have written to [name illegible] on this subject</p>

<p>remember me to <persName>Mrs. Sweet</persName> and <persName>Sarah</persName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:]<persName> S. M. Williams</persName>   <placeName>Austin</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
