<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4752">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Samuel M. Williams to Stephen F. Austin, 03-31-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Samuel M. Williams</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-02-21">02-21-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F. Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Monclova, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Mexico</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 56-58
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-03-31">03-31-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-02-21" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Governor and Legislature will petition for release of Austin. Robertson Colony business. Two thousand persons immigrated into Texas in January and February</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Monclova </placeName><date when="1835-03-31">31st March 1835</date></p>

<p>I will not undertake my good <persName>friend </persName>to give you an exact description of
my feelings on receiving your welcome letter of <date when="1835-03-14">14th inst</date>&#8212;because as
you will know I feel quick, strong, and violent all at one moment. 
Believing that you would consider me in this place, from the letter I wrote
you before I started from <placeName>home</placeName>, which <persName>Almonte </persName>informed me you had recd.
from him, and not having heard one word from you for 3 mails, myself
and <persName>Companions </persName>were rejoicing in the opinion that you were liberated and
on the road <placeName>home</placeName>. In this we were strengthened by a clause in a letter
from <persName>Mr. Parrott</persName> to <persName>Mr. Almy</persName>, that spoke of your leaving in a few days.
Today although your letter assured us of health and resignation, it 
destroyed our hopes, and opened to our view the horrid reality of <persName>Mariana </persName>and
pasada Mariana&#8212;truly such a state may be called the essence of tantalising
persecution. God knows I am unable to devise how you bear up under it.
I immediately waited upon the <persName>Governor</persName>, informed him of your situation,
and urged him with all the rhetoric and warmth of feeling which belongs
to me, to address the <persName>Gen Govt</persName> on the subject of your situation, as a duty
to a <persName>fellow Citizen</persName>, and as a duty to the <persName>citizens </persName>of a part of the <placeName>State</placeName>
that Cannot much longer bear with such a course in silence. I am, proud
to say that although his politeness permitted me to finish with my ideas&#8212;
he met the first impulses of my wishes and was ready to acceed to my
request. And regretted that his burthened occupation would not permit
him to do it by this mail&#8212;but authorized me to say to you that it should
be done by the next. I then went to work amongst the <persName>Deputies </persName>to get
<persName>Congress </persName>to make something of a similar character, and although it is a
body not like a person I flatter myself with success with them, and have
no doubt but this additional weight will be given if you should still be so
unfortunate as to remain under the operations of an uncertain tomorrow.
Had I not permitted myself to be lulled into a belief from your letter of
<date n="02-xx-1835">February </date>that you would certainly be relieved by or before the <date when="1835-03-01">first of
this month</date>, I should long since have moved what I today have performed.
You have some <persName>friends </persName>here who respect and esteem you for various reasons
and with the exception of <persName>Chambers </persName>and some one or two others of our<pb n="57"/>
<persName>Countrymen </persName>no bitter <persName>enemies</persName>&#8212;not one I think among the <persName>natives</persName>&#8212; As
for <persName>Chambers </persName>I shall try my strength on him, And all I require of you is
to look on and if you cant be for me don't be against me&#8212; The <persName>Texas
people that is <placeName>East of Bejar</placeName></persName> in order to be consistent with their vote in
<date n="09-xx-1834">Septem</date>. voted the old Ticket, consequently <persName>McKinney </persName>is suplente, my
absence prevents his leaving, and the <persName>Brazos department</persName> goes unrepresented.
Individually I am pleased because I dislike beyond Measure a popular 
appointment&#8212; I consented to serve in this instance but think I shall never
do so again,&#8212; By next session, if the Census is taken, <placeName>Brazos </placeName>and 
<placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>will each have two <persName>members</persName>. In <date n="01-xx-1835">Jany </date>and <date n="02-xx-1835">Feby </date>2000 persons arrived
in at the <placeName>mouth of the Brazos</placeName>. Emigration has been tremendous <date n="xx-xx-1835">this year</date>,
and still continues.</p>

<p>This <persName>Legislature </persName>is liberal and are determined, to be the last to yield
up the Federal system. I have in union with others recommended the 
establishment of <placeName>schools </placeName>and a <placeName>College </placeName>to be founded out of Monies arising
from lands. The <persName>Government </persName>refuse to acknowledge the <persName>families </persName>about
<placeName>Trinity </placeName>and <placeName>Nacogdches </placeName>etc etc as a part of those belonging to the <persName>New
York Companies</persName> contracts, those who have been possessioned by their
<persName>Commissioner </persName>remain with their lands&#8212;but they will not be counted for
the <persName>Company</persName>.</p>

<p>I have not yet gotten my business before <persName>Congress</persName>, my documents are all
ready&#8212;and in the hands of the <persName>members </persName>as individuals, unless they
deceive me I shall succeed&#8212; <persName>Don Marcial Borrego</persName>&#8212;(a man of the
most [weight?] here) <persName>first counsellor and acting Governor</persName> in the absence
of <persName>Viesca</persName>, and who was a <persName>member of the last Legislature</persName>, and by the way
with <persName>Augustin Viesca</persName>, the <persName>supporters of Robertson</persName>, is my friend and
assisting me in my business, confesses they have been deceived, but does
not want the matter so remedied as to compromit the decoro of the Govt
I have told him, that redress is what we want, and that as <persName>citizens </persName>do not
wish to stigmatise the Govt- under which we live&#8212;</p>

<p>I have letters from <placeName>home </placeName>to the <date when="1835-03-17">17th inst</date> all are well, my own <persName>family</persName>
and my <persName>friends </persName>desire to be remembered to you they think you are
at this place. They complain of a backward <date n="Spring-1835">spring</date>, much rain and cold&#8212;
With a hope of hearing from you by the next mail that you are released
and about starting <placeName>home</placeName>, I will close this asuring you that I shall inform
all in <placeName>Texas </placeName>of your situation and write as you requested; And notify
<persName>McKinney </persName>of your draft. You must not permit yourself to want for any
thing, if money can get your release let us know <placeName>Texas </placeName>will come out like
a white head, and raise what may be necessary. <persName>Johnson </persName>and <persName>Peebles</persName><pb n="58"/>
desire affectionate remembrance to you and you have our united prayers
for your liberty, health and speedy and prosperous journey <placeName>home</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>[Samuel M. Williams] Rubric</p>

<p>If you are to be detained in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>let us know</p>

<p>If you should want more money draw on <persName>McKinney </persName>and <persName>Wms</persName>. at 60 ds
sight and advise us by mail</p>

<p>Rubric</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Stephen F. Austin Esq</persName> <placeName>Mexico</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
