<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4328">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Mary Austin Holley, 02-19-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-22">09-22-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mary Austin Holley
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 753-754
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-02-19">02-19-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-22" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">The troubles of Brazoria in December. His attitude misrepresented. Revolution in Mexico.
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Austin </placeName><date when="1832-02-19">Feb: 19, 1832</date></p>

<p>I was made happy to day by the receipt of yours of <date when="1832-01-05">5th </date>and <date when="1832-01-06">6th</date>
Ultimo. I had before heard of the arrival of the Spica, and 
presumed you were well, but wished for the assurance from yourself
before I leave.   It was like a gleam of sunshine after days of clouds.</p>

<p>How cautious ought we to be, in all stations of life, but especially
in places where our opinions and expressions are liable to be 
misunderstood or perverted for evil purposes, never to deviate, even <hi rend="italic">in
appearance</hi> from permanent rules of action. You know that my
motto is <hi rend="italic">fidelity to <placeName>Mexico</placeName></hi> I never departed from it, and never
intend to depart from it. The most unfortunate, and furious 
excitement, a part of which you saw at <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>, placed me in a peculiar
situation. To control that excitement and keep it within bounds I
had but one course left, which was to float along with it for the
moment so as to temper it down after a few days of reflection
had cooled the first effervescence. This matter has cost me more
uneasiness than I expected. My own expressions drawn from me
by the heat of others, and by the circumstances of the moment, have
been caught at, and a much wider meaning given them than I 
intended; and this, too, by those who ought to be my <persName>friends</persName>. It is
now over&#8212;I think&#8212;and all will go on quietly, harmoniously, and<pb n="754"/>
peaceably with the <persName>Government</persName>, a respectful memorial has been
adopted by the <persName>Ayuntamiento </persName>praying for a repeal of the prohibition
against <persName>North American emigrants</persName>, a modification of the tariff,
removal of <persName>Fisher</persName>, etc.</p>

<p>Our last dates from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>are to the <date when="1832-01-10">10 Jany.</date> the next mail no
doubt will bring us something important relating to <persName>Gen, Santana</persName>s
movements and plans. What is to be the fate of this <placeName>Nation </placeName>? 
Constantly torn to pieces by internal discord and civil war&#8212;where will
it end ? They have all my sympathy for success and happiness 
because they have <hi rend="italic">tried to be free</hi>, and considering the state of civil
and mental vassalage they have so long been in we must give them
credit for many things they have done.</p>

<p>I expect I have tired you out with my long letters. Taciturn, as
they say I am, you see I can be loquacious some times, and to some
persons. It is long since I have been able to talk frankly as I
wished. This is the last letter you will receive from me for the
present. Now to business. In a few days, I shall be off, to return,
a free man, about <date n="06-xx-1832">June</date>, and commence my improvements. Nothing
can be done to advantage until then. To employ <persName>workmen </persName>without
personal inspection would be to waste money to no purpose. You
can go on preparing for your removal according to your wishes
Your <placeName>league of land </placeName>is not very far from where my <persName>brother in law
</persName>is settling. It is on a <placeName>navigable tide water Creek, called Dickinsons
Creek</placeName>, (<placeName><persName>Perry</persName>'s is on Chocolate</placeName>)<placeName> on the South side</placeName>, beautifully
situated, has some timber and rich prairie, and is <placeName>within a few hours
sail of Galveston Harbor</placeName>.   Farewell, a long farewell</p>

<p><persName>S F A.</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
