<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB4339">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel M Williams, 04-09-1832</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2010-09-22">09-22-2010</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel M Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Leona Vicario, Coahuila</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1919: The Austin Papers</hi>, (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office, 1924), 3 vols., Vol 1, Part 2, pp. 762-764
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1832-04-09">04-09-1832</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2010-09-22" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Retail law passed over governor's opposition. Political conditions prevent relief to settlers in east Texas.   Prudence and moderation, however, will bring relief in the end.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            
<p>
[From Williams Papers, Rosenberg Library, Galveston, Tex.]</p>

<p><placeName>Leona Vicario </placeName><date when="1832-04-09">9 April 1832</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir.</p>

<p>I arrived here Sin Novedad, on the <date when="1832-04-05">5 </date>and took my seat on the <date when="1832-04-06">6th</date>.
Nothing has been done except the ley de comercio, which I presume
you have seen. The <persName>Govr </persName>opposed it very violently and returned it,
but the <persName>legislature </persName>approved it a second time, only <hi rend="italic">three </hi>voted against
it. <persName>Aguirre</persName>, <persName>Fuentes</persName>, and <persName>Figueroa</persName>. It will do the <persName>colonies </persName>no
material harm, for not many of them have ever retailed goods out of
the <placeName>colony</placeName>. In principle it is unconstitutional, but nothing need be
said on that ground at present.</p>

<p>The <persName>Governor </persName>is decidedly in favor of the <persName>colonists</persName>, he will sustain
them if they act prudently, and had it not been for this <persName>Santana</persName>
business he would have taken some measures relative to the <hi rend="italic">Trinidad
de la Libertad</hi> affair, but to notice it now would be adding fuel to
the flame of discord that threatens the ruin of the <placeName>confederation</placeName>.
The opinion of <hi rend="italic">many </hi>who are opposed to the <persName>ministers</persName>, and of <hi rend="italic">all </hi>who
are opposed ton <persName>Santana </persName>is, I that <hi rend="italic">his </hi>real object is <hi rend="italic"><placeName>centralismo</placeName></hi>. The
<persName>Ministers </persName>are suspected to have the same views. The real <persName>federalists</persName>
are therefore opposed to the <persName>ministers </persName>and support <persName>Santana </persName>so far
as to insist on their removal, but <hi rend="italic">there </hi>they will stop, and if <persName>Santana</persName>
still persists all <persName>parties </persName>will [be] united against him except his 
personal <persName>friends </persName>and he will fall. <persName>Tamaulipas </persName>is in great confusion.
<persName>Santana </persName>is besieged in <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>&#8212;all the rest of the <placeName>nation </placeName>is quiet.</p>

<p>On my arrival here I found rumors in great abundance relative
to <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;that it had separated and declared independence etc. etc.
The <persName>Govr </persName>did not believe anything of the kind, and I have fully
satisfied him, on that subject, he is in favor of the memorial and
will recommend it when it returns through the <persName>Chief of 
Department</persName>&#8212; he thinks it will be granted if no imprudence is committed
by the <persName>colonists</persName>. There will be a change of <persName>ministers</persName>, an express
who arrived last night from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, I am told brought news that
it had been finally determined to change all the <persName>ministers</persName>. The
Memorial will therefore reach <placeName>Mexico </placeName>with the <persName>Govrs </persName>
recommendation in the right time, just after the new <persName>cabinet </persName>is formed, and
whilst <hi rend="italic">reform </hi>is the order of the day. The object is a very important
one, and it is best to bear almost any thing rather than jeapordise all
by rashness and ill timed passion and imprudence. All the wild
sayings and gabbling over cups and <hi rend="italic">speeches </hi>etc at <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>have
been circulated over this <placeName>country </placeName>with wonder full augmentations.
The fact is that the great majority of the thinking and intelligent
part of the <persName>people </persName>in the <placeName>towns </placeName>I passed through and in this place<pb n="763"/>
are in favor of the <persName>colonists </persName>but they fear the <persName>settlers </persName>will ruin
themselves by their imprudence. If they are unjustly oppressed
and can so make it appear the majority of the whole <placeName>nation </placeName>will be
in their favor, but if the reverse of this is the case, and they fly
into a fit of passion for slight causes the whole <placeName>nation </placeName>will be against
them.</p>

<p>The advice I have reed, from a high source is, as follows&#8212; " 
Harmonize as much as possible with the <persName>military</persName>&#8212;give no cause for
disgust&#8212;be calm and never shew any passion&#8212;never use threats
or harsh language. The <persName>Alcalde </persName>or <persName>Ayuntamto</persName>. ought to keep an
exact and detailed account of all the oppressive acts of the <persName>military</persName>
or <persName>revenue officers</persName> and report the same to the <persName>Chief of Department</persName>.
Any one who is illtreated by a <persName>military </persName>or <persName>revenue officer </persName>ought to
exhibit proof of the same to the <persName>Alcalde </persName>who ought to report it
immediately to the <persName>Chief of Department</persName>. No violence must be used
on any pretext&#8212;no imprudent talking etc."</p>

<p>Better advice could not have been given and if properly followed
will produce favourable results. Do try and impress this on everyone, 
and especially on those in <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>who are rather warmer
than they ought to be, tho perhaps not much more so than rigid
justice requires.</p>

<p>Some <persName>men </persName>in the <placeName>world </placeName>hold the doctrine that it is degrading and
corrupt to use <hi rend="italic">policy </hi>in anything. Without saying whether I 
approve of this doctrine or not, I do say that there is no degradation
in prudence and a well tempered and well timed moderation. The
absolute freedom of speech that is used in the <placeName>U. S. of the North</placeName>
is unknown in this <placeName>country </placeName>and hence it is not properly understood,
and for this reason <hi rend="italic">just complaints</hi> when made in harsh language
are construed into rebellion etc. etc. As a general rule all over the
<placeName>world </placeName><hi rend="italic">Language </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Acts</hi>, must be regulated in a great degree by
<hi rend="italic">circumstances </hi>and <hi rend="italic">characters</hi></p>

<p><persName>Genl Teran</persName> has evidently been deceived very much by the arts
and management of <persName>Fisher </persName>but he will soon be convinced of that, if
he is not already, and all will end right.</p>

<p>Some amendments to the colonization law are proposed&#8212;they are
not very unfavourable&#8212;the quantity of land is proposed to be 
reduced to<placeName> half a Sitio</placeName> for those who exhibit proof that they have at
least 100 head of Ganado Mayor&#8212;those who have not that quantity
are only to get one <placeName>labor</placeName>&#8212;the price is proposed to be increased a
little etc. I doubt whether anything will be done with it this 
session. The <persName>members </persName>do not harmonize amongst themselves. The
prospect is good that <hi rend="italic">nothing </hi>will be done by this <persName>Legislature </persName>except
the retail law.</p>

<p>I presume that <persName>Ugartachea </persName>is in <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>&#8212;remember me to him&#8212;
his sister <persName>Mrs. Ibarra</persName> is in good health and all the <persName>family</persName>.<pb n="764"/></p>

<p>The memorial to divide the <placeName>municipality </placeName>will be passed to the
house tomorrow&#8212;there seems to be no objection to it&#8212; you can
read this letter to whoever you think proper&#8212; remember me to
<persName>Sarah</persName>,</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>Shew this to <persName>John Austin</persName>&#8212;</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
