<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5188">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William H Wharton to Stephen F Austin, 06-02-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William H Wharton</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-08">08-08-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Washington,</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 363-365
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-06-02">06-02-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Account of a visit to Jackson</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>(Strictly Confidential)</p>

<p><placeName>Washington </placeName><date when="1836-06-02">2d June 1836</date></p>

<p>Dear Sir:</p>

<p>By special invitation I took a family dinner with the <persName>President </persName>on the
<date when="1836-05-31">day before yesterday</date> and with the <persName>Vice President</persName> on <date when="1836-06-01">yesterday</date>. I was 4<pb n="364"/>
or 5 hours alone with the <persName>President </persName>and the sole subject of conversation
was <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Texas</placeName></hi>. He asked Where are your letters from your <persName>Government</persName>?
Where <persName>Houston</persName>s official account of the Victory? Where your <persName>President</persName>s
proclamation calling upon the <persName>inhabitants </persName>to return to their <placeName>homes </placeName>and
attend to their crops? Where an official annunciation of the fact that the
<persName>inhabitants </persName>are at their <placeName>homes </placeName>and in possession of the Most of <placeName>Texas</placeName>?
Where the publication opening your <placeName>ports </placeName>and fixing your Tariff and 
Tonnage. Sir says he your <persName>President </persName>should send an <persName>express </persName>once a week to
<placeName>New Orleans</placeName> to his <persName>agent </persName>and have published by authority the true 
situation of your <placeName>country </placeName>and every thing that goes to shew you are a <hi rend="italic">de facto
<persName>government</persName>.</hi> This is indispensible. He then commenced on <persName>Butler </persName>and
said that but for his delay and misconduct <placeName>Texas </placeName>would have belonged to
this <hi rend="italic"><persName>Government </persName></hi>before this war broke out and sir says he be not 
surprised if I yet soon announce a cession by <placeName>Mexico </placeName>of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to the <placeName>United
States</placeName>. This gave me to understand that he was <hi rend="italic">in treaty</hi> with <hi rend="italic"><persName>Gorostiza</persName></hi>
and I announced to him for the 10th time that <placeName>Texas </placeName>protested against any
sale or cession by <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. He answered that if such took place a quit claim
would be all that would be obtained from <placeName>Mexico </placeName>leaving the preliminaries
to be afterwards arranged between <placeName>Texas </placeName>and the <placeName>United States</placeName>. I again
renewed my protest against any disposition of <placeName>Texas </placeName>by <placeName>Mexico</placeName>.</p>

<p>I write you this to let you know What is wanted here in order to procure
our recognition. Do urge our <persName>government </persName>to write to the <persName>agents </persName>here at
least once a week and to make frequent publications in relation to the state
of affairs in <placeName>Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>Our latest dates from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> are of the <date when="1836-05-13">13th May</date>. The <persName>Indians</persName>
have cut off all communication for some time. We should now have <placeName>New
Orleans</placeName> dates of the <date when="1836-05-22">22d</date>&#8212;. All is anxiety about the <placeName>Texas </placeName>news Many
doubt the capture of <persName>Santa Anna</persName> because the <persName>agents </persName>here have received no
letters from the <persName>Texas Government</persName>. Do urge them to write often. I shall
leave here as soon as the news is placed beyond all doubt&#8212;which will be
in 2 or 3 days as we are now getting the <placeName>New Orleans papers</placeName> Via <placeName>Nashville</placeName>
-and <placeName>Louisville</placeName>. When the news is placed beyond all doubt I will
<hi rend="italic">demand </hi>of this <persName>Government </persName>a <hi rend="italic">decisive </hi>answer in relation to our recognition.
When this is given I will start for <placeName>Texas </placeName>via <placeName>Nashville</placeName>. Do write to me
often at <placeName>Nashville </placeName>and <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>. <persName>Childress </persName>has not been here since
you left. <persName>Carson</persName>'s leaving <placeName>Texas</placeName>, I mean the <persName>Secretary of State</persName> has done
considerable harm. <persName>Genl. Jackson</persName> observed to me that it in some measure
justified <hi rend="italic"><persName>Gorostiza </persName></hi>in Calling our <persName>government </persName>a <persName>fugitive government</persName>.</p>

<p>I could get nothing definite out of <persName>Van Buren</persName> at his dinner although we
had much conversation. He professed to believe all the accounts in 
relation to <persName>Santa Anna</persName>s Capture and said that his feelings were decidedly
with us. Do attend to the suggestions herein contained and write fre<pb n="365"/>
quently first to <placeName>Nashville </placeName>where I shall remain only a day or two and then
to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></p>

<p><persName>Wm. H. Wharton</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:]<persName> Genl. S. F. Austin</persName> <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> Via <placeName>Wheeling</placeName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
