<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5296">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>P W Grayson to Stephen F Austin, 11-03-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>P W Grayson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-28">08-28-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Louisville, Kentucky</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 445-446
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-11-03">11-03-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-28" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Thinks Jackson will delay recognition of Texas. Embarrassment caused by close relation between recognition and annexation. Thinks best way would be for United States to quiet the Mexican claim </add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Louisville </placeName><date when="1836-11-03">Nov. 3. 1836</date></p>
<p>Dr Sir</p>
<p>I came here a few days ago, from a sort of necessity, to await further
Communications from <placeName>Texas </placeName>if they are intended&#8212;</p>

<p>On the subject of recognition I think <persName>Genl Jackson</persName> will still wait a little
to observe the <hi rend="italic">Course and character of Civil affairs in <placeName>Texas</placeName>;</hi> this being
the only matter at present upon which any real doubt or solicitude 
remains; our Independence of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>being pretty generally looked upon as
<hi rend="italic">established</hi>&#8212;</p>

<p>The great misfortune of the delay to recognize consists in its bringing
too near together, for the action on them by this <placeName>Government </placeName>of the two
questions&#8212;<hi rend="italic">recognition and annexation</hi>.</p>

<p>A <hi rend="italic">decent </hi>time you know ought to transpire after the disposition of the one
before taking up of the other for reasons which will readily Occur to you&#8212;</p>

<p>I am strongly persuaded however still, as I was many Months ago, that
an interposition by this <persName>Government </persName>with <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, based upon <hi rend="italic">terms to
quiet her claim to <placeName>Texas</placeName></hi> would be the safest and shortest mode of settling
all the difficulties; (that is if recent events of which I will speak directly
have not spoiled all the influence which this <persName>Government </persName>might otherwise
have had with <placeName>Mexico</placeName>)&#8212; The objection with some that such a mode of
accommodation, would be selling us to the <placeName>U States</placeName>, is altogether Nominal
and without the least substance. It would in fact be a sensible compromise
by an honorable <persName>third party</persName> of an unsettled question which might under the
influence of mutual passion run on to an indefinite length and involve both
the disputants in all manner of inconvenience loss and suffering&#8212; I think
our <persName>Government </persName>would do well to <hi rend="italic">think </hi>of this alternative, at any rate, in
case the expedient of <hi rend="italic">recognition </hi>and <hi rend="italic">annexation </hi>should seem likely to be
postponed too long&#8212; In the latter Contingency instructions shd. be given
to their <persName>Agents </persName>here, to solicit the interposition of this <persName>Government </persName>in the
mode suggested&#8212;</p>

<p>What do you think of this?&#8212; if in your opinion it deserves any 
Consideration, please mention it to <persName>Doct. Archer</persName> that it may also receive his&#8212;
he being as I understand a <persName>member of Congress</persName></p>

<p>The recent events to which I have alluded as probably affecting the 
influence of the <placeName>U States</placeName> with <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, are the departure of <persName>Gorostiza </persName>from
<placeName>Washington </placeName>and the circumstancs under which it appears he left which
were those of great dissatisfaction&#8212; There is I think no doubt he 
required the recall of the <persName>U S troops</persName> from <placeName>beyond the Sabine</placeName>, and on that
point found this <persName>Government </persName>immoveable&#8212;as well as on the other in regard
to the restraining of <persName>Volunteers </persName>from going on to <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; Some antici-<pb n="446"/>
pate a rupture immediately between the two <persName>Governments</persName>&#8212; I confess I
have no hope of it, when I consider the weakness of <placeName>Mexico </placeName>Compared
with this <placeName>country </placeName>But who can do any thing more than guess in the dark
about such matters?&#8212;</p>

<p>I am sorry to inform you that up to the last accounts I have had on the
subject, the Sale of Land Scrip was very dull&#8212; This is truly disheartening</p>

<p>I am anxiously looking for some account of the proceedings of our 
<persName>Congress</persName>&#8212; Every thing depends on their harmony of procedure and propriety
of deliberation&#8212;</p>

<p>Please to give my respects to <persName>Mr Perry </persName>and his <persName>family</persName></p>

<p><persName>P. W. Grayson</persName></p>
<p><persName>Genl S. F Austin</persName> <placeName>Texas</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
