<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5096">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Mrs Mary Austin Holley, 01-07-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-22">07-22-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Mrs Mary Austin Holley
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 300-301
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-01-07">01-07-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-22" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Describing the purpose of his mission to the United States</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, <date when="1836-01-07">Jan 7, 1836</date>.</p>

<p>I hope to have the pleasure of seeing you soon, but it is not certain, as
I may not be able to visit <placeName>Lexington </placeName>until I return from the <placeName>Eastward </placeName>as
we are very much pressed for time. I am bound to <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <placeName>New York</placeName>
etc. in company with <persName>Docr. B. T. Archer</persName>, and <persName>W. H. Wharton Esqr.</persName> We
are <persName>commissioners for the Texan Government</persName>. Our principal object is to
raise money means and <persName>men </persName>to sustain our cause.</p>

<p>The War for Liberty goes on prosperously, so far, in <placeName>Texas</placeName>. It must,
and will, end in Independence&#8212;<hi rend="italic">a full Declaration</hi> will be made in <date n="03-xx-1836">March</date>.
That of <date when="1836-11-07">7th November</date> was the first step, preparatory to the second and
final one. The fact is, we have no other remedy left. By the last accounts
the <persName>Central Government</persName> is established, and the <hi rend="italic">Federal </hi>system totally 
destroyed. The <persName>Texans </persName>may, therefore, for the future, be considered an 
<persName>independent people</persName>, intirely separate from <placeName>Mexico</placeName>. We are young to set up for
ourselves, but we are the sons of that <placeName>great nation</placeName> which has astonished the
world by its deeds, and progress in the cause of liberty, light and truth.
When I left <placeName>Texas </placeName>there was not an <persName>enemy </persName>within our limits, nor <placeName>east of
the River Bravo del Norte</placeName>. <persName>Gen. Santanna</persName>, however, is marching on in
person with all the <persName>force </persName>he can collect to <hi rend="italic">anihilate </hi>us. We have no fears,
but we must be ready for him. We need all the aid we can get in <persName>men </persName>and
money, provisions, arms and ammunition.</p>

<p>Large contributions have been made in the <placeName>United States</placeName> for the 
extension of Christianity over the <placeName>South Sea Islands</placeName> by means of <persName>Missionary
societies</persName>. Is not our cause quite as important and sacred? We are trying
to banish from our <placeName>homes </placeName>religious intolerance and despotism, and to
establish in the place of it, liberty and freedom of conscience. How many
thousands of pious <persName>families </persName>of all denominations might find a home and
become the proprietors of the soil in <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;the best soil and climate
accessible to <persName>north Americans</persName>&#8212;if religious toleration were once firmly
rooted there! Religion, morality, the arts and sciences, the great sources<pb n="301"/>
of liberty&#8212;which is in fact, the cause of mankind&#8212;all unite in calling
upon the free, the generous, the enterprising and the pious, to step forward
in aid of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. We expect aid from the <persName>religious portion of the 
community</persName>, and that the <placeName>pulpit </placeName>will pour out its fervent prayers to a just God
for his blessing on our endeavors, and send its eloquent voice to the people
in the cause of all free churches&#8212;the cause of truth and justice.</p>

<p>Our fate will probably be decided in three months. <persName>Santanna </persName>is making
a great effort. If he fail, it must be his last. Now is the time to aid us&#8212;
now is the time of salvation. We need everything&#8212;provisions and money&#8212;
and men well armed, officered, and provided. Their expenses will all be
refunded at the close of the war, with interest, besides donations in <placeName>land</placeName>,
The opening is a great one, if it were only a matter of speculation&#8212;it is
glorious in its cause. A <placeName>new republic</placeName> is about to rear its independent
banner over a country but lately a <placeName>wilderness</placeName>&#8212; There is magnificence in
the idea&#8212;prosperity freedom and glory in the results.</p>

<p>We shall stop one day at <placeName>Louisville</placeName>. I should like much to visit 
<placeName>Lexington</placeName>. Some of my much cherished <persName>schoolmates </persName>and <persName>companions </persName>of happy
days still reside there: <persName>John McCalla</persName>, <persName>Pierce Butler</persName> the <persName>Todds</persName> etc. please
remember me to them. Tell my <persName>Cousins E_________ and H____________</persName>
I hope it will not be long before they can live in <placeName>Texas </placeName>with such comforts
as they merit. If we weather the storm untill <date n="06-xx-1836">June </date>all will end well and
prosperously. I have no doubt we shall, for we rely on aid from the
<persName>people of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName></persName>&#8212;<hi rend="italic">but it must be prompt.</hi></p>

<p>There is a <persName><placeName>Louisiana </placeName>Battalion</persName>; a <persName><placeName>Georgia </placeName>Battalion</persName>; a <persName><placeName>Mississippi</placeName>
Battalion</persName>; an <persName><placeName>Alabama </placeName>Battalion</persName>; and a <persName><placeName>Tennessee </placeName>Battalion</persName>; why can
there not be a <persName><placeName>Kentucky </placeName>Battalion</persName>? It would be a fine opening for a 
<persName>military man of standing</persName>&#8212;a <placeName>Lafayette </placeName>service. They might go by land from
<placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>, or by water from here. The former I prefer, as <persName>Mexican</persName>
cruisers are <placeName>on the coast</placeName>. We are fitting out some to meet them, but our
money is rather short.</p>

<p>I have written hastily and must close, for I am at the end of the paper,
but not at the end of the subject. It is a copious one, and I am perhaps
rather enthusiastic in the view I take of it. My whole heart and soul is
devoted to it. I am well.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. A</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
