<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5139">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Henry Austin to Asa Brigham and J S D Byrom, 03-31-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Henry Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-30">07-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Asa Brigham 
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        J S D Byrom
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brazoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 320-323
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-03-31">03-31-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Neglect of its financial agents by the government. Naval policy</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>To <persName>Honble Asa Brigham</persName></p>
<p><persName>J. S. D. Byrom</persName>.</p>
<p><persName>Delegates </persName>of the <persName>Hon. Convention</persName> from <placeName>Brazoria</placeName></p>

<p><placeName>Gentn</placeName>.</p>

<p>I am impelled by a sense of duty as an individual <persName>citizen of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> to
apprize you and through you if you think it consistent with your public
duties the <persName>President </persName>and <persName>members of the Convention</persName> of the deranged state<pb n="321"/>
of the interests of <placeName>Texas </placeName>in this city The <persName>Commissioners of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> when
here appointed <persName>Mr. William Bryan General Agent</persName> and <persName>Edward Hall 
Purchasing Agent for <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> and contracted a loan here for Two hundred 
thousand dollars of which ten per cent or Twenty thousand dollars was paid in
cash, the balance to be paid in instalments on receipt of the ratification of
the conditions of the loan by the <persName>Convention</persName>. Another Loan of Fifty 
thousand dollars was also contracted here on which it is said Forty thousand
dollars cash was paid, of this amount say Sixty thousand dollars, Eleven
thousand only have been received by the <persName>Agents</persName>, Ten thousand remain in
the <placeName>Bank </placeName>subject to the draft of the <persName>Government of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> only, nearly all
the remainder it is believed was placed in the hands of sundry <persName>purchasing
Agents</persName>,* and disbursed to their discretion without supervision by any 
<persName>comptroaling officer</persName> or the usual checks upon disbursements of public moneys.
The <persName>Agents </persName>here in full confidence that the loan would be promptly 
ratified and the money be ordered to be placed at their disposition have 
purchased and accepted for the <persName>navy </persName>and supplies to an amount exceeding
Ninety thousand Dollars. Such articles as could only be had for cash have
been paid for cash untill the <persName>General Agent</persName> is actually in advance of cash
to the amount of Six thousand Dollars, and has cash responsibilities for
Two thousand Dollars over and above all he has received. The 
<persName>Commissioners </persName>wrote him from <placeName>Nashville </placeName>that they had requested the <persName>Provisional
Government</persName> to send him a check on the <placeName>Bank </placeName>for Five thousand dollars.
None has been transmitted and there is reason to fear that before this will
be attended to the credit of the <persName>Government of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> will be utterly 
prostrate whilst the public money is idle in the <placeName>Bank</placeName>. For the payment of
supplies purchased the <persName>Agent </persName>has issued promisory notes signed by him
as <persName>Agent for <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> where such would be received, where not&#8212;his own 
individual responsibility. These notes are falling due and not a dollar of
public money to meet them. No ratification of the loan has been received.
No authority to the <placeName>Agent </placeName>to receive what money there is in the <placeName>bank </placeName>has
been transmitted and it is apprehended [that ere] this shall be attended to
the credit of the <persName>Government </persName>will be prostrate and the <persName>Agent </persName>injured in his
credit and private business if not involved in ruin. Had the <persName>Government</persName>
attended to the all important matter of sustaining the public credit the 
proceeds of the loan would have been now at the disposition of the <persName>Agent </persName>who
could by discounting at this moment of unpresedented pressure for money
the paper now out have raised the credit of the <persName>Texas Govt</persName>. to such high
repute as to have made all future purchases on the faith of <persName><placeName>Texas </placeName>
Government </persName>on long credit and have left the balance of the money disposable for
the payment of the <persName>troops</persName>. Our only hope now is that the ratification of the
terms of the loan and a check of the bank for the funds in deposits may<pb n="322"/>
arrive before the operation of protesting commences. You <persName>Mr. Byrom</persName> are
too well acquainted with fiscal matters not to know that public credit like
a <persName>woman</persName>'s reputation once lost is seldom regained, never without time and
difficulty. I solicit your immediate attention to these subjects as one 
involving all our interests and all our hopes in an eminent degree&#8212; I take
the liberty to call your attention to the insecurity and improvidence of
authorizing numerous receiving and <persName>disbursing agents</persName> of the public money
without connection with or accountability to the chief or foreign <persName>Agent of
the Government</persName>. Champaigne and laced uniforms will not kill <persName>Mexicans</persName>
though they be merged in charges for <placeName>naval or military stores</placeName>, and it would
be absurd to expect that young and inexperienced <persName>officers </persName>unacquainted wilh
business would disburse money placed in their hands to fit out an armed
ship or equip a regiment with that economy and judgement indispensable
for the success of such a cause as ours which can only be sustained by the
most prompt and vigorous exertions and the most frugal use of the scanty
means at our command.</p>

<p>The <persName>commissioners </persName>have in my opinion made a most judicious selection
of <persName>Agents </persName>in <persName>Mr. William Bryan</persName> and <persName>Mr Edward Hall</persName>, Gentlemen of sound
integrity and sufficient capital not involved in extensive business or 
speculations and whose books accounts and vouchers shew them to be well
acquainted to the necessity of transacting public business with such 
scrupulous exactness as to enable them to submit an exhibit of their doings to
the most rigid scrutiny.&#8212; There appears to be an effort making to procure
a separation of the agency giving to a new <persName>agent </persName>the control of the money
and to the others the present <persName>agents </persName>the burthen of the work and 
responsibility that is the purchase and shipment of supplies correspondence and
forwarding of <persName>volunteers </persName>etc. this will be impolitic and unjust in the 
extreme, I believe you will so view it and I beg your strenuous opposition to
such a measure should it be proposed. The neglect of the fiscal concerns of
<placeName>Texas </placeName>has heretofore been ascribed to the unfortunate quarrel of the 
<persName>executive </persName>with the <persName>council </persName>but now that the <persName>convention </persName>has been organized a
month and nothing done I am forced to the conclusion that the 
correspondence of the <persName>agents </persName>with the <persName>Government </persName>and the needful information
on this subject may have been witheld from that body. I feel it my duty to
apprize you of the alarming excitement which the capture by one of our
cruisers in the<placeName> Sisal Roads</placeName> of a schooner owned by an <persName>american merchant</persName>
resident in <placeName>Campeachy </placeName>and a house here, wearing the <persName>Mexican </persName>flag for the
benefit of difference in import duty has produced in this <placeName>city</placeName>. If our armed
vessels are to be employed to rob the very <persName>citizens </persName>of this city who furnished
the money to purchase them, of the property which they think proper to ship
to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>under cover of the <persName>Mexican </persName>flag for greater profit instead of being
directed to protect the commerce between the <placeName>United States</placeName> and <placeName>Texas </placeName>and
to prevent the transportation of provisions and <persName>troops </persName>by sea to the <persName>army of<pb n="323"/>
Santa Anna</persName>, the disposition to aid our cause which has been so ardently
evinced by the <persName>citizens of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></persName> will speedily be changed to an 
extreme disapprobation. Large quantities of provisions and other supplies are
shipping from this place by the <persName>house of M. de Lizardi &amp; Co agents of Santa
Anna to <placeName>Matamoros</placeName></persName> in American vessels&#8212; were our little <persName>squadron </persName>
confined strictly to public service between <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>and <placeName>Matagorda </placeName>they
could not only protect our own commerce but effectually prevent the 
transmission of <persName>troops </persName>and provisions by sea to the <placeName>seat of war</placeName> or other parts of
the <placeName>coast</placeName>. Capturing American vessels would no doubt produce great 
dissatisfaction but taking out of them provisions and munitions destined to the
<persName>enemy </persName>and for the <persName>enemy</persName>'s use and paying the freight would I think be
justified by the necessity of the case and not be censured by any reasonable
man. You will pardon me for troubling you so long with so long a 
communication, I am impelled to it by the conviction that it is the duty of every
<persName>citizen </persName>to do spontaneously whatever he may believe to be serviceable in
any degree to the community of which he is a member.</p>

<p><date when="1836-03-31">March 31st 1836</date>	<persName>Henry Austin</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
