<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5282">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Samuel Williams, 10-12-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-17">08-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel Williams
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Columbia, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 435-436
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-10-12">10-12-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Heartbroken because cannot accept Williams' explanation of land speculation</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Colombia </placeName><date when="1836-10-12">Oct. 12. 1836</date></p>

<p><persName>S. M. Williams.</persName></p>

<p>yours of <date when="1836-08-29">29 Augt</date>, recd/ at <placeName><persName>Mr Perry</persName>s</placeName> on the <date when="1836-10-01">1st instant</date>. I was then just
able to sit up from an attack of fever and am now barely able to crawl
about a little&#8212; I read your letter with such feelings as a drowning man
would seize a plank&#8212; <persName>Sam Williams</persName> you were wound around and rooted
in my affections more than any man ever was or ever can be again&#8212; I
wished, and hoped to see or hear something that would convince me I was
wrong or had too seriously viewed your acts etc since I left in <date n="xx-xx-1833">1833</date>. you
were to have closed the land business pending of the <placeName>old colonies</placeName> and 
attended to the last one&#8212;nothing was done or next to nothing, and I still
have all that cursed trouble on my hands besides the censure and Gabble
of discontent, which is of little consequence it is true but is not very 
pleasant&#8212; But all this is nothing, those cursed <placeName>Monclova </placeName>speculations and
Contracts by which you have involved yourself and <persName>friends </persName>and country in
evils which will last for years, and which you certainly never even drempt
of and know nothing of now&#8212; <persName>W. H. Jack</persName> was the man who gave me the
first account of that damn.d transaction that I understood. That an attempt
was made by you to get up an excitement in the <placeName>Colony </placeName>and to draw men
from here under the pretext of defending the <persName>Governor</persName>, when in reality they
were to be used as a part of the <hi rend="italic">pay </hi>you and others were to be given on one
of those contracts&#8212; I was led and bound to believe by <persName>Jack</persName>'s statement;<pb n="436"/>
and also that you spared no kind of pains to precipitate the <placeName>country </placeName>into
war immediately, an event which you must have known would have 
perpetuated my imprisonment indefinitely&#8212; you also must have known that
all the odium of those things, would be cast on me by the envious and 
slanderous owing to our long friendship and relations. The fact is <persName>Williams</persName>
that all those <placeName>Monclova </placeName>matters, I mean the speculations, and precipitating
the <placeName>country </placeName>into war, were morally wrong, they have some very criminal
and dreadfull features&#8212; I am too much debilitated to say more you say
your motives were good&#8212; In the name of God convince me of that&#8212;
Had I cared nothing about you and <persName>McKinney </persName>these things would have had
no effect on me&#8212; <persName>McKinney </persName>began abusing and slandering me when I was
absent in the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> his idea of friendship is that one must be the tool of
his friend right or wrong&#8212; he has chosen his course and is quite welcome
to keep it&#8212; he is very far from being the high minded man I once 
believed him to be&#8212; But you will probably get on well&#8212; Speculation and
honesty cannot contend in <placeName>Texas </placeName>the former will gain some twenty or
100 to one. What I mean by honesty here is honesty to the public interest
and the public good&#8212; Convince me in the name of God that you have
been and are honest to the public interest and the public good as you say
you have been and restore yourself where you once stood in the opinion of</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>It seems that <persName>Jack </persName>and <persName>Warren Hall</persName> are about commencing a sistem of
persecution against me on some pretext of a claim of old <persName>Andy Roberson</persName>
about a <placeName>half league of <persName>Elders</persName></placeName> I know nothing about it&#8212; <persName>R.</persName> has no
claim on me</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
