<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5219">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>S B Dickinson to Stephen F Austin, 07-08-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>S B Dickinson</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-12">08-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Fayett, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 388-389
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-07-08">07-08-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Advising how to obtain military and political aid for Texas</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Fayette Mi</placeName> <date when="1836-07-08">July 8th 1836</date></p>

<p><persName>Hon S F Austin</persName></p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>I have just been advertised through the medium of the <persName>press</persName>, of the 
expected invasion of <placeName>Texas </placeName>by the <persName>Mexicans</persName>&#8212; I had hoped that the battle of
<placeName>San Jacinto</placeName> was a decisive one, but circumstances seem to have directed it
otherwise. The present appears to be an unfortunate moment for the
<persName>Texians</persName>, the war with the <persName>Indians </persName>must necessarily divide their <persName>army </persName>and
thereby render it difficult for them to meet the <persName>Mexicans </persName>in sufficient force
upon the <placeName>frontiers </placeName>to resist successfully the impending invasion&#8212; Joined
with the above, it unfortunately happens that the proceedings of <persName>D G 
Burnett</persName> and his <persName>Cabinet</persName>, has been throughout his whole <persName>administration </persName>so 
directly opposite to the necessities of his own <persName>Government </persName>and the 
expectations of the people here, that they have no confidence whatever in him,
Notwithstanding these untoward circumstances of the <persName>Govt</persName>. I am daily
doing all I can to promote her welfare, by inducing persons to emigrate
and to volunteer in the service of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and I hope my efforts tho' feeble
are not without effect, there have many young men at my instigation left
here for the <persName>Texian army</persName> and I hope I may be instrumental in sending
many more I have had many and long conversations with <persName>Genl T. Hinds</persName>
whose character you may possibly know from his activity in the <persName>Creek </persName>war
and battle of <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>&#8212; he has told me repeatedly if he was solicited
by the <persName>Texian Govt</persName>, or any of its respectable <persName>officers </persName>he would 
unhesitatingly lend his aid personally and take as many with him as he possibly
could to share in your struggles for liberty. I seem to think it possible
from his popularity for him to take 2 or <persName>3 hundred</persName> or more. I mention
this for your consideration not presuming to dictate nor even advise you,
knowing your patriotism and interest for your <placeName>country</placeName>'s welfare&#8212; Your
election is now near at hand and I sincerely hope you will make a good<pb n="389"/>
selection for your <persName>President</persName>. Bring the <persName>people </persName>to see and feel the necessity
of a radical change, if you elect another <persName>D G</persName> you are lost, I am daily
ask'd what are the inducements to go to <placeName>Texas</placeName>? You have no <persName>govt</persName>: and
should you succeed in repelling the <persName>Mexicans </persName>you will have a civil war of
your own, more exterminating than that of your <persName>foreign enemy</persName>&#8212;such is
the general opinion here and such their language&#8212; Yet I endeavour to hold
forth fair prospects after the <date when="1836-09-01">first of Sept</date>. in the subsequent <persName>Govt</persName>. I
should like to be with you but my circumstances will not permit, I was
absent at the time I could have collected Moneys due me and during that
absence drained my purse, tho' I shall be in <placeName>Texas </placeName>as soon as possible&#8212;
I would mention also that a correspondence with <persName>Genl. Hamilton of
<placeName>Charleston S. C.</placeName></persName> might be profitable&#8212;he is deeply devoted to the Texian
Cause and of great influence We have not yet reed, the long expected and
much desired news of the recognition of <placeName>Texas </placeName>by the <placeName>U. S. </placeName>It must come
in a few days if recognized this last session If you see <persName>Dr Archer</persName> and
<persName>W H Wharton</persName> remember me to them tell them I am deeply devoted to
the <persName>Texan </persName>Cause and can only regret that it is impossible for me to be
with you to share in the struggles of my adopted country for her 
independence, while for the success of your arms the prosperity of your 
country, and the welfare of her <persName>Citizens </persName>and particularly yourself. You will
please to accept the prayers and best wishes of your friend and servt</p>

<p><persName>S B Dickinson</persName></p>

<p>Should you have time to write and feel willing to drop me a few lines I
should feel pleased to hear from you</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
