<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5345">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Elias Wightman to Unknown, 12-31-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Elias Wightman</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-31">08-31-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unsent</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unsent</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 479-480
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Deposition</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-12-31">12-31-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-31" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Deposition concerning Austin's landholdings</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>I <persName>Elias R Wightman</persName> on my oath say and declare that I became 
acquainted with <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> and <persName>James B Austin</persName> in <date n="xx-xx-1825">1825 </date>and that in
<date n="xx-xx-1826">1826 </date>I entered into a contract with <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> to give him one
fourth of the <placeName>matagorda Town League N° 11</placeName> for and in consideration of
the like quantity of lands, else where</p>

<p>That in <date n="xx-xx-1827">1827</date> I obtained title to said <placeName>league N° 11.</placeName> When I requested
to know what lands the sd <persName>Austin </persName>would point out that we might lift our
bonds, and take title when he offered a <placeName>fourth of the <persName>Crownover </persName>League
N° 6 west of Rio Colorado</placeName>, for which he executed to me his bond for title,
and I made title to <persName>James B. Austin</persName> to one fourth of said <placeName>L. N° 11.</placeName> and
so it remained till <date n="xx-xx-1830">1830 </date>(as I think) when in compliance with said bond
and other considerations, he agreed to give me <placeName>one fourth of the <persName>James
Jones</persName> tract</placeName> <hi rend="italic">number </hi>not recollected which he considered worth double the
<placeName><persName>Crownover </persName>quarter</placeName>, (as he said to me in a letter still in my possession) in
all this <persName>James B Austin</persName> was unknown in the stipulations and agreements
or in the consideration of the fourth of <placeName>N° 11.</placeName> L. other then receiving the
title that I recollect, and when in <date n="xx-xx-1827">1827</date> I <hi rend="italic">think </hi>we the <persName>proprietors </persName>met to
form regulations for the advancement of the projected Town of <placeName>Matagorda</placeName>,
out of compliment to <persName>James B Austin</persName> invited him to attend, He did so
and was one of the four <persName>signers </persName>of the first Constitution for the regulation
and transactions of the said Town, which Constitution is still in my 
possession with the signature of <persName>H. H. League</persName> <persName>Owner </persName>of one fourth <persName>James B.
Austin</persName> <persName>owner </persName>of one fourth <persName>Duke </persName>and <persName>Selkirk</persName>, by <persName>T. M. Duke</persName> <persName>owners </persName>of
one fourth and <persName>E R Wightman</persName> <persName>owner </persName>of one fourth, which was the 
principal act of ownership he ever exercised over it I wrote to him, at 
<placeName>Brazoria </placeName>or <placeName>Velasco </placeName>once, in <date n="xx-xx-1830">30</date>&#8212;or <date n="xx-xx-1831">31 </date>I <hi rend="italic">think </hi>on the subject of offering a
portion of it at sale in <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName> which he answered and much approved
but refered me however to <persName>Col Austin S. F.</persName> for his opinion as he said his
<persName>Brother</persName>'s approval would be necessary, as he knew more about those
things or something to that amount (which letter I still have among my
papers) <persName>Col Austin</persName> discouraged for this time the project of the sale of
Town property saying it was too soon to push <placeName>Matagorda </placeName>He was doing
more for <placeName>Matagorda </placeName>than all we could do by premature sale He was
settling the country up the <placeName>Colorado </placeName>with <persName>Kentucs </persName>and <persName>Tennesseans </persName>who
would, go down and make a frolic throwing the raft out etc. and I went
home and waited for the <persName>Kentuc </persName>frolic All other matters before and after
the demise of <persName>J. B. Austin</persName> <persName>Col S. F. Austin </persName>had the whole control of the
<placeName>4th of Matagorda</placeName>, and when the present Constitution was formed he acted
as the representative of <persName>J B. Austin</persName> at the same time avering that He was
the true and real <persName>owner </persName>which in due time he would show, and made such
declaration a matter of record in the <placeName><persName>Alcalde</persName>s office in the Town of San<pb n="480"/>
filipe de Austin</placeName>, since which time and before I have many letters in which
he exercised ownership over it and finally at <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> in <date n="xx-xx-1835">1835</date>&#8212;he did
the same when I saw him in <date n="12-xx-1835">Dec of same year</date>, and was recognized by the
<persName>board of proprietors</persName>, Yet nominally as the representative of his Brother
<persName>James B. Austin</persName> Through my <hi rend="italic">agency </hi>which was constituted at the framing
of the Instrument called the Constitution of the <persName>Board of proprietors</persName>, and
never revoked while he lived</p>

<p>As to the question of the lands deeded to <persName>James B Austin</persName> I cannot say
on what tenure he so secured them only from common report But I know
that <hi rend="italic">titles </hi>were made to him of which he knew nothing untill explained to
him as was the case of the <placeName>Matagorda </placeName>fourth interest</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
