<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5023">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Philip Dimmitt to Stephen F Austin, 11-06-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Philip Dimmitt</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-12">06-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Fort of Goliad, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Head Quarters, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 241-242
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-11-06">11-06-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Preparations to receive volunteers from New Orleans </add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Fort of Goliad</placeName>, <date when="1835-11-06">Nov. 6th. 1835</date>&#8212;6 o.c. AM.</p>
<p>To <persName>Gen. Stephen F. Austin</persName>,</p>
<p><persName>Com. in Ch. of the Army of the People</persName>,</p>
<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>Yours of the <date when="1835-11-03">3d. inst</date> by hand of <persName>Mr. Kemball</persName>, was duly recd, about
9 o. c. <date when="1835-11-05">last evening</date>. The <persName>Volunteers from <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName></persName>, have not yet reached
here. They were to arrive at the <placeName>Guardeloupe</placeName>, <date when="1835-11-05">last night</date>, and take up the
line of march at 4 o.c. <date when="1835-11-06">this morning</date>. We expect them with us <date when="1835-11-06">this evening</date>.
Your letter will be laid before them immediately on their arrival at <placeName>this
place</placeName>.</p>

<p>I forwarded to them <date when="1835-11-05">yesterday </date>by <persName>express</persName>, a communication addressed
to the <persName>Officers </persName>and <persName>privates of that Corps</persName>, greeting their arrival, and near
approach to <placeName>this post</placeName>, and tendering such congratulations as the time and
occasion seemed to recommend. I sent also an <persName>escort </persName>of <persName>7 men</persName> to meet
them, and by whom as many horses as could be spared, were sent along to
mount a <hi rend="italic">part</hi>, at least, of those who had not been able to procure horses,
at the time of our last advices.</p>

<p>I will here observe, that, we are assured, <hi rend="italic">another </hi>company, nearly ready
to leave when that now so near us, left <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName>, were to embark for
<placeName>Velasco </placeName>by the next departure, and are supposed to be now on the way.
<persName>Two other companies from <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName></persName>, who proceeded by water to 
<placeName>Natchitoches</placeName>, and were to come through by land, are now supposed to be <placeName>this
side the Sabine</placeName>.</p>

<p>To those who are expected to arrive here <date when="1835-11-06">to night</date>, as also to all others,
taking a like participation in the present and approaching struggle, every
facility in our power to extend, and every aid we can possibly give, will be
cheerfully, gratefully, and promptly afforded.</p>

<p>I have now <hi rend="italic">one </hi>request to make, and one which carries with it every
solicitude of my heart for the success of our arms, every deep, every strong<pb n="242"/>
and lively sensibility to the glorious termination of the present campaign&#8212;
I ask for permission to exercise my own discretion as to the force requisite
to sustain <placeName>this post</placeName>&#8212;and for leave to proceed with the balance, <hi rend="italic">forthwith</hi>,
to <placeName>Head Quarters</placeName>.</p>

<p>Cherishing the hope that you will grant this request, and advise me 
accordingly, as speedily as possible, permit me to subscribe myself, with 
sentiments of the highest consideration and Esteem,</p>

<p><persName>P. Dimitt Com g </persName>[Rubric]</p>

<p>P. S. Yours of the same date as that above acknowledged, but, we are
<hi rend="italic">informed</hi>, previously written, and forwarded by <persName>Volunteer Baylor</persName>, was also
recd, at the same time <date when="1835-11-05">last evening</date>. I infer from the tenor of the one <hi rend="italic">last</hi>
penned, that, the implied proposal "to fall back," as stated in the first, was
ultimately withdrawn, or overruled. Nothing could have been more 
gratefying than this implied information&#8212;as, on the other hand, nothing could
have been more unwelcome than <hi rend="italic">even </hi>the <hi rend="italic">suggestion </hi>that such a step was
among <hi rend="italic">possible </hi>expedients. The adoption of a retrograde movement, at
the present moment, unless coerced by imperious necessity, would, it 
appears to me, with all due respect for the wisdom of your Council, prove
little less than fatal. To develope, at length, all the evils, direct and 
consequential, mediate and immediate, of such a movement, in our <hi rend="italic">first </hi>essay,
with the <placeName>legions to the east</placeName>, at our backs, cheering and sustaining us, would
require pages, whereas it is allowed me to say but <hi rend="italic">little</hi>, and that <hi rend="italic">little </hi>in
<hi rend="italic">few </hi>words.</p>

<p><persName>Savriego</persName>, I am assured, is below, endeavouring to reorganize&#8212;. If I
take him again, which I shall try to do, he will hardly be permitted, <hi rend="italic">by me,</hi>
to <hi rend="italic">rally </hi>a second time.</p>

<p><persName>P. Dimitt </persName><hi rend="italic">Com g</hi> [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] To <persName>Gen. Stephen F. Austin Com. in Ch. of the Army of the
People</persName>,<placeName> Head Quarters</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
