<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5180">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Treat [?] to Stephen F Austin, Branch T. Archer, William H Wharton, xx-xx-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Treat [?]</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-08">08-08-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         Branch T. Archer
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         William H Wharton
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 355-357
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836">xx-xx-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Offering muskets</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><hi rend="italic">Memorandum Confidential Muskets.&#8212;</hi></p>

<p>There are 960, muskets in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>: English, Tower proof&#8212;<hi rend="italic">oz bore</hi>:
a first rate article: which I can controul, if not sold, on receipt of orders,
given for their delivery, from this place, which can go in a moment, through
you, whenever an arrangement can be concluded as <hi rend="italic">follows</hi>:</p>

<p>960 Muskets______________________________________________________6$ short price is	$5760.&#8212;</p>

<p>1/3 for cash ___________________________________________________ $1920.&#8212;</p>

<p>1/3 3 mot Credit_________________________________________________ 1920</p>

<p>1/3 may be merged in the loan____________________________________ 1920	             5.760.&#8212;</p>

<p>Should any portion of these be sold on receipt of the order that may be
given, the balance, that are unsold (whatever be the number) may be 
delivered instanter. &#8212;What think you of this proposition ? ?&#8212; I doubt not
these 960 Muskets remain unsold yet, but this I cannot, of course vouch
for.&#8212;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Again</hi>: There are 2000 Muskets <hi rend="italic">here </hi>of same description, good article
tower proof and ounce Ball or bore&#8212;The <persName>Holders </persName>ask for these $4.81 and
would amt to $9620&#8212; They will not sell them, Except for <hi rend="italic">part cash,</hi> and,
balance<hi rend="italic"> satisfactory short paper.</hi> They refused making any proposition
for the sale of them to you or your <persName>Govnt</persName>. as they are very cautious 
prudent folks, and know nothing of <placeName>Texas </placeName>affairs. &#8212;Probably we can manage
it here, to make an arrangement, for them, and deliver, them, at <placeName>N. 
Orleans</placeName>, as soon as they can be sent there, at the same <hi rend="italic">price </hi>and <hi rend="italic">terms</hi>, as the
<hi rend="italic">960, first </hi>spoken of, on this paper&#8212;. This, I repeat I think we can
<hi rend="italic">manage</hi>, provided <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, the <persName>commissioners</persName>, think the good cause, will be
promoted thereby by <hi rend="italic">so doing</hi> &#8212; and you must understand; at same time,
that the small Gain, in the operation, is not a sufficient <hi rend="italic">object </hi>for us or any
one to Embark in this last arrangement, Unless you should consider it an
object to the <persName>Texian Governt</persName>. to send them on</p>

<p>They can be shippd <hi rend="italic">At once,</hi> and sent to <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName>, and if all is right,
go down to <placeName>G. Bay</placeName> at once&#8212;probably without discharging at all &#8212;The
same vessel that takes these <hi rend="italic">(if they go)</hi> can also take anything else you
may have to send down from here&#8212; tell me what you think of the matter
1st- as regards the 960&#8212;and then as regards the 2000 here &#8212;If we can get<pb n="356"/>
the Loan up to 100.000 that will give us $10,000 Cash&#8212;and a portion of
this might perhaps be appropriated to the muskets.&#8212; <hi rend="italic">Now </hi>dont forget that
in connection with this and other <hi rend="italic">kindred topics</hi> of great interest to the
cause, you <hi rend="italic">must </hi>give us timely Notice, when you intend to leave 
<placeName>Washington</placeName>&#8212;and you must let us know a week or at least 4 or five days before
Hand, so that <hi rend="italic">one </hi>of <hi rend="italic">us </hi>can go on and arrange all&#8212;</p>

<p>This I consider important in many points of view, as in 6 or less Hours
all can be done which would require days and sheets of paper and then 
perhaps not be as well understood.&#8212;So, <hi rend="italic">tell us</hi> or me, in answer to this and if
you can, by return post, how your time goes, and when you fix your 
departure in anticipation, and let us know, I will run on and see you, if 
possible and if not one of us <hi rend="italic">will </hi>go, and this will give us time to see what we
can do in the way of extending the Loan and also with subscription 
Donation lists etc.</p>

<p>Pardon my scrawl for I have been interrupted momently since I set down
at my desk&#8212; If <date n="05-xx-1836">tomorrow</date>s mail, or <date n="05-xx-1836">tomorrow</date>s steam boat confirms the
rumors (in <persName>Bryan</persName>'s Letter) that <hi rend="italic"><persName>Sam </persName></hi>has whippd- the <persName><persName>Mexicans</persName></persName>. It will of
course have a good effect on our collections and Subscriptions&#8212;</p>

<p>Excuse my lengthy communications for I have not had time to make
them <hi rend="italic">shorter</hi>&#8212; Very truly</p>

<p><persName>El mismo</persName></p>

<p>Dont let these papers or my letters lay about or be exposed&#8212;</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Private Continued</hi></p>

<p>As regards the insurance there may be no claim on any one&#8212; If the
office Insured the property <hi rend="italic">against all risk&#8212; Including Capture</hi> by the
<persName>Enemy </persName>then there is no claim&#8212; If not against capture, but only against
sea Risk then the <persName>owners </persName>have no claim on the Insurance. &#8212;but <hi rend="italic">lose the</hi>
property, <hi rend="italic">without recourse</hi> to any one</p>

<p>I shall send you the <placeName>Evening paper</placeName> and C and <placeName>Enquirer </placeName>of this <date n="05-xx-1836">morning</date>.
<hi rend="italic">also</hi>;&#8212; The former will no doubt Copy from the <placeName>Orleans papers</placeName> of <date when="1836-05-02">2d</date>
came to hand this morning&#8212; Nothing direct from <placeName>Texas</placeName>, but some 
interesting advice from <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>, which ought to appear in <placeName>the Globe</placeName>&#8212;
<persName>Gorostizal </persName>is, in <placeName>Phila</placeName>. or will be today&#8212;He intends publishing in <placeName>the Globe</placeName>
or <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Nat Intel</placeName></hi>, his full correspondence with this <persName>Govnt</persName>. also you will see
the <persName>President</persName>s answer to the call of the <persName>House of Reps.</persName> which has not
reached us, &#8212;I call your attention to the enclosed paper in reference to
<persName>M</persName>&#8212;which you will please reply to, as soon as possible, and give me a
definite answer, as regards this transaction. Let it be a separate paper in
reply to mine, to show to the <persName>parties</persName>.&#8212; I have this morns. Letter from
<persName>S. F. Austin</persName> at <placeName>Phila</placeName>. dated <date when="1836-05-14">14th</date> and note its contents. I hope to hear from<pb n="357"/>
<persName>the <hi rend="italic">head </hi>of the <hi rend="italic">Committee </hi>at <placeName>Phila</placeName>.</persName> on the subject of the men, money,
wanted, to move them etc.&#8212; I was going to write him but shall wait, until
<date n="05-xx-1836">tomorrow </date>to receive his Letter We shall move in this business, without
doubt, and that promptly&#8212; See <persName>Stone</persName>s letter to you of yesterday addressd-
either at <placeName>Baltimore </placeName>or <placeName>Washington</placeName>&#8212;I dont remember which&#8212;I agree with
you that the <placeName>south </placeName>will save you&#8212; Still, I am sorry nothing further has
been done here&#8212; that [than] when you left us&#8212; Tho I think something
further <hi rend="italic">will </hi>be done&#8212;today has been the first working day among us&#8212;and
I suppose all are at work but myself&#8212; I confess I have done nothing, and
the reason is before you&#8212;all calls on the subject of <placeName>Texas </placeName>are made to
me&#8212;all <persName>enquirers </persName>sent to me&#8212;I have to get the news from the files of
papers <hi rend="italic">then</hi>, confer with <persName>Editors</persName>, and Talk up and answer inquiries etc. then
write you etc. etc. So that I trust you will find some excuse for me at
least for today&#8212; I do all I can and will do my utmost of this you must not
doubt. But I have to do all myself, none can act for me: or write for me&#8212;
This keeps me hard at work without fulfilling my promise of going on as I
intended today&#8212; Still will tomorrow&#8212; The Charleston Boat, tomorrow
might bring us news no doubt&#8212; I also send you a <placeName>western paper</placeName> just recd-&#8212;
it might contain something of interest: Yours etc</p>

<p>Very truly and cordially	The same</p>

<p>Pray let me hear from you fully and as often as possible and pardon
my scrawl Papers herewith.</p>

<p>Again Truly	<persName>El Mismo</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
