<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5251">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Thomas J Rusk, 08-09-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-16">08-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Thomas J Rusk
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Navidad, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 412-414
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-08-09">08-09-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Explaining his attitude toward Santa Anna's release and disclaiming interest in Williams's land speculations</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Navidad</placeName>, <date when="1836-08-09">August 9, 1836</date></p>

<p><persName>BRGR. GEN. T. J. RUSK</persName></p>

<p>Dr Sir&#8212;</p>

<p>I met <persName>Dr. Archer</persName> and <persName>Mr. Wharton</persName> at this place&#8212; They showed me
your letter to the <persName>secretary of War</persName> and instructions to them, as to the 
contemplated movement of the army against <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>&#8212; <persName>Archer </persName>requested
me to return with them so as to combine all our efforts in support of this
measure and I shall do so&#8212;</p>

<p>It was my intention to have visited you before this, but hearing that the
<persName>enemy </persName>had Made no move from <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>I remained at my <placeName><persName>brother in
law</persName>s</placeName> to obtain a few days rest and recruit my health&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Dr Archer</persName> and Many others whose opinions I feel bound to respect, 
insisted that I should be a <persName>candidate </persName>for <persName>President </persName>at the <date n="09-xx-1836">September </date>
elections&#8212; <persName>Mr. W. H. Wharton</persName> was also of the number who requested it.
My name is accordingly before the <persName>people</persName>&#8212; I have consented to this for
only one reason, which is that I believe I can be of material service in 
procuring the annexation of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> should the <persName>people </persName>here wish it,
as I have no doubt they do.</p>

<p>As is usual in such cases, there no doubt are many erronious reports in
circulation&#8212;I have heard two&#8212; One that I am interested in the land<pb n="413"/>
speculations of <persName>Williams </persName>and others when they were at <placeName>Monclova</placeName>&#8212; This
is utterly false&#8212;I never have been, am not, and never will be interested in
those speculations, directly nor indirectly, and no one in <placeName>Texas </placeName>is more
opposed to them than I am, and this I say in the nature of a rule of Action,
so far as one can be formed from my knowledge of the subject, for the fact
is that I never have fully understood it, untill within a few days, and I do
not know that I understand it all yet, for these events all took place in my
absence.</p>

<p>The other report is that I have been the means of saving <persName>General Santa
Anna</persName>. That man was saved by <persName>Gen. Sam. Houston</persName>, as you know better
than I do, and was used by him to procure the Armistice, or arrangement
of <date when="1836-04-22">22d. April</date> by which I am told orders were issued by <persName>Santa Anna</persName> to
<persName>Filisola</persName>&#8212;he was also saved by the <persName>Cabinet of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> subsequently, and
treaties made with him. I disapprove of all these measures-The first
I think was almost ruinous to <placeName>Texas </placeName>for it saved the balance of the 
<persName>Mexican Army</persName>, and the other I think was wrong in principle, and more so in
the <hi rend="italic">mode </hi>or <hi rend="italic">manner </hi>of using <persName>Santa Anna</persName></p>
<p>If the principle was adopted at all of using <persName>Santa Anna</persName> for the public
good of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, on the basis of saving his life, the only use that could or
ought to have been made of him in my opinion was with the <persName>U. S. Govt</persName>,
and not by an armistice or a treaty&#8212; An application from <persName>Santa Anna</persName>
to that <persName>Govt</persName>, to mediate between <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and <placeName>Texas</placeName>, on the basis of a 
recognition of the independence of the latter, in all probability would have led
to a correspondence on the subject between the <persName>U. S. Govt</persName>, and that of
<placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212; If <persName>Santa Anna's friends or party</persName> had remained in power, they
would no doubt have come to an arrangement through the Mediation of
the <placeName>U. S.</placeName>&#8212; If his party had lost their influence, no good would have 
resulted, and we should still have kept <persName>Santa Anna </persName>a close prisoner, and all
the bad effects of attempting to liberate him by the treaty with him would
have been avoided&#8212; I expressed this opinion to <persName>Mr Burnet</persName> and other 
<persName>members of the Govt</persName>, and asked whether <persName>Santa Anna</persName> had written to the <persName>U. S.
Govt.</persName>&#8212; The answer was that he had not I was at <placeName>Colombia </placeName>a few days
afterwards and saw <persName>Santa Anna</persName>,&#8212;he said much about his desire to procure
the mediation of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName>&#8212; I told him that no mediation would be 
accepted by <placeName>Texas</placeName>, except on the basis of a recognition of our independence&#8212;
he said that was the basis on which he acted and proposed to write to <persName>Gen.
Jackson</persName>&#8212; I replyed that he ought to do so, and to state in his letter his
firm and full conviction that <placeName>Mexico </placeName>could not continue the war with
<placeName>Texas </placeName>etc&#8212;</p>

<p>It is certainly clear that no harm can grow out of this letter, and 
admitting that no good results, as to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, it will evidently do good to
<placeName>Texas </placeName>in public estimation, elsewhere, by showing to the world that the<pb n="414"/>
proud despot of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, acknowledges that the physical force and 
resources of <placeName>Texas </placeName>are Sufficient to sustain herself, and that he has yielded
the point.</p>

<p>As to whether <persName>Santa Anna</persName> is sincere or not, every one will doubt or 
disbelieve, and justly so, As regards his promises or declarations made to the
<persName>Govt</persName>, or <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>;&#8212;but, very few will believe that he would 
attempt to make -a tool of <persName>Gen. Jackson</persName> by telling him lies under his own
signature&#8212;The <hi rend="italic">Moral </hi>effect therefore of <persName>Santa Anna</persName>'s letter to <persName>Gen. 
Jackson</persName> must be in favor of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, because it will be considered as a confession
by our principal <persName>enemy</persName>, that <placeName>Texas </placeName>has the power to sustain herself&#8212; I
wrote to <persName>Gen Jackson</persName>&#8212;my object was to try and get the intervention of
the<placeName> U. S.</placeName> and to have <placeName>Texas </placeName>annexed to the <placeName>U. S.</placeName></p>

<p>This is all I have done in this matter, and such have been the motives
which influenced me&#8212; They are pure and disinterested. I could derive
no benifit, but on the contrary I knew that it would injure me even to see
<persName>Santa Anna</persName>&#8212; I disregarded that injury because I saw that it was <hi rend="italic">possible</hi>
to do good to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and <hi rend="italic">impossible </hi>to do harm by <persName>Santa Anna</persName>'s letter to
<persName>Gen. Jackson</persName>&#8212; If a man who is governed by these kind of motives is to
receive the curses of those he is laboring to serve, then I should say that
purity of intention and disinterestedness have lost their moral influence.
I never did approve of the principle that was adopted as to <persName>Santa Anna</persName>
when he was first taken I think he merited death, and that the <placeName>country</placeName>
ought not to have been compromised to save him, nor do I approve of the
acts of the <persName>Cabinet </persName>in this, and other things, but I would not on that 
account do any thing to overturn our <persName>civil govt</persName>. I will always resist such
an attempt so far as I can&#8212; As a <persName>Texian </persName>I have no sympathies for <persName>Santa
Anna</persName>, and every possible cause to hate him. My sympathies are all for
the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> and I have labored faithfully to serve them regardless
of myself or popularity as the past and also this <persName>Santa Anna</persName>'s letter proves.
I shall return to <placeName>Velasco </placeName>and cooperate all I can to carry into effect the
plan of campaign which has been adopted In doing this I shall also be
slandered because it will be used against me by those who are opposed to
the <persName><placeName>Matamoras </placeName>expedition</persName>, and also because it will retard my visit to the
<persName>Army </persName>and the false reports which have been circulated against me will 
remain uncontradicted, except by this letter which I must beg the favor of
you to communicate to Generals <persName>Green</persName> and <persName>F. Huston</persName> and to the <persName>officers</persName>
and <persName>men </persName>so far as you can conveniently&#8212;</p>

<p>I am also very anxious to see you, the friendship we formed in time of
my ill health before <placeName>Bexar</placeName>, is I assure you unabated on my part and
strengthened rather than diminished by absence&#8212; I feel truly grateful to
you for the services you have rendered <placeName>Texas</placeName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
