<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5022">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to President of the Consultation, 11-05-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-12">06-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        President of the Consultation
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Head Quarters above Bexar, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Where ever the Consultation may be</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 239-241
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-11-05">11-05-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Advises letters of marque, organization of regular army, expedition from New Orleans against Matamoras. Send no more whiskey to camp</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Confidential</p>
<p><placeName>Head Quarters above Bexar</placeName> <date when="1835-11-05">Nov. 5, 1835</date></p>

<p>I have heretofore expressed an opinion that it would be doubtfull policy
to grant letters of mark, on more mature reflection I am inclined to change
that opinion&#8212; Every effort will be made to distroy us&#8212;we are therefore
fully justified in resorting to every possible means of defense.</p>

<p>After the <persName>convention </persName>have declared for the Constitution and federal
sistem, and <hi rend="italic">war </hi>against centralism, letters of mark might be granted to
defend our <placeName>coasts </placeName>and cruise against the vessels of the <persName>centralists </persName>and 
<persName>military usurpers</persName>&#8212;under this view I am in favor of it, and recommend the
measure ,</p>

<p>In short we are in a war, in which the objects of our <persName>enemies </persName>is our <hi rend="italic">total
extermination</hi>. It is a matter of life and death&#8212;there is no medium or
middle course left&#8212; none at all&#8212;under these circumstances there must be<pb n="240"/>
no half way measures on our side&#8212;no hesitation or scruples&#8212; The basis of
the Constitution is just, and to defend that Constitution and ourselves, we
are fully justifiable in calling in all the aid of <hi rend="italic">every description</hi>, we can get.</p>

<p>I again recommend the immediate organization of a <persName>civil Govt</persName>, and the
appointment of a <persName>Govr</persName>. or <persName>civil head</persName>&#8212; Also the organization of a <persName>regular
army</persName>, with a <persName>Genl</persName>. of well known military talents experience, integrity and
moral influence. This is very important.</p>

<p>With regard to certain <persName>individuals </persName>about whom I have been written to&#8212;
I beg leave to say that the <persName>convention </persName>is the only competent authority to
decide whether they are <persName>enemies to our country</persName> and cause or not&#8212; I would
on this subject respectfully recommend moderation and prudence&#8212; The
<persName>Army </persName>is in good spirits&#8212;the three cannon have arrived and 
<persName>reenforcements </persName>of <persName>180 men</persName>&#8212; I must however say that the taking of <placeName>Bexar </placeName>is very
difficult&#8212; My health for the last two weeks has been so bad that I have
been unable to attend actively in person to the duties of my station&#8212; they
would be truly arduous to the most experienced man, considering the nature
of a <persName>militia </persName>force, where there is no law but moral principle and 
enthusiasm to keep them together, but they' are doubly so to me with a 
debilitated constitution and bad health, added to a want of experience in Military
operations&#8212;I trust however that the <persName>people </persName>will be satisfied with the efforts
and the movements of the <persName>army </persName>so far.</p>

<p>We have in every instance driven the <persName>enemy </persName>within his <placeName>fortifications</placeName>
which are very strong and have gained many signal advantages.</p>

<p>Nothing will aid <placeName>Texas </placeName>so much as an <persName>expedition from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></persName>
against <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>under <persName>Genl Mexia</persName>&#8212; It is <hi rend="italic">all </hi>important&#8212; I recommend
that every possible effort be made to fit out such an <persName>expedition </persName>if it has not
already been done, as I hope it has been</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F. Austin </persName>[Rubric]</p>

<p>If <placeName>matamoros </placeName>is attacked and revolutionized by <persName>Mexia</persName>, <placeName>Bexar </placeName>would fall
as a matter of course, for all supplies of funds or <persName>troops </persName>would be cut off.
There is no way in which funds or <persName>men </persName>could be employed to so much
advantage to <placeName>Texas </placeName>as in an <persName>expedition </persName>against <placeName>Matamoros</placeName></p>

<p>This enterprise merits the first attention of the convention an <persName>express</persName>, at
any expense should be sent to the <persName>committee of <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName></persName> urging this
<persName>expedition</persName>, also to<placeName> N. York</placeName>&#8212;<persName>Zavala </persName>ought to write to <placeName>N. York</placeName> on the 
subject&#8212;even a <hi rend="italic">rumor </hi>of such a thing would keep <persName>troops </persName>from being sent
to <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>The military operations will be pressed now very rapidly, as much so
as practicable&#8212; The convention however must not be surprised should
<placeName>Bexar </placeName>hold out for a long time&#8212; It has been unanimously decided in a
<persName>council of war</persName> with one exception, that it ought not to be stormed&#8212; they
have plenty of provisions inside&#8212; The corn and country around <placeName>Bexar</placeName><pb n="241"/>
might be laid waste, it is true and [unreadable] <placeName>Guadalupe </placeName>but this will
ruin the <persName>inhabitants </persName>who are our <persName>friends </persName>The grass will all be burnt <placeName>from
Rio Grande to Bexar</placeName>&#8212; I shall send <persName>parties </persName>for this purpose but the other
measures of laying waste the <placeName>country round Bexar</placeName>, I think too hard on the
<persName>inhabitants</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin </persName>[Rubric]</p>

<p>By <persName>Express </persName>very important to be sent without delay</p>

<p>To the <persName>President of the General Consultation of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> <placeName>wherever it is in
session</placeName></p>

<p>In the name of Almighty God send no more ardent spirits to this <placeName>camp</placeName>&#8212;
if any is on the road turn it back, or have the head knocked out&#8212;</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
