<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5040">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Philip Dimmitt to Stephen F Austin, 11-14-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Philip Dimmitt</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-14">06-14-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Goliad, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 252-253
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-11-14">11-14-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-14" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Liberals in the interior cool toward Texas. Advises march on Matamoras</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Fort of Goliad, Nov. 14th 1835</p>

<p>To <persName>Gen. S. F. Austin,
Com. in Ch/ of the Army of the People</persName>,</p>

<p>Dear Sir, The facts communicated by <persName>Dr. Grant</persName>, and others, who 
accompanied <persName>Citizen Yiesca</persName> to <placeName>this place</placeName>, relative to the present state of
affairs in the <placeName>interior of the Country</placeName>, presents an unexpected, and highly
interesting prospect to the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>. From all that I have been
able to learn from these <persName>Gentlemen</persName>, it seems to be expected by our <persName>friends
<placeName>beyond the Rio Grande</placeName></persName>, that <placeName>Texas </placeName>should not only sustain herself against
the spread of Centralism, but it is also expected that she will send a <persName>force</persName>
to the <placeName>interior</placeName>, and give an impulse to a reaction there. But a small a
<hi rend="italic">very small</hi> portion, of what is called the <persName>liberal party</persName>, are either under
arms, or even making an effort to resist the strides of the <persName>usurper</persName>. They
do not appear from what I can learn, to be in a state of readiness to receive
or to be actuated by a temper to <hi rend="italic">invite, our</hi> interference with an <persName>armed
force</persName>, even were it convenient for <placeName>Texas </placeName>to take such a step.</p>

<p>An apparently studious, and a prolonged silence of the professed <persName>enemies
of the military system</persName>, concerning the course which <placeName>Texas </placeName><hi rend="italic">ought </hi>to take;
their forbearance to encourage her, even on paper, in the prosecution of
the one she has so nobly, and so fearlessly adopted; their failure to strike
there, whilst the <persName>enemy </persName>is thrilled with dismay here, are symptoms, 
portending a violent, perhaps a fearful crisis. If no effort is made along the
<placeName>Rio Grande</placeName> to revive the <placeName>republic</placeName>, can we hope for opposition <hi rend="italic">there </hi>to the
movement of <persName>troops from the <placeName>interior</placeName></persName>, to reinforce <persName>Cos</persName>, and recapture
<placeName>Goliad</placeName>? The <persName>population of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> is mostly of <placeName>foreign </placeName>origin. The 
<persName>inhabitants </persName>are considered <persName>foreigners</persName>. May not, and will not this be used as
an argument, (and will it not be all powerful as such,) to unite all <persName>parties</persName>
<hi rend="italic">there</hi>, for the particular object of crushing <placeName>Texas</placeName>? And whilst doing, or
trying to do this, time, and opportunity will have been afforded the 
<persName>Dictator</persName>, effectually to entrench himself behind the bulwarks of centralism.
In this way, he may hope to make, and perhaps <hi rend="italic">may </hi>make, a complete
conquest of the <placeName>whole country South of the Rio Grande</placeName>. This done, he
might well afford to withdraw from <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and leave her to the 
unmolested management of her own affairs. In the meantime, a sanguinary war
must rage and bleed Campaign after campaign would have been 
opened-<persName>army </persName>after <persName>army</persName>, would have been arrayed, and the resources of the 
<placeName>country </placeName>greatly impoverished, perhaps entirely exhausted.</p>

<p>Thus to divide and conquer, may not be embraced in the plan of the
<persName>Usurper</persName>. But whether it be or not, such a scheme, or something like it, is
certainly among possible occurrences, it is even highly probable.<pb n="253"/></p>

<p>In a former communication, I hinted the policy of a dash at <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>,
hoping from what I had then heard, that the movement would be approved
and sustained by a <persName>majority of the people</persName> in <placeName>that section of the country</placeName>.
But now, I fear it would not be. On the contrary, I am fully satisfied that
such a movement on the part of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, would be as likely to be opposed,
as to be approved</p>

<p>But another view of this subject is presented. If <placeName>Texas </placeName>cannot achieve
her liberation on any easier terms than those above supposed, would it
not be wise to use in the prosecution of the war, every weapon which she
can seize and weild, now in the hands of the <persName>enemy</persName>, or within his reach?
The <placeName>post of Matamoros</placeName>, if properly, and honestly superintended, would
yield a very considerable revenue. At present, its income is said to be
$100,000 per month. It is said that it ought to produce much more. This
is a formidable and efficient weapon. The position is imposing&#8212;it is 
commanding and its occupation would be likely to releive the grate and 
increasing <persName>population of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, from the immediate, and more appalling
calamities of war. <persName>Foreign volunteers</persName> can be introduced at that point, as
readily, and with as little expense, as at any other; and the position would
afford many facilities for annoying the commerce of the <persName>enemy</persName>, not 
furnished by any point on the <placeName>coast of Texas</placeName>.</p>

<p>This is a subject of immense importance to our <placeName>country</placeName>; and the policy
which she may adopt in relation to it, may greatly mitigate, or it may
multiply, and aggravate, the calamities of the war.</p>

<p>The <persName>Gerraro Battallion</persName>, our friends from the <placeName>interior </placeName>inform us, had
reached <placeName>Saltillo</placeName>, before they crossed the <placeName>N. River</placeName>, and had been ordered to
march immediately for <placeName>Bexar</placeName>. <persName>400 convicts</persName> were also to join them. This
information was communicated by <persName>Colo. Powers</persName> who said it was told to
him, a few hours previous.</p>

<p><persName>Cos</persName>, no doubt, has strong assurances of the arrival of <persName>reinforcements</persName>;
and on these he must rely, to enable him to hold <placeName>Bexar</placeName>.</p>

<p>Your opinion on the subject of this letter is urgently solicited.</p>

<p><persName>P. Dimitt</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
