<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5261">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Samuel M Williams to Stephen F Austin, 08-29-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Samuel M Williams</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-16">08-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, Lousiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Peach Point, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 424-426
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-08-29">08-29-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Declaring keen regard for Austin's good name, denying that he has done anything to tarnish it, and suggesting that Austin's enemies are gaining his confidence to ruin him</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date when="1836-08-29">29th August 1836</date></p>

<p>My Dear Sir</p>

<p>If any single expression of mine in this letter should wound or mortify
your feelings I entreat you "nothing extenuate nor set down aught in
malice"&#8212;for hurt and crush'd as is my spirit I would not on you inflict
the wound you have given me. I say given me, for although I have 
nothing direct from you, nevertheless I am informed that you charge me with
a want of regard for your standing and character&#8212; That you my dear sir
may have drawn such a conclusion, or that, by others you may have been
induced to believe such has been the fact, is a matter which has now passed
beyond the power of my control, and it is impossible for me to prevent
what has already been ushered into existence, and therefore all that I can
at this time do, is to call upon you to reflect and examine into the motives
you think I could have for such a proceeding towards any man I esteemed
as a <persName>friend</persName>, and more especially towards you, in whom at the same time
I ever have been proud to connect the title of friend and <persName>benefactor</persName>&#8212; I
believe you will readily grant&#8212;that it never could have been political
power, for that I never courted&#8212; It could not have been, money, for
that I am regardless of farther than it administers to my Comfort, and I
am not avaricious&#8212; If it has been an error in judgement in any matter
of policy, such error my friend (if you believe me possessed of feeling)
should have been more lightly visited than by a charge that at once sinks
every thing that is honorable, and stamps me with indelible marks of 
infamy&#8212;for If I am regardless of your fair fame, what is there I ask in the
name of God that I care for?</p>

<p>You may rest assured that it never has for once entered my mind that
your elevation to the Presidency was necessary for my personal interest&#8212;
no&#8212;I wished and desired it, and I still wish and desire it, for the fair fame
of our young <placeName>republic</placeName>; for its character and well being with other <placeName>nations</placeName>;
its prosperity at home and its pride abroad&#8212; Too well am I acquainted
with your principles of justice and your integrity, to believe for a moment
that your office, will be held for personal benefit of <persName>friends</persName>; or for the<pb n="425"/>
destruction of <persName>enemies</persName>&#8212;and too well, ever to ask or sue from you as 
<persName>President </persName>a favor not to be extended to the humblest individual&#8212; And from no
man, Govt, or country do I ask for more. &#8212;As <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> I would
have applied for favors, which I would not have asked of any living man,
for the reason that to <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName> will I grant and concede that which
I will not concede to any man that lives.</p>

<p>So far my dear sir, with respect to any designs or expectations that may
have been attributed to me, for desiring your election as <persName>President</persName>, and
now my dear sir permit me to make an observation or two on the subject
of those men (once bitter, deadly and determined <persName>foes</persName>) who are now
anxious to entwine themselves into your feelings and hold undisputed
sway over your heart&#8212;. You may rest assured that if your life is spared,
and God grant it may&#8212;you will see that it is not me that they are jealous
of, nor persons like me&#8212; We are not running for the goal they aim at&#8212;
you and you alone are the devoted the doomed individual&#8212;they have tried
open and villanous abuse; they have tried every thing with the people that
art could suggest; Malice could invent; and bare faced impudence put in
practice; By one of them you have been traduced from <placeName>New York</placeName> to the
<placeName>City of Saltilla</placeName>&#8212; they have been foiled in all their attempts, you have
had your reverses in the feelings of the people now up&#8212;then down&#8212;
Now forgotten and then remembered with gratitude&#8212; Of such materials
will you make friends?&#8212; dangerous experiment&#8212; In my opinion now
comes the master stroke of policy (God forbid I be prophetic in my 
conjectures) to ingratiate themselves in your confidence, work themselves into
your very heart of hearts; withdraw you from all your old friends and
adherents; and if possible cause you to commit acts of crying injustice,
in order to tarnish your fair fame in the page of history and then hold you
up to scorn and contempt thro, your own acts. If such be not their 
determination&#8212;if such be not their aim&#8212;Heaven pardon me for my suspicion&#8212;
If your avocations will permit, I should like to hear from you&#8212; I
should like to know what beyond a morbid feeling has aroused you (for
it may be two months before I can get back) and of what it is you 
complain in me&#8212; And be assured great as is my affliction under your censure
&#8212;greater is my esteem for you; and no matter what may be the exertions
of my <persName>enemies</persName>; no matter what you may believe necessary as your course
toward me&#8212;and no matter what I may suffer&#8212;I will disappoint their
hearts expectation; for long long ago have I sworn eternal friendship&#8212;
long ago have I sworn, come what will, come <hi rend="italic">what </hi>may never to forget the
confidence which once existed between us, and all the machinations of hell
shall not change my purpose nor my determination&#8212; Therefore write to
me and do so freely&#8212; send your letter to <persName>Mr Toby </persName>and he will send it to
me in the <placeName>western country</placeName> where I am bound from here.<pb n="426"/></p>

<p>I am pleased to say that the idea of your being made the <persName>President</persName> of
our Infant <placeName>republic </placeName>is well received in this <placeName>Country</placeName>, and it will tend very
much to give character and confidence to our new institutions&#8212;and God
grant you may succeed&#8212;</p>

<p>I hope a better state of feelings will take place between you and 
<persName>McKinney</persName>&#8212; he does not know you so well as I do&#8212;nor has he perhaps the
same obligation upon him that I have on me to bear your rebukes, and
even your injuries if I am doomed to receive them&#8212;but I feel persuaded
that under less excited feelings he is desirous of doing you justice. Nothing
would afford me more true satisfaction than to learn that all 
misunderstanding between you and him was buried in oblivion.</p>

<p>Suffer me again to intreat you, to let me hear from you&#8212;and permit me
to warn you from the snares and traps that designing <hi rend="italic"><persName>friends </persName></hi>are anxious
to put under your feet&#8212; I have used the word friends, altho. as reconciled
<persName>enemies </persName>I do not believe they ever will be found <hi rend="italic"><persName>friends</persName></hi>&#8212; yet heaven grant
they may be, and truly <hi rend="italic">friends </hi>in need&#8212;</p>

<p>Present my kindness to your <persName>sister</persName>, to <persName>Mr. Perry</persName> and the <persName>children</persName>, and
accept the assurance of my never varying esteem and friendship under all
circumstances.</p>

<p><persName>Samuel M Williams</persName> ...</p>

<p><persName>Stephen F Austin Esqr</persName></p>

<p>[Note by Austin]: Delivered to me by <persName>Col. Bernard Bee</persName> at My <persName>brother
in law</persName>s <placeName>Peach point</placeName> <date when="1836-10-01">october 1, 1836.</date>&#8212;Sunday&#8212; I was then too unwell to
accompany <persName>Col Bee</persName> and <persName>Gray </persName>[s] on up to <persName>congress </persName>at <placeName>Colombia</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
