<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5348">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Mirabeau B. Lamar to Gail Borden, Jr, 01-20-1837</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Mirabeau B. Lamar</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-31">08-31-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Gail Borden
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         Jr
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Brazoria, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 482-484
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1837-01-20">01-20-1837</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-31" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Tribute to Austin. Asks help in collecting material for a biography of Austin</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Brazoria </placeName><date when="1837-01-20">20th January 1837</date></p>

<p><persName>Gail Bourden [Borden] Esqr</persName>.</p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>For some time passed I have been collecting materials for the life of the
late lamented <persName>Genl. Stephen F. Austin</persName>. The task was originally under-<pb n="483"/>
taken in conformity with the wishes of the deceased; and it was upon him
that I relied for a greater portion of the matter which was to impart 
interest and value to the work; but before his public duties would allow
him the necessary leisure to examine and arrange his papers, <hi rend="italic">"the insatiate
archer"</hi> came&#8212;and laying low the brightest example of human enterprize
and virtue, has imposed upon his <persName>Biographer </persName>the painful necessity and
duty of seeking information from other sources. What we have lost in
loosing him, remains to be supplied as far as possible, by the contributions
of friendship and public spirit. The claims of <persName>General Austin</persName> upon the
affections of the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> were of the strongest kind. He was not
only the <persName>founder of our <placeName>Republic</placeName></persName>, but there is scarcely a blessing which
has flowed to the <placeName>country </placeName>that may not fairly be attributed to his untiring
efforts for its welfare; whilst almost every calamity and misfortune which
have befallen it, might have been averted by an adherence to his wise and
prudent counsels. The world has afforded but few examples of superior
intelligence and sagacity; and as for disinterested and extended 
philanthropy&#8212;his long sufferings for the weal of others&#8212;his patient endurance
under persecution&#8212;his generous forgiveness of <persName>enemies</persName>&#8212;and his final
sacrifice of health, happiness and life in the service of his <placeName>country</placeName>, all
conspire to place him without a modern rival amongst the first of <persName>patriots</persName>
and the best of men. Now that he lives no more to serve us by his 
counsels, or to receive the reward of labors, let us manifest our gratitude, by
doing justice to his memory&#8212;let us make a full and faithful record of his
good works, and following the example of his own generosity give each
venial error to the stream of Lethe. To pay due tribute to departed 
excellence, is a pleasing performance to the generous mind; and not to do
it&#8212;to deny just homage to exalted worth&#8212;evinces a sad insensibility to
virtue. Surely no one who casts his eyes over our broad and beautiful
<placeName>Prairies</placeName>, and reflects that he has come to the bright inheritance through the
toils and afflicting vicissitudes of one whose home, for our benefit, has been
the <placeName>wilderness </placeName>and the <placeName>dungeon</placeName>, can for a moment refuse his small 
contribution toward erecting a monument to the memory of the noble 
<persName>benefactor</persName>? And of what shall that monument consist?&#8212;of marble?&#8212; No&#8212;-
The best and purest superstructure which can be reared to the honor of
<persName>General Austin</persName>, is the record of his actions&#8212;the history of his life; and he
who shall contribute to this object by preserving any anecdote and 
interesting fact illustrative of his character, will not only render service to the
cause of truth and justice, but will be making some small return for the
many blessings which we are all enjoying from his labors. Permit me,
therefore, to ask the favor of you, to announce in your valuable paper, my
intention to compile his biography, and that I shall be pleased to receive,
by voluntary contribution, any information which may be servicable to the
undertaking. The labors of <persName>General Austin</persName> were extensive and important;<pb n="484"/>
so intimately connected with all the interesting events of his times, that a
faithful account of his life must necessarily embrace a large portion of the
history of our <persName>country</persName>. It will be perceived therefore that the materials
appropriate to such a work, will not be limited to any particular epoch,
but will include what ever relates to past wars&#8212;to the <persName>aborigines</persName>&#8212;to the
thrilling events of our present revolutionary struggle for Independence&#8212;
and indeed to every subject and circumstance in any wise connected with
the <placeName>country </placeName>and worthy to be remembered in its annals. His 
correspondence was extensive; and if collected, will go great way in explaining our
political history; such letters as may be entrusted to my use will be 
carefully preserved and returned to the <persName>proprietors </persName>whenever demanded; and
for all well authenticated facts and valuable documents, proper 
acknowledgements will be made and due credit given to the <persName>contributors</persName>. Be so
kind as to act as one of my <persName>agents </persName>in receiving and collecting materials for
the object proposed; and also state in your journal, that all contributions
intended for my use, may be address to the Care of<persName> Col Henry Austin of
<placeName>Bolivar</placeName></persName>, to yourself at <placeName>Columbia </placeName>and to <persName>Mr. Perry</persName> below <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>. As
<persName>Boswell </persName>said of <persName>Doctor Johnson</persName>, we ought not to <hi rend="italic">"loose one drop of our
immortal friend"</hi>; and it is to be hoped that the early followers of <persName>Genl.
Austin</persName>&#8212;the hardy adventurers, who blazed their way through the bottoms
of the <placeName>Brazos</placeName>&#8212;will not permit the soul stirring scenes of former days to
fade from memory, or go unchronicled, before the witnesses are called
upon to follow their faithful Pioneer to other and more beautiful Prairies
of the spirit land.</p>

<p><persName>Mirabeau B. Lamar</persName></p>

<p>[Note on back] : In setting up the above in type, correct the 
<hi rend="italic">orthography</hi>, but preserve my <hi rend="italic">punctuation</hi>.	<persName>M. B. L.</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
