<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5140">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>A J Yates to Stephen F Austin et Al, 04-01-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>A J Yates</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-30">07-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin et Al
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Washington City, U.S.</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 323-325
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-04-01">04-01-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reporting purchase of steamboat</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>(Letter F.)	Washington City April 1st 1836.</p>

<p>Messrs. <persName>S F Austin</persName> <persName>B T. Archer</persName> and <persName>W. H. Wharton</persName> <persName>Commissioners of
<placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>.</p>

<p>Gentleman</p>

<p>In compliance with your two several letters of Instruction to me dated at
<placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date when="1836-01-21">January 21st</date> and <date when="1836-01-22">22d ulto</date>. I proceeded to <placeName>New York</placeName>, and 
report the following as the result of my operations.</p>

<p>I found in the City of <placeName>New York</placeName> a Steam Boat called the Sandusky which
had been fitted for sea, and was for sale at $20,000. I employed a person
to take her out in the Bay that I might have an opportunity of fair 
examination of her engine etc, and on trial discovered serious and insurmountable
objections to her engine, which was double geared, and not calculated to
work with safety in rough weather at sea. I then inquired for others, and
found the Steam Boat "Frank," about one year old of 170 Tons, draws 4 1/2
feet water, price $25,000, and will require an expenditure of about $3,000.
to prepare her for sea service. Her boiler is old, she has but little 
furniture, and would not bear more than one nine pounder on her deck. I found
the "American Eagle," about the same size, a little deeper hold, with a new
engine, two years old, little furniture, a fast boat, rather stronger than the
"Frank," but would not bear a heavier armament, price $30,000 will require
about $2,500. to put in order for sea service. I also found the Steam Boat
"Constellation" for sale and can be purchased for $14,000. she is much<pb n="324"/>
larger than either of the others, has large and powerful engine, and a great
deal of furniture, Her boilers were new <date n="07-xx-1835">last July</date>, and good judges tell me
that her engine alone is worth more than the price of the boat. The hulk is
11 years old, but the <persName>builder </persName>tells me she was built of live oak and cedar at
his yard in <date n="xx-xx-1825">1825</date>, and he believes the timber to be sound. She draws 5 1/2
feet of water, and it would require $10,000 or $12,000 to put her in good
order for sea service. In getting advice on the subject from persons who
are fully competent, I have been advised to purchase her, take out the 
furniture and engine, and sell the old hulk, which would probably bring $2,000,
and build a new hulk expressly for sea navigation, and the purposes desired,
and she can then carry 5 eighteen pounders if necessary, It will take about
6 weeks to repair her, using the old hulk, and to build a new one would cost
$18,000 or $20,000, giving a large and complete Steam Ship for 35,000, at
the utmost, capable of carrying 600 passengers, if necessary. And this can
be completed in 60 days. The <persName>ship builders in <placeName>New York</placeName></persName> have had much
trouble with their <persName>workmen </persName>recently and it would be better therefore to
build, or repair at <placeName>Salem in Conn</placeName>, or some <placeName>Eastern port</placeName>. I would be happy
to receive the instruction of the <persName>Commissioners </persName>in relation to the course I
am to pursue, and give me some discretionary powers on the subject&#8212; I
have employed an experienced <persName>Captain </persName>to aid me in my examinations, and
he has prepared a model for a new hulk, which can be used if thought proper
to build.</p>

<p>The Brig "Chanticleer" is a very superior coppered and copper fastened
vessel, for sale in the City of <persName>New York</persName>, built for the <persName>African Slave </persName>trade,
pierced for 14 guns, and can be got ready in 2 weeks, for sea. An 
experienced and excellent man can be engaged to take command of her, and she
can be purchased, provisioned and got ready for sea for $20,000.</p>

<p>If the <persName>Commissioners </persName>should come to conclusion in favor of the 
negociacion for the <persName>Milam Furtrading and Land Company</persName>, I would propose that
it be conditional with them, forthwith to advance the funds necessary to 
purchase and fit out the "Chanticleer," and pay the expenses of fitting out the
<persName>308 men</persName> raised by <persName>Col. Macomb</persName>, and that I be authorized to send out the
same with all possible despatch&#8212; That they also be required to advance the
cash on my drafts of $20,000, and advance the additional sum necessary to
purchase the Steam Boat "Constellation," build a new hulk and fit her out,
with all possible dispatch, and I be authorized to attend to the execution of
the same. The contract can be executed by the <persName>Commissioners </persName>here, and 
delivered me, to be delivered to the applicants of the <persName>Company</persName>, on their 
acceptance of the terms, and <persName>Mr. Hal</persName>l can receive a letter from the 
<persName>Commissioners</persName>, stating their terms.</p>

<p>Allow me to say something in this communication, relative to my 
compensation, for my services. In my first letter of instructions, it was left to be
determined on my arrival in <placeName>Texas</placeName>. Since that time it has occurred to me<pb n="325"/>
that, it may occasion difficulty, as an express law must necessarily be enacted
for the purpose, and as it was my original suggestion to pursue this course,
and I did not anticipate the serious and unavoidable delays that have taken
place, I would now respectfully request, in order that these difficulties may
be obviated, that it be fixed by the <persName>Commissioners </persName>at once&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>A. J. Yates</persName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
