<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5087">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to F W Johnson, Daniel Parker, D C Barrett, J W Robinson, Wyatt Hanks, P Sublette, Asa Hoxey, 12-22-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-13">07-13-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        F W Johnson
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         Daniel Parker
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         D C Barrett
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         J W Robinson
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         Wyatt Hanks
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         P Sublette
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         Asa Hoxey
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Quintana, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 289-290
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-12-22">12-22-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Urging strict adherence to the Mexican Federal Union. Independence would entail maintenance of standing army
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Quintana</placeName>, <date when="1835-12-22">December 22, 1835</date>.</p>

<p>Dear Sirs: We expect to get off <date when="1835-12-23">to-morrow</date> in the Wm. Robbins; <persName>Archer</persName>,
the two <persName>Whartons</persName> and myself and several other <persName>passengers</persName>.</p>

<p>There has been a great deal of low intrigue in the political maneuvering
of a <persName>party </persName>who I am at last forced to believe have their own personal 
ambition and aggrandizement in view, more than the good of the country. These
men have operated on <persName>Archer </persName>until they have made him almost a political
<persName>fanatic</persName>, preaching a crusade in favor of liberty against the <placeName>city of Mexico</placeName>,
the only place short of which the <persName>army of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> ought to stop, etc.</p>

<p>The <persName>Mexicans </persName>say that it is rather curious that the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> should
fight against <persName>military rulers</persName>, and at the same time try to build up an <persName>army</persName>
that may, in its turn, rule <persName>Texas </persName>as it pleases. I think it probable there
will be some thousands [of] <persName>volunteers from the <placeName>United States</placeName></persName> in a few
months. They nearly all wish to join the <persName>regular army</persName> on the basis of
<persName>volunteers</persName>. What shall we do with so many? How support them? I fear
that the true secret of the efforts to declare independence is, that there must
then be a considerable <persName>standing army</persName>, which, in the hands of a few, would
dispose of the <persName>old settlers</persName> and their interests as they thought proper.</p>

<p>The true policy for <placeName>Texas </placeName>is to call a convention, amend the declaration
of the <date when="1835-11-07">7th of November last</date>, by declaring <placeName>Texas a State of the Mexican
Confederacy</placeName> under the basis laid down in the fifth and other articles of
said declaration of the <date when="1835-11-07">7th of November</date>, form a constitution and organize
a <persName>permanent government</persName>. Every possible aid should be given to the 
<persName>Federal party</persName> in the <placeName>interior</placeName>; but it should be done as <persName>auxiliary </persName>aid, in 
conformity with the second article of the declaration. By doing this the war
will be kept out of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. This <placeName>country </placeName>will remain at peace. It will fill
up rapidly with <placeName>families</placeName>, and there will be no great need of a <persName>standing
army</persName>. I believe that the combinations in the <persName>state of Tamaulipas</persName> are very
extensive to form a new republic by <placeName>a line from Tampico, west to the
Pacific</placeName>, and it is probable that the capitulation at <placeName>Bexar </placeName>was made to 
promote that object. In short, it is much easier to keep the war out of <placeName>Texas</placeName>,
than to bring it back again to our own doors. All that is necessary is for
us <hi rend="italic">not to do any king that will compel the <persName>Federal party</persName> to turn against us,
</hi>and if they call on us for aid let it be given as <hi rend="italic"><persName>auxiliary </persName>aid</hi>, and on no
other footing.<pb n="290"/></p>

<p>This takes away the character of a national war, which the <persName>government
in <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> is trying to give it, and it will also give to <placeName>Texas </placeName>just claims on
the <persName>Federal party</persName>, for remuneration out of the proceeds of the <placeName>custom
houses of Matamoros and Tampico</placeName>, for our expenses in furnishing the
<hi rend="italic"><persName>auxiliary </persName>aid.</hi> But if <placeName>Texas </placeName>sends an <hi rend="italic">invading </hi><persName>force of foreign troops</persName>
against <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>, it will change the whole matter. <persName>Gen. Mexia</persName> ought to
have commanded the <persName>expedition to <placeName>Matamoros</placeName></persName> and only waited to be asked
by the <persName>Provisional Government</persName> to do so.</p>

<p>I repeat: It is much easier to keep the war out of <placeName>Texas </placeName>and <placeName>beyond the
Rio Grande</placeName>, thah to bring it here to our own doors. The <persName>farmers </persName>and 
<persName>substantial men of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> <hi rend="italic">can yet save themselves</hi>, but to do so they must act
in union and as one man.</p>

<p>This, I fear, is impossible. In the <placeName>upper settlement</placeName> <persName>Dr. Hoxey</persName> is loud
for independence. Of Course he is in favor of a large <persName>standing army</persName> to
sustain it, and will no doubt be ready to give up half, or all, of his 
property to support thousands of <persName>volunteers</persName>, etc., who will flood the <placeName>country</placeName>
from <placeName>abroad</placeName>.</p>

<p>It is all very well and right to show to the world that <placeName>Texas </placeName>has just and
equitable grounds to declare independence; but it is putting the <persName>old settlers</persName>
in great danger to make any such declaration, for it will turn all the
<persName>parties in <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName> against us. <hi rend="italic">It will</hi> bring back the war to our doors,
which is now far from us, and <hi rend="italic">it will</hi> compel the <persName>men of property in <placeName>Texas</placeName>
</persName>to give up half or all to support a <persName>standing army</persName> of sufficient magnitude to
contend with all <placeName>Mexico </placeName>united.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName>.</p>

<p>[To F. W. Johnson, Daniel Parker, D. C. Barrett, J. W. Robinson, Wyatt
Hanks, P. Sublette, Asa Hoxey.]</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
