<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5176">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>A J Yates to Stephen F Austin, 05-14-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>A J Yates</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-08">08-08-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Schenectady, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Washington City, U.S.</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 351-353
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-05-14">05-14-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Good meeting at Albany, but strong counter current due to Van Buren politics. Could send 2000 "emigrants" to Texas on certain conditions.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Schenectada </placeName><date when="1836-05-14">May 14, 1836</date></p>

<p>My Dear Sir,</p>

<p>We had a very respectable meeting at <placeName>Albany </placeName>on <date when="1836-05-12">Thursday evening,</date> and
I held forth to them (if I may judge by their plaudits) with much 
acceptance&#8212; They adopted a string of resolutions, and among others, to 
appoint a <persName>Committee of 5</persName> from <placeName>each ward in the City</placeName> to solicit aid, to 
circulate a memorial, and to correspond with <placeName>every county in the State</placeName>. There
was a very powerful counter current there, and I do not know what to
ascribe it to unless it be <persName>Van Buren</persName> Politicks. I have never before 
believed in the stories about the Regency but I am now satisfied of the truth
of the collar business. I have been for years engaged in the Politicks of
<placeName>New York</placeName>, and well know that political movements were and must of course<pb n="352"/>
be controlled and <persName>party </persName>must be disciplined to rank and file, but I never
would believe that the feelings, the sympathies, the most holy affections of
men were to be controlled by a <persName>political party</persName>. I can ascribe it to nothing
else, unless there may have been a reaction, on account of <persName>Urrea</persName>'s return
of the safety of <persName>Fanning </persName>and his men, which I presume was made before
their Massacre&#8212; [Illegible name] has published a letter from a <persName>member
of Congress</persName> about the gullability of our <persName>Countrymen</persName>, and instances the
case of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and particularly of <persName>Fanning</persName>&#8212; I hope the facts of that case
will be now elicited, and if the massacre is found to be true, the reaction
of those who have been deceived by this course of the <persName>Mexican General</persName> and
<persName>Minister</persName>, will be tremendous&#8212;</p>

<p>If I had a power to appropriate any of the funds I receive towards 
fitting out <persName>emigrants </persName>(ie) authorize me to draw on the <persName>Agent at <placeName>New 
Orleans</placeName></persName>, for the monies remitted, at the same time charging the <persName>emigrant </persName>say
$20. for his passage and outfit, I could send out a 1000 [to] 2000 within
40 days. I would publish a <placeName>circular </placeName>establishing a rendevous at a certain
time and place, say <placeName>Pittsburg </placeName>applications to be made by <date when="1836-06-18">18th June</date>&#8212;
expedition to sail the 20th price of passage including equipment $15, in 
advance&#8212;the <persName>emigrant </persName>to have a draft on the <persName>Govt</persName>, for that amount on his
arrival in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, provided he enters the <persName>army </persName>there for 6 mos. One 
Thousand men would give $15000, The charter and expenses of two steam
Boats to <placeName>Natchitoches </placeName>would be say $3,000, 1000 muskets and equipments
say $7,000. 10 baggage waggons, 4 horses each $250, each is $2500. 
ammunition and provisions $2000. Any one thus going out, and not entering
the service forfeits his passage money, and the arms, ammunition,
equipments, wagons horses etc belong to the <persName>Govt</persName>, on the arrival of the <persName>emigrants
into <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>. Many <placeName>neighbourhoods</placeName>, would raise <persName>companies </persName>and pay their
passage, if the arrangements could be made for their going out in this
manner, without requiring a return of the money, and this I presume I
have power to attend to in the powers already given me. I found many of
the <placeName>pamplets </placeName>very imperfect, and have received no more than those I took
up myself.</p>

<p>My own private business will require my personal presence in this part
of the country during the <date n="Summer-1836">Summer </date>but you will hear from me, and I shall
continue my operations for <placeName>Texas </placeName>in a manner that will tell as well, and
perhaps better than if I went through to <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>. I shall probably go
as far as <placeName>Pittsburg</placeName>, certainly to <placeName>Buffalo</placeName>, and there are many in the <placeName>country</placeName>
ready to go out.</p>

<p>Please inform me who remains at <placeName>Washington City</placeName> as the <persName>Representative
of the Govt</persName>, and if <persName>Mr. Childress</persName>&#8212;mention my name to him, and send me
his address&#8212;<pb n="353"/></p>

<p>I expect the proceedings of our meeting at <placeName>Albany </placeName>are in this mornings
papers.</p>

<p><persName>A. J. Yates</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Gen. Stephen F. Austin Commissioner of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName></p>

<p><placeName>Washington City</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
