<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5183">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William H Wharton to Stephen F Austin, 05-28-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William H Wharton</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-08">08-08-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Washington City, U.S.</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 360-361
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-05-28">05-28-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Shocked to hear that Houston opposes annexation. Anxious to get home and talk to him before opinions become fixed. Present senate favorable to annexation and so is Jackson.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Washington </placeName><date when="1836-05-28">28th May 1836</date></p>

<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p><persName>Mr Sumner</persName> a friend of mine from <placeName>Nashville </placeName>has just arrived and shocked
me with the intelligence, that it is understood at <placeName>Nashville </placeName>that <persName>Genl 
Houston</persName> is opposed to the annexation of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to the <placeName>United States</placeName>. If this be
so it is truly and deeply to be deplored. Like all triumphant <persName>conquerors</persName>
he will be omnipotent for a time at least. I plainly see before me the 
turmoil and confusion and injustice and the demagogueism which must ensue
in <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Texas </placeName></hi>after the war is over before we can establish an orderly and 
harmonious independent <persName>government</persName>. Nothing can transcend the horrors of
this state of things but the cold blooded Massacres of the last few Months.
Knowing therefore that I have some influence with <persName>Houston </persName>I shall be in
misery until I see him before his opinions on this subject are generally
known or firmly fixed. I have therefore written on to <persName>Childress </persName>and 
<persName>Hamilton </persName>to come immediately here that I may start for <placeName>Texas</placeName>. This I shall do
as soon as they arrive. I am compelled to go to <placeName>New York</placeName> to get the 
remainder of the 10 pr cent. I will not however delay there more than one
day and will then start for <placeName>Texas </placeName>via <placeName>Nashville </placeName>where I will not stop more
than another day. I feel it more important than all other things in the
world<pb n="361"/></p>

<p>the present <persName>Senate </persName>should act upon the question of annexation. I bottom
this upon reasons known to you in which all of our <persName>friends </persName>fully coincide
and they speak to me about it every hour in the day. For this reason it is
indispensible to be at home and get the <persName>leading men</persName> in favour of it. 
<persName>President Burnett</persName> I know cannot depute power to any one to make a treaty of
Cession of <placeName>Texas </placeName>that will be binding upon the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>. But he
can have the treaty take place subject to the ratification of the <persName>people </persName>
hereafter or senate as are all treaties of this <persName>government</persName>. The great object is to
get it acted on here by the present <persName>Senate </persName>and we will act on it in <placeName>Texas</placeName>
afterwards and if we first get the <persName>leading men</persName> in favour of it in <placeName>Texas </placeName>all
will go right. For this reason as above stated I am determined to start
home immediately&#8212;</p>

<p>I have had frequent interviews with the <persName>President </persName>and he fully coincides
in these views and is exceedingly anxious on the subject. I will ascertain
from him the exact terms on which <persName>Texas </persName>can be admitted such as paying
the public debt, allowing her to keep her <placeName>public lands</placeName> etc. Write to me in
answer to this at <placeName>Nashville</placeName>. You may rely upon seeing me soon after you
are in <placeName>Texas</placeName>. With a perfect oblivion of all the past I am truly Your
Friend</p>

<p><persName>Wm. H. Wharton</persName></p>

<p>P. S. Our <persName>friends </persName>say they will if possible keep <persName>congress </persName>together until
<date n="08-xx-1836">August </date>on account of this business. I trust in God that it is a Mistake
about <persName>Houston</persName>s being opposed to annexation. If he is I will exert my little
influence with him. We have always been and are the best of friends. Do
hurry on home without a moments delay&#8212;</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Genl. S. F Austin</persName> Care of <persName>Wm Bryan</persName> <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
