<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5207">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William Bryan to Stephen F Austin, 06-28-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William Bryan</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-12">08-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 375-376
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-06-28">06-28-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Distress caused him by President Burnet's appointment of Toby and Brother to represent Texas</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date when="1836-06-28">June 28th 1836</date></p>

<p><persName>Stephen F Austin Esq</persName> <placeName>Velasco</placeName></p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>We have no news from <placeName>Texas </placeName>or <placeName>Mexico </placeName>since you left, shortly after
your departure <persName>Messrs Toby and Bros</persName> came out with a proclamation of
the <persName>President</persName>, naming them as <persName>sole agents for the <placeName>United States</placeName></persName> etc. The
result has been disaterous in the extreme. We have been obliged to stop
all expenditures on the vessels, the <persName>mechanicks </persName>have all broken off work.
<persName>Toby </persName>says he has no funds, and cannot sell the <placeName>lands </placeName>sent him, in fact the
untoward appointment has thrown every thing into confusion. The public
have come out in a manner totally unexpected, they say the unwarranted
change of the <persName>Agency </persName>is unjust, that they can have no confidence in a 
<persName>Government </persName>that could commit so flagrant an act. And that they cannot 
hereafter obtain one dollar of credit in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>. <persName>Toby </persName>can do nothing
unless by pledge of the <placeName>public lands</placeName>, writs of attachment are now out
against the vessels, and more are threatened, they cannot sustain them but
the vessels will have to be bonded. In a word the change of <persName>Agency </persName>has
much to our surprise drawn out the public voice in our favour and deeply
injured the cause of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. Of the sum left by you we had expended Three
Thousand Dollars, the Proclamation annul'd the <persName>Agency</persName>, of course we
could expend no more. It will require five times the balance to pay the
Bills upon which we are personally liable. We shall stop the Payments on
<persName>government </persName>account as far as it is possible until we hear from you. The
account was placed in our hands as <persName>agents of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, on account of the
<persName>Government </persName>for a specific purpose, our <persName>agency </persName>being broken up, it should
go as far as it will to pay other urgent demands, and we shall anxiously
wait your opinion upon the subject&#8212; It is our opinion the <persName>Agency </persName>of
<persName>Toby and Bro</persName>, cannot continue, as it depends on the popularity of <persName>Mr
McKinny</persName>, which must fall with the present <persName>Administration</persName>, but little can
be done unless the country is invaded until <date n="Fall-1836">Fall</date>, and it might be as well
to let the <persName>people </persName>have a trial of him, they will be fully satisfied in a short
tims as to who can, and have best promoted the public interests. Our only
concern now is in regard to meeting the demand against the <persName>Agency</persName>, should
the <persName>Executive </persName>accede to our request to grant us script for the amount, we
could arrange to restore the public credit so far as we are concerned in two
months. Your friendly feelings towards us will induce you to urge such
a measure, as it is probably the only means that can be resorted to, to pay
the amount and restore confidence, we would urge it upon you for one
strong reason, that the impression is general, that the <persName>government </persName>have
changed the <persName>Agency </persName>to avoid meeting our demands, If something is not
soon done my private character and interests must suffer, I am implicated<pb n="376"/>
in no common terms by the public in the debts of Texas, and unless they
are soon arranged my private credit will be prostrated, I must therefore
beg of you to do all you can for me, It is hard for me after working for
<placeName>Texas </placeName>through all her darkest days, to see Individuals who have literally&#8212;
done nothing come forward and reap the advantage of my labours, but I
must submit with the best grace I can, and trust to time for justice. I have
heard nothing from Messers <persName>Archer </persName>and <persName>Wharton </persName>since I saw you,</p>

<p><persName>William Bryan</persName></p>

<p>Pr <persName>Samuel Ellis</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
