<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5291">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William B Lewis to Stephen F Austin, 10-27-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William B Lewis</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-28">08-28-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Washington, U.S.</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 439-441
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-10-27">10-27-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-28" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Giving Jackson's views on release of Santa Anna</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Washington </placeName><date when="1836-10-27">27: Oct. 1836</date>.</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">(Duplicate)	</hi></p>

<p>My Dr. Sir,</p>

<p>In my last letter to you I remarked that possibly a state of things might
arise which would make it sound policy to liberate <persName>Santa Anna</persName>. It strikes
me that the period, has arrived, and that such a state of things now exists.
<persName>Bustamenta</persName>, the <persName>enemy </persName>of the <persName>President of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>, it is said has returned
to that <placeName>country </placeName>and will endeavour, no doubt, to place himself at the <persName>head
of the Government</persName>, if he is not already at its head. Now Sir, under such
circumstances, would it not be the interest of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to turn <persName>Santa Anna</persName>
loose upon those <persName>gentry </persName>who have possessed themselves of his place and the
power of the <persName>Government </persName>to make War upon <placeName>Texas</placeName>? It strikes me so at<pb n="440"/>
least. If he were to return to <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, I have no doubt he would give them
enough to do at home, instead of collecting and marching their force against
you. You might enter into another arrangement with him and proffer your
services to assist, if required, in restoring him to the station he occupied
before his Capture, provided he would guarantee the Independence of
<placeName>Texas</placeName>, so far as depended upon him and <placeName>Mexico</placeName>.</p>

<p>Were <hi rend="italic">you </hi>to liberate him under such circumstances and with such an
understanding, I have no doubt he would be true to his engagements, and
become the warm and sincere <persName>friend of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> and her <persName>President elect</persName>. But
it might be asked what could be expected of him, if liberated, as he might
be <hi rend="italic">powerless</hi>? Suppose such to be the fact, then in answer it might be said
if he were unable to render <placeName>Texas </placeName>any <hi rend="italic">services</hi>, neither could he do her any
<hi rend="italic">harm</hi>. But if his <persName>friends </persName>and <persName>followers </persName>have not abandoned him in 
consequence of his fallen fortunes, and it is likely they have not, he might still
be a match for his <persName>enemies</persName>, and by compelling them to take care of 
themselves at <placeName>home</placeName>, relieve you from the disasters of another campaign the
coming <date n="Winter - 1836">winter</date>. Others would suggest, (and no doubt <hi rend="italic">think </hi>so too) that
if he were again entrusted with power he might disregard his promises to
<placeName>Texas </placeName>and endeavour to retrieve his lost honors by again invading her 
territory and making war upon her <placeName>citizens</placeName>. If he were to attempt this, after
stipulating to guarantee her independence as a condition of his liberation,
I have no doubt your independence would be acknowledged forthwith by
<placeName>foreign nations</placeName>, and ample means furnished you severely to punish such
perfidious Conduct. However much the present <persName>Mexican authorities</persName> may
object to the arrangement entered into between your <persName>Government </persName>and <persName>Santa
Anna</persName>, in consequence of his being a <persName>prisner</persName>, he could not deny its 
authenticity, and especially if sanctioned and confirmed after he was set at liberty.</p>

<p>These, my friend, are not only my views upon this all important subject,
but they are the views and opinions of one who I know has great weight
with you. <hi rend="italic">The <persName>President</persName></hi> in a conversation with a <persName>friend </persName><date when="1836-10-26">last evening</date>, 
<hi rend="italic">expressed the same opinions as to the policy of liberating <persName>Santa Anna</persName>, and
permitting him to return to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>without delay. He said he had no doubt
but it was the best thing the <persName>Government of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> could do, as it would
give the <persName>Mexicans </persName>employment at home instead of making war upon their
<placeName>Neighbours</placeName>.</hi> If liberated I should think it would be best for him to go to
<placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, as he probably has more friends there than in any other part of
<placeName>Mexico</placeName>; but he of course would be the best judge of that himself.</p>

<p><persName>Gorostiza, the Mexican Minister</persName> has demanded his passport, and will I
suppose soon leave the <placeName>U. States</placeName> if he has not already done so. The cause
of his departure, was the refusal, on the part of this <persName>Government</persName>, to recall
the <persName>troops stationed at <placeName>Nacogdoches</placeName></persName>. The necessity of their remaining
there for the protection of our <placeName>fontier settlements</placeName> is left entirely to the<pb n="441"/>
discretion of the <placeName>commanding officer</placeName>, who now is <persName>Colo. Arbuckle</persName>. He has
instructions I believe to withdraw them if in his opinion the situation of
things do not make it necessary for them longer to continue at that <placeName>post</placeName>,
but not otherwise.</p>

<p>I think it more than probable that the existing <persName>Authorities of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>
</persName>are endeavouring to get <placeName>England </placeName>to interfere in her behalf. Possibly she
may do so in consequence of the large sums of Money owing by <placeName>Mexico </placeName>to
<persName>English subjects</persName>, but not to the extent of involving herself in a War with
the <placeName>U. States</placeName>. This is another reason why it might be to the interest of
<placeName>Texas </placeName>to set <persName>Santa Anna</persName> at liberty. Were he again at the <persName>head of the 
Mexican Government</persName> and the <persName>friend of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, he would ask no such 
interference, and there could then be no pretext for that Government to take any
part in the matter. It strikes me if you <persName>Texans </persName>have any <hi rend="italic">diplomatic </hi>tact,
that by taking advantage of the present state of things in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, you might
avert, for many years at least to come, the calamities of a war with that
country, if not obtain its acknowledgement of your independence. I think
<hi rend="italic">both </hi>might be effected.</p>

<p>I have got to the bottom of my paper and must conclude by subscribing
Myself truly and sincerely,</p>

<p><persName>Wm. B Lewis</persName></p>

<p>[No address.]</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
