<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5075">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Provisional Government, 12-14-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-07">7-07-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Provisional Government
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Columbia, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 282-284
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-12-14">12-14-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-07" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Plans for cooperation with Mexican liberals. Important to abide by declaration of November 7, and make no move toward independence. Recommendations concerning Mexia </add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Confidential	<placeName>Columbia </placeName><date when="1835-12-14">Decr. 14. 1835 </date>At night&#8212;</p>

<p>To the <persName>provisional Gov.t of Texas</persName>,</p>

<p>On my arrival here <date when="1835-12-14">this afternoon</date>, I met <persName>Genl. Mexia</persName> and <persName>Col. Pettus</persName> on
horseback starting for <placeName>San Felipe</placeName></p>

<p>The first informed me that the principal object of his journey to <placeName>San
Felipe</placeName>, was to inform the <persName>provisional Govt</persName> of the nature of his relations,
and of the situation of things in the <placeName>interior</placeName>&#8212; As these matters are of the
greatest importance, he returned with me to this place, and we have had a
conference of much interest to the general good of the cause we are 
defending, but more especially to <placeName>Texas</placeName>. He has shown me his correspondence
with <persName>persons of the highest standing</persName>, especially a letter which he recd. a
few days since by a <persName>confidential express</persName> from the <placeName>interior</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have not time to write fully on this all important subject, nor will my
health (exhausted as I am by the ride down) permit it or to enter into long
details, which I will do from my <placeName><persName>brother in law</persName>'s</placeName> or from <placeName>Velasco</placeName>; I will
therefore at present merely say that the general good seems to require&#8212;</p>

<p>First&#8212;That <persName>Genl. Mexia</persName> should return with as little delay as possible to
<placeName>N. Orleans</placeName>, where his presence is necessary for the furtherance of the plans
and combinations that are made and maturing in the <placeName>interior </placeName>in favor of
federalism, and of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. These plans are very extensive and are 
calculated to cover and secure <placeName>Texas </placeName>effectually, provided we adhere <hi rend="italic">strictly</hi>, in
words, acts, and deeds, to the declaration of the consultation of <date when="1835-11-07">7th 
November last</date>.</p>

<p>2.d	That as a part of his <persName>troops </persName>marched <date when="1835-12-13">yesterday</date>, [with] <persName>Cap Allin's
Company</persName>, for <placeName>Bexar</placeName>, the balance should proceed to <placeName>Copano </placeName>by water, for
which purpose they have gone to <placeName>Velasco</placeName>, and should take the two long
brass sixes and two iron ones and the arms and shot, which will be very
usefull either in the siege of <placeName>Bexar </placeName>or in other operations in that <placeName>quarter</placeName>.</p>

<p>3.d	That as he has spent $18,000 in this expedition, and places the 
cannon (the two brass ones cost $400 each), and shot, of which there is a good
supply, at the disposition of the <persName>provisional Govt of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> to be used in<pb n="283"/>
defense of the common cause, at least one thousand dollars should be 
furnished him, to meet his present exigencies, for he is without a dollar.</p>

<p>He requests me to say that whether he goes to <placeName>Orleans</placeName>, or wherever he
may be, he wishes to be considered a <persName>citizen of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>&#8212; He has a 
considerable interest in the <placeName>country</placeName>.</p>

<p>I am more and more convinced every day, and especially on calm 
reflection during a solitary ride down here, that the political position of <placeName>Texas</placeName>,
should continue as established by the declaration of <date when="1835-11-07">7th Novr. last</date>. This
declaration secures to <placeName>Texas </placeName><hi rend="italic">everything</hi>, and without any hazard, for it
satisfies the <persName>federal party</persName>, and is sufficient to secure their support and 
cooperation, should the federal system fall, the 5 article is a declaration of
independence as a matter of course. I think that a constitution ought to be
formed and a <persName>permanent Govt.</persName> established on the basis of said declarations,
and that the <persName>provisional Govt.</persName> should <hi rend="italic">not legislate any more</hi>, if possible to
avoid it&#8212;</p>

<p>A change of the basis now, to that of independence, w.d give us no more
than is secured by the declaration, provided a constitution is formed, but
it would injure us abroad by giving an idea that we are unstable in our
opinions and it would paralise the efforts of the <persName>federal party</persName> which are
now in our favor, and no doubt turn them against us&#8212; <placeName>Texas </placeName>ought 
therefore to adhere rigidly and firmly to the declaration of <date when="1835-11-07">7 Nov.r</date> and the
public acts should correspond with it, in <hi rend="italic">words </hi>and in <hi rend="italic">object</hi>, without 
regarding the opinions of excited moments, no matter by whom expressed.
These are my firm convictions, after the most calm reflection.&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Genl. Mexia</persName> is compelled to go to <placeName>Velasco</placeName>, to make arrangements to start
his <persName>men </persName>to <placeName>Copano </placeName>under the command of <persName>Col Peraza</persName>, in case he does not
go himself, from that place, I will inform you of his final conclusions&#8212;
These will be made with a view to the <hi rend="italic">good of <placeName>Texas</placeName></hi>&#8212; of this you need
have no doubt whatever&#8212;</p>

<p>I am told that letters of <hi rend="italic">recent </hi>date have been rec.d from <persName>persons of high
standing</persName> and correct information as to Mexican and Texas politics, and as
to the opinions with <persName>men of judgement</persName> in the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> which say, "Make no
change in your declaration of <date when="1835-11-07">7 Novr.</date> and do not even pronounce the word
independence in a whisper."</p>

<p>I have given you my opinion frankly&#8212; will write again from <placeName>Velasco</placeName>&#8212;
in the meantime I recommend that some provision be made, if any can be,
to supply <persName>Genl. Mexia</persName> with $1000&#8212; I go below early <date when="1835-12-15">tomorrow morning</date></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName> [Rubric]</p>

<p>I will add I have full confidence in the good faith and sincerity of <persName>Genl
Mexia</persName> in his efforts and desires to serve the cause of <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;<pb n="284"/></p>

<p>The address to the <persName>Mexican peopl</persName>e sh.d be sent into the <placeName>interior </placeName>by every
possible means&#8212;send a number to <persName>McKinney</persName> for me and <persName>Mexia </persName>and send
them to <placeName>Goliad </placeName><placeName>Bexar </placeName>and <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>and every where&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S. F. A.</persName></p>

<p>I think the situation of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, may in a great degree, depend on 
adhering to the declaration of <date when="1835-11-07">7 Novr.</date> and on enlisting the <persName>federal party</persName> in our
favor&#8212; I repeat this idea so often, because I am satisfied much depends
on it.</p>

<p>I have marked this letter <hi rend="italic">confidential</hi>, because I do not wish that part of
it that speaks of the <placeName>interior </placeName>published in print, but if my opinion will do
any good as to adhering to the declaration of <date when="1835-11-07">7 Novr.</date> you can make any
use of those opinions you think proper</p>

<p><persName>S. F. A.</persName></p>

<p>read and referred to <persName>select committee of 5</persName>.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
