<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5253">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to W. S. Archer, 08-15-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-16">08-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        W. S. Archer
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Peach Point, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 415-417
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-08-15">08-15-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Offering Archer the office of Secretary of State if he is elected president of Texas. Wants his influence to work for annexation </add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Peach Point</placeName> near <placeName>Velasco </placeName><date when="1836-08-15">August 15th 1836</date></p>

<p><persName>W. S. Archer</persName></p>

<p>Dear Sir</p>

<p>Your most esteemed and truly gratifying letter dated "<placeName>Elk Hill</placeName> <date when="1836-07-03">July 3d.</date>
has just been handed to me by my friend <persName>Dr B. T. Archer</persName></p>

<p>The Kind interest you take in the affairs of this <placeName>Country</placeName>, and the 
expression of your intentions to visit <placeName>Texas </placeName><date n="Fall-1836">next fall</date> with the probable view
of emigrating here, is in the highest degree encouraging, for it gives new life
to hopes, which I have long cherished, of seing <placeName>Texas </placeName>populated with men
who will bring to it such resources of experience, of wisdom, of virtue, and
of mental treasures as well as of enterprise, and pecuniary wealth</p>

<p>It is no disparagement to the present population of <placeName>Texas </placeName>to say that we
need such men&#8212;all countries need them&#8212;tho perhaps not to the extent that
this does. Pioneering a <placeName>wilderness </placeName>and laying a foundation, require one
discription of men, while the aid of another kind is important to rear upon
that foundation such a superstructure as will fully meet the wishes and
accomplish the great object of all concerned, which is the general good,
and common accommodation and hapiness of all</p>

<p>I consider that the foundation is laid&#8212;the superstructure is in progress,
and is precisely in the stage when able <persName>architects </persName>are most needed. <placeName>Texas</placeName>
is fully redeemed from the <placeName>wilderness</placeName>, and its independence is virtually
achieved&#8212; This I call the <hi rend="italic">foundation</hi>&#8212;</p>

<p>What is to be its future political position&#8212; An <placeName>independent republic</placeName>,
or a member of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName>?</p>

<p>What the details of its constitution in either Case? What the specific
terms of Admission in the latter Case? How is it to be effected? etc, etc,
etc, These Kind of matters are embraced in what I call the <hi rend="italic">superstructure</hi>&#8212;
I am in favor of Annexation to the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> I have full confidence that if
admitted at all, it will be on the most fair and liberal terms, I think the
great mass of the <persName>Citizens of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> are of the same opinion, tho a short
time will test the question, as the <persName>voters </persName>are called upon to express their
wish for or against annexation at the general election the <date when="1836-09-01">first Monday of
September next</date></p>

<p>My <persName>friends </persName>have nominated me a candidate for <persName>President </persName>at said 
elections and are sanguine of success&#8212; It is not to be supposed however that<pb n="416"/>
there will be much unanimity about any thing in a new community like
this, where aspirants are numerous and where conflicting hopes and 
projects of the future, or fancied complaints and misconstructions of the past,
furnish so many materials for <persName>demagogues </persName>to distract or mislead the public
mind.</p>

<p>I have been connected with the public affairs of this <placeName>country </placeName>in one way
or another for, fifteen years, and under circumstances, during the whole of
that period, the most difficult, perplexing, and embarrassing&#8212; With
more power than ought to have been given to one man, I was for many
years in the first stages of the <placeName>settlements</placeName>, the main organ of the local
administration and of communication between the <persName>settlers </persName>(who came direct
from a <persName>free and organized Govt</persName>.&#8212; The <placeName>U. S.</placeName> with all their habits fresh)
and the <persName>Mexican Govt.</persName>, which then was, as it still is, in that state of Chaos,
produced by the sudden transition from extreme spanish slavery and 
ignorance, to extreme republican liberty. You Can at once see the difficulty of
such a position, liable to jealousy and suspicion from both sides, it made
me a mark for all to shoot at&#8212; our land laws have always been complex,
and their execution difficult&#8212; Our political horizon has always been
clouded, and public sentiment much divided etc It has been under such
circumstances that I have been connected with the affairs of <placeName>Texas</placeName></p>

<p>I mention these things to give you some faint idea of the difficulties of
the past, and as an explanation of the assurance that I am truly uneasy and
sick of every thing connected with public affairs&#8212; I shall however never
shrink from them so long as the country is in an unsettled state, and hence
it is, that I am now before the public a <persName>candidate </persName>for <persName>president</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>Dr B. T. Archer</persName> has assured me that you would not refuse to lend the
aid of your well stored mind, in regulating our public affairs, in the event
of your determining to settle here permanently&#8212; I have in consequence
assured him, and now say the same to you, that I should esteem it a great
public good to <placeName>Texas </placeName>if you will accept of a station in the <persName>cabinet councils
of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>&#8212; If I am elected, my favorite object will be annexation to the
<placeName>U. S.</placeName> on fair and liberal terms, that effected, I am determined never again
to have any thing to do with public affairs if I can avoid it&#8212;</p>

<p>Now sir I am emboldened by my friend <persName>Dr B. T. Archer</persName> to ask you
whether you will come on without delay and occupy the station of <persName>secretary
of state</persName> and as such conduct the negotiation with the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> for our admission 
etc etc provided however always, that the <hi rend="italic">sovereigns </hi>elect me</p>

<p>In the event of coming on you might perhaps obtain some important 
information as to the difficulties to be surmounted and the best mode of 
getting over or around them etc, Also it may be important for you to know
that we are totally destitute of all books of forms or of state papers, diplomatic 
history or correspondence&#8212;in short we have nothing of the Kind&#8212;no
books of reference of any description<pb n="417"/></p>
<p>All mine were burnt at <placeName>San Felipe</placeName> when that place was distroyed by the
<persName>mexican </persName>invasion&#8212; I had but few</p>

<p>If we cannot be admitted into the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> we shall of course set up for
ourselves, and shall stand more in need of your experience and talents&#8212;
I think the field a vast one here for the profitable investment of Capital
this is a very valuable, planting, farming, and grazing country, and must
populate rapidly and become very wealthy in a few years of <hi rend="italic">good Government</hi> 
and <hi rend="italic">peace</hi></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
