<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5263">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Joseph Ficklin to Stephen F Austin, 08-xx-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Joseph Ficklin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-16">08-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Lexington, Kentucky</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 426-428
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-08">08-xx-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Popular attitude toward Texas despondent. Confidence in Houston. Santa Anna must not be killed</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Lexington </placeName><date n="08-xx-1836">Augt &#8212;1836</date></p>

<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p>The call of <persName>Genl Gains</persName> on the <persName>Govr of <placeName>Kentucky</placeName></persName> for <persName>10 companies of
mounted men</persName> has been met by the <placeName>counties near Frankfort</placeName> the first week
leaving out the rest of the state. The <persName>Co. from <placeName>Lexington</placeName></persName> when complete
sent off to the <persName>Govr </persName>at midnight and was the last being the <persName>10th company
</persName>offered and the [illegible] night others were in making up to this time <persName>12
companies</persName> more than required <persName>Genl Chambers</persName> is here and entertains
hopes that several of these <persName>companies </persName>will go to <placeName>Texas</placeName>; the military feeling
of the <placeName>state </placeName>would be most favorable for <placeName>Texas </placeName>if your affairs were as they
were <date n="Winter-1835">last winter</date>, but appearances are so alarming that public feeling<pb n="427"/>
abroad and out of your <placeName>country </placeName>is fast approaching a most dangerous point
of giving up all hope and the same state of feeling must arise in <placeName>Texas</placeName>
itself&#8212; The removal of <hi rend="italic"><persName>Houston </persName></hi>is one among the heaviest blows&#8212; The
objections to <persName>Houston </persName>can not equal the confidence the world has in him,
and the very circumstance of dismissing him proves a want of fitness in
the authorities of the <placeName>Country </placeName>which must do the greatest injury&#8212; The
attempt to send off <persName>Santa Anna</persName> by the <persName>cabinet </persName>and the desire to kill him
by an other portion of your <persName>Citizens </persName>forms an other cause of division
among you and both equally defective as regards policy&#8212; The latter has
the addition in public feeling of a violation of all law and principle to
reach an outlaw who was placed on the footing of all other <persName>prisoners of
war</persName> the moment his orders to his <persName>troops </persName>to retreat was accepted by the
<persName>Authorities of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>&#8212; Whether his orders were obeyed or not or whether
so far as they were observed was an advantage to <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Texas </placeName></hi>or not matters not
a straw because <hi rend="italic"><persName>Santa Anna</persName></hi> can not be blamed and the acceptance of his
proposals was a commencement of negotiations which took his case from
the position he stood in when taken, The world is too ready to consider
<placeName>Texas </placeName>like all new countries rash and cruel in its measures. The death of
<hi rend="italic"><persName>St. Anna</persName></hi> would ruin your <placeName>country</placeName>. Efforts are making in this <placeName>country </placeName>by
the <persName>friends </persName>of the unfortunate who fell with <persName>fanning</persName>, but public feeling is
against them. <persName>Fanning </persName>remains pitied like <persName>Travis</persName>, but this can not last
the latter will gain by time but the fame of Poor <persName>Fannin </persName>must be lost by
the excessive folly of the manner he conducted when dangers came&#8212; he
was brave no doubt&#8212;but the way he lost <persName>600</persName> of the best force of the 
<placeName>Country </placeName>and his own useless life will when properly considered leave his name
a Blank this case should be a warning to your <placeName>Country </placeName>the caution of
<hi rend="italic"><persName>Houston </persName></hi>makes him worth all the untried men in your armies&#8212;many men
may Possess equal or even superior talents and still be unfit to command,
the daring spirits of [those] who fight for you if indulged at all times
no hope remains, but by a proper restraint you have nothing to fear&#8212; I
do not believe you will ever have a hostile <persName>Mexican </persName>on your soil&#8212; the
present attempt may explode in discord at home before the maturity of
the armiment&#8212; Still you want all the help you can get to force the treaty
already begun by invassion on your part if found necessary&#8212; if you can
Harmonise and avoid offending against Public feeling you are safe&#8212; you
owe much to the <hi rend="italic">high </hi>handed black deed of <hi rend="italic">Santa Anna</hi> in creating a 
feeling in your favour and I hope will do nothing to produce a reaction&#8212; you
stood on high grounds 3 months ago and it requires all the wisdom of your
best men to preserve the station. <persName>Genl Chambers</persName> thinks <persName>Genl Houston</persName> is not
displaced but only provisions made untill his wounds are healed&#8212; I hope
this is the case&#8212; <persName>Mrs. Holly</persName>s late addition to the History of <placeName>Texas </placeName>is
highly approved and I should say will find a brisk sale&#8212; There is so little<pb n="428"/>
of what we hear entitled to credit from your <placeName>country </placeName>that I should suggest
the plan of some faithful person writing Regularly to the papers in <placeName>N.
Orleans</placeName> all of whom appear to be friendly and supply the most of the news
we receive</p>

<p>The wars under <persName>Bolivar </persName>were like yours greatly misrepresented and
sufferd for the want of a regular agent at proper points&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Jos Ficklin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Genl Stephen F. Austin</persName> <placeName>Texas</placeName></p>

<p>The <persName>Texan agent in <placeName>N Orleans</placeName></persName> will please put this letter
under cover</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
