<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5256">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Gail Borden, Jr, xx-xx-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-16">08-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Gail Borden
                    </persName>
                </person>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                         Jr
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 418-421
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Printed Handbill</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="public"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836">xx-xx-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Denies implication in land speculations, reviews past services for Texas. Became candidate by request, and in hope of serving the country. Personally indifferent whether elected or not&#8212;</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><hi rend="italic">Letter from S. F. Austin to G. Borden, Jr.</hi></p>

<p><persName>Mr. G. Borden, Jr.</persName>:</p>

<p>Dear Sir,&#8212; </p>

<p>I have just received your letter of the <date when="1836-08-15">15th instant</date>, informing me that
great efforts are making to circulate reports and slanders, for the purpose
of injuring me, at the election which is to be held on the <date when="1836-09-01">first Monday of
next month.</date></p>

<p>Such things are to be expected. In all <placeName>communities</placeName>, there are <persName>men</persName>, who
attempt to rise and effect their individual views, by trying to mislead the
<persName>public</persName>. The check upon them, is the good sense and sound judgment of
the <persName>people</persName>. Relying upon this check, I have not considered it necessary
to notice any of the <hi rend="italic">slang </hi>that has been circulated about me.</p>

<p>I feel but little anxiety, of a personal character, whether I am elected or
not. I am not a volunteer candidate, for I agreed to become one from a
sense of duty, because I was solicited to do so, by persons whose opinions
I could not disregard, without laying myself liable, at least in some degree,
to the imputation of having shrunk from a high and responsible station,
at a time when the situation of <placeName>Texas </placeName>was most critical, and its political
affairs most difficulty. Had I refused being a <persName>candidate</persName>, I should then
have been censured for abandoning, in the time of difficulty, the public
affairs of a <placeName>country</placeName>, to which I have devoted so many years to build up
and bring forward.</p>

<p>To place before you in a succint manner, the nature of the reports spoken
of by you, I will recall to your mind a few facts in relation to the past.
I have been connected with the public affairs of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, in one way or
another, for fifteen years, and under circumstances, during the whole of
that period, the most difficult, perplexing and embarrassing.</p>

<p>I was for many years the principal organ of the <persName>local administration</persName>,
and of communication between the settlers of this colony, (who, be it 
remembered, came direct from a free and well organised government, the
<placeName>United States</placeName>, with all their political ideas and habits fresh upon their
minds,) and the <persName>Mexican government</persName>, which then was, as it still is, in that
state of chaos produced by a sudden transition from extreme slavery and
ignorance, to extreme republican liberty. The difficulty of such a position
is evident. The dangers of premature and ruinous collisions, produced by
a difference of language, forms, laws, habits, etc., were almost 
insurmountable. The very nature of things opened an almost boundless field for
demagogues and personalities, and the country was placed, during the<pb n="419"/>
whole of that eventful period, upon a volcano, subject to be ruined by
popular excitements on the one hand, or by the jealousy of the <persName>Mexicans</persName>
on the other. I was individually liable to suspicion, and to fancied or
real complaints from all quarters; and a mark for the shafts of envy, and
personal animosity, as well as for the attacks of those who honestly differed
in opinion with me, or were misinformed. That period was more difficult
and dangerous to the settlement of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and to its ultimate emancipation
and liberty, than any which has subsequently threatened, or which now
threatens its destinies; for had its colonization failed, there would have
been no <hi rend="italic">foundation </hi>to plant independence, or any thing else upon.</p>

<p>We passed through that period, however, in safety. A <hi rend="italic">foundation </hi>was
then laid, which I believed, and am now convinced, could not, and cannot
be broken up. No one knows or can appreciate so well as I do, the labor
it has cost, and perhaps but few have maturely considered its strength, and
results&#8212;they are co-durable with the English language and with the 
<persName>Anglo-American race</persName>.</p>

<p>In <date n="04-xx-1833">April, 1833</date>, I was appointed by the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, represented in
general convention, to go to the <placeName>city of Mexico</placeName> as their <persName>agent </persName>or 
<persName>commissioner</persName>, to apply for the admission of <placeName>Texas </placeName>into the <placeName>Mexican confederation
</placeName>as a <placeName>State</placeName>. This appointment was ruinous to my individual interests, and
in every respect hazardous and fatiguing. I accepted it, however, from a
sense of duty and went to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>at my individual expense, for I never
asked, or received one dollar from the <placeName>country </placeName>for that trip. I was 
imprisoned in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, as is well known, and detained about two years. 
During this time, it seems that some persons engaged in large land speculations
at <placeName>Monclova</placeName>, the <placeName>seat of government of the state of Coahuila and Texas</placeName>.
These are the speculations to which you allude in your letter of the <date when="1836-08-15">15th
instant</date>, and which, you say, are ruinous to my election.&#8212; You ask me to
say whether I am or not concerned with them.</p>

<p>The whole of the circumstances connected with that affair&#8212;my absence
from the <placeName>country </placeName>at the time&#8212;the almost impossibility of communicating
with me, then, owing to my imprisonment in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>&#8212;my known, and
uniform and undeviating opposition to every thing that was in any manner
calculated to entangle the land or political affairs of <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;all, prove to
impartial minds, that I was not concerned in them. But, as you ask me
a direct question, whether I am interested or not, I will reply out of respect
to you, and <hi rend="italic">say positively that I never have been, and am not, concerned
or interested in those speculations directly nor indirectly.</hi> Neither did I
know the full history of those transactions, until within a few days past,
nor am I certain that I understand them yet.</p>

<p>I pass to another point-&#8212;the Convention of <date n="11-xx-1835">November last</date>, adopted a
declaration on the <date when="1835-11-07">7th of that month</date>&#8212;it was the voice of the <persName>people </persName>legally
expressed, Whether the Constitution of <date n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date> was the proper basis for the<pb n="420"/>
country to take, or not, it was taken by that declaration with certain 
limitations, and consequently the said declaration of <date when="1835-11-07">7th Nov.</date> was, for the time
being, the fundamental law of the land, and as such, it became the duty of
every <persName>citizen </persName>to sustain it, until it was changed. The country acted upon
this principle at that time&#8212;I did so, as it was my duty to do, and it seems
that I am now denounced for so doing, and isolated expressions are raked,
without any reference to the peculiar circumstances and temporary 
excitements of those days, or to the idea which was entertained by many, of 
trying to keep the seat of war beyond the limits of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, until the country
was better prepared, and by that means save the <persName>families </persName>from the 
devastations of invasion which they have suffered.</p>

<p>I was appointed, and not at my solicitation, by the said <date when="1835-11-07">November </date>
Convention, to go to the <placeName>United States</placeName> as a <persName>Commissioner </persName>in conjunction with
<persName>Dr. B. T. Archer</persName>, and <persName>W. H. Wharton, Esq</persName>. I obeyed the call of my 
<placeName>country</placeName>, thus expressed, and labored faithfully and arduously in the cause, as
did both of my <persName>colleagues</persName>. Our services were of a nature that it is difficult
to explain or appreciate&#8212;we made loans that were beneficial, and did not
hesitate to pledge our private property&#8212;our accounts have been rendered
to the <persName>government </persName>and are matter of record&#8212; We labored assiduously to
enlighten and inform the public mind, as to the origin, principles, and
objects of the contest with <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and in every respect obeyed our 
instructions. The estimate in which my own services were held by my <persName>colleagues</persName>
is sufficiently shown by their request that I would be a <persName>candidate for 
President</persName>, and by their support of my election. And yet it is now charged upon
me as sort of a crime that I obeyed the call of the <date when="1835-11-07">November </date>Convention,
and left <placeName>Texas </placeName>at all, and it is also said that nothing was done by the 
<persName>Commissioners </persName>but to eat fine dinners, drink wine, etc.</p>

<p>Such is the kind of <hi rend="italic">slang </hi>you inform me will destroy my election. The
people ought to be competent to analize these matters, and judge for 
themselves. They are however liable to be misled, by wrong impressions, but
will do justice in the end, and I assure you that it will be no personal 
mortification to me, individually, if I am not elected while such erroneous 
impressions exist. I have one proud consolation which nothing can deprive
me of, and <hi rend="italic">that is the approbation of my own conscience</hi>, and the certainty
that all I have done since I came to <placeName>Texas </placeName>in <date n="xx-xx-1821">1821</date>, will bear the test of the
most rigid scrutiny. I do not pretend by this to say, that I have not erred
in judgment, and perhaps from imprudent council, but I do say, that no
man has labored with purer intentions, or with a more ardent and 
disinterested desire to promote the prosperity, and happiness, and liberty of
<placeName>Texas</placeName>, and I will also say, that I consented to become a <persName>candidate </persName>at this
election with great reluctance. I have been absent from <placeName>Texas</placeName>, on public
business, for about three years. During this time, my individual affairs<pb n="421"/>
have been neglected, and much of the old colonizing business remained 
unclosed. It was my wish and intention to devote this year to those objects,
at the same time giving all the aid I could, as a citizen, to the public cause.
You requested a reply to your letter&#8212;I have given a long one, and you
can make any use of it you think proper.</p>

<p>Respectfully, your fellow citizen,	<persName>S. F. Austin</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
