<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5275">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>George P Digges to Stephen F Austin, 09-28-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>George P Digges</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-16">08-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Washington County,Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 432
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-09-28">09-28-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Reporting mission to General Gaines.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Washington County</placeName> <date when="1836-09-28">Sept: 28th 1836</date></p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>After parting with you at <placeName>Columbia </placeName>I proceeded as expeditiously as 
possible to the <placeName>neighbourhood of <persName>Mr. Landrum</persName>s</placeName>, to whom you gave me an
order for a Horse, and from whom I received none; I was there taken very
Ill, but from the attention paid me by <persName>Doct: Fitchen</persName>, I was able in three
days to proceed on my journey, which I was compelled to do even with a
fever, as I could not prevail on any person to go in my place, who I could
depend on:&#8212; On arriving at <placeName>Nachadoges</placeName>, I could only get five dollars in
cash, and nine dollars worth of necessary summer apparrell; <persName>Mr. Thorn
</persName>was in the <placeName>U. S. of the North</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>Upon arriving at <placeName>St. Augustine</placeName> I applyed to <persName>Mr. Hoghkis</persName> for funds and
received five dollars of him. Upon arriving at <placeName><persName>Genl. Houston</persName> Quarters</placeName> I
made known my errand to him, he wished me to proceed to <placeName><persName>Genl: Ganes</persName>'
camp</placeName> and deliver the dispatches myself, but could render me no assistance,
although my horse could then scarcely travell at all.&#8212; Upon seeing <persName>Genl:
E P Ganes</persName>, I delivered the dispatches to him and was again attacked with
the bilious fever; <persName>Genl Ganes</persName> requested me to remain a fiew days 
calculating on receiving some information from the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> that would be 
interesting to our government; but upon remaining the length of time he proposed
and finding myself unable to travel; and believing it would be some time
before I should recover my strength; and hearing that <persName>St. Anna</persName> was about
to be tried by Court Marshall for murder; and believing he would be shot;
I addressed a letter to <persName>Genl: Ganes</persName> on that subject and received in answer
a letter which <persName>Mr. Moody</persName> will shew you; I have ever since and still 
continue to be sick or very unwell and weak, or I would have been or even now
would visit <placeName>Columbia</placeName>.&#8212;</p>

<p>Enclosed you will find a statement of my expenditure on the road, 
togeather with the monies reed. etc.-</p>

<p>It is now my wish to settle myself and endeavour to make a support for
myself and <persName>family</persName>; you have a <placeName>Leigue of Land</placeName> not far from this (Viz
<persName>Grimes</persName>') called the <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Spring Liegue</placeName></hi> I am informed, which I would be glad
to settle on, if you will exchange with me for the <placeName>Leigue </placeName>that I am entitled
to as a <persName>settler </persName>and <persName>citizen </persName>previous to the Decliration of Independence; and
if you require that any difference be paid you by me <persName>Mr. Moody</persName> is fully
authorised to enter into a contract with you to that effect.</p>

<p>I have written to you twice since I arrived at <placeName><persName>Genl. Ganes</persName>' Camp</placeName>; but as
there is no mail and the transportation and safe delivery of letters so 
uncertain; I repeat every thing in this letter feeling certain it will be safely
delivered into your hand,&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Geo: P. Digges</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
