<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5149">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Nicholas Biddle, 04-09-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-30">07-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Nicholas Biddle
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Philadephia, Pennsylvania</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 328-330
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-04-09">04-09-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Proposal for loan on Texan bonds</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Philadelphia </placeName><date when="1836-04-09">April 9th 1836</date></p>

<p><persName>Hon. N. Biddle</persName></p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>As the enclosed memorandum embraces the general outlines of the loan
for <placeName>Texas </placeName>on which I conversed with you <date when="1836-04-09">this morning</date>, I take the liberty
of handing it to you.</p>

<p>I should esteem it as a favor if I could be informed within a Short time,
Whether you think any thing could be effected in this Matter&#8212;</p>

<p>I consider that the cause of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, is the cause of <persName>freemen </persName>and of 
<persName>mankind</persName>, but more emphatically of the <persName>people of the <placeName>United States</placeName></persName>, than any<pb n="329"/>
other. I flatter myself that you view it in the same light, and that the
security we offer is good, and therefore have no doubt you will give to it
the attention which its importance merits&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>leading men of all parties in <placeName>Washington</placeName></persName> are favourably disposed
towards <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;a reference to them will I think satisfy all persons as to
this fact&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName> [Rubric]</p>

<p>[Enclosure]:</p>

<p>It is proposed to negociate a Loan of $500,000 for the <persName>Government of
<placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> on the following basis,</p>

<p>The <persName>Commissioners of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, shall assign to the <persName>Bank of the <placeName>United
States</placeName> at <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></persName>, The Bonds of the <persName>Government of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, which they
have in their possession for the sum of $500,000, payable in not less than
5 years and bearing an interest of 8% per annum, to be held in Trust by
said <persName>Bank</persName>, for the benefit of the <persName>holders of a Scrip</persName> to be issued by the 
<persName>Commissioners</persName>, based on said Bonds.</p>

<p>Books of subscription shall be opened in the Cities of <placeName>Boston</placeName>, <placeName>New York</placeName>,
<placeName>Philadelphia </placeName>and <placeName>Baltimore </placeName>for a scrip to be issued by the <persName>Commissioners</persName>,
in shares of $100, each, which said scrip shall entitle the <persName>holder </persName>to an 
interest in said Bonds, equal to the amount of the scrip thus held by him and
said scrip shall be payable as follows:</p>

<p>of all purchases of <placeName>lands </placeName>at the <placeName>land offices of Texas</placeName>, 20% of the Sums
due may be paid, and shall be receivable in said scrip. Of all customs due
at the <placeName>Custom Houses of Texas</placeName> 20% of the sums due may be paid and shall
be receivable in said scrip. The <persName>holder </persName>shall be entitled to an interest of
8% per annum, payable at the <persName>Bank of the <placeName>United States </placeName>in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName></persName>,
on all portions of said scrip unpaid, and the <persName>Govt. of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> shall have the
privilege of paying the whole amount of said scrip and redeeming these
said Bonds by paying 20% of the principal annually after the expiration
of 5 years, or the whole payable at 6 months notice, after the expiration of
10 years.</p>

<p>The payments of the <persName>subscribers </persName>to said scrip shall be made, 25% at the
time of subscription and the remainder in 3 equal payments at 60, 90 and
120 days thereafter, to be secured at the time of subscription, by the notes
of the <persName>subscribers</persName>, endorsed to the satisfaction of the <persName>Directors of the Bank
of the <placeName>United States</placeName></persName>, or <persName>persons </persName>appointed by them and payable at such
place, as said <persName>Directors </persName>shall designate, provided the same be in the <placeName>Cities
where said Stock is subscribed</placeName>.</p>

<p>The <persName>Bank of the <placeName>United States</placeName></persName> shall discount the notes thus paid in, and
pay over the whole amount of the proceeds thereof and the amount of the<pb n="330"/>
first instalment thus paid in, to the <persName>Commissioners of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, and hold said
Bonds as an additional guarantee for the payment of said notes.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p><placeName>Phia</placeName>. <date when="1836-04-09">April 9. 1836</date></p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>I have taken the liberty of submitting to you a proposition for the 
negotiation of a loan of $500,000 for the <persName>Government of Texas</persName>, to which I would
respectfully ask your consideration, provided no arrangement can be made
on the basis of which we conversed today.</p>

<p>The personal interest you were kind enough to express for the welfare
and success of my struggling <placeName>country</placeName>, together with your intimate 
knowledge of such operations have induced me to make this communication.
Your answer as to your opinion of its practicability, the amount that could
probably be obtained in this <placeName>City</placeName>, the manner in which the subject should
be presented, and the willingness of the <persName>Bank </persName>to accept the Trust, and 
negotiate the paper, with such other suggestions as you may think important,
would greatly add to the obligation, I feel under to you for kindness and
attentions already received.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
