<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5259">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Samuel Ellis to Stephen F Austin, 08-23-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Samuel Ellis</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-16">08-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 421-423
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-08-23">08-23-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Texan credit in the United States low. Speculation has spoiled sale for land&#8212;</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New York</placeName> <date when="1836-08-23">August 23d 1836</date></p>

<p><persName>Genl S F Austin</persName></p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>Since my arrival in <placeName>New York</placeName> from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>, I have engaged myself
among the <persName>friends of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, to obtain all possible information in regard to
the general affairs of <placeName>Texas</placeName>. Such information as I may gain, that can
promote your views, it will always give me pleasure to communicate, from<pb n="422"/>
the public feeling in <placeName>Texas </placeName>you will undoubtedly hold an important 
station, and much of the destinies of the <placeName>Country </placeName>must rest upon you. Feeling
as I do a deep interest in the welfare of your country, I shall be amply
compensated for any labour it may be to me, should I be able in a single
instance to direct your mind to one movement, that might directly 
advantage the cause.</p>

<p>The two Gun Brigs contracted for by the <persName>Mexican Government</persName> have, as
I learn been launched in <placeName>Baltimore</placeName>, and will mount each 12 Guns exclusive
of Bridle ports and stern Guns. I shall soon visit <placeName>Baltimore </placeName>whence I
shall examine minutely the vessels, and report to the Govt their armament,
character and discription, and the circumstances under which they will
leave for <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, as it will be impossible for them to obtain <persName>Crews </persName>in the
<placeName>United States</placeName>, <placeName>Texas </placeName>has nothing to fear from them, for many months,
and if a proper lookout is kept they may yet become part of the <persName>Navy of
<placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>. I shall make such arrangements in <placeName>Baltimore </placeName>as to insure to <placeName>Texas</placeName>
accurate information of the time of sailing and the character of their
equipment.</p>

<p>In regard to Loans, from the best information I can gain, nothing can
be done to advantage until a new <persName>Executive </persName>is established, and the <placeName>Treasury
department</placeName> placed upon a permanent basis, the conduct of <persName>President 
Burnett</persName>, and his <persName>Cabinet </persName>has destroyed all confidence, here, and the 
appointment of the new <persName>agents in <placeName>New Orleans</placeName></persName> is considered as outrageous and
unwarranted, it appears to me that the greatest care and caution is 
necessary in all, future movements, to restore the shaken credit of the <persName>Govt</persName>.
Unless the affairs of <placeName>Texas </placeName>should become desperate no further 
voluntary contributions can be expected from this part of the <placeName>States</placeName>&#8212; Should
the war continue and the country is obliged to depend upon the sale or
pledge of the <placeName>public Lands</placeName>, to raise money, I would strongly recommend,
that a practical business man should be intrusted with full powers, and
that the selection should be made from some well known individual or
House in the <placeName>States</placeName>, experience has sufficiently proven to the old 
<persName>Commissioners</persName>, the difficulty that a <persName>citizen of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> will have to encounter in
such transactions, The establishment of a new <persName>Executive </persName>will in a great
measure change the present current of opinion in regard to your financial
affairs, and should your name (fortunately for <placeName>Texas</placeName>) be placed at the
head of the Executive a prudent course of conduct will soon restore the
public credit. Such opinions I have heard expressed here by those whose
conduct warrant them to be your friends, I look with extreme interest to
the result of the next election as upon it, depends in a great measure the
welfare of the country. My friend <persName>Bryan </persName>writes me that he has left for
<placeName>Texas</placeName>, whatever may be the result of his application for Justice, he feels
with me the strongest interest in the welfare of the <placeName>country</placeName>, and as our past<pb n="423"/>
exertions fully shew will make any posible sacrifice for the benefit of the
cause.</p>

<p>The sale of Scrip here by the different <placeName>Texas </placeName>companies has rendered
the price of <placeName>Land </placeName>nominal, when they can purchase nominal titles at less
than a cent an acre at auction, it cannot be expected that even real titles
should be worth much, I do not believe that at this moment <hi rend="italic">Head rights</hi>
would bring at auction Ten cents an acre, with this astounding fact before
you, you will perceive the necessity of some immediate measures to restore,
the value of land and place the <persName>Government </persName>in a Situation to command
credit, One measure that would almost immediately insure such credit,
would be to overturn at a blow the sales of the <persName>old land companies</persName>, or to
place such restrictions upon them, as to make the value of their lands
prospective, and predicating all titles upon actual settlement,</p>

<p>Trusting you will excuse the liberty I have taken, in forwarding to you
the above remarks,</p>

<p><persName>Samuel Ellis</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
