<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5004">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Philip Dimmitt to Stephen F Austin, 10-30-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Philip Dimmitt</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-08">06-08-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Fort Goliad, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 221-223
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-10-30">10-30-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Lack of discipline. Volunteers anxious to go to Bexar and some refuse to remain at Goliad. Military movements. Supplies</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Fort Goliad</placeName>, <date when="1835-10-30">Oct. 30th. 1835</date></p>
<p>To <persName>Gen. Stephen F. Austin,<lb/>
Com. in Ch. of the Army of the People,</persName></p>

<p>Dear Sir,</p>
<p>Since the date of my last (<date when="1835-10-28">28th inst</date>.) by hands of <persName>Maj. Geo. Southerland</persName>,
who left this on <date when="1835-10-28">that day</date>, in charge of the teams, dispatched to <placeName>Head 
Quarters</placeName> with provisions, events have transpired here which call for a free and
full exposition.</p>

<p>On the receipt of yours of the <date when="1835-10-23">23d ins.</date> prohibiting any <persName>volunteer </persName>the
option of leaving this <placeName>fortress </placeName>without permission from the <persName>Commandt</persName>.,
under the penalty of being reported and published a <persName>deserter</persName>, it was 
publickly read on parade to the <persName>men under my command</persName>. On some, it had a
salutary effect, and produced a change of purpose, highly favoarable to the
success of the campaign. On others, it either had no effect, or, if any, a
very different one, from that intended.</p>

<p><date when="1835-10-29">Yesterday</date>, three <persName>officers</persName>, <persName>Dr. Erwin, Surgeon</persName>; <persName>Lieut. David M. 
Collinsworh</persName>, and <persName>Lieut. A. H. Jones</persName>; and three <persName>privates</persName>, <persName>Milton Hicks</persName>, <persName>Edward B.
Wooten</persName> and-<persName>Atkinson</persName>, mustered and left this <placeName>fortress</placeName>, not only <hi rend="italic">without</hi>
permission, but in open contempt of the general order above quoted, and
took up the line of march for <placeName>Head Quarters</placeName>, near <placeName>Bexar</placeName>. This occurred
about 4 o. c. in the afternoon; and a little after 9 in the evening, <hi rend="italic">five </hi>of the
party returned, and <hi rend="italic">four</hi>, <persName>Lieut. Jones</persName>, <persName>Woottin</persName>, <persName>Hicks</persName>, and <persName>Atkinson</persName>, came
into the <placeName>fortress</placeName>, reporting the loss of one of their number&#8212;<persName>Lieut. 
Collinsworth</persName>. Not considering themselves under my command, no official report
was made to me. Their verbal statement, however, is, that they were fired
on by a <persName>party</persName>, lying in ambush <placeName>by the road side</placeName>&#8212;that the fire was instantly
succeeded by a shrill yell, at which their horses were greatly alarmed&#8212;one<pb n="222"/>
of the pary was thrown from his horse&#8212;one lost his gun and all the others,
one excepted, were carried some distance before they could stop their
horses. They further state, that, at the crack of the <persName>enemy</persName>'s guns, <persName>Lieut.
Collinsworth</persName> was seen to fall from his horse and heard to utter the 
exclamation&#8212;"0 Lord"&#8212;<persName>Jones </persName>and <persName>Wootten </persName>say they were in favor of 
returning to the scene of action, but as the others were unwilling to do so, they
all returned, without firing a gun, and without making an effort to relieve,
or bring off their wounded <persName>companion</persName>. He was therefore left on the
ground, to the mercy of the <persName>enemy</persName>.</p>

<p>Early <date when="1835-10-30">this morning</date>, the five <persName>survivors </persName>returned with 8 or <persName>10 others</persName>, to
the scene of action, or rather, of attack and flight, for the purpose of 
reconnoitering and bringing in the <persName>dead</persName>.</p>

<p>It would be doing much injustice to confound these <persName>volunteers</persName>, 
indiscriminately together. That <persName>Doctor Irwin</persName> originated, and headed the
mutiny; and drew the others, either directly, or indirectly into it, proof
abundant, and of the most respectable character, can be furnished from
here, on the shortest notice. The conduct of this man too, on former 
occasions, has been highly improper, unmilitary, and very rash.</p>

<p><date when="1835-10-31">Oct. 31st</date>. 1 o.c. P.M.&#8212;Since writing the above, the <persName>party </persName>that left 
<date when="1835-10-30">yesterday morning</date>, have returned with the dead body of the deceased, <persName>David,
M. Collinsworth</persName>&#8212;He was shot in the neck, scalped, and mangled in the
face with a tomahawk or hatchet.</p>

<p>The <persName>Deceased </persName>was buried to day, with the honors of War. From the
statements of those who returned with the Body, there can be little doubt
that the assailants were <persName>savages</persName>. The number quoted, varies from 6 to
10&#8212;The <persName>assailants </persName>did not even wait to divest the body of its apparel&#8212;
The cap only, was missing. His gun was probably taken, as it was not
found. His belt, shot-pouch, etc. etc. and pocket money $7.37 1/2 were
found on him, and returned. These facts furnish their own comment, and
supersede the necessity for any remarks by me.</p>

<p>A <persName>recruit </persName>of <persName>20 men </persName>arived here <date when="1835-10-29">last evening</date> from <placeName>Bay Prairie</placeName>. An
Iron, Six pound Cannon, with a small supply of ammunition, from 
<placeName>Matagorda</placeName>, has been forwarded by order of the <persName>Committee </persName>there, in compliance
with my request, and is now at <placeName>Guardeloupe Victoria</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have ordered a <persName>detachment of 35 men</persName>, under the Command of <persName>Adjutant
Ira Westover</persName>, to proceed forthwith to <placeName>Le Panteclan</placeName>, the <persName>garrison on the
<placeName>Nueces</placeName></persName>, reduce and burn it. The arms and Ammunition if possible, will be
brought off; and, if practicable, the public horses taken, and driven to this
place.</p>

<p>The <persName>citizens of <placeName>this vicinity</placeName></persName> have furnished 20 horses for this campaign
&#8212;and those of <persName>Guardeloupe Victoria</persName>, have made a tender of thirty head of
Beeves for the public service.<pb n="223"/></p>

<p>I am informed, that, <persName>Capt. Savriago</persName> has left <placeName>S. Felipe</placeName>, on parole, granted
by <persName>Zavalla </persName>and others&#8212;and that he has gone to <placeName>Matamoros</placeName>; but I have
ordered the making of <persName>every officer at the <placeName>Nueces</placeName></persName> <persName>prisoner</persName>, if possible. I
am informed, that, a <persName>party of 25 or 30 Comanches</persName> have been seen near
<placeName><persName>Baing</persName>'s</placeName>(?) in the <placeName>neighborhood of Guardeloupe Victoria</placeName>.</p>

<p>On the reduction of <placeName>Bexar</placeName>, the earliest instructions concerning the 
disposition of the Arms and ammunition at <placeName>this place</placeName>, are particularly
solicited. Your instructions too, relative to the property left in the <placeName>houses</placeName>
from which the flour, sugar, coffee, candles, soap, liquors, etc. etc. have
been taken, the title to which is contested, or is supposed by some to belong
to <persName>private individuals</persName>&#8212;by others, to the <placeName>nation</placeName>.&#8212;are earnestly solicited.</p>

<p><persName>P. Dimitt <hi rend="italic">Comg </hi></persName>[Rubric]</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
