<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5280">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Henry Austin to Stephen F Austin, 10-10-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Henry Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-17">08-17-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Columbia, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 434-435
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-10-10">10-10-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-17" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Suggesting compromise; with Texas creditors. Texas in English parliament. Financial crisis in the United States</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date when="1836-10-10">10th Oct /36</date></p>

<p><persName>Genl S F Austin</persName></p>

<p>My dear Sir</p>

<p>I wrote you on <date when="1836-10-07">Friday </date>since then I have had a sitting with <persName>Breedlove</persName>
and <persName>D Mieux</persName> <persName>agents for the contractors</persName>&#8212; I apprised them distinctly that
I had nothing to do with the <persName>Govt</persName>&#8212;but would take and deliver to you any
distinct proposition which they might think proper to make, defining in
terms not to be misunderstood what they understood the compromise to 
entitle them to, and that they would consider the compromise binding if the
govt Acceeded to those terms to pay the 180.000$</p>

<p><persName>Dr Mieux</persName> stated that the issue of Scrip in conformity with the 
compromise <hi rend="italic">without </hi>the proviso introduced by the <persName>Cabinet</persName>, that is to say with 
liberty to locate at their own expense when they please, would be satisfactory
but as few of the <persName>parties </persName>were here they could only make the proposition
binding on those here and give an assurance of their belief that the others
would concur&#8212; <persName>Dr Mieux</persName> will prepare the paper and address it to you,
by me. As I have been denounced as a cracked brained old citizen, for
apprising <persName>Burnet </persName>as an individual acquaintance of the impending danger of
a total prostration of public credit, it is not proper for my name to appear
in any public matter, but the fact that not a dollar can now be had either
on public or private credit of <placeName>Texas </placeName>will enable any one to judge whether
I was or not cracked brained when I anticipated this result from the course
pursued and did what as a Citizen I was bound to do; <hi rend="italic">all in my power to
avert it?</hi></p>

<p>Nothing can resuscitate the public credit but redeeming the public faith
by compliance with contract as compromised, The bonds of the new loan
will not command money until confidence in the Moral integrity of <persName>Govt</persName>
shall be restored by sound legislation.</p>

<p>I have offered my best <placeName>land </placeName>at 2$ pr Acre with bond to repay the Money
and 20 pr Ct if the <persName>party </persName>shall be disatisfied with his purchase at the end
of 12 months I cannot get a dollar neither <placeName>up country</placeName> or here, and have
my <persName>family </persName>unprovided</p>

<p>Cracked brained or not I have taken measures to counteract the 
impression made in <placeName>England </placeName>by the debate on <placeName>Texas </placeName>in <placeName>Parliament</placeName>, by sending to
<persName>Mr. Gordon</persName> and the <persName>Editor of the <placeName>London Atheneum</placeName></persName> each a copy of <persName>Mrs<pb n="435"/>
Holley</persName>s book with my view of the effect of the revolution in <placeName>Texas </placeName>upon
<persName>British </persName>interests, they are both old <persName>correspondents</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Mr Beal</persName> and <persName>Mr Ringold</persName> come out with me whether in the Independence
or <persName>Fannin </persName>undecided&#8212;</p>

<p>you can subscribe 5,000 Ds for me to the new loan as stated in the 
Telegra[p]h of <date when="1836-09-13">13th Sept</date> if you think proper</p>

<p>There is a frightfull collaps in the circulating medium, the <placeName>Western
Banks</placeName> will in all probability be compelled to stop before christmas and
there are fears for the <placeName>Banks of this City</placeName> None of them discount a dollar
but for the <persName>debtors of the Bank</persName>, Not even exchange unless the money is
to be paid to the <placeName>Bank</placeName>, save in <placeName>N York</placeName>, best security 3 or 4 prCt pr
Month here and there&#8212; Respectfully</p>

<p><persName>H Austin</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] To <persName>Genl. S F Austin</persName> <placeName>Columbia Texas</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
