<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5021">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Gail Borden, Jr to Stephen F Austin, 11-05-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Gail Borden, Jr</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-12">06-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">San Antonio, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 238-239
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-11-05">11-05-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Procedure of Consultation. Suspending land business. Newspaper</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe</placeName> <date when="1835-11-05">Nov 5th 1835</date></p>
<p>Dear <persName>Genl</persName>.</p>

<p>I would say something of the proceedings of our <persName>Convention </persName>were it not
that you will get the most important transactions in the hand bill of the
first days proceedings&#8212; <date when="1835-11-04">Yesterday</date>, however, the day was principally 
occupied in discussion on the resolution offered by <persName>Mr. Wharton </persName>appointing a
<persName>committee </persName>"to make a declaration to the world setting forth the reasons for
which we take up arms etc" Though the discussion was lengthy and 
animated yet coolness and moderation pervaded throughout the debate.</p>

<p>Your opinion as to what you believed should be the course to pursue
was introduced as well as several plans all of which were referred to the
<persName>committee </persName>on the subject. Whatever may be the decision it will be 
<hi rend="italic">unanimous</hi>. My opinion is, however, that a large majority will declare for the
principles of the Constitution of <date n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date>&#8212;</p>

<p>Unanimity and good feeling I believe is the order of the day&#8212;and I
trust all will go well.</p>

<p>I am waiting to see what the <persName>Convention </persName>will do on the subject of raising
money before I attempt to obtain it on your own account. I believe they
will raise it. They ought to do it I am certain&#8212;</p>

<p><date when="1835-11-04">Last night</date> was a cold and stormy night, and I thought of you and the
<persName>army</persName>&#8212;that perhaps you were in the <placeName>broad prairy</placeName> without cover and 
perhaps destitute of wood. I regret to hear your health is not good; and fear,
the hardships of the <placeName>Camp </placeName>and what is worse, the labor of the mind will
endanger your health.</p>

<p>Had a conversation with <persName>Genl. Houston</persName> today&#8212;I believe he has the 
interest of <placeName>our country</placeName> at heart. He made the best speech <date when="1835-11-04">yesterday </date>I have
ever heard; the whole tenour of it went to harmonize the feelings of the
<persName>people </persName>and to produce unanimity of sentiment.</p>

<p>I think there is little doubt of much aid and assistance from the <placeName>United
States</placeName>.</p>

<p>Had the favor <date when="1835-11-05">this evening</date> of seeing your letter to <persName>Dr R Peebles</persName> in which
you advise to suspend for the present, any farther locations in <placeName>land</placeName>. Little
business has been done in the <placeName>land office</placeName> for some time past, and I can<pb n="239"/>
assure you no advantages has, or will be taken of those who are <placeName>in the
field</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Mr. Jack</persName> however can tell you what has been done. Now on another
subject.</p>

<p>I have written to <persName>brother Tom</persName>, that without we had more materials in
our <placeName>printing establishment</placeName>, it was impossible to do work to any extent that
it was all important, as well for ourselves as the interest of the <placeName>Country </placeName>to
send an <persName>agent </persName>immediately to <placeName>N. Orleans </placeName>for the purpose of getting what
articles we want, and extend our subscription list, without a great 
patronage, can not stand the heavy expense of carrying on the <placeName>office</placeName>&#8212; We have
sufficient weight of type, but not proportion <persName>Mr. Baker</persName> can not be spared,
because he is our only <persName>translator</persName>&#8212;I can not go for the reasons of my
pressing business, as well of other things, as the improvement of the 
<placeName>printing office</placeName>. This is, therefore, to request you to give <persName>Thomas </persName>a furlough so
soon as you think he can be spared that he may go to the <placeName>U S</placeName> for the 
purposes above named. My reason for saying so much to you is, that I 
discovered from his last letter he was determined not to come <placeName>home </placeName>till after
the campaign; and unless you thought he could better serve the <placeName>country </placeName>by
forwarding our <placeName>printing establishment</placeName>, he would not consent to come from
the <placeName>field</placeName>.</p>

<p>Excuse me for troubling you with so long a letter, and believe me</p>

<p><persName>G. Borden Jr </persName>[Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>S. F. Austin Commander in Chief American Army</persName> <placeName>San
Antonio</placeName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
