<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5223">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to Unknown, 07-10-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-13">08-13-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Velasco, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 393-395
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">memorandum</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-07-10">07-10-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Concerning letters to Jackson and Gaines and advice to Burnet</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>1836&#8212; <placeName>Velasco</placeName>&#8212; <date when="1836-07-10">July 10&#8212;</date></p>

<p><hi rend="italic">Memorandum</hi>&#8212;</p>

<p>The original letter of <date when="1836-07-04">July 4th</date> from <persName>Gen. Santa Anna</persName> to <persName>Gen. Jackson</persName>,
containing the copies of the treaties of <date when="1836-05-14">14th May</date> and <persName>Santa Anna</persName>'s farewell<pb n="394"/>
of <date when="1836-06-01">1 June</date> were sent by me to <persName>Gen. E. P. Gains</persName>, by <persName>Geo. P. Digges</persName> who went
<persName>express</persName>, also my letters to <persName>Gen Jackson</persName> and <persName>Gen Gains</persName>, of <date when="1836-07-04">same date</date> and
to <persName>Grayson </persName>and <persName>Collingsworth </persName>and <persName>President Burnet</persName>s letter to <persName>Gains </persName>
approving of the establishment of his <placeName>head quarters at Nacogdoches</placeName>, should he,
<persName>Gains</persName>, think proper to do so, for the purpose of keeping the <persName>northern 
indians</persName> quiet&#8212; This letter is dated <date when="1836-06-28">June 28</date>, and was written by <persName>Burnet </persName>at
my suggestion, the day after my arrival at <placeName>Velasco </placeName>from the<placeName> U. S</placeName>.</p>

<p><persName>Gen Santa Anna</persName>'s letter to <persName>Gen Jose Urrea</persName> was delivered to me, open, to
<persName>President Burnet</persName> at <placeName>Velasco </placeName>the <date when="1836-07-08">8th of July</date>, and sent by him and a 
translation of <persName>Santa Anna</persName>'s letter to <persName>Jackson </persName>the next day to <persName>Gen M. B. Lamar </persName>in
the <persName>Texas army</persName> by <persName>Capt. Roman</persName>&#8212; I had previously shown it at <placeName>Brazoria</placeName>
to <persName>Lamar </persName>on my way down from <placeName>Columbia </placeName>on the <date when="1836-07-06">6th July</date> and wished him
to take it then, so as to save delay, for he was just starting for the <persName>army</persName>
to assume the chief command, but he preferred that it should be sent to him
officially by <persName>President Burnet</persName> observing that the opinions he had sustained
while in the <persName>cabinet</persName>, against any kind of treaty with <persName>Santa Anna</persName>, or making
any use of him at all for the purpose of terminating the war etc, precluded
him from taking any active part in the matter, but that, as <persName>commander of
the army</persName> he would co-operate with the <persName>Govt</persName>, and interpose no obstacles</p>

<p>The day I arrived at <placeName>Velasco</placeName>, (late in the evening of <date when="1836-06-27">27th June</date>) I 
represented to <persName>president Burnet</persName> the great importance of writing officially once a
week if possible to the <persName>representatives of <placeName>Texas </placeName>at <placeName>Washington City</placeName></persName> in the
<placeName>U. S.</placeName> and stated it as my opinion that the omission of this <persName>Govt</persName>, in not 
furnishing to those <persName>representatives</persName>, whoever they might be, official reports of
the battle of <placeName>San Jacinto</placeName> and of the organization of the <persName><placeName>Texas </placeName>Govt</persName>, and
general situation of the <placeName>country </placeName>etc had been fatal to the interests of <placeName>Texas</placeName>,
as I believed that our independence would have been acknowledged by the
<persName><placeName>U. S.</placeName> govt</persName>, and <persName>congress </persName>if those official documents had been sent in on
time&#8212; Nothing of the kind was ever sent on&#8212;those of us, (<persName>Austin</persName>, 
<persName>Wharton</persName>, <persName>Archer</persName>, <persName>Childress </persName>and <persName>Hamilton</persName>) who were in <placeName>Washington </placeName>received
nothing, not even one word from their <persName>Govt</persName>, and had nothing to operate
with, in their exertions to procure a recognition of our independence, but
<placeName>news paper</placeName> accounts and private letters from <persName>individuals </persName>in <placeName>Texas </placeName><placeName>New
Orleans </placeName>etc&#8212;</p>

<p>I was assured that <persName>Grayson </persName>and <persName>Collingsworth </persName>(the present 
<persName>representatives of <placeName>Texas </placeName>at <placeName>Washington City</placeName></persName>) should be regularly written to, and on
the <date when="1836-07-09">9th July</date> <persName>president Burnet</persName> wrote to them (by the schooner Comanche
bound to <placeName>Orleans</placeName>) and enclosed certified copies of <persName>Gen. Santa Anna</persName>'s letters
to <persName>Gen. Jackson</persName> and <persName>Gen Urrea</persName>, and of the treaties of <date when="1836-05-14">14th May</date> etc I
wrote to them at the same time (see copy <date when="1836-07-09">9th July</date>)&#8212; The duplicate of
<persName>Gen Santa Anna</persName>'s letter to <persName>president Jackson</persName> signed by himself, was given<pb n="395"/>
by me to <persName>president Burnet</persName> on the <date when="1836-07-08">8 july</date> and filed by him, (as he told me,
with the records of the <persName>executive office</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Mr W. H. Jack the secretary of State</persName> left <placeName>velasco </placeName>some twenty days since
for the <placeName>Neches river</placeName> to bring back his <persName>family</persName>, who had fled there with 
<persName>Mckinny</persName>'s and <persName>Williams</persName>'s in time of the general flight <date n="Spring-1836">last spring</date> he is dayly
expected back and it is said will be here <date when="1836-07-10">today (10 July)</date></p>

<p>The <persName>secretary of the Navy, Potter</persName>, went to the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> about two months ago
and has not returned the only <persName>members of the Govt</persName> now here are <persName>Burnet</persName>,
<persName>Hardiman </persName>and <persName>Somerville</persName>&#8212; I gave it as my opinion the importance of
official reports from the <persName>head of each department of the Govt</persName>, relative to
the state of the public affairs of the respective branches, and that such 
reports should be published and sent officially to the <persName>reps. of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> in 
<placeName>Washington </placeName>to be used there in support of our application for independence etc&#8212;</p>

<p>I paid to <persName>G. P. Digges</persName>, the <persName>express </persName>to <persName>Gains</persName>, ten dollars of my own
money for his expenses, and gave him a letter, to hire horses should his
fail&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>W. H. Jack</persName>, <persName>S. M. Williams</persName> and <persName>T. F. McKinney</persName> arrived with their 
<persName>families </persName>in the Steam boat Yellow Stone from the <placeName>river Neches</placeName> <date when="1836-07-10">this afternoon
(July 10)</date>&#8212; The schooner Comanche sailed for <placeName>Orleans </placeName><date when="1836-07-10">to day</date>&#8212;</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
