<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5265">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Morgan to Samuel Swartwout, 09-05-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Morgan</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-16">08-16-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Samuel Swartwout
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Galveston Island, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 429-430
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-09-05">09-05-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-16" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Presenting him with Santa Anna's tent, in recognition of services to Texas</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Galveston Island</placeName> <date when="1836-09-05">Sept. 5th- 1836</date>.&#8212;</p>

<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>From the grateful recollections with which, not only myself, but the
<persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> generally, are impressed, for your immeasurable acts of
kindness to our <persName>pioneers </persName>in the cause of Liberty in an unknown land&#8212;your
munificent donations, as disinterested as it was valuable, at a period when
our struggles were considered at best, but visionary and chimerical, and
your personal persistency in enlisting the sympathies of your generous
<persName>countrymen</persName>&#8212;have decidedly marked you as a person most deserving of
one of our first trophies of victory. You will, therefore, receive by the first
safe conveyance the Tent of <persName>Santa Anna</persName>&#8212;that vampyre who sought to
fatten on the life blood of young Liberty in our now blooming land. With
that tent are associated feelings of <hi rend="italic">triumph </hi>and <hi rend="italic">horror</hi>&#8212;the one at the
chivalrous efforts of our victorious little band, annihilating at one fell
swoop the Hydraheaded monster of Tyranny, with his innumerable 
myrmidons, on the plains of <placeName>San Jacinto</placeName> &#8212;the other at the infernal mandates of
the deeply crimsoned <persName>Tyrant</persName>, issued under cover of that tent, which 
traversed through rivers of gore&#8212;reckless alike of the wailing of unprotected
womanhood, or the manly confidence of the brave soldier, in the open
prostration of his arms.&#8212; In that tent slumbered that Fiend, under the 
consociate demon tutelage of his pillow, who planned, and had executed the
foul massacres&#8212;and ruthless murders&#8212;of the <placeName>Alamo</placeName>, and <placeName>La Bahia</placeName>&#8212;and
then sat in noon day, the sleek hypocrite, on whose lips hung the word of
promised mercy&#8212;but whose signal immolated to his indomitable spirit of
desolation, nearly in his presence, the brave <persName>Fannin</persName>, and his worthy 
<persName>compatriots</persName>! whose blood flowed, even while the echo of mercy vibrated in their
ears.&#8212; But now, while the monster withers under the upas blast of 
retributive justice, the tree of liberty overshadows our fertile plains.</p>

<p>The memorials of Liberty are a nations dearest pledge of the virtue and
valor of its ancestry, and are always justly prized by posterity as a beacon
of example. And what prouder monument to new born freedom in <placeName>Texas</placeName>,
than the <placeName>tent of the Tyrant</placeName>, that doomed its destruction, while its 
glimmering star shone dimly through the darkness of oppression, but now, despite
of the united councils of despotism, and concentrated force of numbers,
blazes in meridian brightness even over the <placeName>Rio Grande del Norte</placeName>.&#8212;</p>

<p>With what different emotions was my mind excited when standing under
the tent of the immortal <persName>Washington</persName>, at <placeName>York Town</placeName>&#8212;from thence through
the vista of the past, might be seen the source from whence the invaluable
blessings of civilization, literature, and happiness have flown to a people
justly and preeminently proud of their almost exclusive right to the 
appelation of <persName>freemen</persName>&#8212; and these the Genius of Universal emancipation taught<pb n="430"/>
her impressive lessons to her highly gifted son. Oh what an antithesis!
the foul den of the furious tiger, and the unsullied abode of peace and
honor&#8212;the one a memorial of valor, intrepidity, and a nation's benison&#8212;
the other of dishonor, perfidy, and execrations!&#8212;</p>

<p>Be pleased to accept the tent withal the trophy of our success, as a tender
of due and grateful acknowledgement, and be assured of the continued 
appreciation of your valued services, and the permanent friendship of</p>

<p><persName>J Morgan</persName></p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Genl. Samuel Swartwout</persName> <placeName>New York</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
