<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5218">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>George Fisher to Stephen F Austin, 07-07-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>George Fisher</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-13">08-13-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New Orleans, Louisiana</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 386-388
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-07-07">07-07-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">People opposed to release of Santa Anna. History of the Correo Atlantico</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date when="1836-07-04">7th. July 1836</date></p>

<p><persName>Genl S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p>My Dr Sir</p>

<p>By the enclosed extracts of the <placeName>Newspapers </placeName>of this City you will perceive,
what the public opinion is in reference to <placeName>Tejas </placeName>in consequence of <persName>Santa
Anna</persName> about being liberated by the <persName>Cabinet </persName>in complyance of the 10th Art°
of the treaty (if such can be called the agreement which <persName>Santa Anna</persName> made<pb n="387"/>
while in durance) which was prevented by timely interference of some of
our <persName>friends</persName>, who knowing <persName>Santa Anna</persName> better than the <persName>Cabinet </persName>have 
interposed the legal and manly means to see the expectations of the <persName>people of
<placeName>Tejas</placeName></persName> not to be paralized by precipitated measures of a few men, whose
object I hope was the advancement of the wellfare of the <placeName>Country</placeName>, yet it
would have proved to be her total ruin.</p>

<p>Notwithstanding the great excitement caused and is still continuing by
this measure of the <persName>Cabinet</persName>, as you must be yourself perfectly aware of as
you have seen it before your departure from this place, we are using our
best endeavours to keep up the credit of <placeName>Tejas </placeName>in this <placeName>country</placeName>,&#8212;<persName>Volunteers</persName>
are arriving almost dayly destined for your <placeName>Country </placeName>but it is almost 
impossible to get a few dollars fund to despatch them&#8212; Many of the best
<persName>friends of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> have become quite cold about contributions, and say that
unless <persName>Santa Anna</persName> is made an example of the law for the cruel butcheries
of which he is guilty, they would not contribute any thing.</p>

<p>The "Correo Atlantico" whose merits you will sufficiently know how to
appreciate is on the eve of stopping. &#8212;The <persName>Editor Mr. Santangelo</persName> can not
get any subscriptions to defray the expences of printing which is $33 pr.
week, say nothing about paying carriers, packing, postages, and other
sundry small expences attending its publication&#8212;independent of this he
does not get any recompense for his Editorial labors as you already know
it by his own statement to you.</p>

<p>Since the comencement of the publication of said <placeName>paper </placeName>in this City, (viz
from No. 17 to No. 32. both inclusive) I have paid <persName>Mr Santangelo</persName> $520.
towards its printing, in this sum are included $200. which I received from
<persName>Mr. Saml. M. Williams</persName> as a contribution and little better than $100 recd
from our <persName>Mexican friends</persName>, the Balance is been paid by me at my individual
expence, and as I can not continue any longer to contribute at such rate, I
must stopp my contributions. No. 33. 34. 35. and the next 36. are at the
expence of the <persName>old Gentleman</persName>, and as his means are short also he is going
to suspend his labors until he can get some assistance, and the only one I
believe will be by the <persName>Govnt of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, as it is almost impossible to get 
<persName>subscribers </persName>on account of its being devoted to the Cause of <placeName>Texas</placeName>, and against
<placeName>Mexico</placeName>, &#8212;<persName>Spaniard</persName>, <persName>French</persName>, and great many <persName>Americans </persName>here are against it,
those that are friendly do not subscribe on the plea of being in <persName>Spanish </persName>and
can not understand it &#8212;But, my, Dr Sir, you are perfectly aware of its good
result in the <placeName>interior of Mexico</placeName>, and it is evident it must if continued, divide
the <persName>parties</persName>, and precipitate the moral and physical revolution of <placeName>Mexico</placeName>,
thus diverting the attention of the <persName>Governt </persName>at home, and keeping their <persName>troops</persName>
in stead of sending them into <placeName>Tejas</placeName>. &#8212;</p>

<p><date when="1836-07-08">To morrow</date> two of our <persName>friends </persName>(<persName>Montero </persName>and <persName>Pinzon</persName>) are going pr <persName>Caleb
Goodwin</persName> to <placeName>Vera Cruz</placeName>, &#8212;one (<persName>coronl. Camara</persName>) to <placeName>Yucatan</placeName>, and <persName>Doct
Portes</persName> is already gone to <placeName>Tampico</placeName>, those men are called from Mo. for<pb n="388"/>
bringing about the Revolution, and sent from here, by <persName>Genl Mexia</persName>, &#8212;There
is no doubt that the affairs of the <placeName>interior </placeName>are drawn to a focus, and before
very long we must hear news, &#8212;<persName>Genl Ma</persName>- sent his <persName>family </persName>to <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>,
they left here <date when="1836-07-03">last Sunday</date> with <persName>Capt. Offutt</persName> and <persName>Melinda</persName>. &#8212;</p>

<p>By the first vessel from <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>I expect letters from <persName>Dr Franco. V.
Fernandez</persName> to whom I have written, and requested him to write me and 
explain himself "sin embozo" &#8212;y que me informe sobre su planecito a favor
de la separasion de los <placeName>E. E. Y. Y.</placeName> del oriente Norte y Occidente &#8212; I
promised him support on the part of <placeName>Texas </placeName>in that case. &#8212;Tell me whether
I have done right or wrong?</p>

<p><persName>George Fisher</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
