<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5056">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 11-22-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-15">06-15-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Before Bexar, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 262-264
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-11-22">11-22-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-15" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Estimate of the army before Bexar. Plans for future</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Before Bexar</placeName> <date when="1835-11-22">Novr. 22 1835</date></p>

<p>Dr <persName>Brother</persName>,</p>

<p><hi rend="italic">My health has been very bad since I left the <placeName>Cibolo</placeName>, <date n="10-xx-1835">more than a month
ago</date>, and I have been unable to attend personally to the duties of my station<pb n="263"/>
with that activity which the service required&#8212;</hi>I believe however that all has
been done that could have been&#8212;I have at various times submitted the
question of storming the <placeName>fortifications </placeName>to a <persName>council of officers</persName> and they have
uniformly decided against it&#8212;<date when="1835-11-21">yesterday </date>I was in hopes the <persName>Army </persName>was 
prepared to do it, and I issued a positive order, to storm at day light <date when="1835-11-22">this 
morning</date>, but on trial I found it impossible to get <persName>half the men</persName> willing for the
measure, and it was abandoned from necessity</p>

<p>I begin to doubt whether much more can be done here, than to leave a
<persName>force </persName>in <placeName><date n="Winter-1835">winter </date>quarters</placeName> at the <placeName>missions below town</placeName>, say <persName>250 men</persName>, untill the
necessary <persName>regular force</persName> and guns and other supplies, come out&#8212;</p>

<p>My health is better than it has been and is improving fast&#8212;I shall make
another effort to get the <persName>army </persName>to storm if it cannot be effected, I shall leave
as many as will stay in <placeName>winter quarters</placeName> and go to the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> under the 
appointment they have given me as <persName>commissioner</persName>&#8212; So far as my own wishes
and feelings are concerned, I much prefer an appointment out of <placeName>Texas</placeName>,
than in it&#8212;<hi rend="italic">I am ready to serve the <placeName>country </placeName>in any way I can&#8212;I accepted
the appointment I now hold here, because I could not do otherwise, I never
sought it, nor wished for it&#8212;my constitution is too much worn out and too
feeble for the exposure and hardships and activity of a winters campaign,
destitute of everything like comforts</hi>. I have done the best I could This
<persName>army </persName>has always been composed of discordant materials, and is without
proper organization&#8212;The <persName>volunteer </persName>sistem will not do for such a service,
I have had a hard and difficult task to perform&#8212;and am <hi rend="italic">really so worn
out,</hi> that <hi rend="italic">I begin to require rest</hi>&#8212; I could have been of more use in the
<persName>convention </persName>than here&#8212;and I can be of service to <placeName>Texas </placeName>by going to the
<placeName>U. S.</placeName> and I wish to go there.</p>

<p>Love to all&#8212; The <persName>boys </persName>are well&#8212;we are about <placeName>600 yards from the 
fortifications</placeName> and we have a battery within 340 yards but have no balls to do
much good&#8212;</p>

<p>This place must fall of itself in a short time&#8212;They are almost destitute
of supplies and but little hope, of getting tham from the <placeName>interior </placeName>soon&#8212;
If <persName>Genral Mexia</persName> has gone to attack <placeName>Matamoros </placeName>and succeeds, in taking that
place this one will fall of course&#8212;</p>

<p>As to <placeName>Texas </placeName>affairs, much more depends at present on a proper 
regulation of the <persName>civil Govt</persName>, than on the military operations&#8212;</p>

<p>If there is unanimity and prudence and no <persName>party </persName>work, hi the <persName>civil 
department</persName>, all will go right the fate of <placeName>Texas </placeName>depends mainly on this&#8212;we
ought to get united to the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> as soon as possible, it is the best we can
do farewell</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName> [Rubric]<pb n="264"/></p>

<p>How I envy a poor and obscure man in his quiet cottage, free from care
and trouble and faction&#8212;A</p>

<p>We have cannonading every day. <date when="1835-11-22">to day</date> it has been very brisk for 
several hours&#8212;no harm has been done to any of our <persName>men</persName>&#8212;we hear that 
several have been <persName>killed </persName>and <persName>wounded </persName>inside one <persName>mexican soldier</persName> was killed
<date when="1835-11-22">this morning</date> who was attempting to reconnoiter our battery	<persName>S F A</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
