<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5215">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to General Gaines, 07-04-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-13">08-13-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        General Gaines
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Columbia, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 384-385
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-07-04">07-04-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Urging Gaines to occupy Nacogdoches to quiet the Indians and to guarantee fulfillment of the treaty of Velasco by Santa Anna</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Columbia, Texas</placeName>, <date n="-04-1836">July 4 &#8212;1836</date></p>

<p><persName>Major Genl. Edmund P. Gain[e]s</persName></p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>I arrived here a few days since from the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> and find this <placeName>country </placeName>still
threatened with war and its evils. The <persName>Indians </persName>have commenced active
hostilities on the whole line of the <placeName>frontier </placeName>along the <placeName>upper or San Antonio
road</placeName>. I am told they are all <persName>Northern indians</persName> with rifles, principally 
Harper's ferry, an arm that is not used by the <persName>native tribes of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>.</p>

<p>The <persName>Mexicans </persName>are concentrating their <persName>forces </persName>at Matamoras and have no
doubt advanced to the <placeName>river Nueces</placeName> by this time. <persName>Genl Urrea</persName> is the 
<persName>commander-in-chief</persName>, he has already been joined by <persName>Genl Cortazar</persName> with fresh
<persName>troops </persName>from the <placeName>interior</placeName>.</p>

<p>The movement of the <persName>Mexican Army</persName> into <placeName>Texas </placeName>again, will embolden the
<persName>indians <placeName>west of the Mississippi</placeName></persName>, who no doubt communicate with those to
the <placeName>east of that river</placeName>, and the probability of an <persName>indian </persName>war on the <placeName>South
western limits of the U. S.</placeName> appears to be much stronger than it ever was.</p>

<p>I confidently believe that the movement of the <persName>troops </persName>under your 
command to <placeName>Nacogdoches </placeName>will stop an <persName>indian </persName>war and preserve the tranquility
of the <placeName>U. S. frontier</placeName>. Such a movement will meet with the approbation of
the <persName>Govt of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, as you will perceive by the letter of <persName>President Burnet</persName>,
which accompanies this, and I am confident it will receive the most decided
sanction of the <persName>people of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>.</p>

<p>The <persName>president of Mexico Genl. Santa Anna</persName>, who is now a <persName>prisoner </persName>in this
place, assures me in the most decided and unequivocal terms of his desire
to end this <placeName>Texas </placeName>war on the basis of a recognition of our independence,
and he has written to <persName>Genl. Jackson</persName>, requesting the mediation of the <persName><placeName>U. S.</placeName>
Government</persName> to terminate the war on that basis.</p>

<p>The packet which I herewith send you for <persName>Genl. Jackson</persName>, contains <persName>Genl
Santa Anna</persName>'s letter to him and many other important papers of great 
interest to the public service of <placeName>both countries</placeName>, and I therefore must beg the
favor of you to forward them with the least possible delay, by <persName>express</persName>, or
in such manner as you may deem expeditious and safe&#8212;</p>

<p>I have no hesitation in saying that I believe <persName>Genl. Santa Anna</persName> is sincere,
and in good faith, in the promises and offers he has made to this <persName>Govt</persName>, to
acknowledge our independence and admit the mediation of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> but he
can do nothing as a <persName>prisoner</persName>, or until he returns to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and reassumes
the <persName>Govt</persName>, or to the <persName>Mexican Army</persName> and resumes the command, and such is
the state of public opinion here and in our <persName>Army </persName>that he can not be 
released until he gives such guarantees, as will satisfy both <persName>Army </persName>and the
people of his sincerity. Now the guarantee of <persName>Genl. Jackson</persName> will be 
sufficient, and I believe that your guarantee, in conjunction with the establish-<pb n="385"/>
ment of your <placeName>head quarters at Nacogdoches</placeName>, would be sufficient&#8212; In this
event <persName>Genl. Santa Anna</persName> would be liberated&#8212; I mean in the event of your
guaranteeing in the name of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> the fulfilment of the treaty made by
<persName>Santa Anna</persName> with the <persName>Govt, of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>. The main substance of this treaty is
to remove all the <persName>Mexican troops</persName> <placeName>beyond the Rio Bravo</placeName> immediately, and
to procure the acknowledgement of the Independence of <placeName>Texas </placeName>from the
<persName>Mexican Congress</persName> and terminate the war by negociation, calling in the
mediation of the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> as he has done by his letter to <persName>Genl. Jackson</persName> of
this date.</p>

<p>Should your instructions admit of the course indicated without waiting
for an answer to <persName>Genl Santa Anna</persName>'s letter to <persName>President Jackson</persName>, I am of the
opinion it will lead to an immediate cessation of hostilities and to a 
termination of the war. In the event that you feel authorised to <hi rend="italic">tender </hi>your
friendly interposition in this matter I have no doubt it will be accepted
both by <persName>Genl Santa Anna</persName> and by the <persName>Govt of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>&#8212;the substance of the
tender being to pave the way for peace and procure the liberation of <persName>Genl
Santa Anna</persName>, the <persName>president of a nation</persName> that is on the most friendly terms
with the <placeName>U. S.</placeName>, and if you could visit this place in person, for the above
purposes it would have a decisive effect and <persName>Genl Santa Anna</persName> would no
doubt be set at liberty, and pave the way through you, for a termination of
all this difficulty.</p>

<p>I make these suggestions as a <persName>citizen of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>&#8212; I hold no office, but
can go into the <persName>Cabinet </persName>whenever it may be necessary and I have no doubt
the <persName>Govt</persName>, and people here will approve of the course I have indicated
should it be adopted by you, nor can I doubt that the <persName><placeName>U. S.</placeName> Govt</persName> will 
approve of it, in as much as the object is to terminate a war upon its <placeName>borders</placeName>
that is viewed by that <persName>Govt</persName>, and <persName>people </persName>with great interest, and to promote
and serve the cause of humanity and procure the liberation of the <persName>President
of <placeName>Mexico</placeName></persName>, on terms that will be satisfactory to all <persName>parties</persName>&#8212;neither can I
doubt that it will be viewed by <placeName>Mexico </placeName>in any other light than an act of
friendship towards <persName>President Santa Anna</persName>. Delay may be pernicious&#8212;the
<persName>Mexican Army</persName> is advancing and if hostilities commence it may be too late
to do anything. The country is turning out <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi>, and I have no doubt
the <persName>Mexican Army</persName> will be cut to pieces, but the <persName>inhabitants </persName>are suffering
greatly by being compelled to keep the field, and their good will be 
promoted by a speedy and <hi rend="italic">final </hi>termination of the war.</p>

<p><persName>Genl. Santa Anna</persName> desires that these matters should not be published in
the <placeName>newspapers </placeName>yet.</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
