<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5092">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses Austin Bryan to James F Perry, 12-30-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Moses Austin Bryan</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-13">07-13-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">San Felipe de Austin, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 295-297
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-12-30">12-30-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Making certified copies of Austin's land titles
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>San Felipe de Austin</placeName> <date when="1835-12-30">Decr 30th 1835</date></p>

<p>Dear <persName>Father </persName>and <persName>Mother</persName></p>

<p>I have nearly finished copying the transfers of <placeName>Lands </placeName>to <persName>Uncle </persName>from
different <persName>individuals </persName>and will have them certified by the <persName>Judge </persName>and will
send them down by the first safe hand. As yet I do not know whether I
shall be able to get hold of <persName>Uncle</persName>s titles to his <placeName>land </placeName>from the <persName>Solomons</persName>
composing the <persName>council </persName>long enough to copy them or not. The <persName>council </persName>have
determined not to open the <placeName>Land Office</placeName>; but as <persName>Doct Peebles</persName> is one of the
<persName>commissioners </persName>who were appointed to take charge of the papers I may
perhaps get them from him long enough to take a copy of them without the<pb n="296"/>
knowledge of the <persName>council</persName>. I have copied about 30 transfers of <placeName>lands </placeName>to
<persName>Uncle </persName>and will secure that much at any rate as I have the originals in
my possession and will not give them up if they are required of me, until
I get the copies certified by the <persName>Judge </persName><persName>Mr. Bordin</persName> thinks perhaps we may
be able through <persName>Dct. Peebles</persName> to get hold of his titles and if I do get hold
of them I will take copies and then if the originals are destroyed the copiss
will be good; and I think there is some risk in leaving papers of such 
importance in the hands of those men who compose the <persName>council </persName>without a 
certified copy of the whole I send this by <persName>Mr Cane a planter from <placeName>Mississippi</placeName>
</persName>who wishes to buy land I recommended him to you knowing that you
would like to sell some land on <placeName>Chocolate </placeName>for the purpose of having the
land improved; he wishes to buy several <placeName>tracts </placeName>as he intends to bring five
or six <persName>families </persName>out with him if he can get land to suit him He is an old 
acquaintance of <persName>Mr Borden</persName>s his traveling companion is by the name of
<persName>Roach </persName>who also wants to purchase some land I expect they are both 
<persName>Gentlemen </persName>at least they appear to be so I write no news because I presume
you get every thing through the <placeName>paper </placeName>of this place and otherwise much
sooner than I could enumerate it by letter. I want you to write me what I
shall do after I get through here whether I can do any thing below or not
I am here without a horse but will buy a good mule the first chance as I
know you want mules that is if I can get the money from <persName>Mr Fletcher</persName>.
<persName>Mr. Somervill</persName> has not got in from the wars yet I look for him daily.
<persName>Johnson is commander in chief of the <persName>forces at <placeName>Bexar</placeName></persName></persName>. Write me often I
have not recd, a letter from you since <persName>Uncle </persName>left <persName>Joel </persName>has gone home some
time ago I heard of his being at <placeName>Bastrop </placeName>on his way <placeName>home</placeName>, but he did
not come by this place. I shall soon be out of business and I would like
to get in some situation where I could improve myself and make 
something at the same time. <persName>Uncle </persName>spoke of taking me to the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> with him
but he finally concluded that he would not until he went on and saw where
I had better be put for a year or two. In fact I did not want to go as the
state of the <placeName>country </placeName>is such that I would have been uneasy about you all the
time consequently he came to the determination of not taking me on
with him</p>

<p>I think you would do well to get this mark to settle on <placeName>Chocolate </placeName>as he
will bring several <persName>families </persName>with him and I expect he is a man of some 
capital he saw so much land on the maps of <placeName>Galveston bay country</placeName> marked
with your name and <persName>Uncle</persName>s that he is induced to believe that you will sell
land cheap on account of having so much and I think the <placeName>chocolate country</placeName>
will suit him very well he will also purchase stock cattle<pb n="297"/></p>

<p><persName>Jones </persName>is selling goods fast and at a very high price</p>

<p>My love to all the <persName>family </persName>Your affectionate <persName>Son</persName></p>

<p><persName>M. Austin Bryan</persName></p>

<p>N B I have heard that I have a fine <persName>sister </persName>that I have never seen</p>

<p><persName>M A B</persName></p>

<p>P. S. I could remain here and perhaps make enough to buy my clothes
and pay my board and have some considerable time to study if you think
I had better remain and apply myself to the study of the Spanish write me
if not what shall I do?	Your <persName>Son</persName></p>

<p><persName>M A B</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
