<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5018">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to President of the Consultation, 11-04-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-06-11">06-11-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        President of the Consultation
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Head Quarters, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 235-236
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-11-04">11-04-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-06-11" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Repeating request for reinforcements. Success of present force great in face of handicaps. Need discipline, and experienced commander</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Head Quarters 1 1/2 miles above Bexar</placeName> <date when="1835-11-04">Nov 4. 1835</date></p>
<p>To the <persName>President of the Consultation of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName></p>

<p>heard by <persName>Mr Mosley Baker</persName> that the opinion is prevalent among the <persName>people
in <placeName>that part of the country</placeName></persName> that no more <persName>reinforcements </persName>are necessary and
that <placeName>Bexar </placeName>will be taken before <persName>reinforcements </persName>can reach here&#8212; On this
subject I have to assure you I am decidedly of opinion that without very
strong <persName>reenforcements </persName><placeName>Bexar </placeName>can not be taken nor with them without 
battering Cannon and from one to two hundred round shots for battering
down walls&#8212;</p>

<p>The <persName>enemy </persName>has sixteen Cannon mounted of various calibre up to 18
pounds&#8212;from 6 to 8 more that will be mounted in a few days&#8212; They
have plenty of provisions and about <persName>700 men</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>In the last few days more than <persName>150 men</persName> have left this <placeName>camp </placeName>to return
<placeName>home </placeName>for winter clothing and other purposes, so that the effective force is
only about <persName>450 men</persName> after deducting the sick&#8212; This <persName>force</persName>, it is known to
all, is but <persName>undisciplined militia</persName> and income respects of very discordant
materials&#8212; The <persName>officers </persName>from the<persName> Commander in chief </persName>down are 
inexperienced in military service&#8212; With such a <persName>force </persName><placeName>Bexar </placeName>can not be 
effectually invested&#8212; All that can be, has been done&#8212; The <persName>enemy </persName>have
been beaten and driven within their walls, with loss in every instance
where they have made sorties&#8212; At the <placeName>Concepcion </placeName>they were defeated by
<persName>Colo. Bowie</persName> and <persName>Captn. Fanning</persName>, with the loss of 1 Cannon and <persName>70 men</persName>
killed wounded and missing Our <persName>army </persName>has so far done wonders&#8212; It has
confined a <persName>superior force</persName> within strongly <placeName>fortified walls</placeName>&#8212; It has beaten
the <persName>enemy </persName>in every contest and not a day passes without skirmishing within
the reach of the <persName>enemy</persName>s grape shot.&#8212; It has struggled against all manner
of privations and sufferings, against want of discipline, dessertion, 
disention, and what is worse than all against what has been considered coldness
and tardiness in sending out <persName>reinforcements</persName>.&#8212;</p>

<p>I repeat <placeName>Bexar </placeName>can not be taken without <persName>1000 men</persName> at the very least and
the battering cannon of which I have spoken [The men now here?] can
I think be kept here till <persName>reenforcements </persName>arrive&#8212; Those who have left have
all promised to return. It is to be hoped they will have sufficient patriotism
to do so.</p>

<p>I have authorized and do authorize the <persName>Convention </persName>to mortgage all my
<placeName>estate </placeName>if necessary for the public service</p>

<p>I have dispatched the <persName>Adjutant Genl Warren D C Hall</persName> and my <persName>Aid de
camp Col°. P. W. Grayson</persName> for the purpose of bringing out 
<persName>reenforcements</persName>&#8212; Stopping the false and silly rumors that they are unnecessary and
bringing in the large Cannon with round shot and <persName>men </persName>to work them<pb n="236"/>
I have further to inform you that there is no medicine in <placeName>camp</placeName>&#8212;and so
far as I am informed, none on the way&#8212; There are no surgical 
instruments nor bandages, nor materials for making lint, nor anything else to
provide for the sick and wounded.&#8212; I hope they will be sent immediately
&#8212;as also that additional <persName>physicians </persName>will come out with the <persName>reenforcements</persName>.</p>

<p>I have the satisfaction to inclose you a Detailed report of the <persName>Capts. of
the engagements of the <date when="1835-10-28">28th</date></persName>-&#8212; The action so brilliant in its results proves
our great superiority to the <persName>enemy </persName>when they come out from behind their
walls&#8212; I last night received dispatches informing me of the gallant <persName>Army
of patriots</persName> who have volunteered and are volunteering from <placeName>Orleans</placeName>&#8212; I
have ordered the <persName>Capt [at] <placeName>Goliad</placeName></persName> to march here&#8212; This news is cheering
and has [raisd the spirits] of the <persName>army </persName>very much&#8212;</p>

<p>I have to request that no whysky be sent with supplies to the <placeName>camp</placeName>&#8212;
Ink Paper and wafers are much wanted</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin Comdt.in Chief</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>By order</p>
<p><persName>WDC Hall Adjt and Inspt&#8212;Genl</persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
