<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5331">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>George W Poe to Stephen F Austin, 12-10-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>George W Poe</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-29">08-29-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Columbia, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 473-474
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-12-10">12-10-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-29" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Suggesting issue of Treasury notes</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Columbia </placeName><date when="1836-12-10">December 10th- 1836</date></p>

<p>To the Honorable the <persName>Secretary of State</persName></p>

<p>Sir</p>

<p>In almost all cases a paralell may be drawn between transactions of a
<persName>Government </persName>and those of an Individual, and the same laws of justice and
equality govern both.</p>

<p>The writer is induced to believe that the cause of the low state of the
financial operations of this <placeName>Country </placeName>is a want of knowledge of the actual
state of the immediate available resources of the <placeName>Country</placeName>, and a false idea
of the magnitude of the debt</p>

<p>A tax bill is before the <persName>house of Representatives</persName> which calculating the
proceeds at a very moderate rate will produce $250,000 a revenue bill on
Imports, which will produce $150000 and the unpaid fees on <placeName>Land</placeName>
granted; located and unlocated, amounts to $100000 Making in all
$500000 which will be available in less than one Year and responsibilities
already audited amounts to $350000 and probably will by the <date when="1837-01-01">1st. of
January 1837</date>; amount to $450000 leaving $50000 balance in favour of the
<persName>Government</persName>.</p>

<p>Without making any remarks on the establishment of a <persName>Bank </persName>or the
probable success of our loan bill, or of the sale of Land scrip, or 
confiscated property and public lands; or the sale of certain leagues of <placeName>land</placeName>;
and a number of the other resources of the <persName>Government</persName>, we would simply
suggest the propriety of permitting the Treasurer to draft countersigned
by the Register for the different amounts in the form of Bank Notes, say
for Five, Ten, Twenty, Fifty, One Hundred and Five Hundred Dollars, and
these to be paid by the <persName>Treasurer </persName>on audited accounts, or the order of the
auditor</p>

<p>It is a general opinion that <placeName>Texas </placeName>is almost insolvent; that for a number
of years she cannot pay the public debt under which she labours at present</p>

<p>I have yet to learn that that debt exceeds two Millions, and the present
population can not only pay the interest of that annually but a large 
proportion of the principal, without relying at all on the great increase of<pb n="474"/>
population, we shall have in a few years and they also paying their 
proportion of the public debt and it is thought that a great portion of the 
expenses of the first and last campaign have been audited, and if so our debt
will prove much less than was really imagined</p>

<p>A fair, clear, and lucid expose of our affairs our debts and our resources
would do more in establishing our Credit on a firm basis than any other
plan whatever; and by proving our abilities to pay punctually the interest
of a loan if not the principal, we shall be enabled to borow as much as we
want and on moderate terms</p>

<p>All which is respectfully submitted</p>

<p><persName>Geo. W. Poe Actg Pay Master General</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
