<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5165">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to David G Burnett, 04-03-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-01">08-01-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        David G Burnett [?]
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 341-342
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-04-03">04-03-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-01" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Statements of embarrassment of commissioners by failure of the Texan government to correspond with them
</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New York</placeName> <date when="1836-04-03">April 3. 1836</date>&#8212;</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>The <persName>commissioners </persName>appointed by the <persName>Provisional Govt of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> in 
<date n="11-xx-1836">November </date>and <date n="12-xx-1836">December </date>last have discharged the duties assigned to them as
fully as their powers and the peculiar circumstances in which they have
been placed would permit</p>

<p>It is with regret we are compelled to say that the state of things at home,
has embarrassed the labors of the <persName>Govt. agents</persName> in this <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>The undersigned, have not receaved one word from the <persName>Govt </persName>since the
meeting of the convention in <date n="03-xx-1836">March</date>, and the <persName>public </persName>have been informed
through the <placeName>newspapers </placeName>that we have been superceded that we have no
powers as <persName>agents </persName>etc. You will at once perceive the bad effect which such
things have on the public mind, for, taken in common with many 
exaggrated accounts of internal dessentions etc., they have had a tendency to
weaken public confidence and to paralise our efforts&#8212;</p>

<p>In our communications from <placeName>New Orleans</placeName> and <placeName>Nashville </placeName>and <placeName>Louisville</placeName>
and <placeName>Washington City</placeName>, we informed the <persName>Govt</persName>. of our proceedings, and that
it was all important for some one to be furnished <hi rend="italic">officially </hi>with the 
declaration of independence and with full instructions&#8212; For the want of these
documents we could do no more in <placeName>Washington </placeName>than to <hi rend="italic">prepare </hi>opinions
to <hi rend="italic">sustain </hi>the declaration of independence made by <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; We feel every
confidence that [as] soon as a <persName>diplomatic agent</persName>, properly authorized 
appears at <placeName>W. [Washington] </placeName>all will be done, that the nature of the subject
will permit.</p>

<p>A loan is in progress in this <placeName>city</placeName>, but we are convinced no loan will 
succeed to a large amount, except on the basis of a positive sale of <placeName>land </placeName>at a<pb n="342"/>
price not exceeding half a dollar an acre&#8212; but only 10 per cent is to be
advanced, the balance is not to be paid untill the <persName>govt </persName>approves of the
transaction, and give to the <persName>lenders </persName>the option of taking land at twenty
five cents pr. acre&#8212; Nothing can be done on this subject without full
powers to sell <placeName>land </placeName>at the best price that can be obtained for the prices of
land will vary according to the news from <placeName>Texas </placeName>and the state of the <placeName>money
markets</placeName> here</p>

<p>We refer you to the proceedings of the meeting in this <placeName>city</placeName>, on the <date when="1836-04-26">26th
</date>and to the <placeName>pamphlet </placeName>published here on the subject, for information as to
public feeling in favor of <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; it is warmly enlisted and is becoming
more so every day&#8212;</p>

<p>We shall attend a public meeting in <placeName>Phila</placeName>- on the <date when="1836-05-02">2d next month</date>, and
then proceed homeward, for, altho we are positively orderd by the 
instructions of<persName> Gov. Smith</persName> <hi rend="italic">not </hi>to do so untill directed by that <persName>Govt </persName>we are 
compelled to believe that an order for our recall has been issued and detained
by miscarriage.</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
