<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5179">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>William Austin to Stephen F Austin, 05-18-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>William Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-08">08-08-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Lowell, Massachusetts</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 353-355
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-05-18">05-18-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-08" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Suggests diversion on west coast of Mexico. Asks terms for well manned privateer. People of New England will support Texas when they understand that it is struggling for republican government and religious toleration</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Lowell, Mass</placeName>, <date when="1836-05-18">May 18th 1836</date></p>

<p>Dear Sir,</p>

<p>An early <persName>acquaintance </persName>with the <placeName>West Coast of Mexico</placeName> and various 
excursions <placeName>from the Pacific to the interior</placeName>, having visited the <placeName>City of Mexico</placeName> in
<date n="xx-xx-1822">1822</date>, and Made Some observations as to the assailible points on that <placeName>Sea
Board</placeName>, and the <placeName>Sections of Country</placeName> through which I extended my 
excursions, has since the Texian War commenced, been brought to my 
recollection, and aroused by the horrible cruelties perpetrated by the <persName>forces of
Santa Anna</persName> I have reviewed the scenes of by gon days, in that Country and
have formed an opinion, that a diversion highly, favorable to the Cause of
<placeName>Texas </placeName>might be made by a small <persName>Naval force</persName> employed on the <placeName>West Coast
of Mexico</placeName>. Where a single ship of 20 guns under a judicious commander
might create consternation and dismay without infringing the Laws of
maritime War fare or encroaching the limits prescribed to it by the Laws
of Nations. Much would depend however on the duration of the contest
in as much as it would require Six to Eight months to give effect to Such
an enterprise and render it subservient. I know not what may be the
views of the <persName>Texian Government</persName>, in regard to Naval operations, but cannot
entertain a doubt that could it avail itself of the Services of a Small <persName>force</persName>
to be there employed that highly favorable results would follow.</p>

<p>In <placeName>this section of the U.S</placeName>. the origin and progress of the Texian 
revolution ar not well understood, and this people as you doubtless may be
aware, are not so easily excited to action, as those of More Sunny regions
but when they shall be better informed, and feel assured, that half the 
barbarities have been exercised by the <persName>Mexican forces</persName>, that have been 
announced in <placeName>newspapers </placeName>of the day, When they shall know that <placeName>Texas</placeName><pb n="354"/>
contended for her rights as an <placeName>Independent State of the Mexican 
Confederacy</placeName>, rights guaranteed by the Constitution of <date n="xx-xx-1824">1824</date>, that failing to secure
those rights and seeing a consolidated military despotism pervading the
country, with <persName>Catholic </persName>intolerance of <hi rend="italic">religious Worship</hi>, She availed herself
of the sacred prerogative of <persName>freemen </persName>and declared herself independent and
assumed the consequences, they will perceive that there is a striking affinity
in the attitude of <placeName>Texas </placeName>and the <placeName>American Colonies</placeName> at the Commencement
of the War of Independence, and yeald their sympathy their services
afloat or in the field, or their wealth in support of so righteous a cause
Constrained by circumstances which preclude at present the devotion of
my services, in her cause, I nevertheless would break the ties that may be
severed without dishonor, and offer myself a sacrifice for such a struggle,
if it shall prove necessary to the attainment of the independence or the
union of <placeName>Texas </placeName>with the <placeName>American Union</placeName>, feeble as those services Might be,
tho' not entirely useless. So far as some experience in Maratime war is
concerned, yet united with thousands of kindred spirits the effect of 
combination would ensure success. In this way I presume it would be 
practicable to procure officers and man a Ship or vessels suited to the enterprise
before mentioned, there would be some difficulty in providing an 
armament, or rather in Embarking it in the vessels in which to employ it, but
not insurmountable diffculties. Would the <persName>commander </persName>of such a force if
offered as a loan to <placeName>Texas</placeName>, with the <persName>officers </persName>he might recommend be 
commissioned so as to give them suitable rank in the Naval Review? their
emoluments to depend on their captures, and the usual bounty in Land but
to be placed under such restraint as to avert the consequences of any 
contravention of the Laws of Nations?&#8212; I feel that; I may be subject to the
imputation of obtruding, myself on your attention but I am anxious that
the history of the events in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, should be better understood in the <placeName>New
England States</placeName>, and know that when the subject of <hi rend="italic">religious liberty</hi>, and
<hi rend="italic">rational freedom</hi> are agitated and contended for and by a people claiming
consanguinity and evincing the most laudable heroism, the <persName>citizens of this
<placeName>Wide spread republiccan Empire</placeName></persName>, will fly to the rescue. It is obvious that
entire secrecy would be indispensible to the success of the enterprise under
consideration. I therefore need not enforce it. When in the <placeName>City of
Mexico</placeName> in <date n="xx-xx-1822">1822</date>, I had the pleasure of an acquaintance with <persName>General Long</persName>
and the <persName>officers of his staff</persName>. Among the latter was <persName>Captain Austin</persName> of the
<persName>infantry</persName>, Whose subsequent history it would afford me pleasure to learn
and especially if successful&#8212; The unfortunate <persName>Genl. Long</persName>; Was 
assassinated at that time and being among those who assisted at his interment, and
having since heard that his <persName>Widow </persName>received from the <persName>Mexican government</persName>
a <placeName>Grant of Land</placeName> in <placeName>Texas</placeName>, I would venture to enquire whether her fate is
Apparently <persName>John Austin</persName>, who died of cholera in <placeName>Texas </placeName>in <date n="xx-xx-1833">1833</date>.<pb n="355"/>
known to You&#8212; I have in my possession a relick of her heroic <persName>husband</persName>
which it would give me pleasure to transmit to her&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>William Austin</persName></p>

<p>P.S. Please address at this place</p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
