<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5160">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>M R Wiggington  to Colonel Lewis, 04-22-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>M R Wiggington </persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-01">08-01-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Colonel Lewis
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Louisville, Missouri</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Lexington, Kentucky</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 337-338
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-04-22">04-22-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-01" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Volunteers for Texas</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Louisville </placeName><date when="1836-04-22">Apl 22nd 1836</date></p>

<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p>It was with great regret that I found myself compelled to leave 
<placeName>Lexington </placeName>on <date when="1836-04-21">yesterday-morning</date>, without seeing You, it being late when I awoke,
the railroad car about to start, and my business at home urgently pressing,
all which will I hope amount to a sufficient apology.</p>

<p>I got here in the stage <date when="1836-04-22">this morning </date>after riding the whole night and as
you May well suppose am in no very felicitous condition for writing. Yet
fearing that unless I do so now you will have no opportunity of receiving
a letter from me, before you leave <placeName>Kentucky</placeName>, I hasten to give you such 
information as I possess with regard to <placeName>Texas </placeName>and her affairs. The rumor
that <persName>Col Fannin</persName> has fought his way to <persName>Gen Houstons army</persName>, seems to gain
credence, the statement that <persName>Houston Quitman</persName> and <persName>Young Crockett</persName> have
taken on a <persName>large force</persName> is not doubted, and that <persName>volunteers </persName>are pouring into
the relief of the <placeName>Country </placeName>from <placeName>every quarter of the western and southern&#8212;
States</placeName> is uncontradicted. My <persName>Brother </persName>who we were informed only started
with <persName>thirty Men</persName>, I learn had certainly forty, and probably upwards of
fifty, for it was found after he got on the Boat which carried him, that there
were many going who had given no previous information of their 
intentions to do so, desiring for reasons only known to themselves, to keep their
intentions secret, until that moment, and the boat getting off before he
could make a Count, no one learned the exact number he carried with him,
and even after he had gone, some came in from the <placeName>Country </placeName>to go.</p>

<p><date when="1836-04-24">24th </date>you will perceive that I was unable to finish this letter on the day
I commenced it, which was owing to professional engagements.</p>

<p>I am pleased to tell you, that on the <date when="1836-04-22">day before yesterday</date> <persName>Mr Stanberry</persName>
arrived here with upward of <persName>forty volunteers from <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName></persName>, and has
been joined by enough here, who were unable to get off with my <persName>Brother</persName>,
to Make out about fifty, as he informs me. I also learned from him that
<persName>two other companies from <placeName>Wheeling </placeName>and <placeName>Pittsburgh</placeName></persName> would shortly be on,
and that a <persName>Mr Ludlow of <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName></persName> was preparing to raise a <persName>Regiment</persName>,
which he <persName>Mr Stanberry</persName> Seemed to think would be an easy task. So we see
that the work goes bravely on,&#8212;<persName>Col Harrison</persName> has heard nothing from <persName>Gen.
Chambers</persName> as yet, but I hope soon will hear, he informs me he can easily
obtain the necessary quota of Men, if he can only get Money to buy horses
etc, write to the <persName>Gen </persName>to come on immediately, for I assure you that 
<persName>Harrison </persName>project is worth his most vigilent attention, if the <persName>Battalion </persName>is raised
I venture to predict, that it will be one of the most efficient and useful in
the service.</p>

<p>I very much wish you could enlist my friend <persName>Gist </persName>in the cause. I mean
not as a <persName>private</persName>, but as an <persName>officer of Rank</persName>, for in him you would take to<pb n="338"/>
your <placeName>country</placeName>, an intelligent and amiable Gentleman, a brave man, and
useful Citizen, and were he to join you, he has the means and I am very
confident would use them with a liberal hand, to fit out a respectable force,
both as it regards numbers and usefulness Let me hear from you, 
immediately, and as often as you may have leisure to write.</p>

<p>If you find that a <persName>Company </persName>or two can be raised in the <placeName>neighborhood of
Lexington</placeName>, I would advise you, if I might advise at all, to connect them
with <persName>Harrison</persName>s command. So as to make out one effective <persName>battallion </persName>ready
for the <placeName>field </placeName>as soon as possible which you can no doubt accomplish by
urging upon those who may take the lead in getting them up, the propriety
of going as soon, and in as great force as possible,</p>

<p><persName>Mortimer R. Wiggington</persName></p>

<p><persName>Col. Lewis</persName></p>

<p>P. S. Please bear in mind that my <persName>brother </persName><persName>Alfred M. Wiggington</persName>
will be in <placeName>Texas </placeName>when you return and that you cannot do me greater 
service, that [than] by obtaining him some situation in which he can be useful
the one you mentioned will be most suitable. <persName>M. R. W</persName>.</p>

<p><persName>Col&#8212;Lewis</persName> <placeName>Lexington Ky</placeName></p>

<p>If <persName>Col L.</persName> has left <persName>Mr Ficklin</persName> is desired to forward this to him.
<persName>M. R. W.</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
