<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5206">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>James Hamilton to Stephen F Austin, 06-28-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>James Hamilton</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-12">08-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Charleston, South Carolian</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Velasco, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 373-374
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-06-28">06-28-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Great interest of the South in cause of Texas. Will urge recognition on Forsyth and Van Buren</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Charleston </placeName><date when="1836-06-28">June 28th 1836</date></p>

<p>Dear Sir&#8212;</p>

<p>I had the honor to receive some short time since, your most kind and
friendly favor of the <date when="1836-05-22">22d May</date> from <placeName>Washington</placeName>, which I should more early
have answered if I had not expected, in compliance with your advices, to
have seen <persName>Dr Archer</persName> here on his way to <placeName>Louisiana </placeName>and by whom I had
proposed writing you.&#8212;</p>

<p>The profound interest which <hi rend="italic">we </hi>of the <placeName>South </placeName>feel in the success of your
cause has made your favor exceedingly acceptable to me.&#8212; I consider your
independence as placed beyond all question and I trust that the 
establishment of social order and an effective system of justice will assure to you
the blessings of liberty and self government&#8212;</p>

<p>I deeply regretted, when I first heard of the invasion of <persName>Santa Ana</persName> that
my domestic engagements, resulting from a large <persName>family</persName>, and multiplied
occupations of business should have prevented my going, at the head of a
<persName>Brigade of South Carolinians</persName> (who would have been ready I am sure to
have followed me) to the rescue, but you have all done more for 
yourselves than your friends have done for you.&#8212;<persName>Gen. Houston</persName> has left nothing<pb n="374"/>
for any one now to do, as his <persName>reapers </persName>literally went "down to the harvest
of death" and have left no gleanings behind them.&#8212; You have won the
<placeName>country </placeName>among yourselves, and are entitled to it.&#8212;</p>

<p>In allusion to this subject permit me to advert to the report which has 
appeared in the <placeName>New York papers</placeName> and which was so well calculated to do
your cause prejudice, that I at once put the seal of my own disavowal to
it&#8212;That the <persName>Commissioners of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> were engaged in <hi rend="italic">"a Plot"</hi> to 
supersede <persName>Gen: Houston</persName> by placing <hi rend="italic">me </hi>at the head of the <persName>Texian army</persName>&#8212;As I
never received the slightest intimation either from yourself or any one of
the <persName>Commissioners </persName>to this effect, I am sure you are all entitled both <hi rend="italic">pri-
vately</hi> as well as publicly to the benefit of my contradiction.&#8212; If 
circumstances even permitted me to join your cause, I would certainly not have
been guilty of the gross arrogance and absurd folly of making my 
appearance in a new country in the shape of a Competitor to a successful General
who was as well entitled to his command as to his laurels.&#8212;</p>

<p>I hope to be able to serve you without even going to your <placeName>country </placeName>and
being any man's rival.&#8212; By sustaining your cause on all public occasions
and by endeavoring to bring the force of public opinion, within the humble
sphere of my influence, to bear beneficially, first on your emancipation
from <persName>Mexican </persName>Domination, and next in favor of your Independence as a
free, sovereign and <placeName>independent Republic</placeName> or as a member of our 
<placeName>Confederacy</placeName>, as you, among yourselves, may deem most compatible with your
own interests&#8212;</p>

<p>I shall leave this on <date when="1836-07-01">Friday, the 1st</date> for <placeName>Washington </placeName>where I shall see
both <persName>Mr. Forsyth</persName> and <persName>Mr. Van Buren</persName> and do your <placeName>Country </placeName>all the good
I can, by urging <hi rend="italic">immediate </hi>recognition.&#8212; Nor shall my exertions be
wanting in <placeName>New York</placeName> among your <persName>friends </persName>to aid your cause, in every 
possible manner in which it can be benefitted, as your <persName>friends </persName>there happen to
be some of the best of <hi rend="italic">My own</hi>.&#8212;</p>

<p>I shall be exceedingly happy to hear from you at all times, and at no
moment will I be more gratified than when I can learn of the prosperity
and entire emancipation of your noble and <placeName>highly promising region</placeName>.&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>J. Hamilton</persName>&#8212;</p>


<p><persName>Gen. S. F. Austin&#8212; Commissioner of Texas</persName>.&#8212;</p>

<p>P. S. Be pleased to direct to <placeName>Charleston South Carolina</placeName> to which I
shall return in about three weeks.&#8212;</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Genl. S F Austin</persName>&#8212;<placeName>Velasco Texas</placeName></p>

<p>Recd Forwarded by your Obt Servt.</p>

<p><placeName>New Orleans</placeName> <date when="1836-07-10">July 10.</date>	<persName>Wm. Bryan</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
