<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5189">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>A J Yates to Stephen F Austin, 06-03-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>A J Yates</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-12">08-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Schenedtady, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 365-366
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-06-03">06-03-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Failure to hold meeting at Troy. War stores.</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>My Dear <persName>General</persName>,</p>

<p>I am here still with my <persName>family</persName>, and much engaged in settling my old
private affairs, which I once mentioned to you. I have had a proposition
from the <persName>persons who have had my property in charge</persName>, and they have 
offered me $15,000 to release them, and I have charged $35,000, and a 
settlement of $30,000 on my <persName>wife</persName>. They have till <date when="1836-06-05">day after tomorrow</date> to accept.
My estate is worth $120,000, by their own admissions, and I shall secure
some $80,000, if I go into a <persName>Chancery </persName>suit, but as that will keep me out of
it for some two or three years and perhaps more, I am determined to close
at once by a sacrifice, provided I can do so on the terms I have offered. If
they accept, it is my intention to charter a vessel from <placeName>New York</placeName> and sail
<date n="07-xx-1836">next month</date> for <placeName>Texas</placeName>. I want much to know the prospects of a 
continuance of the war, and I can bring out two or <persName>three hundred volunteers</persName>. I
have also written to <persName>Colt of <placeName>Patterson</placeName></persName> to inquire the prices of his ten
charge rifles, carbines and pistols, and I want to bring out what will be
most useful to the <placeName>country</placeName>, and dispose of it for <placeName>lands</placeName>.</p>

<p>I have not been able to get up a meeting in <placeName>Troy </placeName>at all. I went there
and saw the <persName>Mayor </persName>and <persName>Recorder </persName>and several of the <persName>leading men of the
<placeName>City</placeName></persName>, and I received a letter from the <persName>Mayor </persName>a few days since stating that
there appeared so much apathy on the subject, that he was fearful that the
attempt would fail. I have not been able to do any thing more in <placeName>Albany</placeName>
than get a <placeName>Memorial </placeName>circulated, which has received a great many signatures,
and will go to <placeName>Washington</placeName>. I do not think I can do any thing of 
importance in the <placeName>West </placeName>in the way of collecting funds&#8212;in fact the scarcity of
money is so great here that, I find the <persName>people </persName>very unwilling to give.
I wish you would inform me if cannon are needed for the fortification
now in progress&#8212; If horses could be promised<persName> 100 men</persName>, provided I could
bring them out with the equipments and arms&#8212; I am inclined to think that
<persName>100 cavalry</persName> with Colts carbines, with spring bayonets, and pistols, will
be a very powerful and efficienct force. Colts carbins and pistols discharge
30 rounds in the same time that it takes to load 3 times. If I get cannon too,.
I would have them with the percussion locks, which we saw at <placeName>Arculanius
N. Y. State Arsenal</placeName>.</p>

<p>If you can learn anything of <persName>Wm Austin</persName>, I beg you will also let me know
for the satisfaction of his <persName>friends </persName>here. I am also very anxious to receive a<pb n="366"/>
copy of the Constitution, and some of the important laws of the <persName>New Govt</persName>,
and please address me at <placeName>New York</placeName>, and advise me of your movements.</p>

<p><persName>A. J. Yates</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
