<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5221">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Samuel Swartwout to Stephen F Austin, 07-09-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Samuel Swartwout</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-13">08-13-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">New York, New York</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 390-391
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-07-09">07-09-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Hopes Austin will prevent release of Santa Anna. Credit of Texas low and loan can only be made on basis of land</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>New York</placeName> <date when="1836-07-09">9th. July 1836</date></p>

<p>My Dear <persName>Friend</persName></p>

<p>Your letter of the <date when="1836-06-16">16th. of June</date> was received the <date when="1836-07-09">day before yesterday.</date></p>

<p>I am most happy to hear from you and to know that you are well and thus<pb n="391"/>
far on your way to the <placeName>seat of Govt</placeName>. I pray to God that your council may
be regarded, for I believe it will be different from the recent disposition
manifested by the <persName>cabinet </persName>and <persName>President</persName>, in relation to <persName>Santa Anna</persName>. I have
never doubted about your final success, until I heard that the <persName>Texian 
cabinet</persName> had resolved to let that <persName>Brute </persName>escape, Then I must confess I gave up
all hope. For, depend upon it, had that trick succeeded,<hi rend="italic"> all sympathy for
<placeName>Texas</placeName></hi> would have been lost, <placeName>in the states</placeName>&#8212; You never could again have
excited us to aid or avenge your cause, As it is, I fear a stain has been
put upon your Escutcheon, that time alone will obliterate. What, in the
name of God could have induced your people to think of such a thing?
After such a victory as that of the <date when="1836-04-21">21st of April</date>, with the <persName>Brute </persName>in your
power and his forces scattered to the winds, the world, in amazement would
have proclaimed the act <hi rend="italic">treachery</hi>, But you are among them again, hold
to the d________rascal. He cannot hurt you where he is, but let him go and you
will not only feel his power, but the want of friends and money too. No
inducements of gain nor entreaties for help could again impose upon the
<persName>people of this <placeName>country</placeName></persName>&#8212;Therefore let him perish.</p>

<p>Write to me from the <placeName>seat of Govt</placeName>. Let me know every thing. And let
me advise you to <hi rend="italic">fortify </hi>and <hi rend="italic">provision </hi>your <placeName>country</placeName>, for an other 
campaign. Rebuild the <placeName>Alamo</placeName>, make strong your <placeName>coast </placeName>and get plenty of pork
and beans, and powder and shot, for an other fight, for, altho I do not
much believe the <persName>Mexicans </persName>will trouble you again, yet for valor's sake, be
prepared. Your own strength and conduct at <placeName>home </placeName>will give confidence to
your <persName>friends </persName>here and elsewhere.</p>

<p>Nothing can be done with the proposed loan. Nothing but <placeName>Lands </placeName>will
satisfy the <persName>lenders</persName>, and that at a low rate. I will not advise your 
<persName>Government</persName>, but I will repeat to you what I said to you and <persName>Wharton </persName>here, let
your <placeName>Lands </placeName>pay the expences of the war, if you sell them for only 5 cents
an acre. You must yet have large sums and that promptly and nothing else
will bring them&#8212; <persName>Childress </persName>left this <placeName>City </placeName>just <date when="1836-07-02">a week ago</date> I did not see
him, he left his card for me, but I did not see him to converse with him&#8212;
Mess <persName>Grayson </persName>and <persName>Collingsworth </persName>have not yet arived. I hear that they are
hourly expected in <placeName>Washington</placeName>. They should have been there ere this, as
the <persName>President </persName>leaves there <date when="1836-07-10">tomorrow </date>for the <placeName>hermitage</placeName>, Your 
<persName>commissioners </persName>are too tardy in their movements. It will be much to be regretted,
if they arrived after the <persName>President </persName>departs.</p>

<p>Your <persName>friends </persName>here etc all well, but much distressed, as well as disgusted,
with the conduct of those who would have permitted <persName>Santa An[na]</persName> to
escape. It has well nigh ruined the cause here.</p>

<p>Believe me my dear friend most sincerely yours.</p>

<p><persName>Saml. Swartwout</persName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin Esqr.</persName></p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
