<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5289">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 10-25-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-28">08-28-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Columbia, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Peach Point, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 438-439
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-10-25">10-25-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-28" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Santa Anna's visit to Washington. Expects annexation. Speculations of McKinney and Williams</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p>Dr. <persName>Brother</persName></p>

<p>I am anxious to hear how you are. the last accounts you were getting
better I shall be at <placeName>Brazoria </placeName>at the <placeName>Ball </placeName>and from there go down&#8212; I am
gaining strength so slowly that it is difficult to perseive much improvement
in my strength&#8212;</p>

<p>I think that matters will go on well and smoothly in both the <persName>Executive
and Legislative departments</persName>&#8212; There evidently is a disposition to 
harmonise in all persons.</p>

<p>I have been solicited to go into the new <persName>cabinet</persName> as <persName>Secretary of State</persName>&#8212;
or to go to the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> as <persName>minister</persName>&#8212; I have declined&#8212; I have all the land
office business to close&#8212; Who can I trust it with in my absence? If <persName>S. M.
Williams</persName> failed me while I was in <placeName>prison in the city of Mexico</placeName>, who can I
hope will not fail me?</p>

<p>Besides all this my health is gone, and I must have rest to nurse my 
constitution and try and restore my strength&#8212; The <placeName>land office</placeName> will be as
much as I can attend to in the present state of my health.</p>

<p>I think I shall effect a sale of some tracts of land, tho, at a great 
sacrifice; which will supply me with something to live on, for the present untill
I raise means to settle a <placeName>farm</placeName>.</p>

<p>I send you by <persName>Simon </persName>two slips of Roses which I brought <date when="1836-10-24">yesterday </date>from
<placeName><persName>Dr Phelps</persName>' place</placeName>, The largest slip is monthly, white, exceedingly 
fragrant, as much so as damask rose&#8212;it forms a <hi rend="italic">tree</hi>&#8212;it is very rare in the
<placeName>U. S.</placeName> and was procured from abroad by a <persName>botanist in <placeName>N. Orleans </placeName></persName>who gave
a slip to <persName>Phelps</persName>&#8212;</p>

<p>The other slip blooms <hi rend="italic">daily </hi>the year round is red and fragrant&#8212;</p>

<p>Do take care of them&#8212;water them every night untill they take root
I also send you black walnuts <hi rend="italic">to plant</hi> They are from a tree that <persName>Bell</persName>
planted in his yard after he settled where he now is&#8212; They ought to be
planted in <date n="01-xx-1837">January </date>Do not neglect them, nor let the <persName>children </persName>eat them&#8212;
If I am here in the <date n="Winter-1836">winter </date>I will go to <placeName><persName>Mrs Allsbury</persName>s</placeName> and get some slips and
roots for you</p>

<p>Have you saved any more of the crow foot Grass seed&#8212; A small patch
in <placeName><persName>Bell</persName>s yard</placeName> has supported about a dozen Horses and kept them fat&#8212; He<pb n="439"/>
says he never has seen any grass half so valuable for a <placeName>pasture</placeName>&#8212; Do not
neglect this&#8212;set <persName>Austin </persName>and <persName>Joel </persName>or the <persName>children </persName>to gathering the seed</p>

<p><persName>Gen Jackson</persName> has answered <persName>Santanna</persName>'s letter of <date when="1836-07-04">4 July</date> in a very friendly
manner&#8212;he has made it the basis of an offer of mediation with <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and
open.d a correspondence with the <persName>Mexican Minister at Washington</persName> Those
who cursed and were for hanging me for going to see <persName>Santana</persName> at all, or
getting him to write to <persName>Jackson</persName>, now say that I was right,&#8212;that measure
<hi rend="italic">then </hi>so bad, is now looked to as one of the best modes of bringing about a
peace <persName>Gen. Houston</persName>'s ideas as to <persName>santana </persName>agree very much with mine.</p>

<p>I have <hi rend="italic">full confidence</hi> that all will go right&#8212;and that by <date n="03-xx-1837">next March</date> we
shall belong to the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> I wish to take the trip to Washington&#8212;but who
can I trust to close the land business? If <persName>Williams </persName>and <persName>McKinney </persName>failed
me in my absence and forgeting their duty to their country became wild
and gambling <persName>land jobbers</persName>&#8212;who can I trust? I know of no one but <persName>Gail
Borden</persName> He <hi rend="italic">can be trusted</hi>, for he is conscienciously an honest man, but
if he refused to chime in with the views of <persName>speculators </persName>they would seek
some way to ruin him&#8212; My confidence in mankind is so destroyed by
<persName>W.</persName> and <persName>McK.</persName> in whom I had unbounded confidence that I am fast falling
or have fallen into the opposite extreme to the principle that always 
governed me&#8212; I once believed all men honest untill the reverse appeared&#8212;
I now think all the reverse untill I see them tryed&#8212; Love to <persName>Emily</persName>
and all</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin</persName></p>

<p><placeName>Columbia </placeName><date when="1836-10-25">July [October] 25. 1836</date>&#8212;</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr James F. Perry</persName> <placeName>Peach point</placeName> <persName>Simon</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
