<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5228">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>W P Hill to Stephen F Austin, 07-15-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>W P Hill</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>Initial TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="BWB">
                <resp>Programmatic and Manual TEI P5 Compliance</resp>
                <persName>Ben W. Brumfield</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-13">08-13-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Stephen F Austin
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Hartford, Connecticut</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 396-397
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-07-15">07-15-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2013-07-15" who="#BWB">Programmatic restructuring and manual clean-up to comply with TEI P5 2.3.0</change>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Explaining cancellation of his authority to negotiate a half million dollar loan to Texas</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Hartford, [Conn.]</placeName> <date when="1836-07-15">15th July, 1836</date></p>

<p><persName>Gen. Stephen F. Austin</persName>,</p>

<p>Sir,</p>

<p>On or about the <date when="1836-06-20">20th ultimo</date>, I deposited at the <placeName>Texian Agency in New
Orleans</placeName>, a letter directed to your address, to be forwarded to you, with
other despatches on board the "Union," then at anchor in the <placeName>Mississippi
River</placeName>. If you have received that letter, you are already informed that I
was instructed by a <persName>company of Merchants in<placeName> N. York</placeName></persName>, to proceed to <placeName>Texas</placeName>,
to negotiate with the <persName>Texian Cabinet</persName>, a loan of half a million dollars and
that specific instructions would be sent to me at <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName>, to govern my
movements in the negotiation. The day after writing you the said letter,
I received from <placeName>N. York</placeName>, not the "specific instruction" I expected, but a<pb n="397"/>
peremptory <hi rend="italic">revocation </hi>of my agency. This communication, after my letter
of the <date when="1836-06-20">20th</date> to you placed me in an unpleasant dilemma, from which I 
resolved to extricate myself, by returning promptly to <placeName>N. York</placeName>, and 
demanding an Explanation, to furnish grounds for my own justification, as well as
to engage my influence in removing any unfavorable impressions, which
might have been made on the minds of my <persName>Employers</persName>, as to the course of
the <persName>Texian </persName>struggle for independence. I arrived in <placeName>N. York</placeName>, the <date when="1836-07-11">11th inst</date>.
and sought and obtained a conference immediately, with my <persName>Employers</persName>
and received in substance, the following reasons as an apology for their
course of proceeding- Shortly after my departure from <placeName>N. York</placeName> for <placeName>Texas</placeName>
the armistice between the <persName>Texian government</persName> and <persName>Santa Anna</persName>, was received,
and gave them great dissatisfaction; they being of opinion, (the <persName>Wall Street
Money changers</persName>, are quite self-opinionated) that inasmuch as the <persName>Mexican
Army</persName>, was completely in the power of the <persName>Texians</persName>, it should have been 
captured and annihilated. It began to be rumored, about that time, also, that
the <persName>Cabinet of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>, was preparing to release <persName>Santa Anna</persName>, and they did
not wish to submit to the <persName>Texian Government</persName>, any propositions respecting
a loan, until this rumor should be contradicted. I used such arguments
and explanations in vindication of the course of the <persName>Cabinet</persName>, as occurred to>
my mind; but the recent confirmation of <persName>Santa Anna</persName>'s intended release and
a card published in the "Commercial Bulletin" of the <date when="1836-06-16">16th ultimo</date>, 
dispensing with the farther aid of <persName>Volunteers from the <placeName>United States</placeName></persName>, fixed their
determination to suspend, if not Entirely relinquish their intentions as above
Explained. If <placeName>Texas </placeName>is wanting funds, I regret the loss of this loan. It
would have been offered to her, not in the spirit of speculation, but from a
pure and disinterested desire, to assist her in her glorious struggle. This
much I have deemed it my duty to write, in defence of my own conduct-
The attempted release of <persName>Santa Anna</persName>, has provoked a general and loud
burst of indignant feeling throughout the <placeName>U. States</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">If he is released,</hi>
<placeName>Texas </placeName>will be compelled to fight her own battles unaided; the last spark of
sympathy in her behalf, will be effectually extinguished.</p>

<p><persName>W. P. Hill</persName></p>

<p><persName>Genl. Stephen F. Austin.</persName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
