<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5091">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin to James F Perry, 12-25-1835</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-13">07-13-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        James F Perry
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Quintana, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Peach Point, Texas</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 294-295
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1835-12-25">12-25-1835</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-13" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Business instructions. Has confidence in S. M. Williams</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Quintana </placeName><date when="1835-12-25">Decr. 25. 1835</date></p>

<p><persName>Mr James F. Perry</persName></p>

<p>I have had a conversation, with <persName>McKinny </persName>about laying off a <placeName>town </placeName>at this
place&#8212; There are a number of applicants for <placeName>lots</placeName>&#8212;</p>

<p>I never realized any thing out of the <placeName>lots at Brazoria</placeName> and I do not wish
that the same result should take place as to this place&#8212;others can make
money in this way, and I see no just cause why I should not</p>

<p>After <persName>Williams </persName>returns, you and <persName>McKinny </persName>and he can consult on the
subject, and lay out the <placeName>lots </placeName>here, have a handsome <placeName>map </placeName>made of them, and
sell them to the best advantage without waiting for my return</p>

<p>I wish to retain some lots in a good situation for <placeName>business</placeName>, and some for
<placeName>building residences</placeName>&#8212;the next <placeName>block below McKinny and Williams's ware
house</placeName> are the best for the first object you will retain them for me and
some high back lots for the second You will also want a place to build a
<placeName>retreat </placeName>in the sickly season.</p>

<p>You can however arrange this matter amongst you, as may be deemed
best for my interest and future convenience for I trust the matter to you as
persons who will not neglect what is due to an absent friend</p>

<p><persName>McKinny </persName>and <persName>Williams </persName>are to have the <placeName>lots </placeName>where their <placeName>ware house</placeName> is. I
will settle this matter with them when I return You will of course lay out
no <placeName>lots </placeName>nor make any disposition of the <placeName>land above the creek</placeName>, (<placeName>west union</placeName>)
what is below will be sufficient for the present&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>Williams </persName>is a good hand at arranging speculations of this kind to the
best advantage&#8212; Great pains have been taken by my <persName>enemies </persName>and <persName>Williams</persName>
to sow suspicion in my mind against him&#8212;all this is intrigue of the basest
kind&#8212;pay no attention to such stuff&#8212;I have told you the same verbally<pb n="295"/>
and now repeat it in writing, and that my confidence in him is in no way
affected by such efforts&#8212;I have written to him to transfer the <placeName>eleven league
tract</placeName> of mine which is in his name to you or to me, or give some 
memorandum how that tract stands&#8212;it was selected by me on the <placeName>east side of 
colorado at the foot of the Mountains</placeName>, surveyed by <persName>Sam. P Browne</persName> All these
matters should be settled or reduced to writing so as to be understood in
case of death&#8212;My object now is to close all my unsettled affairs, pay all
debts and try to fix myself so as to be comfortable and in a situation to
make my <persName>friends </persName>so&#8212;a few days with <persName>Williams </persName>aid will enable you to 
understand how my affairs stand&#8212;but it must not be neglected and put off&#8212;
attend to it at once and to the a/c with <persName>John Austin's estate</persName> as soon as 
<persName>Williams </persName>returns and have all these things finished and put to writing&#8212; If I
have heretofore been too careless and negligent as to such things, I shall in
future be on the opposite extreme and press the closing of all my unsettled
business, I therefore request that you will loose no time at all after 
<persName>Williams </persName>return&#8212;attending to all these matters and closing them as fast as
possible&#8212;</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin </persName>[Rubric]</p>

<p>To avoid all difficulty or misunderstanding in case of my death I will
now say to you that I intend to make a present to <persName>McKinny </persName>and <persName>Williams</persName>
of the <placeName>lot </placeName>where their <placeName>ware house</placeName> is, and should I never return you will
consider this a full authority to make that disposition of it&#8212;I will also
state that I consider myself bound individually to refund to them the money
they advanced to <persName>Grayson </persName>and <persName>Jack </persName>to go to <placeName>Mexico </placeName>and also for my drafts
on them&#8212;the same as to the money advanced by <persName>J. H. Bell</persName> and yourself or
any other of my <persName>friends </persName>for my assistance when in <placeName>prison </placeName>and under 
prosecution in <placeName>Mexico </placeName>in the service of <placeName>Texas</placeName></p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin </persName>[Rubric]</p>

<p>[Addressed:] <persName>Mr James F. Perry</persName> <placeName>Peach Point</placeName></p>



        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
