<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5137">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Stephen F Austin, Branch T Archer, and William H Wharton to William Bryan, 03-31-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Stephen F Austin, Branch T Archer, and William H Wharton</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-07-30">07-30-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        William Bryan
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Washington City, U.S.</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 319-320
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-03-31">03-31-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-07-30" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Plans for raising funds. Capitalists awaiting action of the convention on independence</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Washington </placeName><date when="1836-03-31">March 31. 1836</date></p>
<p><persName>Wm. Bryan Esqr <placeName>Texas </placeName>agt. <placeName>N. Orleans</placeName></persName></p>

<p>D Sir.</p>

<p>Your various communications addressed to us since leaving <placeName>New 
Orleans</placeName> were not received until <date when="1836-03-30">last evening</date>. They are the first accounts we
have had from you. For the attention and zeal for our sacred cause
evinced by them be pleased to accept our heartfelt gratitude, your 
conduct in every respect since acting as <persName>agent </persName>so far as has come to our 
knowledge has met our most cordial approbation. The scarcity of funds of
which you speak has distressed us not a little. We have <persName>agents </persName>in <placeName>New
York</placeName> and elsewhere busily engaged in endeavoring to make monied 
negotiations. Most of the <persName>capitalists </persName>have been awaiting the present <persName>Texas 
Convention</persName>. If that declares absolute independence all will go right 
immediately. We are disappointed at not hearing from the <persName>convention </persName>before
now, and expect the declaration of independence dayly We have just 
received very favorable propositions from <placeName>New York</placeName> in regard to a loan of
a large amount. It is bottomed however on an absolute declaration of
independence by the <persName>convention</persName>. As soon as we get news of this we will
proceed to <placeName>N York</placeName> and contract the loan We will raise funds if we give
10 pr, cent and mortgage every thing we possess on earth even to our
wearing apparel On this you may rely but we cannot accomplish the
matter until we hear from the <persName>convention </persName>In Gods name Do hold on in
the good cause and strain every nerve to keep up the public credit until we
can relieve you the public feeling is all on our side and that of the 
<persName>government </persName>too but this is confidential <persName>Genl Austin</persName> and <persName>W H Wharton</persName> were
very sick at <placeName>Nashville </placeName>which prevented our getting on sooner but we could
have accomplished nothing by being here or in <placeName>New York</placeName> with out having<pb n="320"/>
a declaration of independence to shew Again we conjure you to persevere
and sustain the public credit until we can relieve you which shall be as
soon as possible</p>

<p><persName>S. F. Austin.</persName> <persName>W. H. Wharton</persName></p>
<p><persName>B. T. Archer</persName>&#8212;<persName>Coms. for <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>.</p>


        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
