<?xml version="1.0" encoding="Windows-1252"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/sgmr29/code/digital-austin-papers/tei-2.0.2/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd "
xml:lang="EN"
xml:id="APB5211">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Unknown to Unknown, 07-03-1836</title>
            <author>
                <persName>Unknown</persName>
            </author>
            <respStmt xml:id="AJT">
                <resp>Project Director and Editor</resp> 
                <persName>Andrew J. Torget</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt xml:id="DL">
                <resp>Creation of XML version</resp>
                <persName>Debbie Liles</persName>
            </respStmt>

            <respStmt xml:id="SGM">
                <resp>TEI Formatting</resp>
                <persName>Stephen Mues</persName>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Digital Stephen F. Austin Papers</publisher>
            <date when="2011-08-12">08-12-2011</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>

                <person>
                    <persName type="recipient">
                        Unknown
                    </persName>
                </person>


            </listPerson>
            <listPlace>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="origin">Lexington, Kentucky</placeName>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <placeName type="destination">Unknown</placeName>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <bibl>
                Eugene Barker, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Austin Papers</hi>, (Austin: University of Texas Press, 1927), 3 vols., Vol 3, pp. 377-378
            </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="barker" scope="minor">
                Eugene Barker's summaries and footnotes
            </handNote>
        </handNotes>
        <textDesc>
            <channel mode="w">Letter</channel>
            <constitution type="single"/>
            <derivation type="original"/>
            <domain type="domestic"/>
            <factuality type="fact"/>
            <interaction type="none"/>
            <preparedness type="prepared"/>
            <purpose type="inform"/>
        </textDesc>
        <creation>
            <date when="1836-07-03">07-03-1836</date>
        </creation>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2012-02-15" who="#SGM">Restructured to meet TEI P5 standards</change>
        <change when="2011-08-12" who="#DL">Digital creation of XML file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>
    <body>
        <div1 type="summary">
            <p><add hand="#barker">Congress will act favorably on Texas next session. Advice to keep Santa Anna a prisoner</add></p>
        </div1>
        <div1 type="body">
            

<p><placeName>Lexington Ky</placeName> <date when="1836-07-03">July 3rd 1836</date></p>

<p>Dr Sir,</p>

<p><persName>Mr [Henry] Austin</persName> is at his <placeName><persName>sister</persName>s (<persName>Mrs Holly</persName>)</placeName> in this place he goes
<date when="1836-07-04">in the morning </date>with his <persName>sister </persName>and <persName>Daughter </persName>to the <placeName>Blue Licks</placeName> for his
health and on his way to <placeName>Cincinnati</placeName>. The late news of the rejection of the
treaty of <hi rend="italic"><persName>Santa Anna</persName></hi> by his <persName>Govt</persName>.&#8212;has created a belief here that he and
his <persName>officers </persName>will be shot&#8212; I hope not. My opinion is that sound policy
has induced the <persName>friends of Santa Ana</persName> to make these threats against <placeName>Texas</placeName>
in order to preserve their places and that no attempt is intended to march
again on <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212; What is said and the preparations for War may enable
those in power to sustain themselves and in this way may be better able to
serve <persName>Santa Ana</persName> than by attempting to nullify his treaty&#8212;still your 
<placeName>Country </placeName>Must not relax a moment in all the preparations for war as if the <persName>enemy</persName>
were at your doors&#8212; It is on that preparation you have most to rely for
peace. The report of the <persName>senate </persName>altho nothing more can be done this 
session is a great matter for you and leaves the rest to <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;if she acts
wisely for the <date n="04-xx-1837">next 9 months</date> Our <persName>Congress </persName>will do all she wants</p>

<p>Harmony at <placeName>home </placeName>and moderation in all your measures are the points of
the greatest Moment&#8212;public feeling is worth a kingdom. The folly of
<hi rend="italic"><persName>Santa Ana</persName></hi> in his <hi rend="italic">murderous </hi>orders has destroyed his fame and created for
<placeName>Texas </placeName>a feeling too strong for the <hi rend="italic">power </hi>of <hi rend="italic"><placeName>Mexico </placeName></hi>to Conquer&#8212; The
policy of liberating <hi rend="italic"><persName>Santa Anna</persName></hi> is certainly improper at the present&#8212;While
a <persName>prisoner </persName>the whole plans of his <persName>friends </persName>and his <persName>enemies </persName>at <placeName>home </placeName>remain
unsettled either release him or kill him and they at once are free to adopt
some regular plan against you and the injury to <placeName>Texas </placeName>would be most 
alarming in the divisions it must produce at <placeName>home </placeName>and in the <placeName>U. S.</placeName> as to the<pb n="378"/>
wisdom of the measure and the Motives which lead to it&#8212; All remain
satisfied so long as no steps of liberating or killing is taken. The very
doubts on this head is advantageous to <placeName>Texas</placeName>&#8212;but take either step finally
and the danger of contending opinions at <placeName>home </placeName>creates factions and in the
<placeName>U S</placeName> doubts and distrust of <persName>those in power in <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName>&#8212; If <persName>Santa Ana</persName> and
<persName>Cos </persName>had been shot on the <placeName>field of Battle</placeName> the <placeName>Civilized World</placeName> Must have 
approved of the Justice of the Act however doubtful the policy may have
been&#8212;but your <placeName>Country </placeName>stands committed to save them by the delay 
already and if future events do not impose the necessity of shooting it will
not do to adopt it&#8212; <placeName>Texas </placeName>has profited by the cruelties of <persName>Santa Ana</persName> in
rousing the sympathy of the <placeName>U S</placeName> for her and she must not part with a grain
of that benefit by shooting any <persName>prisoner </persName>at this late period <hi rend="italic"><persName>Santa Ana</persName></hi> is
no doubt a monster but <persName>Cos </persName>who has forfeited his life by the rules of war
acted under the orders of the other and may be the most worthy at any
rate he is in a situation to have more of public sympathy because it is 
believed he was forced to a breach of the rules of war by <hi rend="italic"><persName>Santa Ana</persName></hi>&#8212; A
nation gains immortal fame by even errors on the side of Humanity while
it can suffer irreparable injury by acts strictly Just but not called for by
the situation at <placeName>home</placeName>. On this head the <persName>best men of <placeName>Texas</placeName></persName> must deliberate
to satisfy the spirit of retaliation at <placeName>home </placeName>and high expectations of your
<persName>friends in the <placeName>U. S.</placeName></persName> Delay is the only remedy for the former and as much
kindness as possible to the <persName>prisoners </persName>is the Course for the latter&#8212; <persName>Genl
Houston</persName> stands above all complaints which have reached this <placeName>Country</placeName>, that
of delay appears to be the strongest, for which he deserves the highest
honors and all <persName>military men</persName> adopting the same tardy policy much suffer&#8212;
<hi rend="italic">prudence </hi>was called one of <placeName>Washington</placeName>s rascally virtues by <persName>Conway Lee</persName>
etc, but the man who has firmness to resist the <hi rend="italic">Current </hi>of his <persName>army </persName>at such
times deserves well of his <placeName>country</placeName>&#8212; The single circumstance of 
preserving a camp with the appearance of resistance&#8212;When <hi rend="italic">Panic </hi>was desolating
the <placeName>Country </placeName>is enough to place <persName>Genl Houston</persName> high in Military rank, the
Complaints against him are considered idle or the offspring of that 
impatient spirit so common in military life&#8212; You have a confidence in <persName>Genl
Houston</persName> of great worth and so long as he can serve <placeName>Texas </placeName>with the same
prudence it is wise to employ him. No man living save <persName>Genl Jackson</persName> could
have the same weight in your wars as [he]</p>

<p><persName>Major Grooms</persName> of the <persName>volunteers </persName>from this . . .</p>




        </div1>
    </body>
</text>
</TEI>
